<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<PLAY>
<TITLE>All&#8217;s Well That Ends Well</TITLE>
<TITLESHORT>All&#8217;s Well That Ends Well</TITLESHORT>
<PLAYWRIGHT>William Shakespeare</PLAYWRIGHT>

<PERSONAE>
<PERSONA short="KING.">King of France</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="DUKE.">Duke of Florence</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="BER.">Bertram, Count of Roussillion</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="LAF.">Lafew, an old lord</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="PAR.">Parolles, a parasitical follower of Bertram</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. LORD. DUM.">First French Lord Dumaine, in the Florentine service</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. LORD. DUM.">Second French Lord Dumaine, in the Florentine service</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="STEW.">Rinaldo, a steward</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="CLO.">Lavatch, a clown</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="PAGE.">Page, servants to the Countess of Roussillion</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="GENT.">Gentleman, an astringer</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="COUNT.">Countess of Roussillion, mother to Bertram</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="HEL.">Helena, a gentlewoman protected by the Countess</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="WID.,BOTH. MAR. AND WID.">An Old Widow of Florence</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="DIA.">Diana, daughter to the Widow</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Violenta, neighbor and friend to the Widow</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="MAR.,BOTH. MAR. AND WID.">Mariana, neighbor and friend to the Widow</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. LORD., ALL LORDS.">First French Lord, in the Florentine service</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. LORD., ALL LORDS.">Second French Lord, in the Florentine service</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="ALL LORDS.">Third French Lord, in the Florentine service</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="4. LORD., ALL LORDS.">Fourth Lord (French and Florentine)</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Officers (French and Florentine)</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="MESS.">Messenger</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.">First Soldier as Interpreter</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. SOLD.">Second Soldier</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 1</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Bertram Count of Roussillion, Countess of Roussillion, Helena, Lord Lafew, Parolles, Page)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter young Bertram, Count of Roussillion, his mother the Countess of Roussillion, and Helena, Lord Lafew, all in black.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In delivering my son from me, I bury a second husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I in going, madam, weep  o&#8217;er my father&#8217;s death anew; but I must attend his Majesty&#8217;s command, to whom I am now in ward, evermore in subjection.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall find of the King a husband, madam; you, sir, a father. He that so generally is at all times good must of necessity hold his virtue to you, whose worthiness would stir it up where it wanted rather than lack it where there is such abundance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What hope is there of his Majesty&#8217;s amendment?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath abandon&#8217;d his physicians, madam, under whose practices he hath persecuted time with hope, and finds no other advantage in the process but only the losing of hope by time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This young gentlewoman had a father&#8212;O, that &#8220;had,&#8221; how sad a passage &#8217;tis!&#8212;whose skill was almost as great as his honesty; had it stretch&#8217;d so far, would have made nature immortal, and death should have play for lack of work. Would for the King&#8217;s sake he were living! I think it would be the death of the King&#8217;s disease.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How call&#8217;d you the man you speak of, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He was famous, sir, in his profession, and it was his great right to be so&#8212;Gerard de Narbon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He was excellent indeed, madam. The King very lately spoke of him admiringly and mourningly. He was skillful enough to have liv&#8217;d still, if knowledge could be set up against mortality.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is it, my good lord, the King languishes of?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A fistula, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I heard not of it before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would it were not notorious. Was this gentlewoman the daughter of Gerard de Narbon?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His sole child, my lord, and bequeath&#8217;d to my overlooking. I have those hopes of her good that her education promises her dispositions she inherits, which makes fair gifts fairer; for where an unclean mind carries virtuous qualities, there commendations go with pity: they are virtues and traitors too. In her they are the better for their simpleness; she derives her honesty, and achieves her goodness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your commendations, madam, get from her tears.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis the best brine a maiden can season her praise in. The remembrance of her father never approaches her heart but the tyranny of her sorrows takes all livelihood from her cheek. No more of this, Helena; go to, no more, lest it be rather thought you affect a sorrow than to have&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do affect a sorrow indeed, but I have it too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Moderate lamentation is the right of the dead, excessive grief the enemy to the living.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If the living be enemy to the grief, the excess makes it soon mortal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I desire your holy wishes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How understand we that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be thou blest, Bertram, and succeed thy father</LINE>
<LINE>In manners as in shape! Thy blood and virtue</LINE>
<LINE>Contend for empire in thee, and thy goodness</LINE>
<LINE>Share with thy birthright! Love all, trust a few,</LINE>
<LINE>Do wrong to none. Be able for thine enemy</LINE>
<LINE>Rather in power than use, and keep thy friend</LINE>
<LINE>Under thy own life&#8217;s key. Be check&#8217;d for silence,</LINE>
<LINE>But never tax&#8217;d for speech. What heaven more will,</LINE>
<LINE>That thee may furnish, and my prayers pluck down,</LINE>
<LINE>Fall on thy head!&#8212;Farewell, my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis an unseason&#8217;d courtier, good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Advise him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">He cannot want the best</LINE>
<LINE>That shall attend his love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Heaven bless him!</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell, Bertram.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">The best wishes that can</LINE>
<LINE>Be forged in your thoughts be servants to you!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Countess.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>To Helena.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Be comfortable to my mother, your mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>And make much of her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Farewell, pretty lady,</LINE>
<LINE>You must hold the credit of your father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Bertram and Lafew.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, were that all! I think not on my father,</LINE>
<LINE>And these great tears grace his remembrance more</LINE>
<LINE>Than those I shed for him. What was he like?</LINE>
<LINE>I have forgot him. My imagination</LINE>
<LINE>Carries no favor in&#8217;t but Bertram&#8217;s.</LINE>
<LINE>I am undone, there is no living, none,</LINE>
<LINE>If Bertram be away. &#8217;Twere all one</LINE>
<LINE>That I should love a bright particular star</LINE>
<LINE>And think to wed it, he is so above me.</LINE>
<LINE>In this bright radiance and collateral light</LINE>
<LINE>Must I be comforted, not in his sphere.</LINE>
<LINE>Th&#8217; ambition in my love thus plagues itself:</LINE>
<LINE>The hind that would be mated by the lion</LINE>
<LINE>Must die for love. &#8217;Twas pretty, though a plague,</LINE>
<LINE>To see him every hour, to sit and draw</LINE>
<LINE>His arched brows, his hawking eye, his curls,</LINE>
<LINE>In our heart&#8217;s table&#8212;heart too capable</LINE>
<LINE>Of every line and trick of his sweet favor.</LINE>
<LINE>But now he&#8217;s gone, and my idolatrous fancy</LINE>
<LINE>Must sanctify his reliques. Who comes here?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>One that goes with him. I love him for his sake,</LINE>
<LINE>And yet I know him a notorious liar,</LINE>
<LINE>Think him a great way fool, solely a coward;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet these fix&#8217;d evils sit so fit in him,</LINE>
<LINE>That they take place when virtue&#8217;s steely bones</LINE>
<LINE>Looks bleak i&#8217; th&#8217; cold wind. Withal, full oft we see</LINE>
<LINE>Cold wisdom waiting on superfluous folly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Save you, fair queen!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you, monarch!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you meditating on virginity?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay. You have some stain of soldier in you; let me ask a question. Man is enemy to virginity; how may we barricade it against him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Keep him out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But he assails, and our virginity though valiant, in the defense yet is weak. Unfold to us some warlike resistance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is none. Man, setting down before you, will undermine you and blow you up.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bless our poor virginity from underminers and blowers-up! Is there no military policy how virgins might blow up men?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Virginity being blown down, man will quicklier be blown up. Marry, in blowing him down again, with the breach yourselves made, you lose your city. It is not politic in the commonwealth of nature to preserve virginity. Loss of virginity is rational increase, and there was never virgin got till virginity was first lost. That you were made of is metal to make virgins. Virginity, by being once lost, may be ten times found; by being ever kept, it is ever lost. &#8217;Tis too cold a companion; away with&#8217;t!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will stand for&#8217;t a little, though therefore I die a virgin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There&#8217;s little can be said in&#8217;t, &#8217;tis against the rule of nature. To speak on the part of virginity is to accuse your mothers, which is most infallible disobedience. He that hangs himself is a virgin; virginity murders itself, and should be buried in highways out of all sanctified limit, as a desperate offendress against nature. Virginity breeds mites, much like a cheese, consumes itself to the very paring, and so dies with feeding his own stomach. Besides, virginity is peevish, proud, idle, made of self-love, which is the most inhibited sin in the canon. Keep it not, you cannot choose but lose by&#8217;t. Out with&#8217;t! Within t&#8217; one year it will make itself two, which is a goodly increase, and the principal itself not much the worse. Away with&#8217;t!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How might one do, sir, to lose it to her own liking?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me see. Marry, ill, to like him that ne&#8217;er it likes. &#8217;Tis a commodity will lose the gloss with lying: the longer kept, the less worth. Off with&#8217;t while &#8217;tis vendible; answer the time of request. Virginity, like an old courtier, wears her cap out of fashion, richly suited, but unsuitable&#8212;just like the brooch and the toothpick, which wear not now. Your date is better in your pie and your porridge than in your cheek; and your virginity, your old virginity, is like one of our French wither&#8217;d pears, it looks ill, it eats drily, marry, &#8217;tis a wither&#8217;d pear; it was formerly better, marry, yet &#8217;tis a wither&#8217;d pear. Will you any thing with it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not my virginity yet:</LINE>
<LINE>There shall your master have a thousand loves,</LINE>
<LINE>A mother, and a mistress, and a friend,</LINE>
<LINE>A phoenix, captain, and an enemy,</LINE>
<LINE>A guide, a goddess, and a sovereign,</LINE>
<LINE>A counsellor, a traitress, and a dear;</LINE>
<LINE>His humble ambition, proud humility;</LINE>
<LINE>His jarring concord, and his discord dulcet;</LINE>
<LINE>His faith, his sweet disaster; with a world</LINE>
<LINE>Of pretty, fond, adoptions christendoms</LINE>
<LINE>That blinking Cupid gossips. Now shall he&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>I know not what he shall&#8212;God send him well!</LINE>
<LINE>The court&#8217;s a learning place, and he is one&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What one, i&#8217; faith?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That I wish well. &#8217;Tis pity&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s pity?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That wishing well had not a body in&#8217;t,</LINE>
<LINE>Which might be felt, that we, the poorer born,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose baser stars do shut us up in wishes,</LINE>
<LINE>Might with effects of them follow our friends,</LINE>
<LINE>And show what we alone must think, which never</LINE>
<LINE>Returns us thanks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Page.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAGE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Monsieur Parolles, my lord calls for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Little Helen, farewell. If I can remember thee, I will think of thee at court.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Monsieur Parolles, you were born under a charitable star.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Under Mars, I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I especially think, under Mars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why under Mars?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The wars hath so kept you under that you must needs be born under Mars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When he was predominant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When he was retrograde, I think rather.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why think you so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You go so much backward when you fight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That&#8217;s for advantage.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So is running away, when fear proposes the safety. But the composition that your valor and fear makes in you is a virtue of a good wing, and I like the wear well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am so full of businesses, I cannot answer thee acutely. I will return perfect courtier, in the which my instruction shall serve to naturalize thee, so thou wilt be capable of a courtier&#8217;s counsel, and understand what advice shall thrust upon thee, else thou diest in thine unthankfulness, and thine ignorance makes thee away. Farewell. When thou hast leisure, say thy prayers; when thou hast none, remember thy friends. Get thee a good husband, and use him as he uses thee. So farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our remedies oft in ourselves do lie,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we ascribe to heaven. The fated sky</LINE>
<LINE>Gives us free scope, only doth backward pull</LINE>
<LINE>Our slow designs when we ourselves are dull.</LINE>
<LINE>What power is it which mounts my love so high,</LINE>
<LINE>That makes me see, and cannot feed mine eye?</LINE>
<LINE>The mightiest space in fortune nature brings</LINE>
<LINE>To join like likes, and kiss like native things.</LINE>
<LINE>Impossible be strange attempts to those</LINE>
<LINE>That weigh their pains in sense, and do suppose</LINE>
<LINE>What hath been cannot be. Who ever strove</LINE>
<LINE>To show her merit, that did miss her love?</LINE>
<LINE>The King&#8217;s disease&#8212;my project may deceive me,</LINE>
<LINE>But my intents are fix&#8217;d, and will not leave me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR> 

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Paris. The King&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(King of France, Lords, Attendants, Bertram, Lafew, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish cornets. Enter the King of France with letters, Lords, and divers Attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Florentines and Senoys are by th&#8217; ears,</LINE>
<LINE>Have fought with equal fortune, and continue</LINE>
<LINE>A braving war.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">So &#8217;tis reported, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, &#8217;tis most credible; we here receive it</LINE>
<LINE>A certainty, vouch&#8217;d from our cousin Austria,</LINE>
<LINE>With caution, that the Florentine will move us</LINE>
<LINE>For speedy aid; wherein our dearest friend</LINE>
<LINE>Prejudicates the business, and would seem</LINE>
<LINE>To have us make denial.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">His love and wisdom,</LINE>
<LINE>Approv&#8217;d so to your Majesty, may plead</LINE>
<LINE>For amplest credence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">He hath arm&#8217;d our answer,</LINE>
<LINE>And Florence is denied before he comes.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet for our gentlemen that mean to see</LINE>
<LINE>The Tuscan service, freely have they leave</LINE>
<LINE>To stand on either part.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">It well may serve</LINE>
<LINE>A nursery to our gentry, who are sick</LINE>
<LINE>For breathing and exploit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What&#8217;s he comes here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Bertram, Lafew, and Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is the Count Roussillion, my good lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Young Bertram.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">Youth, thou bear&#8217;st thy father&#8217;s face;</LINE>
<LINE>Frank Nature, rather curious than in haste,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath well compos&#8217;d thee. Thy father&#8217;s moral parts</LINE>
<LINE>Mayst thou inherit too! Welcome to Paris.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My thanks and duty are your Majesty&#8217;s.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I had that corporal soundness now</LINE>
<LINE>As when thy father and myself in friendship</LINE>
<LINE>First tried our soldiership! He did look far</LINE>
<LINE>Into the service of the time, and was</LINE>
<LINE>Discipled of the bravest. He lasted long,</LINE>
<LINE>But on us both did haggish age steal on,</LINE>
<LINE>And wore us out of act. It much repairs me</LINE>
<LINE>To talk of your good father. In his youth</LINE>
<LINE>He had the wit which I can well observe</LINE>
<LINE>Today in our young lords; but they may jest</LINE>
<LINE>Till their own scorn return to them unnoted</LINE>
<LINE>Ere they can hide their levity in honor.</LINE>
<LINE>So like a courtier, contempt nor bitterness</LINE>
<LINE>Were in his pride or sharpness; if they were,</LINE>
<LINE>His equal had awak&#8217;d them, and his honor,</LINE>
<LINE>Clock to itself, knew the true minute when</LINE>
<LINE>Exception bid him speak, and at this time</LINE>
<LINE>His tongue obey&#8217;d his hand. Who were below him</LINE>
<LINE>He us&#8217;d as creatures of another place,</LINE>
<LINE>And bow&#8217;d his eminent top to their low ranks,</LINE>
<LINE>Making them proud of his humility,</LINE>
<LINE>In their poor praise he humbled. Such a man</LINE>
<LINE>Might be a copy to these younger times;</LINE>
<LINE>Which followed well, would demonstrate them now</LINE>
<LINE>But goers backward.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">His good remembrance, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Lies richer in your thoughts than on his tomb.</LINE>
<LINE>So in approof lives not his epitaph</LINE>
<LINE>As in your royal speech.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would I were with him! He would always say&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks I hear him now; his plausive words</LINE>
<LINE>He scatter&#8217;d not in ears, but grafted them,</LINE>
<LINE>To grow there and to bear&#8212;&#8220;Let me not live&#8221;&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>This his good melancholy oft began,</LINE>
<LINE>On the catastrophe and heel of pastime,</LINE>
<LINE>When it was out&#8212;&#8220;Let me not live,&#8221; quoth he,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;After my flame lacks oil, to be the snuff</LINE>
<LINE>Of younger spirits, whose apprehensive senses</LINE>
<LINE>All but new things disdain; whose judgments are</LINE>
<LINE>Mere fathers of their garments; whose constancies</LINE>
<LINE>Expire before their fashions.&#8221; This he wish&#8217;d.</LINE>
<LINE>I, after him, do after him wish too,</LINE>
<LINE>Since I nor wax nor honey can bring home,</LINE>
<LINE>I quickly were dissolved from my hive,</LINE>
<LINE>To give some laborers room.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">You&#8217;re loved, sir;</LINE>
<LINE>They that least lend it you shall lack you first.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fill a place, I know&#8217;t. How long is&#8217;t, Count,</LINE>
<LINE>Since the physician at your father&#8217;s died?</LINE>
<LINE>He was much fam&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Some six months since, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If he were living, I would try him yet.&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>Lend me an arm.&#8212;The rest have worn me out</LINE>
<LINE>With several applications. Nature and sickness</LINE>
<LINE>Debate it at their leisure. Welcome, Count,</LINE>
<LINE>My son&#8217;s no dearer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Thank your Majesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt. Flourish.</STAGEDIR> 

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Countess, Steward Rinaldo, Clown Lavatch, Helen)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Countess, Steward Rinaldo, and Clown Lavatch.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will now hear. What say you of this gentlewoman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, the care I have had to even your content, I wish might be found in the calendar of my past endeavors, for then we wound our modesty, and make foul the clearness of our deservings, when of ourselves we publish them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What does this knave here? Get you gone, sirrah. The complaints I have heard of you I do not all believe. &#8217;Tis my slowness that I do not, for I know you lack not folly to commit them, and have ability enough to make such knaveries yours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis not unknown to you, madam, I am a poor fellow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, madam, &#8217;tis not so well that I am poor, though many of the rich are damn&#8217;d, but if I may have your ladyship&#8217;s good will to go to the world, Isbel the woman and I will do as we may.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wilt thou needs be a beggar?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beg your good will in this case.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In what case?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In Isbel&#8217;s case and mine own. Service is no heritage, and I think I shall never have the blessing of God till I have issue a&#8217; my body; for they say barnes are blessings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell me thy reason why thou wilt marry.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My poor body, madam, requires it. I am driven on by the flesh, and he must needs go that the devil drives.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this all your worship&#8217;s reason?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, madam, I have other holy reasons, such as they are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May the world know them?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been, madam, a wicked creature, as you and all flesh and blood are, and indeed I do marry that I may repent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy marriage, sooner than thy wickedness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am out a&#8217; friends, madam, and I hope to have friends for my wive&#8217;s sake.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Such friends are thine enemies, knave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Y&#8217; are shallow, madam&#8212;in great friends, for the knaves come to do that for me which I am a-weary of. He that ears my land spares my team, and gives me leave to inn the crop. If I be his cuckold, he&#8217;s my drudge. He that comforts my wife is the cherisher of my flesh and blood; he that cherishes my flesh and blood loves my flesh and blood; he that loves my flesh and blood is my friend: ergo, he that kisses my wife is my friend. If men could be contented to be what they are, there were no fear in marriage, for young Charbon the puritan and old Poysam the papist, howsome&#8217;er their hearts are sever&#8217;d in religion, their heads are both one: they may jowl horns together like any deer i&#8217; th&#8217; herd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wilt thou ever be a foul-mouth&#8217;d and calumnious knave?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A prophet I, madam, and I speak the truth the next way:</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">For I the ballad will repeat,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Which men full true shall find:</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Your marriage comes by destiny,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Your cuckoo sings by kind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you gone, sir, I&#8217;ll talk with you more anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May it please you, madam, that he bid Helen come to you. Of her I am to speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sirrah, tell my gentlewoman I would speak with her&#8212;Helen, I mean.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Sings.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE type="lyric">&#8220;Was this fair face the cause,&#8221; quoth she,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">&#8220;Why the Grecians sacked Troy?</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Fond done, done fond,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Was this King Priam&#8217;s joy?&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">With that she sighed as she stood,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">With that she sighed as she stood,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">And gave this sentence then:</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">&#8220;Among nine bad if one be good,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Among nine bad if one be good,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">There&#8217;s yet one good in ten.&#8221;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, one good in ten? You corrupt the song, sirrah.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One good woman in ten, madam, which is a purifying a&#8217; th&#8217; song. Would God would serve the world so all the year! We&#8217;d find no fault with the tithe-woman if I were the parson. One in ten, quoth &#8217;a? And we might have a good woman born but or every blazing star or at an earthquake, &#8217;twould mend the lottery well; a man may draw his heart out ere &#8217;a pluck one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You&#8217;ll be gone, sir knave, and do as I command you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That man should be at woman&#8217;s command, and yet no hurt done! Though honesty be no puritan, yet it will do no hurt; it will wear the surplice of humility over the black gown of a big heart. I am going, forsooth. The business is for Helen to come hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know, madam, you love your gentlewoman entirely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, I do. Her father bequeath&#8217;d her to me, and she herself, without other advantage, may lawfully make title to as much love as she finds. There is more owing her than is paid, and more shall be paid her than she&#8217;ll demand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I was very late more near her than I think she wish&#8217;d me. Alone she was, and did communicate to herself her own words to her own ears; she thought, I dare vow for her, they touch&#8217;d not any stranger sense. Her matter was, she lov&#8217;d your son. Fortune, she said, was no goddess, that had put such difference betwixt their two estates; Love no god, that would not extend his might only where qualities were level; Diana no queen of virgins, that would suffer her poor knight surpris&#8217;d without rescue in the first assault or ransom afterward. This she deliver&#8217;d in the most bitter touch of sorrow that e&#8217;er I heard virgin exclaim in, which I held my duty speedily to acquaint you withal, sithence in the loss that may happen, it concerns you something to know it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have discharg&#8217;d this honestly, keep it to yourself. Many likelihoods inform&#8217;d me of this before, which hung so tott&#8217;ring in the balance that I could neither believe nor misdoubt. Pray you leave me. Stall this in your bosom, and I thank you for your honest care. I will speak with you further anon.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Steward.</STAGEDIR>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Even so it was with me when I was young.</LINE>
<LINE>If ever we are nature&#8217;s, these are ours. This thorn</LINE>
<LINE>Doth to our rose of youth rightly belong;</LINE>
<LINE>Our blood to us, this to our blood is born.</LINE>
<LINE>It is the show and seal of nature&#8217;s truth,</LINE>
<LINE>Where love&#8217;s strong passion is impress&#8217;d in youth.</LINE>
<LINE>By our remembrances of days foregone,</LINE>
<LINE>Such were our faults, or then we thought them none.</LINE>
<LINE>Her eye is sick on&#8217;t; I observe her now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is your pleasure, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">You know, Helen,</LINE>
<LINE>I am a mother to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mine honorable mistress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nay, a mother,</LINE>
<LINE>Why not a mother? When I said &#8220;a mother,&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>Methought you saw a serpent. What&#8217;s in &#8220;mother,&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>That you start at it? I say I am your mother,</LINE>
<LINE>And put you in the catalogue of those</LINE>
<LINE>That were enwombed mine. &#8217;Tis often seen</LINE>
<LINE>Adoption strives with nature, and choice breeds</LINE>
<LINE>A native slip to us from foreign seeds.</LINE>
<LINE>You ne&#8217;er oppress&#8217;d me with a mother&#8217;s groan,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet I express to you a mother&#8217;s care.</LINE>
<LINE>God&#8217;s mercy, maiden! Does it curd thy blood</LINE>
<LINE>To say I am thy mother? What&#8217;s the matter,</LINE>
<LINE>That this distempered messenger of wet,</LINE>
<LINE>The many-color&#8217;d Iris, rounds thine eye?</LINE>
<LINE>&#8212;Why, that you are my daughter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">That I am not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I say I am your mother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Pardon, madam;</LINE>
<LINE>The Count Roussillion cannot be my brother:</LINE>
<LINE>I am from humble, he from honored name;</LINE>
<LINE>No note upon my parents, his all noble.</LINE>
<LINE>My master, my dear lord he is, and I</LINE>
<LINE>His servant live, and will his vassal die.</LINE>
<LINE>He must not be my brother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nor I your mother?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are my mother, madam; would you were&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>So that my lord your son were not my brother&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>Indeed my mother! Or were you both our mothers,</LINE>
<LINE>I care no more for than I do for heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>So I were not his sister. Can&#8217;t no other,</LINE>
<LINE>But, I your daughter, he must be my brother?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, Helen, you might be my daughter-in-law.</LINE>
<LINE>God shield you mean it not! &#8220;daughter&#8221; and &#8220;mother&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>So strive upon your pulse. What, pale again?</LINE>
<LINE>My fear hath catch&#8217;d your fondness! Now I see</LINE>
<LINE>The myst&#8217;ry of your loneliness, and find</LINE>
<LINE>Your salt tears&#8217; head, now to all sense &#8217;tis gross:</LINE>
<LINE>You love my son. Invention is asham&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>Against the proclamation of thy passion,</LINE>
<LINE>To say thou dost not: therefore tell me true,</LINE>
<LINE>But tell me then &#8217;tis so; for look, thy cheeks</LINE>
<LINE>Confess it, t&#8217; one to th&#8217; other, and thine eyes</LINE>
<LINE>See it so grossly shown in thy behaviors</LINE>
<LINE>That in their kind they speak it. Only sin</LINE>
<LINE>And hellish obstinacy tie thy tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>That truth should be suspected. Speak, is&#8217;t so?</LINE>
<LINE>If it be so, you have wound a goodly clew;</LINE>
<LINE>If it be not, forswear&#8217;t; howe&#8217;er, I charge thee,</LINE>
<LINE>As heaven shall work in me for thine avail,</LINE>
<LINE>To tell me truly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Good madam, pardon me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you love my son?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Your pardon, noble mistress!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Love you my son?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Do not you love him, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go not about; my love hath in&#8217;t a bond</LINE>
<LINE>Whereof the world takes note. Come, come, disclose</LINE>
<LINE>The state of your affection, for your passions</LINE>
<LINE>Have to the full appeach&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Then I confess</LINE>
<LINE>Here on my knee, before high heaven and you,</LINE>
<LINE>That before you, and next unto high heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>I love your son.</LINE>
<LINE>My friends were poor, but honest, so&#8217;s my love.</LINE>
<LINE>Be not offended, for it hurts not him</LINE>
<LINE>That he is lov&#8217;d of me; I follow him not</LINE>
<LINE>By any token of presumptuous suit,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor would I have him till I do deserve him,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet never know how that desert should be.</LINE>
<LINE>I know I love in vain, strive against hope;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet in this captious and intenible sieve</LINE>
<LINE>I still pour in the waters of my love</LINE>
<LINE>And lack not to lose still. Thus Indian-like,</LINE>
<LINE>Religious in mine error, I adore</LINE>
<LINE>The sun, that looks upon his worshipper,</LINE>
<LINE>But knows of him no more. My dearest madam,</LINE>
<LINE>Let not your hate encounter with my love</LINE>
<LINE>For loving where you do; but if yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose aged honor cites a virtuous youth,</LINE>
<LINE>Did ever in so true a flame of liking</LINE>
<LINE>Wish chastely, and love dearly, that your Dian</LINE>
<LINE>Was both herself and Love, O then give pity</LINE>
<LINE>To her whose state is such that cannot choose</LINE>
<LINE>But lend and give where she is sure to lose;</LINE>
<LINE>That seeks not to find that her search implies,</LINE>
<LINE>But riddle-like lives sweetly where she dies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Had you not lately an intent&#8212;speak truly&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>To go to Paris?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Madam, I had.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Wherefore? Tell true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will tell truth, by grace itself I swear.</LINE>
<LINE>You know my father left me some prescriptions</LINE>
<LINE>Of rare and prov&#8217;d effects, such as his reading</LINE>
<LINE>And manifest experience had collected</LINE>
<LINE>For general sovereignty; and that he will&#8217;d me</LINE>
<LINE>In heedfull&#8217;st reservation to bestow them,</LINE>
<LINE>As notes whose faculties inclusive were</LINE>
<LINE>More than they were in note. Amongst the rest,</LINE>
<LINE>There is a remedy, approv&#8217;d, set down,</LINE>
<LINE>To cure the desperate languishings whereof</LINE>
<LINE>The King is render&#8217;d lost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">This was your motive</LINE>
<LINE>For Paris, was it? Speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord your son made me to think of this;</LINE>
<LINE>Else Paris, and the medicine, and the King,</LINE>
<LINE>Had from the conversation of my thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>Happily been absent then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">But think you, Helen,</LINE>
<LINE>If you should tender your supposed aid,</LINE>
<LINE>He would receive it? He and his physicians</LINE>
<LINE>Are of a mind; he, that they cannot help him,</LINE>
<LINE>They, that they cannot help. How shall they credit</LINE>
<LINE>A poor unlearned virgin, when the schools,</LINE>
<LINE>Embowell&#8217;d of their doctrine, have left off</LINE>
<LINE>The danger to itself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">There&#8217;s something in&#8217;t</LINE>
<LINE>More than my father&#8217;s skill, which was the great&#8217;st</LINE>
<LINE>Of his profession, that his good receipt</LINE>
<LINE>Shall for my legacy be sanctified</LINE>
<LINE>By th&#8217; luckiest stars in heaven, and would your honor</LINE>
<LINE>But give me leave to try success, I&#8217;d venture</LINE>
<LINE>The well-lost life of mine on his Grace&#8217;s cure</LINE>
<LINE>By such a day, an hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Dost thou believe&#8217;t?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, madam, knowingly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, Helen, thou shalt have my leave and love,</LINE>
<LINE>Means and attendants, and my loving greetings</LINE>
<LINE>To those of mine in court. I&#8217;ll stay at home</LINE>
<LINE>And pray God&#8217;s blessing into thy attempt.</LINE>
<LINE>Be gone tomorrow, and be sure of this,</LINE>
<LINE>What I can help thee to thou shalt not miss.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 2</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Paris. The King&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(King, Lords, Bertram Count Roussillion, Parolles, Lafew, Helen)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the King, with divers young Lords taking leave for the Florentine war, (Bertram) Count Roussillion, and Parolles. Flourish cornets.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, young lords, these warlike principles</LINE>
<LINE>Do not throw from you; and you, my lords, farewell.</LINE>
<LINE>Share the advice betwixt you; if both gain all,</LINE>
<LINE>The gift doth stretch itself as &#8217;tis receiv&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>And is enough for both.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">&#8217;Tis our hope, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>After well-ent&#8217;red soldiers, to return</LINE>
<LINE>And find your Grace in health.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, it cannot be; and yet my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Will not confess he owes the malady</LINE>
<LINE>That doth my life besiege. Farewell, young lords,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether I live or die, be you the sons</LINE>
<LINE>Of worthy Frenchmen. Let higher Italy</LINE>
<LINE>(Those bated that inherit but the fall</LINE>
<LINE>Of the last monarchy) see that you come</LINE>
<LINE>Not to woo honor, but to wed it, when</LINE>
<LINE>The bravest questant shrinks. Find what you seek,</LINE>
<LINE>That fame may cry you loud. I say farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Health, at your bidding, serve your Majesty!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Those girls of Italy, take heed of them.</LINE>
<LINE>They say our French lack language to deny</LINE>
<LINE>If they demand. Beware of being captives</LINE>
<LINE>Before you serve.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BOTH LORDS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Our hearts receive your warnings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell.&#8212;Come hither to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>The King retires apart with some Lords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my sweet lord, that you will stay behind us!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis not his fault, the spark.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, &#8217;tis brave wars!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most admirable! I have seen those wars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am commanded here, and kept a coil with,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Too young&#8221; and &#8220;the next year&#8221; and &#8220;&#8217;tis too early.&#8221;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And thy mind stand to&#8217;t, boy, steal away bravely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall stay here the forehorse to a smock,</LINE>
<LINE>Creaking my shoes on the plain masonry,</LINE>
<LINE>Till honor be bought up, and no sword worn</LINE>
<LINE>But one to dance with! By heaven, I&#8217;ll steal away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There&#8217;s honor in the theft.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Commit it, Count.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am your accessary, and so farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I grow to you, and our parting is a tortur&#8217;d body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, captain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet Monsieur Parolles!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble heroes! My sword and yours are kin. Good sparks and lustrous, a word, good metals: you shall find in the regiment of the Spinii one Captain Spurio, with his cicatrice, an emblem of war, here on his sinister cheek; it was this very sword entrench&#8217;d it. Say to him I live, and observe his reports for me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We shall, noble captain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mars dote on you for his novices!</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Lords.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What will ye do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay the King.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Use a more spacious ceremony to the noble lords; you have restrain&#8217;d yourself within the list of too cold an <FRENCH lang="fr">adieu</FRENCH>. Be more expressive to them, for they wear themselves in the cap of the time, there do muster true gait; eat, speak, and move under the influence of the most receiv&#8217;d star, and though the devil lead the measure, such are to be follow&#8217;d. After them, and take a more dilated farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I will do so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy fellows, and like to prove most sinewy swordmen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Bertram and Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Lafew. The King comes forward.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Kneeling.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Pardon, my lord, for me and for my tidings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll see thee to stand up.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then here&#8217;s a man stands that has brought his pardon.</LINE>
<LINE>I would you had kneel&#8217;d, my lord, to ask me mercy,</LINE>
<LINE>And that at my bidding you could so stand up.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I had, so I had broke thy pate,</LINE>
<LINE>And ask&#8217;d thee mercy for&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Good faith, across!</LINE>
<LINE>But, my good lord, &#8217;tis thus: will you be cur&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>Of your infirmity?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">No.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">O, will you eat</LINE>
<LINE>No grapes, my royal fox? Yes, but you will</LINE>
<LINE>My noble grapes, and if my royal fox</LINE>
<LINE>Could reach them. I have seen a medicine</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s able to breathe life into a stone,</LINE>
<LINE>Quicken a rock, and make you dance canary</LINE>
<LINE>With spritely fire and motion, whose simple touch</LINE>
<LINE>Is powerful to araise King Pippen, nay,</LINE>
<LINE>To give great Charlemain a pen in &#8217;s hand</LINE>
<LINE>And write to her a love-line.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">What her is this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, Doctor She! My lord, there&#8217;s one arriv&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>If you will see her. Now by my faith and honor,</LINE>
<LINE>If seriously I may convey my thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>In this my light deliverance, I have spoke</LINE>
<LINE>With one, that in her sex, her years, profession,</LINE>
<LINE>Wisdom, and constancy, hath amaz&#8217;d me more</LINE>
<LINE>Than I dare blame my weakness. Will you see her&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>For that is her demand&#8212;and know her business?</LINE>
<LINE>That done, laugh well at me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Now, good Lafew,</LINE>
<LINE>Bring in the admiration, that we with thee</LINE>
<LINE>May spend our wonder too, or take off thine</LINE>
<LINE>By wond&#8217;ring how thou took&#8217;st it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Nay, I&#8217;ll fit you,</LINE>
<LINE>And not be all day neither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Goes to the door.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus he his special nothing ever prologues.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, come your ways.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">This haste hath wings indeed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, come your ways;</LINE>
<LINE>This is his Majesty, say your mind to him.</LINE>
<LINE>A traitor you do look like, but such traitors</LINE>
<LINE>His Majesty seldom fears. I am Cressid&#8217;s uncle,</LINE>
<LINE>That dare leave two together; fare you well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, fair one, does your business follow us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, my good lord.</LINE>
<LINE>Gerard de Narbon was my father,</LINE>
<LINE>In what he did profess, well found.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">I knew him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The rather will I spare my praises towards him,</LINE>
<LINE>Knowing him is enough. On &#8217;s bed of death</LINE>
<LINE>Many receipts he gave me; chiefly one,</LINE>
<LINE>Which as the dearest issue of his practice,</LINE>
<LINE>And of his old experience th&#8217; only darling,</LINE>
<LINE>He bade me store up, as a triple eye,</LINE>
<LINE>Safer than mine own two, more dear. I have so,</LINE>
<LINE>And hearing your high Majesty is touch&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>With that malignant cause wherein the honor</LINE>
<LINE>Of my dear father&#8217;s gift stands chief in power,</LINE>
<LINE>I come to tender it, and my appliance,</LINE>
<LINE>With all bound humbleness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">We thank you, maiden,</LINE>
<LINE>But may not be so credulous of cure,</LINE>
<LINE>When our most learned doctors leave us, and</LINE>
<LINE>The congregated college have concluded</LINE>
<LINE>That laboring art can never ransom nature</LINE>
<LINE>From her inaidible estate; I say we must not</LINE>
<LINE>So stain our judgment, or corrupt our hope,</LINE>
<LINE>To prostitute our past-cure malady</LINE>
<LINE>To empirics, or to dissever so</LINE>
<LINE>Our great self and our credit, to esteem</LINE>
<LINE>A senseless help when help past sense we deem.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My duty then shall pay me for my pains.</LINE>
<LINE>I will no more enforce mine office on you,</LINE>
<LINE>Humbly entreating from your royal thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>A modest one, to bear me back again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot give thee less, to be call&#8217;d grateful.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou thought&#8217;st to help me, and such thanks I give</LINE>
<LINE>As one near death to those that wish him live.</LINE>
<LINE>But what at full I know, thou know&#8217;st no part,</LINE>
<LINE>I knowing all my peril, thou no art.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What I can do can do no hurt to try,</LINE>
<LINE>Since you set up your rest &#8217;gainst remedy.</LINE>
<LINE>He that of greatest works is finisher</LINE>
<LINE>Oft does them by the weakest minister:</LINE>
<LINE>So holy writ in babes hath judgment shown,</LINE>
<LINE>When judges have been babes; great floods have flown</LINE>
<LINE>From simple sources; and great seas have dried</LINE>
<LINE>When miracles have by the great&#8217;st been denied.</LINE>
<LINE>Oft expectation fails, and most oft there</LINE>
<LINE>Where most it promises; and oft it hits</LINE>
<LINE>Where hope is coldest, and despair most fits.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must not hear thee; fare thee well, kind maid,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy pains not us&#8217;d must by thyself be paid.</LINE>
<LINE>Proffers not took reap thanks for their reward.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Inspired merit so by breath is barr&#8217;d.</LINE>
<LINE>It is not so with Him that all things knows</LINE>
<LINE>As &#8217;tis with us that square our guess by shows;</LINE>
<LINE>But most it is presumption in us when</LINE>
<LINE>The help of heaven we count the act of men.</LINE>
<LINE>Dear sir, to my endeavors give consent,</LINE>
<LINE>Of heaven, not me, make an experiment.</LINE>
<LINE>I am not an imposture that proclaim</LINE>
<LINE>Myself against the level of mine aim,</LINE>
<LINE>But know I think, and think I know most sure,</LINE>
<LINE>My art is not past power, nor you past cure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Art thou so confident? Within what space</LINE>
<LINE>Hop&#8217;st thou my cure?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">The greatest grace lending grace,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere twice the horses of the sun shall bring</LINE>
<LINE>Their fiery torcher his diurnal ring,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere twice in murk and occidental damp</LINE>
<LINE>Moist Hesperus hath quench&#8217;d her sleepy lamp,</LINE>
<LINE>Or four and twenty times the pilot&#8217;s glass</LINE>
<LINE>Hath told the thievish minutes how they pass,</LINE>
<LINE>What is infirm from your sound parts shall fly,</LINE>
<LINE>Health shall live free, and sickness freely die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Upon thy certainty and confidence</LINE>
<LINE>What dar&#8217;st thou venter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Tax of impudence,</LINE>
<LINE>A strumpet&#8217;s boldness, a divulged shame,</LINE>
<LINE>Traduc&#8217;d by odious ballads; my maiden&#8217;s name</LINE>
<LINE>Sear&#8217;d otherwise; ne worse of worst&#8212;extended</LINE>
<LINE>With vildest torture, let my life be ended.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks in thee some blessed spirit doth speak</LINE>
<LINE>His powerful sound within an organ weak;</LINE>
<LINE>And what impossibility would slay</LINE>
<LINE>In common sense, sense saves another way.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy life is dear, for all that life can rate</LINE>
<LINE>Worth name of life in thee hath estimate:</LINE>
<LINE>Youth, beauty, wisdom, courage, all</LINE>
<LINE>That happiness and prime can happy call.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou this to hazard needs must intimate</LINE>
<LINE>Skill infinite, or monstrous desperate.</LINE>
<LINE>Sweet practicer, thy physic I will try,</LINE>
<LINE>That ministers thine own death if I die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I break time, or flinch in property</LINE>
<LINE>Of what I spoke, unpitied let me die,</LINE>
<LINE>And well deserv&#8217;d. Not helping, death&#8217;s my fee,</LINE>
<LINE>But if I help, what do you promise me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Make thy demand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">But will you make it even?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, by my sceptre and my hopes of heaven.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then shalt thou give me with thy kingly hand</LINE>
<LINE>What husband in thy power I will command.</LINE>
<LINE>Exempted be from me the arrogance</LINE>
<LINE>To choose from forth the royal blood of France,</LINE>
<LINE>My low and humble name to propagate</LINE>
<LINE>With any branch or image of thy state;</LINE>
<LINE>But such a one thy vassal, whom I know</LINE>
<LINE>Is free for me to ask, thee to bestow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is my hand, the premises observ&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy will by my performance shall be serv&#8217;d.</LINE>
<LINE>So make the choice of thy own time, for I,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy resolv&#8217;d patient, on thee still rely.</LINE>
<LINE>More should I question thee, and more I must&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>Though more to know could not be more to trust&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>From whence thou cam&#8217;st, how tended on, but rest</LINE>
<LINE>Unquestion&#8217;d welcome and undoubted blest.&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>Give me some help here ho!&#8212;If thou proceed</LINE>
<LINE>As high as word, my deed shall match thy deed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Countess, Clown)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Countess and Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come on, sir, I shall now put you to the height of your breeding.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will show myself highly fed and lowly taught. I know my business is but to the court.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the court! Why, what place make you special, when you put off that with such contempt? But to the court!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, madam, if God have lent a man any manners, he may easily put it off at court. He that cannot make a leg, put off &#8217;s cap, kiss his hand, and say nothing, has neither leg, hands, lip, nor cap; and indeed such a fellow, to say precisely, were not for the court; but for me, I have an answer will serve all men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, that&#8217;s a bountiful answer that fits all questions.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is like a barber&#8217;s chair that fits all buttocks: the pin-buttock, the quatch-buttock, the brawn-buttock, or any buttock.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will your answer serve fit to all questions?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As fit as ten groats is for the hand of an attorney, as your French crown for your taffety punk, as Tib&#8217;s rush for Tom&#8217;s forefinger, as a pancake for Shrove Tuesday, a morris for May-day, as the nail to his hole, the cuckold to his horn, as a scolding quean to a wrangling knave, as the nun&#8217;s lip to the friar&#8217;s mouth, nay, as the pudding to his skin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you, I say, an answer of such fitness for all questions?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>From below your duke to beneath your constable, it will fit any question.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It must be an answer of most monstrous size that must fit all demands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But a trifle neither, in good faith, if the learned should speak truth of it. Here it is, and all that belongs to&#8217;t. Ask me if I am a courtier: it shall do you no harm to learn.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To be young again, if we could, I will be a fool in question, hoping to be the wiser by your answer. I pray you, sir, are you a courtier?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir!&#8212;There&#8217;s a simple putting off. More, more, a hundred of them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I am a poor friend of yours that loves you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir!&#8212;Thick, thick, spare not me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think, sir, you can eat none of this homely meat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir!&#8212;Nay, put me to&#8217;t, I warrant you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You were lately whipt, sir, as I think.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir!&#8212;Spare not me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you cry, &#8220;O Lord, sir!&#8221; at your whipping, and &#8220;Spare not me&#8221;? Indeed your &#8220;O Lord, sir!&#8221; is very sequent to your whipping; you would answer very well to a whipping, if you were but bound to&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I ne&#8217;er had worse luck in my life in my &#8220;O Lord, sir!&#8221; I see things may serve long, but not serve ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I play the noble huswife with the time,</LINE>
<LINE>To entertain it so merrily with a fool.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir!&#8212;Why, there&#8217;t serves well again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An end, sir; to your business: give Helen this,</LINE>
<LINE>And urge her to a present answer back.</LINE>
<LINE>Commend me to my kinsmen and my son.</LINE>
<LINE>This is not much.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not much commendation to them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not much employment for you. You understand me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most fruitfully, I am there before my legs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Haste you again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Paris. The King&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Bertram, Lafew, Parolles, King, Helen, Attendants, Lords)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter count Bertram, Lafew, and Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They say miracles are past, and we have our philosophical persons, to make modern and familiar, things supernatural and causeless. Hence is it that we make trifles of terrors, ensconcing ourselves into seeming knowledge, when we should submit ourselves to an unknown fear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, &#8217;tis the rarest argument of wonder that hath shot out in our latter times.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so &#8217;tis.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To be relinquish&#8217;d of the artists&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So I say, both of Galen and Paracelsus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Of all the learned and authentic fellows&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Right, so I say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That gave him out incurable&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, there &#8217;tis, so say I too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not to be help&#8217;d&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Right, as &#8217;twere a man assur&#8217;d of a&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Uncertain life, and sure death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Just, you say well; so would I have said.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I may truly say it is a novelty to the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is indeed; if you will have it in showing, you shall read it in what-do-ye-call there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Pointing to a ballad in Lafew&#8217;s hand.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reading the title.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;A showing of a heavenly effect in an earthly actor.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That&#8217;s it I would have said, the very same.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, your dolphin is not lustier. &#8217;Fore me, I speak in respect&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, &#8217;tis strange, &#8217;tis very strange, that is the brief and the tedious of it, and he&#8217;s of a most facinerious spirit that will not acknowledge it to be the&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very hand of heaven.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, so I say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In a most weak&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And debile minister, great power, great transcendence, which should indeed give us a further use to be made than alone the recov&#8217;ry of the King, as to be&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Generally thankful.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter King, Helen, and Attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would have said it; you say well. Here comes the King.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE><DUTCH lang="nl">Lustick</DUTCH>, as the Dutchman says. I&#8217;ll like a maid the better whilst I have a tooth in my head. Why, he&#8217;s able to lead her a coranto.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE><FRENCH lang="fr">Mort du vinaigre!</FRENCH> Is not this Helen?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Fore God, I think so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go call before me all the lords in court.</LINE>
<LINE>Sit, my preserver, by thy patient&#8217;s side,</LINE>
<LINE>And with this healthful hand, whose banish&#8217;d sense</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast repeal&#8217;d, a second time receive</LINE>
<LINE>The confirmation of my promis&#8217;d gift,</LINE>
<LINE>Which but attends thy naming.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter three or four Lords.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Fair maid, send forth thine eye. This youthful parcel</LINE>
<LINE>Of noble bachelors stand at my bestowing,</LINE>
<LINE>O&#8217;er whom both sovereign power and father&#8217;s voice</LINE>
<LINE>I have to use. Thy frank election make;</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast power to choose, and they none to forsake.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To each of you one fair and virtuous mistress</LINE>
<LINE>Fall, when Love please! Marry, to each but one!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;d give bay Curtal and his furniture,</LINE>
<LINE>My mouth no more were broken than these boys&#8217;,</LINE>
<LINE>And writ as little beard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Peruse them well.</LINE>
<LINE>Not one of those but had a noble father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Gentlemen,</LINE>
<LINE>Heaven hath through me restor&#8217;d the King to health.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ALL LORDS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We understand it, and thank heaven for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a simple maid, and therein wealthiest</LINE>
<LINE>That I protest I simply am a maid.</LINE>
<LINE>Please it your Majesty, I have done already.</LINE>
<LINE>The blushes in my cheeks thus whisper me,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;We blush that thou shouldst choose; but be refused,</LINE>
<LINE>Let the white death sit on thy cheek forever,</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll ne&#8217;er come there again.&#8221;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Make choice and see,</LINE>
<LINE>Who shuns thy love shuns all his love in me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, Dian, from thy altar do I fly,</LINE>
<LINE>And to imperial Love, that god most high,</LINE>
<LINE>Do my sighs stream.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>She addresses her to a Lord.</STAGEDIR>

<LINE>Sir, will you hear my suit?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And grant it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">Thanks, sir; all the rest is mute.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had rather be in this choice than throw ames-ace for my life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To a second Lord.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The honor, sir, that flames in your fair eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Before I speak, too threat&#8217;ningly replies.</LINE>
<LINE>Love make your fortunes twenty times above</LINE>
<LINE>Her that so wishes, and her humble love!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No better, if you please.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">My wish receive,</LINE>
<LINE>Which great Love grant, and so I take my leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do all they deny her? And they were sons of mine, I&#8217;d have them whipt, or I would send them to th&#8217; Turk to make eunuchs of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To a third Lord.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Be not afraid that I your hand should take,</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll never do you wrong for your own sake.</LINE>
<LINE>Blessing upon your vows, and in your bed</LINE>
<LINE>Find fairer fortune, if you ever wed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These boys are boys of ice, they&#8217;ll none have her. Sure they are bastards to the English, the French ne&#8217;er got &#8217;em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To a fourth Lord.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You are too young, too happy, and too good,</LINE>
<LINE>To make yourself a son out of my blood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>4. LORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fair one, I think not so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There&#8217;s one grape yet; I am sure thy father drunk wine&#8212;but if thou be&#8217;st not an ass, I am a youth of fourteen. I have known thee already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Bertram.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I dare not say I take you, but I give</LINE>
<LINE>Me and my service, ever whilst I live,</LINE>
<LINE>Into your guiding power.&#8212;This is the man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why then, young Bertram, take her, she&#8217;s thy wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My wife, my liege? I shall beseech your Highness,</LINE>
<LINE>In such a business, give me leave to use</LINE>
<LINE>The help of mine own eyes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Know&#8217;st thou not, Bertram,</LINE>
<LINE>What she has done for me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, my good lord,</LINE>
<LINE>But never hope to know why I should marry her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou know&#8217;st she has rais&#8217;d me from my sickly bed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But follows it, my lord, to bring me down</LINE>
<LINE>Must answer for your raising? I know her well;</LINE>
<LINE>She had her breeding at my father&#8217;s charge&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>A poor physician&#8217;s daughter my wife! Disdain</LINE>
<LINE>Rather corrupt me ever!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis only title thou disdain&#8217;st in her, the which</LINE>
<LINE>I can build up. Strange is it that our bloods,</LINE>
<LINE>Of color, weight, and heat, pour&#8217;d all together,</LINE>
<LINE>Would quite confound distinction, yet stands off</LINE>
<LINE>In differences so mighty. If she be</LINE>
<LINE>All that is virtuous&#8212;save what thou dislik&#8217;st,</LINE>
<LINE>A poor physician&#8217;s daughter&#8212;thou dislik&#8217;st</LINE>
<LINE>Of virtue for the name. But do not so.</LINE>
<LINE>From lowest place when virtuous things proceed,</LINE>
<LINE>The place is dignified by th&#8217; doer&#8217;s deed.</LINE>
<LINE>Where great additions swell &#8217;s, and virtue none,</LINE>
<LINE>It is a dropsied honor. Good alone</LINE>
<LINE>Is good, without a name; vileness is so:</LINE>
<LINE>The property by what it is should go,</LINE>
<LINE>Not by the title. She is young, wise, fair,</LINE>
<LINE>In these to nature she&#8217;s immediate heir;</LINE>
<LINE>And these breed honor. That is honor&#8217;s scorn,</LINE>
<LINE>Which challenges itself as honor&#8217;s born,</LINE>
<LINE>And is not like the sire. Honors thrive,</LINE>
<LINE>When rather from our acts we them derive</LINE>
<LINE>Than our foregoers. The mere word&#8217;s a slave</LINE>
<LINE>Debosh&#8217;d on every tomb, on every grave</LINE>
<LINE>A lying trophy, and as oft is dumb</LINE>
<LINE>Where dust and damn&#8217;d oblivion is the tomb</LINE>
<LINE>Of honor&#8217;d bones indeed. What should be said?</LINE>
<LINE>If thou canst like this creature as a maid,</LINE>
<LINE>I can create the rest. Virtue and she</LINE>
<LINE>Is her own dower; honor and wealth from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot love her, nor will strive to do&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou wrong&#8217;st thyself, if thou shouldst strive to choose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That you are well restor&#8217;d, my lord, I&#8217;m glad.</LINE>
<LINE>Let the rest go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My honor&#8217;s at the stake, which to defeat,</LINE>
<LINE>I must produce my power. Here, take her hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Proud scornful boy, unworthy this good gift,</LINE>
<LINE>That dost in vile misprision shackle up</LINE>
<LINE>My love and her desert; that canst not dream,</LINE>
<LINE>We poising us in her defective scale,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall weigh thee to the beam; that wilt not know</LINE>
<LINE>It is in us to plant thine honor where</LINE>
<LINE>We please to have it grow. Check thy contempt;</LINE>
<LINE>Obey our will, which travails in thy good;</LINE>
<LINE>Believe not thy disdain, but presently</LINE>
<LINE>Do thine own fortunes that obedient right</LINE>
<LINE>Which both thy duty owes and our power claims,</LINE>
<LINE>Or I will throw thee from my care forever</LINE>
<LINE>Into the staggers and the careless lapse</LINE>
<LINE>Of youth and ignorance; both my revenge and hate</LINE>
<LINE>Loosing upon thee, in the name of justice,</LINE>
<LINE>Without all terms of pity. Speak, thine answer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon, my gracious lord; for I submit</LINE>
<LINE>My fancy to your eyes. When I consider</LINE>
<LINE>What great creation and what dole of honor</LINE>
<LINE>Flies where you bid it, I find that she, which late</LINE>
<LINE>Was in my nobler thoughts most base, is now</LINE>
<LINE>The praised of the King, who so ennobled,</LINE>
<LINE>Is as &#8217;twere born so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Take her by the hand,</LINE>
<LINE>And tell her she is thine; to whom I promise</LINE>
<LINE>A counterpoise&#8212;if not to thy estate</LINE>
<LINE>A balance more replete.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I take her hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good fortune and the favor of the King</LINE>
<LINE>Smile upon this contract, whose ceremony</LINE>
<LINE>Shall seem expedient on the now-born brief,</LINE>
<LINE>And be perform&#8217;d tonight. The solemn feast</LINE>
<LINE>Shall more attend upon the coming space,</LINE>
<LINE>Expecting absent friends. As thou lov&#8217;st her,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy love&#8217;s to me religious; else, does err.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt. Lafew and Parolles stay behind, commenting of this wedding.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear, monsieur? A word with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your pleasure, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your lord and master did well to make his recantation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Recantation? My lord? My master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay; is it not a language I speak?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A most harsh one, and not to be understood without bloody succeeding. My master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you companion to the Count Roussillion?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To any count, to all counts: to what is man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To what is count&#8217;s man. Count&#8217;s master is of another style.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are too old, sir; let it satisfy you, you are too old.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must tell thee, sirrah, I write man; to which title age cannot bring thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What I dare too well do, I dare not do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did think thee, for two ordinaries, to be a pretty wise fellow. Thou didst make tolerable vent of thy travel; it might pass: yet the scarfs and the bannerets about thee did manifoldly dissuade me from believing thee a vessel of too great a burden. I have now found thee. When I lose thee again, I care not; yet art thou good for nothing but taking up, and that thou&#8217;rt scarce worth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hadst thou not the privilege of antiquity upon thee&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not plunge thyself too far in anger, lest thou hasten thy trial; which if&#8212;Lord have mercy on thee for a hen! So, my good window of lettice, fare thee well. Thy casement I need not open, for I look through thee. Give me thy hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, you give me most egregious indignity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, with all my heart, and thou art worthy of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have not, my lord, deserv&#8217;d it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, good faith, ev&#8217;ry dram of it, and I will not bate thee a scruple.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I shall be wiser.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ev&#8217;n as soon as thou canst, for thou hast to pull at a smack a&#8217; th&#8217; contrary. If ever thou be&#8217;st bound in thy scarf and beaten, thou shall find what it is to be proud of thy bondage. I have a desire to hold my acquaintance with thee, or rather my knowledge, that I may say in the default, &#8220;He is a man I know.&#8221;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, you do me most insupportable vexation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would it were hell-pains for thy sake, and my poor doing eternal; for doing I am past, as I will by thee, in what motion age will give me leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, thou hast a son shall take this disgrace off me, scurvy, old, filthy, scurvy lord! Well, I must be patient, there is no fettering of authority. I&#8217;ll beat him, by my life, if I can meet him with any convenience, and he were double and double a lord. I&#8217;ll have no more pity of his age than I would have of&#8212;I&#8217;ll beat him, and if I could but meet him again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Lafew.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sirrah, your lord and master&#8217;s married, there&#8217;s news for you. You have a new mistress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I most unfeignedly beseech your lordship to make some reservation of your wrongs. He is my good lord; whom I serve above is my master.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who? God?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The devil it is that&#8217;s thy master. Why dost thou garter up thy arms a&#8217; this fashion? Dost make hose of thy sleeves? Do other servants so? Thou wert best set thy lower part where thy nose stands. By mine honor, if I were but two hours younger, I&#8217;d beat thee. Methink&#8217;st thou art a general offense, and every man should beat thee. I think thou wast created for men to breathe themselves upon thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is hard and undeserv&#8217;d measure, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to, sir, you were beaten in Italy for picking a kernel out of a pomegranate. You are a vagabond and no true traveller. You are more saucy with lords and honorable personages than the commission of your birth and virtue gives you heraldry. You are not worth another word, else I&#8217;d call you knave. I leave you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Bertram Count Roussillion.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good, very good, it is so then. Good, very good, let it be conceal&#8217;d awhile.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Undone, and forfeited to cares forever!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s the matter, sweet heart?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Although before the solemn priest I have sworn,</LINE>
<LINE>I will not bed her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, what, sweet heart?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my Parolles, they have married me!</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll to the Tuscan wars, and never bed her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>France is a dog-hole, and it no more merits</LINE>
<LINE>The tread of a man&#8217;s foot. To th&#8217; wars!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There&#8217;s letters from my mother; what th&#8217; import is,</LINE>
<LINE>I know not yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, that would be known. To th&#8217; wars, my boy, to th&#8217; wars!</LINE>
<LINE>He wears his honor in a box unseen,</LINE>
<LINE>That hugs his kicky-wicky here at home,</LINE>
<LINE>Spending his manly marrow in her arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Which should sustain the bound and high curvet</LINE>
<LINE>Of Mars&#8217;s fiery steed. To other regions!</LINE>
<LINE>France is a stable, we that dwell in&#8217;t jades,</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore to th&#8217; war!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be so. I&#8217;ll send her to my house,</LINE>
<LINE>Acquaint my mother with my hate to her,</LINE>
<LINE>And wherefore I am fled; write to the King</LINE>
<LINE>That which I durst not speak. His present gift</LINE>
<LINE>Shall furnish me to those Italian fields</LINE>
<LINE>Where noble fellows strike. Wars is no strife</LINE>
<LINE>To the dark house and the detested wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will this capriccio hold in thee, art sure?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go with me to my chamber, and advise me.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll send her straight away. Tomorrow,</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll to the wars, she to her single sorrow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, these balls bound, there&#8217;s noise in it. &#8217;Tis hard!</LINE>
<LINE>A young man married is a man that&#8217;s marr&#8217;d;</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore away, and leave her bravely; go.</LINE>
<LINE>The King has done you wrong; but hush, &#8217;tis so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 4</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Paris. The King&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Helena, Clown, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helena and Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My mother greets me kindly. Is she well?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is not well, but yet she has her health. She&#8217;s very merry, but yet she is not well; but thanks be given, she&#8217;s very well, and wants nothing i&#8217; th&#8217; world; but yet she is not well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If she be very well, what does she ail that she&#8217;s not very well?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, she&#8217;s very well indeed, but for two things.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What two things?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One, that she&#8217;s not in heaven, whither God send her quickly! The other, that she&#8217;s in earth, from whence God send her quickly!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bless you, my fortunate lady!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope, sir, I have your good will to have mine own good fortunes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You had my prayers to lead them on, and to keep them on, have them still. O, my knave, how does my old lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So that you had her wrinkles and I her money, I would she did as you say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, I say nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, you are the wiser man; for many a man&#8217;s tongue shakes out his master&#8217;s undoing. To say nothing, to do nothing, to know nothing, and to have nothing, is to be a great part of your title, which is within a very little of nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, th&#8217; art a knave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You should have said, sir, &#8220;Before a knave th&#8217; art a knave,&#8221; that&#8217;s &#8220;Before me th&#8217; art a knave.&#8221; This had been truth, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to, thou art a witty fool, I have found thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did you find me in yourself, sir,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Parolles nods.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>or were you taught to find me?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Parolles shakes his head.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The search, sir, was profitable, and much fool may you find in you, even to the world&#8217;s pleasure and the increase of laughter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A good knave, i&#8217; faith, and well fed.</LINE>
<LINE>Madam, my lord will go away tonight,</LINE>
<LINE>A very serious business calls on him.</LINE>
<LINE>The great prerogative and rite of love,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, as your due, time claims, he does acknowledge,</LINE>
<LINE>But puts it off to a compell&#8217;d restraint;</LINE>
<LINE>Whose want, and whose delay, is strew&#8217;d with sweets,</LINE>
<LINE>Which they distill now in the curbed time,</LINE>
<LINE>To make the coming hour  o&#8217;erflow with joy,</LINE>
<LINE>And pleasure drown the brim.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">What&#8217;s his will else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That you will take your instant leave a&#8217; th&#8217; King,</LINE>
<LINE>And make this haste as your own good proceeding,</LINE>
<LINE>Strength&#8217;ned with what apology you think</LINE>
<LINE>May make it probable need.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What more commands he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That having this obtain&#8217;d, you presently</LINE>
<LINE>Attend his further pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In every thing I wait upon his will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall report it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I pray you. Come, sirrah.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 5</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Paris. The King&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Lafew, Bertram, Parolles, Helena)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Lafew and Bertram.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I hope your lordship thinks not him a soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, my lord, and of very valiant approof.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have it from his own deliverance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And by other warranted testimony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then my dial goes not true. I took this lark for a bunting.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do assure you, my lord, he is very great in knowledge, and accordingly valiant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have then sinn&#8217;d against his experience, and transgress&#8217;d against his valor, and my state that way is dangerous, since I cannot yet find in my heart to repent. Here he comes. I pray you make us friends, I will pursue the amity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Bertram.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>These things shall be done, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, sir, who&#8217;s his tailor?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, I know him well, I, sir, he, sir, &#8217;s a good workman, a very good tailor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside to Parolles.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Is she gone to the King?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will she away tonight?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As You&#8217;ll have her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have writ my letters, casketed my treasure,</LINE>
<LINE>Given order for our horses, and tonight,</LINE>
<LINE>When I should take possession of the bride,</LINE>
<LINE>End ere I do begin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A good traveller is something at the latter end of a dinner, but one that lies three thirds, and uses a known truth to pass a thousand nothings with, should be once heard and thrice beaten. God save you, captain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is there any unkindness between my lord and you, monsieur?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not how I have deserv&#8217;d to run into my lord&#8217;s displeasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have made shift to run into&#8217;t, boots and spurs and all, like him that leapt into the custard; and out of it You&#8217;ll run again, rather than suffer question for your residence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It may be you have mistaken him, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And shall do so ever, though I took him at &#8217;s prayers. Fare you well, my lord, and believe this of me: there can be no kernel in this light nut; the soul of this man is his clothes. Trust him not in matter of heavy consequence; I have kept of them tame, and know their natures. Farewell, monsieur, I have spoken better of you than you have or will to deserve at my hand, but we must do good against evil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An idle lord, I swear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, do you not know him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, I do know him well, and common speech</LINE>
<LINE>Gives him a worthy pass. Here comes my clog.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helena.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have, sir, as I was commanded from you,</LINE>
<LINE>Spoke with the King, and have procur&#8217;d his leave</LINE>
<LINE>For present parting; only he desires</LINE>
<LINE>Some private speech with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">I shall obey his will.</LINE>
<LINE>You must not marvel, Helen, at my course,</LINE>
<LINE>Which holds not color with the time, nor does</LINE>
<LINE>The ministration and required office</LINE>
<LINE>On my particular. Prepar&#8217;d I was not</LINE>
<LINE>For such a business; therefore am I found</LINE>
<LINE>So much unsettled. This drives me to entreat you</LINE>
<LINE>That presently you take your way for home,</LINE>
<LINE>And rather muse than ask why I entreat you,</LINE>
<LINE>For my respects are better than they seem,</LINE>
<LINE>And my appointments have in them a need</LINE>
<LINE>Greater than shows itself at the first view</LINE>
<LINE>To you that know them not. This to my mother.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Giving a letter.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>&#8217;Twill be two days ere I shall see you, so</LINE>
<LINE>I leave you to your wisdom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Sir, I can nothing say,</LINE>
<LINE>But that I am your most obedient servant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, no more of that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">And ever shall</LINE>
<LINE>With true observance seek to eke out that</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein toward me my homely stars have fail&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>To equal my great fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Let that go.</LINE>
<LINE>My haste is very great. Farewell; hie home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, sir, your pardon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Well, what would you say?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not worthy of the wealth I owe,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor dare I say &#8217;tis mine; and yet it is;</LINE>
<LINE>But like a timorous thief, most fain would steal</LINE>
<LINE>What law does vouch mine own.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">What would you have?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Something, and scarce so much; nothing indeed.</LINE>
<LINE>I would not tell you what I would, my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>Faith, yes:</LINE>
<LINE>Strangers and foes do sunder, and not kiss.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you stay not, but in haste to horse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall not break your bidding, good my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where are my other men, monsieur?&#8212;Farewell.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Helena.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Go thou toward home, where I will never come</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst I can shake my sword or hear the drum.</LINE>
<LINE>Away, and for our flight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bravely, coraggio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 3</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. The Duke&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Duke of Florence, two French Lords, troop of soldiers)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Enter the Duke of Florence, the two French Lords, with a troop of soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So that from point to point now have you heard</LINE>
<LINE>The fundamental reasons of this war,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose great decision hath much blood let forth</LINE>
<LINE>And more thirsts after.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Holy seems the quarrel</LINE>
<LINE>Upon your Grace&#8217;s part; black and fearful</LINE>
<LINE>On the opposer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore we marvel much our cousin France</LINE>
<LINE>Would in so just a business shut his bosom</LINE>
<LINE>Against our borrowing prayers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>The reasons of our state I cannot yield</LINE>
<LINE>But like a common and an outward man</LINE>
<LINE>That the great figure of a council frames</LINE>
<LINE>By self-unable motion, therefore dare not</LINE>
<LINE>Say what I think of it, since I have found</LINE>
<LINE>Myself in my incertain grounds to fail</LINE>
<LINE>As often as I guess&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Be it his pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I am sure the younger of our nature,</LINE>
<LINE>That surfeit on their ease, will day by day</LINE>
<LINE>Come here for physic.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Welcome shall they be;</LINE>
<LINE>And all the honors that can fly from us</LINE>
<LINE>Shall on them settle.&#8212;You know your places well;</LINE>
<LINE>When better fall, for your avails they fell.</LINE>
<LINE>Tomorrow to th&#8217; field.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Countess, Clown, Helen, two French Lords)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Countess and Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It hath happen&#8217;d all as I would have had it, save that he comes not along with her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my troth, I take my young lord to be a very melancholy man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By what observance, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, he will look upon his boot and sing, mend the ruff and sing, ask questions and sing, pick his teeth and sing. I know a man that had this trick of melancholy sold a goodly manor for a song.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me see what he writes, and when he means to come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Opening a letter.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have no mind to Isbel since I was at court. Our old ling and our Isbels a&#8217; th&#8217; country are nothing like your old ling and your Isbels a&#8217; th&#8217; court. The brains of my Cupid&#8217;s knock&#8217;d out, and I begin to love, as an old man loves money, with no stomach.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What have we here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>E&#8217;en that you have there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads a letter.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;I have sent you a daughter-in-law; she hath recover&#8217;d the King, and undone me. I have wedded her, not bedded her, and sworn to make the &#8220;not&#8221; eternal. You shall hear I am run away; know it before the report come. If there be breadth enough in the world, I will hold a long distance. My duty to you.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Your unfortunate son, Bertram.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE>This is not well, rash and unbridled boy,</LINE>
<LINE>To fly the favors of so good a king,</LINE>
<LINE>To pluck his indignation on thy head</LINE>
<LINE>By the misprising of a maid too virtuous</LINE>
<LINE>For the contempt of empire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O madam, yonder is heavy news within between two soldiers and my young lady!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, there is some comfort in the news, some comfort. Your son will not be kill&#8217;d so soon as I thought he would.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why should he be kill&#8217;d?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So say I, madam, if he run away, as I hear he does. The danger is in standing to&#8217;t; that&#8217;s the loss of men, though it be the getting of children. Here they come will tell you more; for my part, I only hear your son was run away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen and two French Lords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Save you, good madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, my lord is gone, forever gone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not say so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think upon patience. Pray you, gentlemen,</LINE>
<LINE>I have felt so many quirks of joy and grief</LINE>
<LINE>That the first face of neither on the start</LINE>
<LINE>Can woman me unto&#8217;t. Where is my son, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, he&#8217;s gone to serve the Duke of Florence.</LINE>
<LINE>We met him thitherward, for thence we came;</LINE>
<LINE>And after some dispatch in hand at court,</LINE>
<LINE>Thither we bend again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look on his letter, madam, here&#8217;s my passport.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;When thou canst get the ring upon my finger, which never shall come off, and show me a child begotten of thy body that I am father to, then call me husband; but in such a &#8216;then&#8217; I write a &#8216;never.&#8217;&#8221; This is a dreadful sentence.</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brought you this letter, gentlemen?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Ay, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>And for the contents&#8217; sake are sorry for our pains.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee, lady, have a better cheer;</LINE>
<LINE>If thou engrossest all the griefs are thine,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou robb&#8217;st me of a moi&#8217;ty. He was my son,</LINE>
<LINE>But I do wash his name out of my blood,</LINE>
<LINE>And thou art all my child. Towards Florence is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">And to be a soldier?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Such is his noble purpose, and believe&#8217;t,</LINE>
<LINE>The Duke will lay upon him all the honor</LINE>
<LINE>That good convenience claims.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Return you thither?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, madam, with the swiftest wing of speed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;Till I have no wife, I have nothing in France.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis bitter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="2">Find you that there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Ay, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis but the boldness of his hand haply,</LINE>
<LINE>Which his heart was not consenting to.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing in France, until he have no wife!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s nothing here that is too good for him</LINE>
<LINE>But only she, and she deserves a lord</LINE>
<LINE>That twenty such rude boys might tend upon,</LINE>
<LINE>And call her hourly mistress. Who was with him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A servant only, and a gentleman</LINE>
<LINE>Which I have sometime known.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Parolles, was it not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, my good lady, he.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A very tainted fellow, and full of wickedness.</LINE>
<LINE>My son corrupts a well-derived nature</LINE>
<LINE>With his inducement.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Indeed, good lady,</LINE>
<LINE>The fellow has a deal of that too much,</LINE>
<LINE>Which holds him much to have.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Y&#8217; are welcome, gentlemen.</LINE>
<LINE>I will entreat you, when you see my son,</LINE>
<LINE>To tell him that his sword can never win</LINE>
<LINE>The honor that he loses. More I&#8217;ll entreat you</LINE>
<LINE>Written to bear along.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">We serve you, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>In that and all your worthiest affairs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not so, but as we change our courtesies.</LINE>
<LINE>Will you draw near?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit with Lords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8220;Till I have no wife, I have nothing in France.&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>Nothing in France, until he has no wife!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou shalt have none, Roussillion, none in France;</LINE>
<LINE>Then hast thou all again. Poor lord, is&#8217;t I</LINE>
<LINE>That chase thee from thy country, and expose</LINE>
<LINE>Those tender limbs of thine to the event</LINE>
<LINE>Of the none-sparing war? And is it I</LINE>
<LINE>That drive thee from the sportive court, where thou</LINE>
<LINE>Wast shot at with fair eyes, to be the mark</LINE>
<LINE>Of smoky muskets? O you leaden messengers,</LINE>
<LINE>That ride upon the violent speed of fire,</LINE>
<LINE>Fly with false aim, move the still-peering air</LINE>
<LINE>That sings with piercing, do not touch my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>Whoever shoots at him, I set him there;</LINE>
<LINE>Whoever charges on his forward breast,</LINE>
<LINE>I am the caitiff that do hold him to&#8217;t;</LINE>
<LINE>And though I kill him not, I am the cause</LINE>
<LINE>His death was so effected. Better &#8217;twere</LINE>
<LINE>I met the ravin lion when he roar&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>With sharp constraint of hunger; better &#8217;twere</LINE>
<LINE>That all the miseries which nature owes</LINE>
<LINE>Were mine at once. No, come thou home, Roussillion,</LINE>
<LINE>Whence honor but of danger wins a scar,</LINE>
<LINE>As oft it loses all. I will be gone.</LINE>
<LINE>My being here it is that holds thee hence.</LINE>
<LINE>Shall I stay here to do&#8217;t? No, no, although</LINE>
<LINE>The air of paradise did fan the house,</LINE>
<LINE>And angels offic&#8217;d all. I will be gone,</LINE>
<LINE>That pitiful rumor may report my flight</LINE>
<LINE>To consolate thine ear. Come night, end day!</LINE>
<LINE>For with the dark, poor thief, I&#8217;ll steal away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. Before the Duke&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Duke of Florence, Bertram Count of Roussillion, Soldiers, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Enter the Duke of Florence, Bertram Count of Roussillion, Drum and Trumpets, Soldiers, Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The general of our horse thou art, and we,</LINE>
<LINE>Great in our hope, lay our best love and credence</LINE>
<LINE>Upon thy promising fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Sir, it is</LINE>
<LINE>A charge too heavy for my strength, but yet</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll strive to bear it for your worthy sake</LINE>
<LINE>To th&#8217; extreme edge of hazard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Then go thou forth,</LINE>
<LINE>And Fortune play upon thy prosperous helm</LINE>
<LINE>As thy auspicious mistress!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">This very day,</LINE>
<LINE>Great Mars, I put myself into thy file;</LINE>
<LINE>Make me but like my thoughts, and I shall prove</LINE>
<LINE>A lover of thy drum, hater of love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt omnes.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 4</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Countess, Steward Rinaldo)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Countess and Steward Rinaldo.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas! And would you take the letter of her?</LINE>
<LINE>Might you not know she would do as she has done</LINE>
<LINE>By sending me a letter? Read it again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Reads letter.</LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;I am Saint Jaques&#8217; pilgrim, thither gone.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Ambitious love hath so in me offended</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>That barefoot plod I the cold ground upon</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>With sainted vow my faults to have amended.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Write, write, that from the bloody course of war</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>My dearest master, your dear son, may hie.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Bless him at home in peace, whilst I from far</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>His name with zealous fervor sanctify.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>His taken labors bid him me forgive;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>I, his despiteful Juno, sent him forth</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>From courtly friends, with camping foes to live,</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Where death and danger dogs the heels of worth.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>He is too good and fair for death and me,</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Whom I myself embrace to set him free.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, what sharp stings are in her mildest words!</LINE>
<LINE>Rinaldo, you did never lack advice so much</LINE>
<LINE>As letting her pass so. Had I spoke with her,</LINE>
<LINE>I could have well diverted her intents,</LINE>
<LINE>Which thus she hath prevented.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STEW.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Pardon me, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>If I had given you this at overnight,</LINE>
<LINE>She might have been  o&#8217;erta&#8217;en; and yet she writes,</LINE>
<LINE>Pursuit would be but vain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What angel shall</LINE>
<LINE>Bless this unworthy husband? He cannot thrive,</LINE>
<LINE>Unless her prayers, whom heaven delights to hear</LINE>
<LINE>And loves to grant, reprieve him from the wrath</LINE>
<LINE>Of greatest justice. Write, write, Rinaldo,</LINE>
<LINE>To this unworthy husband of his wife.</LINE>
<LINE>Let every word weigh heavy of her worth,</LINE>
<LINE>That he does weigh too light. My greatest grief,</LINE>
<LINE>Though little he do feel it, set down sharply.</LINE>
<LINE>Dispatch the most convenient messenger.</LINE>
<LINE>When haply he shall hear that she is gone,</LINE>
<LINE>He will return, and hope I may that she,</LINE>
<LINE>Hearing so much, will speed her foot again,</LINE>
<LINE>Led hither by pure love. Which of them both</LINE>
<LINE>Is dearest to me, I have no skill in sense</LINE>
<LINE>To make distinction. Provide this messenger.</LINE>
<LINE>My heart is heavy, and mine age is weak;</LINE>
<LINE>Grief would have tears, and sorrow bids me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 5</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. Without the walls. A tucket far off.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Widow of Florence, her daughter, Diana, Violenta, Mariana, Citizens, Helen, Bertram Count Roussillion, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>A tucket afar off. Enter old Widow of Florence, her daughter, Diana, Violenta, and Mariana, with other Citizens.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, come, for if they do approach the city, we shall lose all the sight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They say the French count has done most honorable service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is reported that he has taken their great&#8217;st commander, and that with his own hand he slew the Duke&#8217;s brother. Tucket. We have lost our labor, they are gone a contrary way. Hark! You may know by their trumpets.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, let&#8217;s return again and suffice ourselves with the report of it. Well, Diana, take heed of this French earl. The honor of a maid is her name, and no legacy is so rich as honesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have told my neighbor how you have been solicited by a gentleman his companion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know that knave, hang him! One Parolles, a filthy officer he is in those suggestions for the young earl. Beware of them, Diana; their promises, enticements, oaths, tokens, and all these engines of lust, are not the things they go under. Many a maid hath been seduc&#8217;d by them, and the misery is, example, that so terrible shows in the wrack of maidenhood, cannot for all that dissuade succession, but that they are lim&#8217;d with the twigs that threatens them. I hope I need not to advise you further, but I hope your own grace will keep you where you are, though there were no further danger known but the modesty which is so lost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall not need to fear me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen habited like a pilgrim.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope so. Look here comes a pilgrim. I know she will lie at my house; thither they send one another. I&#8217;ll question her. God save you, pilgrim, whither are bound?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To Saint Jaques le Grand.</LINE>
<LINE>Where do the palmers lodge, I do beseech you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At the Saint Francis here beside the port.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this the way?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A march afar.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, marry, is&#8217;t. Hark you, they come this way.</LINE>
<LINE>If you will tarry, holy pilgrim,</LINE>
<LINE>But till the troops come by,</LINE>
<LINE>I will conduct you where you shall be lodg&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>The rather for I think I know your hostess</LINE>
<LINE>As ample as myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Is it yourself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you shall please so, pilgrim.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank you, and will stay upon your leisure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You came I think from France?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">I did so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here you shall see a countryman of yours</LINE>
<LINE>That has done worthy service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">His name, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Count Roussillion. Know you such a one?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But by the ear, that hears most nobly of him.</LINE>
<LINE>His face I know not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Whatsome&#8217;er he is,</LINE>
<LINE>He&#8217;s bravely taken here. He stole from France,</LINE>
<LINE>As &#8217;tis reported, for the King had married him</LINE>
<LINE>Against his liking. Think you it is so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, surely, mere the truth, I know his lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is a gentleman that serves the Count</LINE>
<LINE>Reports but coarsely of her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What&#8217;s his name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Monsieur Parolles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">O, I believe with him.</LINE>
<LINE>In argument of praise, or to the worth</LINE>
<LINE>Of the great Count himself, she is too mean</LINE>
<LINE>To have her name repeated. All her deserving</LINE>
<LINE>Is a reserved honesty, and that</LINE>
<LINE>I have not heard examin&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Alas, poor lady,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis a hard bondage to become the wife</LINE>
<LINE>Of a detesting lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I warr&#8217;nt, good creature, wheresoe&#8217;er she is,</LINE>
<LINE>Her heart weighs sadly. This young maid might do her</LINE>
<LINE>A shrewd turn, if she pleas&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">How do you mean?</LINE>
<LINE>May be the amorous Count solicits her</LINE>
<LINE>In the unlawful purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">He does indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>And brokes with all that can in such a suit</LINE>
<LINE>Corrupt the tender honor of a maid.</LINE>
<LINE>But she is arm&#8217;d for him, and keeps her guard</LINE>
<LINE>In honestest defense.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Drum and Colors. Enter (Bertram) Count Roussillion, Parolles, and the whole army.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">The gods forbid else!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, now they come.</LINE>
<LINE>That is Antonio, the Duke&#8217;s eldest son,</LINE>
<LINE>That, Escalus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">Which is the Frenchman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="8">He,</LINE>
<LINE>That with the plume; &#8217;tis a most gallant fellow.</LINE>
<LINE>I would he lov&#8217;d his wife. If he were honester</LINE>
<LINE>He were much goodlier. Is&#8217;t not a handsome gentleman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I like him well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis pity he is not honest. Yond&#8217;s that same knave</LINE>
<LINE>That leads him to these places. Were I his lady,</LINE>
<LINE>I would poison that vile rascal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Which is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That jack-an-apes with scarfs. Why is he melancholy?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Perchance he&#8217;s hurt i&#8217; th&#8217; battle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lose our drum! Well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s shrewdly vex&#8217;d at something. Look, he has spied us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, hang you!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And your courtesy, for a ring-carrier!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Bertram, Parolles, and army.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The troop is past. Come, pilgrim, I will bring you</LINE>
<LINE>Where you shall host. Of enjoin&#8217;d penitents</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s four or five, to great Saint Jaques bound,</LINE>
<LINE>Already at my house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I humbly thank you.</LINE>
<LINE>Please it this matron and this gentle maid</LINE>
<LINE>To eat with us tonight, the charge and thanking</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be for me, and to requite you further,</LINE>
<LINE>I will bestow some precepts of this virgin</LINE>
<LINE>Worthy the note.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BOTH. MAR. AND WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">We&#8217;ll take your offer kindly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 6</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Camp before Florence.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Bertram Count Roussillion, two French Lords, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter (Bertram) Count Roussillion and the two French Lords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, good my lord, put him to&#8217;t; let him have his way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If your lordship find him not a hilding, hold me no more in your respect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On my life, my lord, a bubble.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you think I am so far deceiv&#8217;d in him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Believe it, my lord, in mine own direct knowledge, without any malice, but to speak of him as my kinsman, he&#8217;s a most notable coward, an infinite and endless liar, an hourly promise-breaker, the owner of no one good quality worthy your lordship&#8217;s entertainment.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were fit you knew him, lest reposing too far in his virtue, which he hath not, he might at some great and trusty business in a main danger fail you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I knew in what particular action to try him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None better than to let him fetch off his drum, which you hear him so confidently undertake to do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I, with a troop of Florentines, will suddenly surprise him; such I will have, whom I am sure he knows not from the enemy. We will bind and hoodwink him so, that he shall suppose no other but that he is carried into the leaguer of the adversaries, when we bring him to our own tents. Be but your lordship present at his examination, if he do not, for the promise of his life, and in the highest compulsion of base fear, offer to betray you, and deliver all the intelligence in his power against you, and that with the divine forfeit of his soul upon oath, never trust my judgment in any thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, for the love of laughter, let him fetch his drum; he says he has a stratagem for&#8217;t. When your lordship sees the bottom of his success in&#8217;t, and to what metal this counterfeit lump of ore will be melted, if you give him not John Drum&#8217;s entertainment, your inclining cannot be remov&#8217;d. Here he comes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, for the love of laughter, hinder not the honor of his design. Let him fetch off his drum in any hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, monsieur? This drum sticks sorely in your disposition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A pox on&#8217;t, let it go, &#8217;tis but a drum.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But a drum! Is&#8217;t but a drum? A drum so lost! There was excellent command&#8212;to charge in with our horse upon our own wings, and to rend our own soldiers!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That was not to be blam&#8217;d in the command of the service; it was a disaster of war that Caesar himself could not have prevented, if he had been there to command.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, we cannot greatly condemn our success. Some dishonor we had in the loss of that drum, but it is not to be recover&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It might have been recover&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It might, but it is not now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is to be recover&#8217;d. But that the merit of service is seldom attributed to the true and exact performer, I would have that drum or another, or hic jacet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, if you have a stomach, to&#8217;t, <FRENCH lang="fr">monsieur</FRENCH>: if you think your mystery in stratagem can bring this instrument of honor again into his native quarter, be magnanimious in the enterprise and go on; I will grace the attempt for a worthy exploit. If you speed well in it, the Duke shall both speak of it, and extend to you what further becomes his greatness, even to the utmost syllable of your worthiness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By the hand of a soldier, I will undertake it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But you must not now slumber in it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll about it this evening, and I will presently pen down my dilemmas, encourage myself in my certainty, put myself into my mortal preparation; and by midnight look to hear further from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May I be bold to acquaint his Grace you are gone about it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not what the success will be, my lord, but the attempt I vow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know th&#8217; art valiant, and to the possibility of thy soldiership will subscribe for thee. Farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I love not many words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more than a fish loves water. Is not this a strange fellow, my lord, that so confidently seems to undertake this business, which he knows is not to be done, damns himself to do, and dares better be damn&#8217;d than to do&#8217;t?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You do not know him, my lord, as we do. Certain it is that he will steal himself into a man&#8217;s favor, and for a week escape a great deal of discoveries, but when you find him out, you have him ever after.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, do you think he will make no deed at all of this that so seriously he does address himself unto?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None in the world, but return with an invention, and clap upon you two or three probable lies. But we have almost emboss&#8217;d him, you shall see his fall tonight; for indeed he is not for your lordship&#8217;s respect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll make you some sport with the fox ere we case him. He was first smok&#8217;d by the old Lord Lafew. When his disguise and he is parted, tell me what a sprat you shall find him, which you shall see this very night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must go look my twigs. He shall be caught.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your brother he shall go along with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As&#8217;t please your lordship. I&#8217;ll leave you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now will I lead you to the house, and show you</LINE>
<LINE>The lass I spoke of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">But you say she&#8217;s honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That&#8217;s all the fault. I spoke with her but once,</LINE>
<LINE>And found her wondrous cold, but I sent to her,</LINE>
<LINE>By this same coxcomb that we have i&#8217; th&#8217; wind,</LINE>
<LINE>Tokens and letters which she did re-send,</LINE>
<LINE>And this is all I have done. She&#8217;s a fair creature;</LINE>
<LINE>Will you go see her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">With all my heart, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 7</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. The widow&#8217;s house.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Helen, Widow)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen and Widow.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you misdoubt me that I am not she,</LINE>
<LINE>I know not how I shall assure you further</LINE>
<LINE>But I shall lose the grounds I work upon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though my estate be fall&#8217;n, I was well born,</LINE>
<LINE>Nothing acquainted with these businesses,</LINE>
<LINE>And would not put my reputation now</LINE>
<LINE>In any staining act.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Nor would I wish you.</LINE>
<LINE>First give me trust, the Count he is my husband,</LINE>
<LINE>And what to your sworn counsel I have spoken</LINE>
<LINE>Is so from word to word; and then you cannot,</LINE>
<LINE>By the good aid that I of you shall borrow,</LINE>
<LINE>Err in bestowing it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I should believe you,</LINE>
<LINE>For you have show&#8217;d me that which well approves</LINE>
<LINE>Y&#8217; are great in fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Take this purse of gold,</LINE>
<LINE>And let me buy your friendly help thus far,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I will over-pay and pay again</LINE>
<LINE>When I have found it. The Count he woos your daughter,</LINE>
<LINE>Lays down his wanton siege before her beauty,</LINE>
<LINE>Resolv&#8217;d to carry her. Let her in fine consent,</LINE>
<LINE>As we&#8217;ll direct her how &#8217;tis best to bear it.</LINE>
<LINE>Now his important blood will nought deny</LINE>
<LINE>That she&#8217;ll demand. A ring the County wears,</LINE>
<LINE>That downward hath succeeded in his house</LINE>
<LINE>From son to son, some four or five descents,</LINE>
<LINE>Since the first father wore it. This ring he holds</LINE>
<LINE>In most rich choice; yet in his idle fire,</LINE>
<LINE>To buy his will, it would not seem too dear,</LINE>
<LINE>Howe&#8217;er repented after.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Now I see</LINE>
<LINE>The bottom of your purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You see it lawful then. It is no more</LINE>
<LINE>But that your daughter, ere she seems as won,</LINE>
<LINE>Desires this ring; appoints him an encounter;</LINE>
<LINE>In fine, delivers me to fill the time,</LINE>
<LINE>Herself most chastely absent. After,</LINE>
<LINE>To marry her, I&#8217;ll add three thousand crowns</LINE>
<LINE>To what is pass&#8217;d already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I have yielded.</LINE>
<LINE>Instruct my daughter how she shall persever,</LINE>
<LINE>That time and place with this deceit so lawful</LINE>
<LINE>May prove coherent. Every night he comes</LINE>
<LINE>With musics of all sorts, and songs compos&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>To her unworthiness. It nothing steads us</LINE>
<LINE>To chide him from our eaves, for he persists</LINE>
<LINE>As if his life lay on&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Why then tonight</LINE>
<LINE>Let us assay our plot, which if it speed,</LINE>
<LINE>Is wicked meaning in a lawful deed,</LINE>
<LINE>And lawful meaning in a lawful act,</LINE>
<LINE>Where both not sin, and yet a sinful fact.</LINE>
<LINE>But let&#8217;s about it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 4</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Without the Florentine camp.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(French Lord, Soldiers, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Second French Lord with five or six other Soldiers in ambush.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He can come no other way but by this hedge-corner. When you sally upon him, speak what terrible language you will. Though you understand it not yourselves, no matter; for we must not seem to understand him, unless some one among us, whom we must produce for an interpreter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good captain, let me be th&#8217; interpreter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Art not acquainted with him? Knows he not thy voice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, sir, I warrant you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But what linsey-woolsey hast thou to speak to us again?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>E&#8217;en such as you speak to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He must think us some band of strangers i&#8217; th&#8217; adversary&#8217;s entertainment. Now he hath a smack of all neighboring languages; therefore we must every one be a man of his own fancy, not to know what we speak one to another; so we seem to know, is to know straight our purpose: choughs&#8217; language, gabble enough, and good enough. As for you, interpreter, you must seem very politic. But couch ho, here he comes, to beguile two hours in a sleep, and then to return and swear the lies he forges.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They stand aside. Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ten a&#8217; clock: within these three hours &#8217;twill be time enough to go home. What shall I say I have done? It must be a very plausive invention that carries it. They begin to smoke me, and disgraces have of late knock&#8217;d too often at my door. I find my tongue is too foolhardy, but my heart hath the fear of Mars before it, and of his creatures, not daring the reports of my tongue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This is the first truth that e&#8217;er thine own tongue was guilty of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What the devil should move me to undertake the recovery of this drum, being not ignorant of the impossibility, and knowing I had no such purpose? I must give myself some hurts, and say I got them in exploit. Yet slight ones will not carry it. They will say, &#8220;Came you off with so little?&#8221; And great ones I dare not give; wherefore what&#8217;s the instance? Tongue, I must put you into a butter-woman&#8217;s mouth and buy myself another of Bajazeth&#8217;s mule, if you prattle me into these perils.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Is it possible he should know what he is, and be that he is?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would the cutting of my garments would serve the turn, or the breaking of my Spanish sword.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>We cannot afford you so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or the baring of my beard, and to say it was in stratagem.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>&#8217;Twould not do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or to drown my clothes, and say I was stripp&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hardly serve.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though I swore I leapt from the window of the citadel&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How deep?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thirty fathom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Three great oaths would scarce make that be believ&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I had any drum of the enemy&#8217;s. I would swear I recover&#8217;d it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You shall hear one anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A drum now of the enemy&#8217;s&#8212;</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum within.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Throca movousus, cargo, cargo, cargo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, ransom, ransom!</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>They seize him.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Do not hide mine eyes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They blindfold him.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Boskos thromuldo boskos.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know you are the Muskos&#8217; regiment,</LINE>
<LINE>And I shall lose my life for want of language.</LINE>
<LINE>If there be here German, or Dane, Low Dutch,</LINE>
<LINE>Italian, or French, let him speak to me,</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll discover that which shall undo the Florentine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Boskos vauvado. I understand thee, and can speak thy tongue. Kerelybonto, sir, betake thee to thy faith, for seventeen poniards are at thy bosom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, pray, pray, pray! Manka revania dulche.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oscorbidulchos volivorco.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The general is content to spare thee yet,</LINE>
<LINE>And hoodwink&#8217;d as thou art, will lead thee on</LINE>
<LINE>To gather from thee. Haply thou mayst inform</LINE>
<LINE>Something to save thy life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, let me live,</LINE>
<LINE>And all the secrets of our camp I&#8217;ll show,</LINE>
<LINE>Their force, their purposes; nay, I&#8217;ll speak that</LINE>
<LINE>Which you will wonder at.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">But wilt thou faithfully?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I do not, damn me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Acordo linta.</LINE>
<LINE>Come on, thou art granted space,</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit with Parolles guarded.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>A short alarum within.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go tell the Count Roussillion, and my brother,</LINE>
<LINE>We have caught the woodcock, and will keep him muffled</LINE>
<LINE>Till we do hear from them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Captain, I will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;A will betray us all unto ourselves:</LINE>
<LINE>Inform on that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">So I will, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Till then I&#8217;ll keep him dark and safely lock&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. The widow&#8217;s house.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Bertram, Diana)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Bertram and the maid called Diana.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They told me that your name was Fontibell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, my good lord, Diana.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Titled goddess,</LINE>
<LINE>And worth it, with addition! But, fair soul,</LINE>
<LINE>In your fine frame hath love no quality?</LINE>
<LINE>If the quick fire of youth light not your mind,</LINE>
<LINE>You are no maiden, but a monument.</LINE>
<LINE>When you are dead, you should be such a one</LINE>
<LINE>As you are now; for you are cold and stern,</LINE>
<LINE>And now you should be as your mother was</LINE>
<LINE>When your sweet self was got.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She then was honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">So should you be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="8">No;</LINE>
<LINE>My mother did but duty, such, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>As you owe to your wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">No more a&#8217; that.</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee do not strive against my vows.</LINE>
<LINE>I was compell&#8217;d to her, but I love thee</LINE>
<LINE>By love&#8217;s own sweet constraint, and will forever</LINE>
<LINE>Do thee all rights of service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Ay, so you serve us</LINE>
<LINE>Till we serve you; but when you have our roses,</LINE>
<LINE>You barely leave our thorns to prick ourselves,</LINE>
<LINE>And mock us with our bareness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">How have I sworn!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis not the many oaths that makes the truth,</LINE>
<LINE>But the plain single vow that is vow&#8217;d true.</LINE>
<LINE>What is not holy, that we swear not by,</LINE>
<LINE>But take the High&#8217;st to witness. Then pray you tell me,</LINE>
<LINE>If I should swear by Jove&#8217;s great attributes</LINE>
<LINE>I lov&#8217;d you dearly, would you believe my oaths</LINE>
<LINE>When I did love you ill? This has no holding,</LINE>
<LINE>To swear by Him whom I protest to love</LINE>
<LINE>That I will work against Him; therefore your oaths</LINE>
<LINE>Are words and poor conditions, but unseal&#8217;d&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>At least in my opinion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Change it, change it!</LINE>
<LINE>Be not so holy-cruel. Love is holy,</LINE>
<LINE>And my integrity ne&#8217;er knew the crafts</LINE>
<LINE>That you do charge men with. Stand no more off,</LINE>
<LINE>But give thyself unto my sick desires,</LINE>
<LINE>Who then recovers. Say thou art mine, and ever</LINE>
<LINE>My love, as it begins, shall so persever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see that men make rope&#8217;s in such a scarre,</LINE>
<LINE>That we&#8217;ll forsake ourselves. Give me that ring.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll lend it thee, my dear; but have no power</LINE>
<LINE>To give it from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Will you not, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is an honor &#8217;longing to our house,</LINE>
<LINE>Bequeathed down from many ancestors,</LINE>
<LINE>Which were the greatest obloquy i&#8217; th&#8217; world</LINE>
<LINE>In me to lose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">Mine honor&#8217;s such a ring,</LINE>
<LINE>My chastity&#8217;s the jewel of our house,</LINE>
<LINE>Bequeathed down from many ancestors,</LINE>
<LINE>Which were the greatest obloquy i&#8217; th&#8217; world</LINE>
<LINE>In me to lose. Thus your own proper wisdom</LINE>
<LINE>Brings in the champion Honor on my part,</LINE>
<LINE>Against your vain assault.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Here, take my ring!</LINE>
<LINE>My house, mine honor, yea, my life, be thine,</LINE>
<LINE>And I&#8217;ll be bid by thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When midnight comes, knock at my chamber-window;</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll order take my mother shall not hear.</LINE>
<LINE>Now will I charge you in the band of truth,</LINE>
<LINE>When you have conquer&#8217;d my yet maiden bed,</LINE>
<LINE>Remain there but an hour, nor speak to me.</LINE>
<LINE>My reasons are most strong, and you shall know them</LINE>
<LINE>When back again this ring shall be deliver&#8217;d;</LINE>
<LINE>And on your finger in the night I&#8217;ll put</LINE>
<LINE>Another ring, that what in time proceeds</LINE>
<LINE>May token to the future our past deeds.</LINE>
<LINE><FRENCH lang="fr">Adieu</FRENCH> till then, then fail not. You have won</LINE>
<LINE>A wife of me, though there my hope be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A heaven on earth I have won by wooing thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For which live long to thank both heaven and me!</LINE>
<LINE>You may so in the end.</LINE>
<LINE>My mother told me just how he would woo,</LINE>
<LINE>As if she sate in &#8217;s heart. She says all men</LINE>
<LINE>Have the like oaths. He had sworn to marry me</LINE>
<LINE>When his wife&#8217;s dead; therefore I&#8217;ll lie with him</LINE>
<LINE>When I am buried. Since Frenchmen are so braid,</LINE>
<LINE>Marry that will, I live and die a maid.</LINE>
<LINE>Only in this disguise I think&#8217;t no sin</LINE>
<LINE>To cozen him that would unjustly win.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The Florentine camp.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(French Lords, Soldiers, Messenger, Bertram, Parolles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the two French Lords and some two or three Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have not given him his mother&#8217;s letter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have deliv&#8217;red it an hour since. There is something in&#8217;t that stings his nature; for on the reading it he chang&#8217;d almost into another man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He has much worthy blame laid upon him for shaking off so good a wife and so sweet a lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Especially he hath incurr&#8217;d the everlasting displeasure of the King, who had even tun&#8217;d his bounty to sing happiness to him. I will tell you a thing, but you shall let it dwell darkly with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When you have spoken it, &#8217;tis dead, and I am the grave of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath perverted a young gentlewoman here in Florence, of a most chaste renown, and this night he fleshes his will in the spoil of her honor. He hath given her his monumental ring, and thinks himself made in the unchaste composition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now God delay our rebellion! As we are ourselves, what things are we!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Merely our own traitors. And as in the common course of all treasons, we still see them reveal themselves, till they attain to their abhorr&#8217;d ends; so he that in this action contrives against his own nobility in his proper stream  o&#8217;erflows himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is it not meant damnable in us, to be trumpeters of our unlawful intents? We shall not then have his company tonight?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not till after midnight; for he is dieted to his hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That approaches apace. I would gladly have him see his company anatomiz&#8217;d, that he might take a measure of his own judgments, wherein so curiously he had set this counterfeit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will not meddle with him till he come; for his presence must be the whip of the other.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In the meantime, what hear you of these wars?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hear there is an overture of peace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I assure you a peace concluded.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What will Count Roussillion do then? Will he travel higher, or return again into France?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I perceive by this demand, you are not altogether of his counsel.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let it be forbid, sir, so should I be a great deal of his act.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, his wife some two months since fled from his house. Her pretense is a pilgrimage to Saint Jaques le Grand; which holy undertaking with most austere sanctimony she accomplish&#8217;d; and there residing, the tenderness of her nature became as a prey to her grief; in fine, made a groan of her last breath, and now she sings in heaven.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How is this justified?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The stronger part of it by her own letters, which makes her story true, even to the point of her death. Her death itself, which could not be her office to say is come, was faithfully confirm&#8217;d by the rector of the place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath the Count all this intelligence?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and the particular confirmations, point from point, to the full arming of the verity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am heartily sorry that he&#8217;ll be glad of this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How mightily sometimes we make us comforts of our losses!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And how mightily some other times we drown our gain in tears! The great dignity that his valor hath here acquir&#8217;d for him shall at home be encount&#8217;red with a shame as ample.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The web of our life is of a mingled yarn, good and ill together: our virtues would be proud, if our faults whipt them not, and our crimes would despair, if they were not cherish&#8217;d by our virtues.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now? Where&#8217;s your master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He met the Duke in the street, sir, of whom he hath taken a solemn leave. His lordship will next morning for France. The Duke hath offer&#8217;d him letters of commendations to the King.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They shall be no more than needful there, if they were more than they can commend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter (Bertram) Count Roussillion.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They cannot be too sweet for the King&#8217;s tartness. Here&#8217;s his lordship now. How now, my lord, is&#8217;t not after midnight?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have tonight dispatch&#8217;d sixteen businesses, a month&#8217;s length a-piece, by an abstract of success: I have congied with the Duke, done my <FRENCH lang="fr">adieu</FRENCH> with his nearest; buried a wife, mourn&#8217;d for her, writ to my lady mother I am returning, entertain&#8217;d my convoy, and between these main parcels of dispatch effected many nicer needs. The last was the greatest, but that I have not ended yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If the business be of any difficulty, and this morning your departure hence, it requires haste of your lordship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I mean the business is not ended, as fearing to hear of it hereafter. But shall we have this dialogue between the fool and the soldier? Come, bring forth this counterfeit module, h&#8217;as deceiv&#8217;d me like a double-meaning prophesier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bring him forth, h&#8217;as sate i&#8217; th&#8217; stocks all night, poor gallant knave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No matter, his heels have deserv&#8217;d it, in usurping his spurs so long. How does he carry himself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have told your lordship already: the stocks carry him. But to answer you as you would be understood, he weeps like a wench that had shed her milk. He hath confess&#8217;d himself to Morgan, whom he supposes to be a friar, from the time of his remembrance to this very instant disaster of his setting i&#8217; th&#8217; stocks; and what think you he hath confess&#8217;d?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing of me, has &#8217;a?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His confession is taken, and it shall be read to his face. If your lordship be in&#8217;t, as I believe you are, you must have the patience to hear it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Soldiers and Parolles, with First Soldier as his Interpreter.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A plague upon him! Muffled! He can say nothing of me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hush, hush! Hoodman comes! Porto-tartarossa.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He calls for the tortures. What will you say without &#8217;em?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will confess what I know without constraint. If ye pinch me like a pasty, I can say no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bosko chimurcho.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Boblibindo chicurmurco.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are a merciful general. Our general bids you answer to what I shall ask you out of a note.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And truly, as I hope to live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;First demand of him, how many horse the Duke is strong.&#8221; What say you to that?</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Five or six thousand, but very weak and unserviceable. The troops are all scatter&#8217;d, and the commanders very poor rogues, upon my reputation and credit and as I hope to live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I set down your answer so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do, I&#8217;ll take the sacrament on&#8217;t, how and which way you will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All&#8217;s one to him. What a past-saving slave is this!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Y&#8217; are deceiv&#8217;d, my lord, this is Monsieur Parolles, the gallant militarist&#8212;that was his own phrase&#8212;that had the whole theoric of war in the knot of his scarf, and the practice in the chape of his dagger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will never trust a man again for keeping his sword clean, nor believe he can have every thing in him by wearing his apparel neatly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, that&#8217;s set down.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8220;Five or six thousand horse,&#8221; I said&#8212;I will say true&#8212; &#8220;or thereabouts,&#8221; set down, for I&#8217;ll speak truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s very near the truth in this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I con him no thanks for&#8217;t, in the nature he delivers it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8220;Poor rogues,&#8221; I pray you say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, that&#8217;s set down.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I humbly thank you, sir. A truth&#8217;s a truth, the rogues are marvellous poor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;Demand of him, of what strength they are afoot.&#8221; What say you to that?</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my troth, sir, if I were to live this present hour, I will tell true. Let me see: Spurio, a hundred and fifty; Sebastian, so many; Corambus, so many; Jaques, so many; Guiltian, Cosmo, Lodowick, and Gratii, two hundred fifty each; mine own company, Chitopher, Vaumond, Bentii, two hundred fifty each; so that the muster-file, rotten and sound, upon my life, amounts not to fifteen thousand pole, half of the which dare not shake the snow from off their cassocks, lest they shake themselves to pieces.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What shall be done to him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing, but let him have thanks. Demand of him my condition, and what credit I have with the Duke.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, that&#8217;s set down.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;You shall demand of him, whether one Captain Dumaine be i&#8217; th&#8217; camp, a Frenchman; what his reputation is with the Duke; what his valor, honesty, and expertness in wars; or whether he thinks it were not possible with well-weighing sums of gold to corrupt him to a revolt.&#8221; What say you to this? What do you know of it?</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I beseech you let me answer to the particular of the inter&#8217;gatories. Demand them singly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you know this Captain Dumaine?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know him. &#8217;A was a botcher&#8217;s prentice in Paris, from whence he was whipt for getting the shrieve&#8217;s fool with child, a dumb innocent, that could not say him nay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, by your leave, hold your hands&#8212;though I know his brains are forfeit to the next tile that falls.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, is this captain in the Duke of Florence&#8217;s camp?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Upon my knowledge, he is, and lousy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, look not so upon me; we shall hear of your lordship anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is his reputation with the Duke?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Duke knows him for no other but a poor officer of mine, and writ to me this other day to turn him out a&#8217; th&#8217; band. I think I have his letter in my pocket.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, we&#8217;ll search.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In good sadness, I do not know. Either it is there, or it is upon a file with the Duke&#8217;s other letters in my tent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here &#8217;tis, here&#8217;s a paper. Shall I read it to you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not know if it be it or no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our interpreter does it well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Excellently.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;Dian, the Count&#8217;s a fool, and full of gold&#8221;&#8212;</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That is not the Duke&#8217;s letter, sir; that is an advertisement to a proper maid in Florence, one Diana, to take heed of the allurement of one Count Roussillion, a foolish idle boy, but for all that very ruttish. I pray you, sir, put it up again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I&#8217;ll read it first, by your favor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My meaning in&#8217;t, I protest, was very honest in the behalf of the maid; for I knew the young Count to be a dangerous and lascivious boy, who is a whale to virginity, and devours up all the fry it finds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Damnable both-sides rogue!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads the letter.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;When he swears oaths, bid him drop gold, and take it;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>After he scores, he never pays the score.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Half won is match well made; match, and well make it;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>He ne&#8217;er pays after-debts, take it before,</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>And say a soldier, Dian, told thee this:</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Men are to mell with, boys are not to kiss;</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>For count of this, the Count&#8217;s a fool, I know it,</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Who pays before, but not when he does owe it.</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Thine, as he vow&#8217;d to thee in thine ear,</RECITE></LINE>
<LINE><RECITE>Parolles.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He shall be whipt through the army with this rhyme in &#8217;s forehead.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is your devoted friend, sir, the manifold linguist and the armipotent soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I could endure any thing before but a cat, and now he&#8217;s a cat to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I perceive, sir, by the general&#8217;s looks, we shall be fain to hang you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My life, sir, in any case! Not that I am afraid to die, but that my offenses being many, I would repent out the remainder of nature. Let me live, sir, in a dungeon, i&#8217; th&#8217; stocks, or any where, so I may live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll see what may be done, so you confess freely; therefore once more to this Captain Dumaine. You have answer&#8217;d to his reputation with the Duke, and to his valor; what is his honesty?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He will steal, sir, an egg out of a cloister. For rapes and ravishments he parallels Nessus. He professes not keeping of oaths; in breaking &#8217;em he is stronger than Hercules. He will lie, sir, with such volubility, that you would think truth were a fool. Drunkenness is his best virtue, for he will be swine-drunk, and in his sleep he does little harm, save to his bed-clothes about him; but they know his conditions, and lay him in straw. I have but little more to say, sir, of his honesty. He has every thing that an honest man should not have; what an honest man should have, he has nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I begin to love him for this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For this description of thine honesty? A pox upon him for me, he&#8217;s more and more a cat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What say you to his expertness in war?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, sir, h&#8217;as led the drum before the English tragedians. To belie him I will not, and more of his soldiership I know not, except in that country he had the honor to be the officer at a place there call&#8217;d Mile-end, to instruct for the doubling of files. I would do the man what honor I can, but of this I am not certain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath out-villain&#8217;d villainy so far, that the rarity redeems him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A pox on him, he&#8217;s a cat still.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His qualities being at this poor price, I need not to ask you if gold will corrupt him to revolt.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, for a cardecue he will sell the fee-simple of his salvation, the inheritance of it, and cut th&#8217; entail from all remainders, and a perpetual succession for it perpetually.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s his brother, the other Captain Dumaine?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why does he ask him of me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>E&#8217;en a crow a&#8217; th&#8217; same nest; not altogether so great as the first in goodness, but greater a great deal in evil. He excels his brother for a coward, yet his brother is reputed one of the best that is. In a retreat he outruns any lackey; marry, in coming on he has the cramp.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If your life be sav&#8217;d, will you undertake to betray the Florentine?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and the captain of his horse, Count Roussillion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll whisper with the general, and know his pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE> I&#8217;ll no more drumming, a plague of all drums! Only to seem to deserve well, and to beguile the supposition of that lascivious young boy the Count, have I run into this danger. Yet who would have suspected an ambush where I was taken?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is no remedy, sir, but you must die. The general says, you that have so traitorously discover&#8217;d the secrets of your army, and made such pestiferous reports of men very nobly held, can serve the world for no honest use; therefore you must die. Come, headsman, off with his head.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Lord, sir, let me live, or let me see my death!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That shall you, and take your leave of all your friends. <STAGEDIR>Unblinding him.</STAGEDIR> So, look about you. Know you any here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good morrow, noble captain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God bless you, Captain Parolles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God save you, noble captain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Captain, what greeting will you to my Lord Lafew? I am for France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. LORD. DUM.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good captain, will you give me a copy of the sonnet you writ to Diana in behalf of the Count Roussillion? And I were not a very coward, I&#8217;d compel it of you, but fare you well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Bertram and Lords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are undone, captain, all but your scarf; that has a knot on&#8217;t yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who cannot be crush&#8217;d with a plot?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you could find out a country where but women were that had receiv&#8217;d so much shame, you might begin an impudent nation. Fare ye well, sir, I am for France too. We shall speak of you there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit with Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet am I thankful. If my heart were great,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Twould burst at this. Captain I&#8217;ll be no more,</LINE>
<LINE>But I will eat and drink, and sleep as soft</LINE>
<LINE>As captain shall. Simply the thing I am</LINE>
<LINE>Shall make me live. Who knows himself a braggart,</LINE>
<LINE>Let him fear this; for it will come to pass</LINE>
<LINE>That every braggart shall be found an ass.</LINE>
<LINE>Rust sword, cool blushes, and, Parolles, live</LINE>
<LINE>Safest in shame! Being fool&#8217;d, by fool&#8217;ry thrive!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s place and means for every man alive.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll after them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 4</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Florence. The widow&#8217;s house.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Helen, Widow, Diana)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen, Widow, and Diana.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That you may well perceive I have not wrong&#8217;d you,</LINE>
<LINE>One of the greatest in the Christian world</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be my surety; &#8217;fore whose throne &#8217;tis needful,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere I can perfect mine intents, to kneel.</LINE>
<LINE>Time was, I did him a desired office,</LINE>
<LINE>Dear almost as his life, which gratitude</LINE>
<LINE>Through flinty Tartar&#8217;s bosom would peep forth,</LINE>
<LINE>And answer thanks. I duly am inform&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>His Grace is at Marsellis, to which place</LINE>
<LINE>We have convenient convoy. You must know</LINE>
<LINE>I am supposed dead. The army breaking,</LINE>
<LINE>My husband hies him home, where heaven aiding,</LINE>
<LINE>And by the leave of my good lord the King,</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll be before our welcome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Gentle madam,</LINE>
<LINE>You never had a servant to whose trust</LINE>
<LINE>Your business was more welcome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Nor you, mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>Ever a friend whose thoughts more truly labor</LINE>
<LINE>To recompense your love. Doubt not but heaven</LINE>
<LINE>Hath brought me up to be your daughter&#8217;s dower,</LINE>
<LINE>As it hath fated her to be my motive</LINE>
<LINE>And helper to a husband. But O, strange men,</LINE>
<LINE>That can such sweet use make of what they hate,</LINE>
<LINE>When saucy trusting of the cozen&#8217;d thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>Defiles the pitchy night; so lust doth play</LINE>
<LINE>With what it loathes for that which is away&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>But more of this hereafter. You, Diana,</LINE>
<LINE>Under my poor instructions yet must suffer</LINE>
<LINE>Something in my behalf.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Let death and honesty</LINE>
<LINE>Go with your impositions, I am yours</LINE>
<LINE>Upon your will to suffer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Yet, I pray you:</LINE>
<LINE>But with the word the time will bring on summer,</LINE>
<LINE>When briers shall have leaves as well as thorns,</LINE>
<LINE>And be as sweet as sharp. We must away:</LINE>
<LINE>Our waggon is prepar&#8217;d, and time revives us.</LINE>
<LINE>All&#8217;s well that ends well! Still the fine&#8217;s the crown;</LINE>
<LINE>What e&#8217;er the course, the end is the renown.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 5</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Clown, Countess of Roussillion, Lafew)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Clown, old Lady Countess, and Lafew.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, no, your son was misled with a snipt-taffata fellow there, whose villainous saffron would have made all the unbak&#8217;d and doughy youth of a nation in his color. Your daughter-in-law had been alive at this hour, and your son here at home, more advanc&#8217;d by the King than by that red-tail&#8217;d humble-bee I speak of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I had not known him; it was the death of the most virtuous gentlewoman that ever nature had praise for creating. If she had partaken of my flesh, and cost me the dearest groans of a mother, I could not have ow&#8217;d her a more rooted love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>&#8217;Twas a good lady, &#8217;twas a good lady. We may pick a thousand sallets ere we light on such another herb.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, sir, she was the sweet marjorom of the sallet, or rather the herb of grace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are not herbs, you knave, they are nose-herbs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am no great Nebuchadnezzar, sir, I have not much skill in grass.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whether dost thou profess thyself&#8212;a knave or a fool?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A fool, sir, at a woman&#8217;s service, and a knave at a man&#8217;s.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your distinction?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would cozen the man of his wife and do his service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So you were a knave at his service indeed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I would give his wife my bauble, sir, to do her service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will subscribe for thee, thou art both knave and fool.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At your service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, sir, if I cannot serve you, I can serve as great a prince as you are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who&#8217;s that? A Frenchman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, sir, &#8217;a has an English name, but his fisnomy is more hotter in France than there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What prince is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The black prince, sir, alias the prince of darkness, alias the devil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold thee, there&#8217;s my purse. I give thee not this to suggest thee from thy master thou talk&#8217;st of; serve him still.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a woodland fellow, sir, that always lov&#8217;d a great fire, and the master I speak of ever keeps a good fire. But sure he is the prince of the world; let his nobility remain in &#8217;s court. I am for the house with the narrow gate, which I take to be too little for pomp to enter. Some that humble themselves may, but the many will be too chill and tender, and they&#8217;ll be for the flow&#8217;ry way that leads to the broad gate and the great fire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go thy ways, I begin to be a-weary of thee, and I tell thee so before, because I would not fall out with thee. Go thy ways, let my horses be well look&#8217;d to, without any tricks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I put any tricks upon &#8217;em, sir, they shall be jades&#8217; tricks, which are their own right by the law of nature.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A shrewd knave and an unhappy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So &#8217;a is. My lord that&#8217;s gone made himself much sport out of him. By his authority he remains here, which he thinks is a patent for his sauciness, and indeed he has no pace, but runs where he will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I like him well, &#8217;tis not amiss. And I was about to tell you, since I heard of the good lady&#8217;s death, and that my lord your son was upon his return home, I mov&#8217;d the King my master to speak in the behalf of my daughter, which in the minority of them both, his Majesty, out of a self-gracious remembrance, did first propose. His Highness hath promis&#8217;d me to do it, and to stop up the displeasure he hath conceiv&#8217;d against your son, there is no fitter matter. How does your ladyship like it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With very much content, my lord, and I wish it happily effected.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His Highness comes post from Marsellis, of as able body as when he number&#8217;d thirty. &#8217;A will be here tomorrow, or I am deceiv&#8217;d by him that in such intelligence hath seldom fail&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It rejoices me, that I hope I shall see him ere I die. I have letters that my son will be here tonight. I shall beseech your lordship to remain with me till they meet together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I was thinking with what manners I might safely be admitted.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You need but plead your honorable privilege.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lady, of that I have made a bold charter, but I thank my God it holds yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Clown.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O madam, yonder&#8217;s my lord your son with a patch of velvet on &#8217;s face. Whether there be a scar under&#8217;t or no, the velvet knows, but &#8217;tis a goodly patch of velvet. His left cheek is a cheek of two pile and a half, but his right cheek is worn bare.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A scar nobly got, or a noble scar, is a good liv&#8217;ry of honor; so belike is that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But it is your carbinado&#8217;d face.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us go see your son I pray you. I long to talk with the young noble soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, there&#8217;s a dozen of &#8217;em, with delicate fine hats, and most courteous feathers, which bow the head, and nod at every man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 5</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Marseilles. A street.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Helen, Widow, Diana, Attendants, Gentleman)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helen, Widow, and Diana, with two Attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But this exceeding posting day and night</LINE>
<LINE>Must wear your spirits low; we cannot help it.</LINE>
<LINE>But since you have made the days and nights as one,</LINE>
<LINE>To wear your gentle limbs in my affairs,</LINE>
<LINE>Be bold you do so grow in my requital</LINE>
<LINE>As nothing can unroot you.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Gentleman, an astringer.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE offset="6">In happy time!</LINE>
<LINE>This man may help me to his Majesty&#8217;s ear,</LINE>
<LINE>If he would spend his power. God save you, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I have seen you in the court of France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been sometimes there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do presume, sir, that you are not fall&#8217;n</LINE>
<LINE>From the report that goes upon your goodness,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore goaded with most sharp occasions,</LINE>
<LINE>Which lay nice manners by, I put you to</LINE>
<LINE>The use of your own virtues, for the which</LINE>
<LINE>I shall continue thankful.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What&#8217;s your will?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That it will please you</LINE>
<LINE>To give this poor petition to the King,</LINE>
<LINE>And aid me with that store of power you have</LINE>
<LINE>To come into his presence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The King&#8217;s not here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Not here, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="8">Not indeed.</LINE>
<LINE>He hence remov&#8217;d last night, and with more haste</LINE>
<LINE>Than is his use.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Lord, how we lose our pains!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All&#8217;s well that ends well yet,</LINE>
<LINE>Though time seem so adverse and means unfit.</LINE>
<LINE>I do beseech you, whither is he gone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, as I take it, to Roussillion,</LINE>
<LINE>Whither I am going.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I do beseech you, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Since you are like to see the King before me,</LINE>
<LINE>Commend the paper to his gracious hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I presume shall render you no blame,</LINE>
<LINE>But rather make you thank your pains for it.</LINE>
<LINE>I will come after you with what good speed</LINE>
<LINE>Our means will make us means.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">This I&#8217;ll do for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you shall find yourself to be well thank&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>What e&#8217;er falls more. We must to horse again.</LINE>
<LINE>Go, go, provide.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>


</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. Before the count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Clown Lavatch, Parolles, Lafew)</SCENEPERSONAE>


<STAGEDIR>Enter Clown Lavatch and Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good Master Lavatch, give my Lord Lafew this letter. I have ere now, sir, been better known to you, when I have held familiarity with fresher clothes; but I am now, sir, muddied in Fortune&#8217;s mood, and smell somewhat strong of her strong displeasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, Fortune&#8217;s displeasure is but sluttish if it smell so strongly as thou speak&#8217;st of. I will henceforth eat no fish of Fortune&#8217;s butt&#8217;ring. Prithee allow the wind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, you need not to stop your nose, sir; I spake but by a metaphor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, sir, if your metaphor stink, I will stop my nose, or against any man&#8217;s metaphor. Prithee get thee further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, sir, deliver me this paper.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLO.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Foh, prithee stand away. A paper from Fortune&#8217;s close-stool to give to a nobleman! Look here he comes himself.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Lafew.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here is a purr of Fortune&#8217;s, sir, or of Fortune&#8217;s cat&#8212;but not a musk-cat&#8212;that has fall&#8217;n into the unclean fishpond of her displeasure, and as he says, is muddied withal. Pray you, sir, use the carp as you may, for he looks like a poor, decay&#8217;d, ingenious, foolish, rascally knave. I do pity his distress in my similes of comfort, and leave him to your lordship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, I am a man whom Fortune hath cruelly scratch&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And what would you have me to do? &#8217;Tis too late to pare her nails now. Wherein have you play&#8217;d the knave with Fortune that she should scratch you, who of herself is a good lady, and would not have knaves thrive long under her? There&#8217;s a cardecue for you. Let the justices make you and Fortune friends; I am for other business.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I beseech your honor to hear me one single word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You beg a single penny more. Come, you shall ha&#8217;t; save your word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My name, my good lord, is Parolles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You beg more than &#8220;word&#8221; then. Cox my passion! Give me your hand. How does your drum?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my good lord, you were the first that found me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was I, in sooth? And I was the first that lost thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It lies in you, my lord, to bring me in some grace, for you did bring me out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Out upon thee, knave! Dost thou put upon me at once both the office of God and the devil? One brings thee in grace, and the other brings thee out.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Trumpets sound.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The King&#8217;s coming, I know by his trumpets. Sirrah, inquire further after me. I had talk of you last night; though you are a fool and a knave, you shall eat. Go to, follow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I praise God for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>
 
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Roussillion. The Count&#8217;s palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(King, Countess of Roussillion, Lafew, two French Lords, Attendant, Bertram, Gentleman, Old Widow of Florence, Diana, Parolles, Helena)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Enter King, old Lady Countess, Lafew, the two French Lords, with Attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We lost a jewel of her, and our esteem</LINE>
<LINE>Was made much poorer by it; but your son,</LINE>
<LINE>As mad in folly, lack&#8217;d the sense to know</LINE>
<LINE>Her estimation home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">&#8217;Tis past, my liege,</LINE>
<LINE>And I beseech your Majesty to make it</LINE>
<LINE>Natural rebellion, done i&#8217; th&#8217; blade of youth,</LINE>
<LINE>When oil and fire, too strong for reason&#8217;s force,</LINE>
<LINE> o&#8217;erbears it, and burns on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">My honor&#8217;d lady,</LINE>
<LINE>I have forgiven and forgotten all,</LINE>
<LINE>Though my revenges were high bent upon him,</LINE>
<LINE>And watch&#8217;d the time to shoot.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">This I must say&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>But first I beg my pardon&#8212;the young lord</LINE>
<LINE>Did to his Majesty, his mother, and his lady</LINE>
<LINE>Offense of mighty note; but to himself</LINE>
<LINE>The greatest wrong of all. He lost a wife</LINE>
<LINE>Whose beauty did astonish the survey</LINE>
<LINE>Of richest eyes, whose words all ears took captive,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose dear perfection hearts that scorn&#8217;d to serve</LINE>
<LINE>Humbly call&#8217;d mistress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Praising what is lost</LINE>
<LINE>Makes the remembrance dear. Well, call him hither,</LINE>
<LINE>We are reconcil&#8217;d, and the first view shall kill</LINE>
<LINE>All repetition. Let him not ask our pardon,</LINE>
<LINE>The nature of his great offense is dead,</LINE>
<LINE>And deeper than oblivion we do bury</LINE>
<LINE>Th&#8217; incensing relics of it. Let him approach</LINE>
<LINE>A stranger, no offender; and inform him</LINE>
<LINE>So &#8217;tis our will he should.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I shall, my liege.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What says he to your daughter? Have you spoke?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All that he is hath reference to your Highness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then shall we have a match. I have letters sent me</LINE>
<LINE>That sets him high in fame.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Count Bertram.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">He looks well on&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not a day of season,</LINE>
<LINE>For thou mayst see a sunshine and a hail</LINE>
<LINE>In me at once. But to the brightest beams</LINE>
<LINE>Distracted clouds give way, so stand thou forth,</LINE>
<LINE>The time is fair again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">My high-repented blames,</LINE>
<LINE>Dear sovereign, pardon to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">All is whole,</LINE>
<LINE>Not one word more of the consumed time.</LINE>
<LINE>Let&#8217;s take the instant by the forward top;</LINE>
<LINE>For we are old, and on our quick&#8217;st decrees</LINE>
<LINE>Th&#8217; inaudible and noiseless foot of time</LINE>
<LINE>Steals ere we can effect them. You remember</LINE>
<LINE>The daughter of this lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Admiringly, my liege. At first</LINE>
<LINE>I stuck my choice upon her, ere my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Durst make too bold a herald of my tongue;</LINE>
<LINE>Where the impression of mine eye infixing,</LINE>
<LINE>Contempt his scornful perspective did lend me,</LINE>
<LINE>Which warp&#8217;d the line of every other favor,</LINE>
<LINE>Scorn&#8217;d a fair color, or express&#8217;d it stol&#8217;n,</LINE>
<LINE>Extended or contracted all proportions</LINE>
<LINE>To a most hideous object. Thence it came</LINE>
<LINE>That she whom all men prais&#8217;d, and whom myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Since I have lost, have lov&#8217;d, was in mine eye</LINE>
<LINE>The dust that did offend it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Well excus&#8217;d.</LINE>
<LINE>That thou didst love her, strikes some scores away</LINE>
<LINE>From the great compt; but love that comes too late,</LINE>
<LINE>Like a remorseful pardon slowly carried,</LINE>
<LINE>To the great sender turns a sour offense,</LINE>
<LINE>Crying, &#8220;That&#8217;s good that&#8217;s gone.&#8221; Our rash faults</LINE>
<LINE>Make trivial price of serious things we have,</LINE>
<LINE>Not knowing them until we know their grave.</LINE>
<LINE>Oft our displeasures, to ourselves unjust,</LINE>
<LINE>Destroy our friends, and after weep their dust;</LINE>
<LINE>Our own love waking cries to see what&#8217;s done,</LINE>
<LINE>While shameful hate sleeps out the afternoon.</LINE>
<LINE>Be this sweet Helen&#8217;s knell, and now forget her.</LINE>
<LINE>Send forth your amorous token for fair Maudlin.</LINE>
<LINE>The main consents are had, and here we&#8217;ll stay</LINE>
<LINE>To see our widower&#8217;s second marriage-day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which better than the first, O dear heaven, bless!</LINE>
<LINE>Or, ere they meet, in me, O nature, cesse!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come on, my son, in whom my house&#8217;s name</LINE>
<LINE>Must be digested; give a favor from you</LINE>
<LINE>To sparkle in the spirits of my daughter,</LINE>
<LINE>That she may quickly come.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Bertram gives a ring.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE offset="5">By my old beard,</LINE>
<LINE>And ev&#8217;ry hair that&#8217;s on&#8217;t, Helen, that&#8217;s dead,</LINE>
<LINE>Was a sweet creature; such a ring as this,</LINE>
<LINE>The last that e&#8217;er I took her leave at court,</LINE>
<LINE>I saw upon her finger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Hers it was not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now pray you let me see it; for mine eye,</LINE>
<LINE>While I was speaking, oft was fasten&#8217;d to&#8217;t.</LINE>
<LINE>This ring was mine, and when I gave it Helen,</LINE>
<LINE>I bade her, if her fortunes ever stood</LINE>
<LINE>Necessitied to help, that by this token</LINE>
<LINE>I would relieve her. Had you that craft to reave her</LINE>
<LINE>Of what should stead her most?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">My gracious sovereign,</LINE>
<LINE>Howe&#8217;er it pleases you to take it so,</LINE>
<LINE>The ring was never hers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Son, on my life,</LINE>
<LINE>I have seen her wear it, and she reckon&#8217;d it</LINE>
<LINE>At her live&#8217;s rate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I am sure I saw her wear it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are deceiv&#8217;d, my lord, she never saw it.</LINE>
<LINE>In Florence was it from a casement thrown me,</LINE>
<LINE>Wrapp&#8217;d in a paper, which contain&#8217;d the name</LINE>
<LINE>Of her that threw it. Noble she was, and thought</LINE>
<LINE>I stood engag&#8217;d; but when I had subscrib&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>To mine own fortune, and inform&#8217;d her fully</LINE>
<LINE>I could not answer in that course of honor</LINE>
<LINE>As she had made the overture, she ceas&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>In heavy satisfaction, and would never</LINE>
<LINE>Receive the ring again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Plutus himself,</LINE>
<LINE>That knows the tinct and multiplying med&#8217;cine,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath not in nature&#8217;s mystery more science</LINE>
<LINE>Than I have in this ring. &#8217;Twas mine, &#8217;twas Helen&#8217;s,</LINE>
<LINE>Whoever gave it you. Then if you know</LINE>
<LINE>That you are well acquainted with yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>Confess &#8217;twas hers, and by what rough enforcement</LINE>
<LINE>You got it from her. She call&#8217;d the saints to surety</LINE>
<LINE>That she would never put it from her finger,</LINE>
<LINE>Unless she gave it to yourself in bed,</LINE>
<LINE>Where you have never come, or sent it us</LINE>
<LINE>Upon her great disaster.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">She never saw it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou speak&#8217;st it falsely, as I love mine honor,</LINE>
<LINE>And mak&#8217;st conjectural fears to come into me,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I would fain shut out. If it should prove</LINE>
<LINE>That thou art so inhuman&#8212;&#8217;twill not prove so;</LINE>
<LINE>And yet I know not: thou didst hate her deadly,</LINE>
<LINE>And she is dead, which nothing but to close</LINE>
<LINE>Her eyes myself could win me to believe,</LINE>
<LINE>More than to see this ring. Take him away.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Guards seize Bertram.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My fore-past proofs, howe&#8217;er the matter fall,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall tax my fears of little vanity,</LINE>
<LINE>Having vainly fear&#8217;d too little. Away with him!</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;ll sift this matter further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">If you shall prove</LINE>
<LINE>This ring was ever hers, you shall as easy</LINE>
<LINE>Prove that I husbanded her bed in Florence,</LINE>
<LINE>Where yet she never was.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit guarded.</STAGEDIR>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Gentleman, the astringer.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am wrapp&#8217;d in dismal thinkings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GENT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Gracious sovereign,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether I have been to blame or no, I know not.</LINE>
<LINE>Here&#8217;s a petition from a Florentine,</LINE>
<LINE>Who hath for four or five removes come short</LINE>
<LINE>To tender it herself. I undertook it,</LINE>
<LINE>Vanquish&#8217;d thereto by the fair grace and speech</LINE>
<LINE>Of the poor suppliant, who by this I know</LINE>
<LINE>Is here attending. Her business looks in her</LINE>
<LINE>With an importing visage, and she told me,</LINE>
<LINE>In a sweet verbal brief, it did concern</LINE>
<LINE>Your Highness with herself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Reads a letter.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE><RECITE>&#8220;Upon his many protestations to marry me when his wife was dead, I blush to say it, he won me. Now is the Count Roussillion a widower, his vows are forfeited to me, and my honor&#8217;s paid to him. He stole from Florence, taking no leave, and I follow him to his country for justice. Grant it me, O King, in you it best lies; otherwise a seducer flourishes, and a poor maid is undone. Diana Capilet.&#8221;</RECITE></LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will buy me a son-in-law in a fair, and toll for this. I&#8217;ll none of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The heavens have thought well on thee, Lafew,</LINE>
<LINE>To bring forth this discov&#8217;ry. Seek these suitors.</LINE>
<LINE>Go speedily, and bring again the Count.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt some Attendants.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I am afeard the life of Helen, lady,</LINE>
<LINE>Was foully snatch&#8217;d.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">Now, justice on the doers!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Bertram guarded.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wonder, sir, sith wives are monsters to you,</LINE>
<LINE>And that you fly them as you swear them lordship,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet you desire to marry. What woman&#8217;s that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Widow, Diana.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am, my lord, a wretched Florentine,</LINE>
<LINE>Derived from the ancient Capilet.</LINE>
<LINE>My suit, as I do understand, you know,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore know how far I may be pitied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WID.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am her mother, sir, whose age and honor</LINE>
<LINE>Both suffer under this complaint we bring,</LINE>
<LINE>And both shall cease, without your remedy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come hither, Count, do you know these women?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, I neither can nor will deny</LINE>
<LINE>But that I know them. Do they charge me further?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why do you look so strange upon your wife?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She&#8217;s none of mine, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">If you shall marry,</LINE>
<LINE>You give away this hand, and that is mine;</LINE>
<LINE>You give away heaven&#8217;s vows, and those are mine;</LINE>
<LINE>You give away myself, which is known mine;</LINE>
<LINE>For I by vow am so embodied yours,</LINE>
<LINE>That she which marries you must marry me,</LINE>
<LINE>Either both or none.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your reputation comes too short for my daughter, you are no husband for her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, this is a fond and desp&#8217;rate creature,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom sometime I have laugh&#8217;d with. Let your Highness</LINE>
<LINE>Lay a more noble thought upon mine honor</LINE>
<LINE>Than for to think that I would sink it here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, for my thoughts, you have them ill to friend</LINE>
<LINE>Till your deeds gain them; fairer prove your honor</LINE>
<LINE>Than in my thought it lies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Ask him upon his oath, if he does think</LINE>
<LINE>He had not my virginity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What say&#8217;st thou to her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">She&#8217;s impudent, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>And was a common gamester to the camp.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He does me wrong, my lord; if I were so,</LINE>
<LINE>He might have bought me at a common price.</LINE>
<LINE>Do not believe him. O, behold this ring,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose high respect and rich validity</LINE>
<LINE>Did lack a parallel; yet for all that</LINE>
<LINE>He gave it to a commoner a&#8217; th&#8217; camp,</LINE>
<LINE>If I be one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COUNT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">He blushes, and &#8217;tis hit.</LINE>
<LINE>Of six preceding ancestors, that gem,</LINE>
<LINE>Conferr&#8217;d by testament to th&#8217; sequent issue,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath it been owed and worn. This is his wife,</LINE>
<LINE>That ring&#8217;s a thousand proofs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Methought you said</LINE>
<LINE>You saw one here in court could witness it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did, my lord, but loath am to produce</LINE>
<LINE>So bad an instrument. His name&#8217;s Parolles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I saw the man today, if man he be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Find him, and bring him hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit an Attendant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">What of him?</LINE>
<LINE>He&#8217;s quoted for a most perfidious slave,</LINE>
<LINE>With all the spots a&#8217; th&#8217; world tax&#8217;d and debosh&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose nature sickens but to speak a truth.</LINE>
<LINE>Am I or that or this for what he&#8217;ll utter,</LINE>
<LINE>That will speak any thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">She hath that ring of yours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think she has. Certain it is I lik&#8217;d her,</LINE>
<LINE>And boarded her i&#8217; th&#8217; wanton way of youth.</LINE>
<LINE>She knew her distance, and did angle for me,</LINE>
<LINE>Madding my eagerness with her restraint,</LINE>
<LINE>As all impediments in fancy&#8217;s course</LINE>
<LINE>Are motives of more fancy, and in fine,</LINE>
<LINE>Her inf&#8217;nite cunning, with her modern grace,</LINE>
<LINE>Subdu&#8217;d me to her rate. She got the ring,</LINE>
<LINE>And I had that which any inferior might</LINE>
<LINE>At market-price have bought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">I must be patient.</LINE>
<LINE>You that have turn&#8217;d off a first so noble wife,</LINE>
<LINE>May justly diet me. I pray you yet</LINE>
<LINE>(Since you lack virtue, I will lose a husband)</LINE>
<LINE>Send for your ring, I will return it home,</LINE>
<LINE>And give me mine again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I have it not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What ring was yours, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="7">Sir, much like</LINE>
<LINE>The same upon your finger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Know you this ring? This ring was his of late.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And this was it I gave him, being a-bed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The story then goes false, you threw it him</LINE>
<LINE>Out of a casement.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">I have spoke the truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Parolles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, I do confess the ring was hers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You boggle shrewdly, every feather starts you.</LINE>
<LINE>Is this the man you speak of?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Ay, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell me, sirrah&#8212;but tell me true, I charge you,</LINE>
<LINE>Not fearing the displeasure of your master,</LINE>
<LINE>Which on your just proceeding I&#8217;ll keep off&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>By him and by this woman here what know you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So please your Majesty, my master hath been an honorable gentleman. Tricks he hath had in him, which gentlemen have.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, to th&#8217; purpose. Did he love this woman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, sir, he did love her, but how?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He did love her, sir, as a gentleman loves a woman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He lov&#8217;d her, sir, and lov&#8217;d her not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As thou art a knave, and no knave. What an equivocal companion is this!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a poor man, and at your Majesty&#8217;s command.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s a good drum, my lord, but a naughty orator.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you know he promis&#8217;d me marriage?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, I know more than I&#8217;ll speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But wilt thou not speak all thou know&#8217;st?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, so please your Majesty. I did go between them as I said, but more than that, he lov&#8217;d her, for indeed he was mad for her, and talk&#8217;d of Sathan and of Limbo and of Furies and I know not what. Yet I was in that credit with them at that time that I knew of their going to bed, and of other motions, as promising her marriage, and things which would derive me ill will to speak of; therefore I will not speak what I know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast spoken all already, unless thou canst say they are married. But thou art too fine in thy evidence, therefore stand aside.</LINE>
<LINE>This ring you say was yours?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Ay, my good lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where did you buy it? Or who gave it you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was not given me, nor I did not buy it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who lent it you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">It was not lent me neither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where did you find it then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I found it not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it were yours by none of all these ways,</LINE>
<LINE>How could you give it him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I never gave it him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This woman&#8217;s an easy glove, my lord, she goes off and on at pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This ring was mine, I gave it his first wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It might be yours or hers for aught I know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take her away, I do not like her now,</LINE>
<LINE>To prison with her; and away with him.</LINE>
<LINE>Unless thou tell&#8217;st me where thou hadst this ring,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou diest within this hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I&#8217;ll never tell you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take her away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">I&#8217;ll put in bail, my liege.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think thee now some common customer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By Jove, if ever I knew man, &#8217;twas you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wherefore hast thou accus&#8217;d him all this while?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Because he&#8217;s guilty, and he is not guilty.</LINE>
<LINE>He knows I am no maid, and he&#8217;ll swear to&#8217;t;</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll swear I am a maid, and he knows not.</LINE>
<LINE>Great King, I am no strumpet, by my life;</LINE>
<LINE>I am either maid, or else this old man&#8217;s wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Pointing to Lafew.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She does abuse our ears. To prison with her!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good mother, fetch my bail.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Widow.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Stay, royal sir.</LINE>
<LINE>The jeweller that owes the ring is sent for,</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall surety me. But for this lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Who hath abus&#8217;d me, as he knows himself,</LINE>
<LINE>Though yet he never harm&#8217;d me, here I quit him.</LINE>
<LINE>He knows himself my bed he hath defil&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>And at that time he got his wife with child.</LINE>
<LINE>Dead though she be, she feels her young one kick.</LINE>
<LINE>So there&#8217;s my riddle: one that&#8217;s dead is quick&#8212;</LINE>
<LINE>And now behold the meaning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Widow and Helen.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Is there no exorcist</LINE>
<LINE>Beguiles the truer office of mine eyes?</LINE>
<LINE>Is&#8217;t real that I see?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="4">No, my good lord,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Tis but the shadow of a wife you see,</LINE>
<LINE>The name, and not the thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Both, both. O, pardon!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my good lord, when I was like this maid,</LINE>
<LINE>I found you wondrous kind. There is your ring,</LINE>
<LINE>And look you, here&#8217;s your letter. This it says:</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;When from my finger you can get this ring,</LINE>
<LINE>And are by me with child, etc.&#8221; This is done.</LINE>
<LINE>Will you be mine now you are doubly won?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If she, my liege, can make me know this clearly,</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll love her dearly, ever, ever dearly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it appear not plain and prove untrue,</LINE>
<LINE>Deadly divorce step between me and you!</LINE>
<LINE>O my dear mother, do I see you living?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LAF.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mine eyes smell onions, I shall weep anon.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Parolles.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Good Tom Drum, lend me a handkercher. So, I thank thee; wait on me home, I&#8217;ll make sport with thee. Let thy curtsies alone, they are scurvy ones.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us from point to point this story know,</LINE>
<LINE>To make the even truth in pleasure flow.</LINE>

<STAGEDIR>To Diana.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>If thou beest yet a fresh uncropped flower,</LINE>
<LINE>Choose thou thy husband, and I&#8217;ll pay thy dower,</LINE>
<LINE>For I can guess that by thy honest aid</LINE>
<LINE>Thou kept&#8217;st a wife herself, thyself a maid.</LINE>
<LINE>Of that and all the progress, more and less,</LINE>
<LINE>Resolvedly more leisure shall express.</LINE>
<LINE>All yet seems well, and if it end so meet,</LINE>
<LINE>The bitter past, more welcome is the sweet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>


<EPILOGUE>
<SCENETITLE>Epilogue</SCENETITLE>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(King)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Advancing.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The king&#8217;s a beggar, now the play is done;</LINE>
<LINE>All is well ended, if this suit be won,</LINE>
<LINE>That you express content; which we will pay,</LINE>
<LINE>With strife to please you, day exceeding day.</LINE>
<LINE>Ours be your patience then, and yours our parts;</LINE>
<LINE>Your gentle hands lend us, and take our hearts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt omnes.</STAGEDIR>

</EPILOGUE>

</ACT>





<AUTHORDETAILS>
<AUTHOR>PlayShakespeare.com</AUTHOR>
<AUTHORURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com</AUTHORURL>
<COPYRIGHT>2005-2010 by PlayShakespeare.com</COPYRIGHT>
<VERSION>3.1</VERSION>
<LICENSE>GFDL License 1.3</LICENSE>
<LICENSEURL>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</LICENSEURL>
<TERMSURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com/about-us</TERMSURL>
</AUTHORDETAILS>

</PLAY>



