<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../plays.xsl"?>

<PLAY>
<TITLE>Cardenio or the Second Maiden&#8217;s Tragedy</TITLE>
<TITLESHORT>Cardenio</TITLESHORT>
<PLAYWRIGHT>William Shakespeare</PLAYWRIGHT>

<PERSONAE>
<PERSONA short="TYR.">The Tyrant, King Fernando</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="GOV.">Govianus, a usurper also known as Cardenio</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="ANS.">King Anselmus, deposed, also named Anselmo</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="VOT.">Votarius, brother to King Anselmus, also named Lotario</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="HELV.">Helvetius, a friend to Anselmus </PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="MEMP.">Memphonius, </PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="SOPH.">Sophonirus, a noble</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="BEL.">Bellarius, a noble and lover of Leonella</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="LADY.">The Lady, Luscinda, daughter of Helvetius</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="WIFE.">Wife to Votarius, Camilla</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="LEON.">Leonella, waiting-woman to Camilla</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="LADY G.">Lady of Govianus</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="PAGE.">Govianus' Page</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. NOBLE.">First Nobleman</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. NOBLE.">Second Nobleman</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. FEL.">First Fellow</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. FEL.">Second Fellow</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="SERV.">Servant</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. SERV.">First Servant</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. SERV.">Second Servant</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="1. SOLD.">First Soldier</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="2. SOLD.">Second Soldier</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="3. SOLD.">Third Soldier</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="4. SOLD.">Fourth Soldier</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 1</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The royal palace.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Tyrant, Memphonius, Sophonirus, Helvetius, Govianus, Lady Luscinda)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the new Usurping Tyrant, the nobles of his faction, Memphonius, Sophonirus, Helvetius, with others; the right heir Govianus, deposed. A sennet.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus high, my lords, your powers and constant loves</LINE>
<LINE>Hath fixed our glories like unmov&#8217;d stars</LINE>
<LINE>That know not what it is to fall or err.</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;re the kingdom&#8217;s love, and he that was</LINE>
<LINE>Flattered awhile, so stands before us now</LINE>
<LINE>Readier for doom than dignity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">So much</LINE>
<LINE>Can the adulterate friendship of mankind,</LINE>
<LINE>False Fortune&#8217;s sister, bring to pass on kings, And lay usurpers sunning in their glories Like adders in warm beams.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">There was but one</LINE>
<LINE>In whom my heart took pleasure (amongst women), One in the whole creation, and in her You dared to be my rival! Was&#8217;t not bold? Now we are king, she'll leave the lower path And find the way to us. Helvetius! It is thy daughter. Happier than a king And far above him, for she kneels to thee Whom we have kneeled to, richer in one smile That came from her than she in all thy blessings! If thou be&#8217;st proud, thou art to be forgiven;</LINE>
<LINE>It is no deadly sin in thee. While she lives,</LINE>
<LINE>High lust is not more natural to youth</LINE>
<LINE>Than that to thee. Be not afraid to die in&#8216;t;</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis but the sign of joy. There is no gladness</LINE>
<LINE>But has a pride it lives by. That&#8217;s the oil</LINE>
<LINE>That feeds it into flames. Let her be sent for</LINE>
<LINE>And honorably attended, as beseems</LINE>
<LINE>Her that we make our queen. My lords Memphonius</LINE>
<LINE>And Sophonirus, take into your care</LINE>
<LINE>The royal business of my heart. Conduct her</LINE>
<LINE>With a respect equal with that to us.</LINE>
<LINE>If more, it shall be pardoned; so still err,</LINE>
<LINE>You honour us, but ourself honours her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Strange fortune! Does he make his queen of her?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Memphonius.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have a wife; would she were so preferred! I could be but her subject; so I&#8217;m now:</LINE>
<LINE>I allow her her one friend to stop her mouth</LINE>
<LINE>And keep her quiet, gi' him his table free,</LINE>
<LINE>And the huge feeding of his great stone horse</LINE>
<LINE>On which he rides in pomp about the city</LINE>
<LINE>Only to speak to gallants in bay-windows.</LINE>
<LINE>Marry, his lodging he pays dearly for;</LINE>
<LINE>He gets me all my children; there I save by&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>Besides I draw my life out by the bargain</LINE>
<LINE>Some twelve years longer than the times appointed;</LINE>
<LINE>When my young prodigal gallant kicks up&#8217;s heels</LINE>
<LINE>At one-and-thirty, and lies dead and rotten</LINE>
<LINE>Some five-and-forty years before I&#8217;m coffined.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis the right way to keep a woman honest:</LINE>
<LINE>One friend is barricado to a hundred</LINE>
<LINE>And keeps &#8216;em out. Nay more, a husband&#8217;s sure</LINE>
<LINE>To have his children all of one man&#8217;s getting,</LINE>
<LINE>And he that performs best can have no better.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;m e&#8217;en as happy then that save a labour.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Thy honours with thy daughter&#8217;s love shall rise. I shall read thy deservings in her eyes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O may they be eternal books of pleasure</LINE>
<LINE>To show you all delight!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The loss of her sits closer to my heart Than that of kingdom or the whorish pomp Of this world&#8217;s titles, that with flattery swells us And makes us die like beasts fat for destruction.</LINE>
<LINE>But when she turns her head by chance and sees The fortunes that are my companions,</LINE>
<LINE>She'll snatch her eyes off and repent the looking.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis well advised: we doom thee, Govianus, To banishment forever from our kingdom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What could be worse to one whose heart is locked Up in another&#8217;s bosom! Banishment!</LINE>
<LINE>And why not death? Is that too easy for me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But that the world would call our way to dignity</LINE>
<LINE>A path of blood, it should be the first act in all our reign.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She&#8217;s lost forever!</LINE>
<LINE>To Nobles Farewell, virtuous men, Too honest for your greatness. Now y&#8217;are mightier Than when we knew the kingdom; your style&#8217;s heavier.</LINE>
<LINE>Then, ponderous nobility, farewell!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. NOBLE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How&#8217;s that, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Weighty and serious!—O, sir, is it you?</LINE>
<LINE>When your discretion sucked; is&#8216;t come from nurse yet?</LINE>
<LINE>You seem to be a scholar; you were born better.</LINE>
<LINE>You have good lands; that&#8217;s the best grounds of learning.</LINE>
<LINE>If you can conster but your doctor&#8217;s bill,</LINE>
<LINE>Pierce your wife&#8217;s waiting-women, and decline your tenants</LINE>
<LINE>Till they're all beggars with new fines and rackings,</LINE>
<LINE>Y'are scholar good enough for a lady&#8217;s son</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s born to living. If you list to read,</LINE>
<LINE>Ride but to th' city and bestow your looks</LINE>
<LINE>On the court library, the mercers&#8217; books;</LINE>
<LINE>They&#8217;ll quickly furnish you: do but entertain</LINE>
<LINE>A tailor for your tutor to expound</LINE>
<LINE>All the hard stuff to you, by what name and title</LINE>
<LINE>Soever they be called.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. NOBLE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I thank you, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis happy you have learnt so much manners, Since you have so little wit. Fare you well, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him be stayed awhile.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. NOBLE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="9">Stay!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. NOBLE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">You must stay, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s not so honest, sure, to change his mind, Revoke his doom. Hell has more hope on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have not ended yet; the worst part&#8217;s coming: Thy banishment were gentle were that all. But t'afflict thy soul, before thou goest Thou shalt behold the heaven that thou must lose In her that must be mine. Then to be banished, then to be deprived, Shows the full torment we provide for thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here&#8217;s a right tyrant now; he will not bate me Th'affliction of my soul; he'll have all parts Suffer together.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter the Nobles with the Lady clad in black.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now I see my loss; I never shall recover&#8216;t; my mind&#8217;s beggared.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Black! Whence risse that cloud? Can such a</LINE>
<LINE>thing be seen</LINE>
<LINE>In honour&#8217;s glorious day, the sky so clear?</LINE>
<LINE>Why mourns the kingdom&#8217;s mistress? Does she come</LINE>
<LINE>To meet advancement in a funeral garment?</LINE>
<LINE>Back! She forgot herself. 'Twas too much joy</LINE>
<LINE>That bred this error, and we heartily pardon&#8217;t.</LINE>
<LINE>To the attending Nobles Go, bring me her hither like an illustrious bride With her best beams about her. Let her jewels Be worth ten cities; that beseems our mistress, And not a widow&#8217;s case, a suit to weep in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not to be altered.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I have a mind</LINE>
<LINE>That must be shifted ere I cast off these, Or else I shall wear strange colours. 'Tis not titles, Nor all the bastard honours of this frame That I am taken with. I come not hither</LINE>
<LINE>To please the eye of glory, but of goodness;</LINE>
<LINE>And that concerns not you, sir; you're for greatness I dare not deal with you: I have found my match, And I will never lose him.</LINE>
<LINE>Looks at Govianus</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If there be man Above a king in fortunes, read my story</LINE>
<LINE>And you shall find him there. Farewell, poor kingdom!</LINE>
<LINE>To the Tyrant Take it to help thee; thou hast need on&#8217;t now. I see thee in distress, more miserable Than some thou lay&#8217;st taxations on, poor subjects! Th'art all beset with storms, more overcast</LINE>
<LINE>Than ever any man that brightness flattered.</LINE>
<LINE>Tis only wretchedness to be there with thee, And happiness to be here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Sure some dream crowned me.</LINE>
<LINE>If it were possible to be less than nothing, I wake the man you seek for. There&#8217;s the kingdom Within yon valley fixed, while I stand here</LINE>
<LINE>Kissing false hopes upon a frozen mountain, Without the confines. I am he that&#8217;s banished. The king walks yonder, chose by her affection, Which is the surer side, for where she goes</LINE>
<LINE>Her eye removes the court. What is he here</LINE>
<LINE>Can spare a look? They're all employed on her. Helvetius! Thou art not worth the waking neither; I lose but time in thee. Go sleep again: Like an old man, thou can&#8217;st do nothing;</LINE>
<LINE>Thou tak&#8217;st no pains at all to earn thine honours</LINE>
<LINE>Which way shall we be able to pay thee</LINE>
<LINE>To thy content, when we receive not ours?</LINE>
<LINE>The master of the work must needs decay</LINE>
<LINE>When he wants means, and sees his servant play.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">To the Lady</LINE>
<LINE>Have I bestowed so many blessings on thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And do they all return to me in curses? Is that the use I ha&#8217; for &#8216;em? Be not to me A burden ten times heavier than my years! Thou'd&#8217;st wont to be kind to me and observe</LINE>
<LINE>What I thought pleasing. Go, entreat the king!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will do more for you, sir; y&#8217;are my father; I&#8217;ll kiss him, too.</LINE>
<LINE>She kisses Govianus</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How am I dealt withal?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why that&#8217;s the usurper, sir; this is the king. I happened lighter than you thought I had.</LINE>
<LINE>And were all kingdoms of the earth his own,</LINE>
<LINE>As sure as this is not, and this dear gentleman</LINE>
<LINE>As poor as virtue and almost as friendless,</LINE>
<LINE>I would not change this misery for that sceptre</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein I had part with him. Sir, be cheerfiil.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis not the reeling fortune of great state</LINE>
<LINE>Or low condition that I cast mine eye at. It is the man I seek; the rest I lose As things unworthy to be kept or noted. Fortunes are but the outsides of true worth.</LINE>
<LINE>It is the mind that sets his master forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has there so many bodies been hewn down Like trees in progress, to cut out a way That was ne&#8217;er known, for us and our affections, And is our game so crossed? There stands the first Of all her kind that ever refused greatness—</LINE>
<LINE>A woman to set light by sovereignty! What age can bring her forth, and hide that book? 'Tis their desire most commonly to rule More than their part comes to—sometimes their husbands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis in your power, my lord, to force her to you</LINE>
<LINE>And pluck her from his arms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Thou talk&#8217;st unkindly.</LINE>
<LINE>That had been done before thy thought begot it If my affection could be so hard-hearted To stand upon such payment. It must come</LINE>
<LINE>Gently and kindly, like a debt of love,</LINE>
<LINE>Or &#8216;tis not worth receiving.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Now usurper,</LINE>
<LINE>I wish not happier freedom than the banishment That thou hast laid upon me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, he kills me</LINE>
<LINE>At mine own weapon! 'Tis I that live in exile. Should she forsake the land, I&#8217;ll feign some cause</LINE>
<LINE>Far from the grief itself to call it back.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Govianus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>That doom of banishment was but lent to thee To make a trial of thy factious spirit, Which flames in thy desire. Thou wouldst be gone. There is some combination betwixt thee</LINE>
<LINE>And foreign plots; thou hast some powers to raise, Which, to prevent, thy banishment we revoke,</LINE>
<LINE>Confine thee to thy house nearest our court, And place a guard about thee. Lord Memphonius, See it effected.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With best care, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Confine me? Here&#8217;s my liberty in mine arms; I wish no better to bring me content. Love&#8217;s best freedom is close prisonment!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Lady and Govianus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks the day e&#8217;en darkens at her absence.</LINE>
<LINE>I stand as in a shade, when a great cloud</LINE>
<LINE>Muffles the sun, whose beams shine afar off On tow'rs and mountains; But I keep the valleys, The place that is last served.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your reason, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your grace is mild to all but your own bosom. They should have both been sent to several prisons, And not committed to each other&#8217;s arms. There&#8217;s a hot durance! He'll ne&#8217;er wish more freedom!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis true; let &#8216;em be both forced back. Stay, we command you!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou talk&#8217;st not like a statesman. Had my wrath Took hold of such extremity at first, They'd lived suspectful still, warned by their fears; Where, now that liberty makes &#8216;em more secure, I&#8217;ll take &#8216;em at my pleasure. It gives thee Freer access to play the father for us, And ply her to our will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mass, so it does.</LINE>
<LINE>Let a man think on&#8217;t twice, your grace hath happened Upon a strange way, yet it proves the nearest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, more to vex his soul, give command straight</LINE>
<LINE>They be divided into several rooms,</LINE>
<LINE>Where he may only have a sight of her To his mind&#8217;s torment, but his arms and lips Locked up like felons from her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Now you win me.</LINE>
<LINE>I like that cruelty passing well, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give order with all speed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Though I be old,</LINE>
<LINE>I need no spur, my lord; honour pricks me. I do beseech your grace look cheerfully. You shall not want content if it be locked In any blood of mine. The key&#8217;s your own. You shall command the words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Say&#8217;st thou so, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>I were ingrateful then, should I see thee Want honour, that provides content for me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt. A Flourish.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The home of Anselmus.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Lord Anselmus, Votarius, Wife Camilla, Leonella, Bellarius)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Lord Anselmus, the deposed king&#8217;s brother, with his friend, Votarius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, sir, confine your thoughts and excuse me.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks the deposed king your brother&#8217;s sorrow Should find you business enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How, Votarius!</LINE>
<LINE>Sorrow for him? Weak ignorance talks not like thee. Why, he was never happier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Pray prove that, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>H&#8217;as lost the kingdom, but his mind&#8217;s restored.</LINE>
<LINE>Which is the larger empire, prithee tell me.</LINE>
<LINE>Dominions have their limits; the whole earth Is but a prisoner, nor the sea her jailor, That with a silver hoop locks in her body.</LINE>
<LINE>They're fellow prisoners, though the sea looks bigger</LINE>
<LINE>Because he is in office and pride swells him.</LINE>
<LINE>But the unbounded kingdom of the mind</LINE>
<LINE>Is as unlimitable as heaven, that glorious court of spirits,</LINE>
<LINE>All honest courtiers!</LINE>
<LINE>Sir, if thou lov&#8217;st me, turn thine eye to me,</LINE>
<LINE>And look not after him that needs thee not.</LINE>
<LINE>My brother&#8217;s well attended; peace and pleasure</LINE>
<LINE>Are never from his sight. He has his mistress.</LINE>
<LINE>She brought those servants and bestowed them on him.</LINE>
<LINE>But who brings mine?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Had you not both long since</LINE>
<LINE>By a kind, worthy lady, your chaste wife?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That&#8217;s it that I take pains with thee to be sure of. What true report can I send to my soul Of that I know not? We must only think</LINE>
<LINE>Our ladies are good people, and so live with &#8216;em:</LINE>
<LINE>A fine security for them! Our own thoughts Make the best fools of us; next to them, our wives.</LINE>
<LINE>But say she&#8217;s all chaste, yet is that her goodness?</LINE>
<LINE>What labour is&#8216;t for a woman to keep constant</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s never tried or tempted? Where&#8217;s her fight?</LINE>
<LINE>The war&#8217;s within her breast, her honest anger</LINE>
<LINE>Against the impudence of flesh and hell:</LINE>
<LINE>So let me know the lady of my rest,</LINE>
<LINE>Or I shall never sleep well. Give not me</LINE>
<LINE>The thing that is thought good, but what&#8217;s approved so:</LINE>
<LINE>So wise men choose. O, what a lazy virtue Is chastity in a woman if no sin Should lay temptation to&#8217;t! Prithee, set to her And bring my peace along with thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">You put to me</LINE>
<LINE>A business that will do my words more shame Than ever they got honour among women. Lascivious courtings among sinful mistresses Come ever seasonably, please best. But let the boldest ruffian touch the ear Of modest ladies with adulterous sounds, Their very looks confound him and force grace Into that cheek where impudence sets her seal. That work is never undertook with courage That makes his master blush. However, sir, What profit can return to you by knowing That which you do already, with more toil? That a man needs, in having a rich diamond, Put it between a hammer and an anvil, And not believing the true worth and value, Break it in pieces to find out the goodness, And in the finding lose it? Good sir, think on&#8217;t! Nor does it taste of wit to try their strengths That are created sickly, nor of manhood. we ought not to put blocks in women&#8217;s ways, For some too often fall upon plain ground. Let me dissuade you, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Have I a friend?</LINE>
<LINE>And has my love so little interest in him That I must trust some stranger with my heart, And go to seek him out?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nay, hark you, sir!</LINE>
<LINE>I am so jealous of your weaknesses, That rather than you should lie prostituted Before a stranger&#8217;s triumph, I would venture A whole hour&#8217;s shaming for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Be worth thy word, then!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Wife.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Yonder she comes. I&#8217;ll have an ear to you both; I love to have such things at the first hand. He hides within hearing</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll put him off with somewhat; guile in this Falls in with honest dealing. O, who could move Adultery to yon face! So rude a sin May not come near the meekness of her eye. My client&#8217;s cause looks so dishonestly I&#8217;ll ne&#8217;er be seen to plead in&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What, Votarius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good morrow, virtuous madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Was my lord</LINE>
<LINE>Seen lately here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">He&#8217;s newly walked forth, lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How was he attended?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Faith, I think with none, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That sorrow for the king his brother&#8217;s fortune</LINE>
<LINE>Prevails too much with him, and leads him strangely From company and delight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How she&#8217;s beguiled in him!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s no such natural touch, search all his bosom.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aloud.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>That grief&#8217;s too bold with him indeed, sweet madam. And draws him from the pleasure of his time,</LINE>
<LINE>But &#8216;tis a business of affection</LINE>
<LINE>That must be done. we owe a pity, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>To all men&#8217;s misery, but especially</LINE>
<LINE>To those afflictions that claim kindred of us.</LINE>
<LINE>We&#8217;re forced to feel &#8216;em: all compassion else</LINE>
<LINE>Is but a work of charity, this, of nature, And ties our pity in a bond of blood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet, sir, there is a date set to all sorrows. Nothing is everlasting in this world. Your counsel will prevail: persuade him, good sir, To fall into life&#8217;s happiness again, And leave the desolate path. I want his company: He walks at midnight in thick shady [dark] woods Where scarce the moon is starlight. I have watched him In silver nights when all the earth was dressed Up like a virgin in white innocent beams; Stood in my window cold and thinly clad T'observe him through the bounty of the moon That liberally bestowed her graces on me. And when the morning dew began to fall, Then was my time to weep. H&#8217;as lost his kindness, Forgot the way of wedlock, and become A stranger to the joys and rites of love. He&#8217;s not so good as a lord ought to be. Pray tell him so from me, sir. Exit Wife</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That will I, madam.</LINE>
<LINE>How must I dress a strange dish for his humour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Anselmus from his hiding place.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Call you this courting? Life, not one word near it! There was no syllable but was twelve score off. My faith, hot temptation! Woman&#8217;s chastity</LINE>
<LINE>In such a conflict had great need of one</LINE>
<LINE>To keep the bridge. 'Twas dangerous for the time.</LINE>
<LINE>Why, what fantastic faiths are in these days</LINE>
<LINE>Made without substance! Whom should a man trust</LINE>
<LINE>In matters about love?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Anselmus comes forward.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Mass, here he comes, too!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, Votarius! What&#8217;s the news for us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You set me to a task, sir, that will find Ten ages work enough, and then unfinished. Bring sin before her! Why, it stands more quaking Than if a judge should frown on&#8217;t. Three such fits Would shake it into goodness, and quite beggar</LINE>
<LINE>The under-kingdom. not the art of man, Woman or devil—</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, peace, man! Prithee, peace!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Can make her fit for lust.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Yet again, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>Where lives that mistress of thine, Votarius,</LINE>
<LINE>That taught thee to dissemble? I&#8216;d fain learn;</LINE>
<LINE>She makes good scholars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art the son of falsehood. Prithee, leave me. How truly constant, charitable, and helpful Is woman unto woman in affairs</LINE>
<LINE>That touch affection and the peace of spirit;</LINE>
<LINE>But man to man, how crooked and unkind; I thank my jealousy I heard thee all, For I heard nothing; now thou'it sure I did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now by this light, then, wipe but off this score,</LINE>
<LINE>Since y&#8217;are so bent, and if I ever run</LINE>
<LINE>In debt again to falsehood and dissemblance,</LINE>
<LINE>For want of better means, tear the remembrance of me</LINE>
<LINE>From your best thoughts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For thy vow&#8217;s sake, I pardon thee</LINE>
<LINE>Thy oath is now sufficient watch itself</LINE>
<LINE>Over thy actions. I discharge my jealousy:</LINE>
<LINE>I ha&#8217; no more use for&#8216;t now. To give thee way</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll have an absence made purposely for thee, And presently take horse. I&#8217;ll leave behind me An opportunity that shall fear no starting. Let thy pains deserve it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am bound to&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For a small time, farewell then. Hark thee!</LINE>
<LINE>Anselmus whispers in his ear</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O good sir!</LINE>
<LINE>It will do wondrous well.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What a wild seed Suspicion sows in him, and takes small ground for&#8216;t! But happy were this lord if he would leave</LINE>
<LINE>To tempt his fate and be resolved he were so!</LINE>
<LINE>He would be but too rich.</LINE>
<LINE>Man has some enemy still that keeps him back</LINE>
<LINE>In all his fortunes, and his mind is his,</LINE>
<LINE>And that&#8217;s a mighty adversary. I had rather</LINE>
<LINE>Have twenty kings my enemies than that part;</LINE>
<LINE>For let me be at war with earth and hell So that be friends with me! I ha&#8217; sworn to make A trial of her faith. I must put on A courtier&#8217;s face and do&#8216;t; mine own will shame me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Wife.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is most strange of all! How one distraction Seconds another!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s the news, sweet madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>H&#8217;as took his horse, but left his leave untaken. What should I think on&#8217;t, sir? Did ever lord Depart so rudely from his lady&#8217;s presence?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did he forget your lip?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That nobleness remembers.</LINE>
<LINE>He forgot all</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;m ashamed on him.</LINE>
<LINE>Let me help, madam, to repair his manners, And mend that unkind fault.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir! Pray, forbear!</LINE>
<LINE>You forget worse than he.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>So virtue save me,</LINE>
<LINE>I have enough already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tis himself</LINE>
<LINE>Must make amends, good sir, for his own faults.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I would he'd do&#8216;t then, and ne&#8217;er trouble mein&#8216;t.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aloud.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>But, madam, you perceive he takes the course</LINE>
<LINE>To be far off from that. He&#8217;s rode from home,</LINE>
<LINE>But his unkindness stays, and keeps with you.</LINE>
<LINE>Let whose will please his wife; he rides his horse;</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s all the care he takes. I pity you, madam;</LINE>
<LINE>Y'ave an unpleasing lord. Would &#8216;twere not so.</LINE>
<LINE>I should rejoice with you.</LINE>
<LINE>You're young, the very spring&#8217;s upon you now.</LINE>
<LINE>The roses on your cheeks are but new blown.</LINE>
<LINE>Take you together, y&#8217;are a pleasant garden</LINE>
<LINE>Where all the sweetness of man&#8217;s comfort breathes.</LINE>
<LINE>But what is it to be a work of beauty</LINE>
<LINE>And want the heart that should delight in you?</LINE>
<LINE>You still retain your goodness in yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>But then you lose your glory, which is all.</LINE>
<LINE>The grace of every benefit is the use,</LINE>
<LINE>And is&#8216;t not pity you should want your grace?</LINE>
<LINE>Look you like one whose lord should walk in groves</LINE>
<LINE>About the peace of midnight? Alas, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis to me wondrous how you should spare the day</LINE>
<LINE>From amorous clips, much less the general season</LINE>
<LINE>When all the world&#8217;s a gamester!</LINE>
<LINE>That face deserves a friend of heart and spirit,</LINE>
<LINE>Discourse, and motion, indeed such a one That should observe you, madam, without ceasing, And not a weary lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Sure I was married, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>In a dear year of love, when scarcity And famine of affection vexed poor ladies, Which makes my heart so needy. It ne&#8217;er knew Plenty of comfort yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, that&#8217;s your folly,</LINE>
<LINE>To keep your mind so miserably, madam. Change into better times; I&#8217;ll lead you to &#8216;em. What bounty shall your friend expect for his?</LINE>
<LINE>O you that can be hard to your own heart,</LINE>
<LINE>But would you use your friend&#8217;s? If I thought kindly, I&#8216;d be the man myself to serve your pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Now, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, and ne&#8217;er miss you, too. I&#8216;d not come sneaking Like a retainer once a week or so To show myself before you for my livery; I&#8216;d follow business like a household servant, Carry my work before me, and dispatch Before my lord be up, and make no words on&#8217;t— The sign of a good servant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">'Tis not friendly done, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>To take a lady at advantage thus: Set all her wrongs before her, and then tempt her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Heart! I grow fond myself! 'Twas well</LINE>
<LINE>she waked me</LINE>
<LINE>Before the dead sleep of adultery took me; 'Twas stealing on me. Up, you honest thoughts, And keep watch for your master! I must hence.</LINE>
<LINE>I do not like my health; &#8216;t'as a strange relish.</LINE>
<LINE>Pray heaven I plucked mine eyes back time enough! I&#8217;ll never see her more. I praised the garden But little thought a bed of snakes lay hid in&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>He prepares to leave</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I know not how I am! I&#8217;ll call my woman— Stay, for I fear thou'rt too far gone already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll see her but once more. Do thy worst, love!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art too young, fond boy, to master me.</LINE>
<LINE>He returns to the Wife I come to tell you, madam, and that plainly I&#8217;ll see your face no more. Take&#8216;t how you please.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You will not offer violence to me, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>In my lord&#8217;s absence! What does that touch you If I want comfort?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Will you take your answer?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is not honest in you to tempt woman:</LINE>
<LINE>When her distresses takes away her strength, How is she able to withstand her enemy?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would fain leave your sight and I could possible.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is&#8216;t to you, good sir, if I be pleased</LINE>
<LINE>To weep myself away, and run thus violently Into the arms of death, and kiss destruction? Does this concern you now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Ay, marry, does it!</LINE>
<LINE>What serve these arms for but to pluck you back, These lips but to prevent all other tasters,</LINE>
<LINE>And keep that cup of nectar for themselves?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Heart, I&#8217;m beguiled again! Forgive me, heav&#8217;n, My lips have been naught with her! Sin&#8217;s mere</LINE>
<LINE>witchcraft.</LINE>
<LINE>Break all the engines of life&#8217;s frame in pieces, I will be master once, and whip the boy</LINE>
<LINE>Home to his mother&#8217;s lap. Face, fare thee well!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Votarius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Votarius! Sir! My friend! Thank heav&#8217;n, he&#8217;s gone.</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall never come so near again; I&#8217;ll have my frailty watched over. Henceforward I&#8217;ll no more trust it single. It betrays me</LINE>
<LINE>Into the hands of folly. Where&#8217;s my woman?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Leonella.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My trusty Leonella!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Call you, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call I? I want attendance! Where are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never far from you, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Pray be nearer,</LINE>
<LINE>Or there is some that will, and thank you, too,</LINE>
<LINE>May perhaps bribe you to be absent from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Is that strange to a lady&#8217;s woman?</LINE>
<LINE>There are such things i&#8216;th world, many such buyers And sellers of a woman&#8217;s name and honour,</LINE>
<LINE>Though you be young in bribes, and never came</LINE>
<LINE>To the flesh-market yet. Beshrew your heart For keeping so long from me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What ail you, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Somewhat commands me, and takes all the power Of myself from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What should that be, lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When did you see Votarius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Is that next?</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, then I have your ladyship in the wind.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aloud.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I saw him lately, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Whom didst see?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Votarius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What have I to do with him</LINE>
<LINE>More than another man? Say he be fair,</LINE>
<LINE>And has parts proper both of mind and body,</LINE>
<LINE>You praise him but in vain in telling me so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Yea, madam, are you prattling in your sleep? 'Tis well my lord and you lie in two beds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I was ne&#8217;er so ill. I thank you, Leonella,</LINE>
<LINE>My negligent woman! Here you showed your service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Life! Have I a power or means to stop a sluice At a high water? What would sh'ave me do in&#8216;t?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I charge thee, while thou liv&#8217;st with me, henceforward Use not an hour&#8217;s absence from my sight.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Wife.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my faith, madam, you shall pardon me.</LINE>
<LINE>I have a love of mine own to look to, And he must have his breakfast. Pist! Bellarius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Bellarius, muffled in his cloak.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Leonella!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come forth, and show yourself a gentleman,</LINE>
<LINE>Although most commonly they hide their heads,</LINE>
<LINE>As you do there, methinks! And why a taffety muffler? Show your face, man! I&#8217;m not ashamed on you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear the servants.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And they fear their mistresses, and ne&#8217;er think on you;</LINE>
<LINE>Their thoughts are upon dinner and great dishes.</LINE>
<LINE>If one thing hap, impossible to fail to</LINE>
<LINE>(I can see so far in&#8216;t), you shall walk boldly, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>And openly in view through every room</LINE>
<LINE>About the house, and let the proudest meet thee;</LINE>
<LINE>I charge you give no way to &#8216;em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How thou talk&#8217;st!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I can avoid the fool, and give you reason for&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>i f</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis more than I should do, if I asked more on thee. I prithee tell me how.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With ease, i&#8217;faith, sir.</LINE>
<LINE>My lady&#8217;s heart is wondrous busy, sir, About the entertainment of a friend too;</LINE>
<LINE>And she and I must bear with one another, Or we shall make but a madhouse betwixt us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;m bold to throw my cloak off at this news, Which I ne&#8217;er durst before, and kiss thee freelier. What is he, sirrah?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Faith, anindifferent fellow</LINE>
<LINE>With good long legs—a near friend of my lord&#8217;s.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A near friend of my lady&#8217;s, you would say! His name, I prithee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">One Votarius, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What sayest thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">He walks under the same title.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The only enemy that my life can show me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your enemy! Let my spleen then alone with him. Stay you your anger; I&#8217;ll confound him for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As how, I prithee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I&#8217;ll prevent his venery.</LINE>
<LINE>He shall ne&#8217;er lie with my lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Troth, I thank you.</LINE>
<LINE>Life, that&#8217;s the way to save him! Art thou mad?</LINE>
<LINE>Whereas the other way fie confounds himself, And lies more naked to revenge and mischief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then let him lie with her, and the devil go with him!</LINE>
<LINE>He shall have all my furtherance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, now you pray heartily, and speak to purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 2</ACTTITLE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The house of Govianus&#8217;s imprisonment.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Lady of Govianus, Servant, Helvetius)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter The Lady of Govianus, with a Servant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who is&#8216;t would speak with us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">My lord your father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My father! Pray make haste; he waits too long. Entreat him hither.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Servant.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>In spite of all</LINE>
<LINE>The tyrant&#8217;s cruelties, we have got that friendship</LINE>
<LINE>E&#8217;en of the guard that he has placed about us.</LINE>
<LINE>My lord and I have free access together,</LINE>
<LINE>As much as I would ask of liberty.</LINE>
<LINE>They&#8217;ll trust us largely now, and keep sometimes</LINE>
<LINE>Three hours from us, a rare courtesy</LINE>
<LINE>In jailors&#8217; children. Some mild news, I hope,</LINE>
<LINE>Comes with my father.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>No, his looks are sad; There is some further tyranny. Let it fall! Our constant suff&#8217;rings shall amaze it.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>She kneels before her father.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Rise.</LINE>
<LINE>I will not bless thee. Thy obedience</LINE>
<LINE>Is after custom, as most rich men pray,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose saint is only fashion and vainglory.</LINE>
<LINE>So &#8216;tis with thee in thy dissembled duty;</LINE>
<LINE>There is no religion in&#8216;t, no reverent love;</LINE>
<LINE>Only for fashion and the praise of men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why should you think so, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think? You come too late</LINE>
<LINE>If you seek there for me. I know&#8216;t and see&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll sooner give my blessing to a drunkard,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom the ridiculous power of wine makes humble,</LINE>
<LINE>As foolish use makes thee. Base-spirited girl,</LINE>
<LINE>That can&#8217;st not think above disgrace and beggary,</LINE>
<LINE>When glory is set for thee and thy seed,</LINE>
<LINE>Advancement for thy father, beside joy</LINE>
<LINE>Able to make a latter spring in me</LINE>
<LINE>In this my fourscore summer, and renew me</LINE>
<LINE>With a reversion yet of heat and youth!</LINE>
<LINE>But the dejection of thy mind and spirit</LINE>
<LINE>Makes me, thy father, guilty of a fault</LINE>
<LINE>That draws thy birth in question, and e&#8217;en wrongs</LINE>
<LINE>Thy mother in her ashes, being at peace</LINE>
<LINE>With heaven and man. Had not her life and virtues</LINE>
<LINE>Been seals unto her faith, I should think thee now</LINE>
<LINE>The work of some hired servant, some house-tailor,</LINE>
<LINE>And no one part of my endeavor in thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Had I neglected greatness, or not rather</LINE>
<LINE>Pursued almost to my eternal hazard,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'dst ne&#8217;er been a lord&#8217;s daughter.</LINE>
<LINE>A shepherd&#8217;s, I&#8216;d been happier and more peaceful.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy very seed will curse thee in thy age When they shall hear the story of thy weakness: How in thy youth thy fortunes tendered thee A kingdom for thy servant, which thou left&#8217;st Basely to serve thyself. What does thou in this But merely cozen thy posterity Of royalty and succession, and thyself Of dignity present?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Sir, your king did well</LINE>
<LINE>'Mongst all his nobles to pick out yourself And send you with these words. His politic grace Knew what he did, for well he might imagine None else should have been heard:</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Had I been</LINE>
<LINE>They'd had their answer</LINE>
<LINE>Before the question had been half-way through. But, dearest sir, I owe to you a reverence, A debt which both begins and ends with life, Never till then discharged; &#8216;tis so long-lasting Yet could you be more precious than a father, Which, next a husband, is the richest treasure Mortality can show us, you should pardon me (And yet confess too that you found me kind) To hear your words, though I withstood your mind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say you so, daughter? Troth, I thank you kindly, I am in hope to rise well by your means, or you to rise yourself. We&#8217;re both beholding to you. Well, since I cannot win you, I commend you; I praise your constancy and pardon you. Take Govianus to you, make the most of him; Pick out your husband there, so you'll but grant me One light request that follows.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Heaven forbid else, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me the choosing of your friend, that&#8217;s all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, sir, my friend! A light request indeed! Somewhat too light, sir, either for my wearing or your own gravity, and you look on&#8217;t well!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pish! Talk like a courtier, girl, not like a fool! Thou know&#8217;st the end of greatness, and hast wit Above the flight of twenty feathered mistresses That glister in the sun of princes&#8217; favors. Thou hast discourse in thee fit for a king&#8217;s fellowship, A princely carriage and astonishing presence. What should a husband do with all this goodness? Alas, one end on&#8217;t is too much for him, Nor is it fit a subject should be master Of such a jewel. 'Tis in the king&#8217;s power To take it for the forfeit; but I come To bear thee gently to his bed of honours, All force forgotten. The king commends him to thee With more than the humility of a servant,</LINE>
<LINE>That since thou wilt not yield to be his queen, Be yet his mistress. He shall be content with that or nothing; he shall ask no more And with what easiness that is performed Most of your women know. Having a husband, That kindness costs thee nothing: y'ave that in All over and above to your first bargain, And that&#8217;s a brave advantage for a woman If she be wise, as I suspect not thee. And having youth, and beauty, and a husband, Thou&#8217;st all the wish of woman. Take thy time, then; Make thy best market.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Can you assure me, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether my father spake this? Or some spirit Of evil-wishing that has for a time Hired his voice of him to beguile me that way,</LINE>
<LINE>Presuming on his power and my obedience? I&#8216;d gladly know, that I might frame my answer According to the speaker.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How now, baggage!</LINE>
<LINE>Am I in question with thee? Does thy scorn cast So thick an ignorance before thine eyes</LINE>
<LINE>That I am forgotten too? Who is&#8216;t speaks to thee But thy father?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Govianus, discharging a pistol</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">The more monstrous he!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Helvetius falls.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Art down but with the bare voice of my fury? Up, ancient sinner! Thou'it but mocked with death. I missed thee purposely; thank this dear creature.</LINE>
<LINE>O, hadst thou been anything beside her father I&#8216;d made a fearful separation on thee. I would have sent thy soul to a darker prison Than any made of clay, and thy dead body</LINE>
<LINE>As a token to the lustful king thy master.</LINE>
<LINE>Art thou struck down so soon with the short sound Of this small earthen instrument, and dost thou So little fear th' eternal noise of hell?</LINE>
<LINE>What&#8217;s she? Does she not bear thy daughter&#8217;s name?</LINE>
<LINE>How stirs thy blood, sir? Is there a dead feeling</LINE>
<LINE>Of all things fatherly and honest in thee?</LINE>
<LINE>Say thou couldst be content, for greatness&#8217; sake,</LINE>
<LINE>To end the last act of thy life in panderism</LINE>
<LINE>(As you perhaps will say your betters do),</LINE>
<LINE>Must it needs follow that unmanly sin</LINE>
<LINE>Can work upon the weakness of no woman</LINE>
<LINE>But her whose name and honour natural love</LINE>
<LINE>Bids thee preserve more charily than eyesight,</LINE>
<LINE>Health, or thy senses? Can promotion&#8217;s thirst</LINE>
<LINE>Make such a father? Turn a grave old lord</LINE>
<LINE>To a white-headed squire? Make him so base</LINE>
<LINE>To buy his honours with his daughter&#8217;s soul</LINE>
<LINE>And the perpetual shaming of his blood?</LINE>
<LINE>Hast thou the leisure, thou forgetful man,</LINE>
<LINE>To think upon advancement at these years?</LINE>
<LINE>What wouldst thou do with greatness? Dost thou hope</LINE>
<LINE>To fray death with&#8216;t? Or hast thou that conceit</LINE>
<LINE>That honour will restore thy youth again?</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art but mocked, old fellow! Tis not so;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy hopes abuse thee. Follow thine own business</LINE>
<LINE>And list not to the sirens of the world.</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, thou hadst more need kneel at an altar</LINE>
<LINE>Than to a chair of state,</LINE>
<LINE>And search thy conscience for thy sins of youth;</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s work enough for age; it needs no greater.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'it called within. Thy very eyes look inward</LINE>
<LINE>To teach thy thoughts the way, and thy affections.</LINE>
<LINE>But miserable notes that conscience sings</LINE>
<LINE>That cannot truly pray, for flattering kings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This was well searched indeed, and without</LINE>
<LINE>favoring.</LINE>
<LINE>Blessing reward thee! Such a wound as mine Did need a pitiless surgeon. Smart on, soul! Thou&#8217;lt feel the less hereafter. Sir, I thank you. I ever saw my life in a false glass</LINE>
<LINE>Until this friendly hour. With what fair faces</LINE>
<LINE>My sins would look on me! But now truth shows &#8216;em, How loathsome and how monstrous are their forms!</LINE>
<LINE>Be you my king and master still! Henceforward My knee shall know no other earthly lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Well may I spend this life to do you service,</LINE>
<LINE>That sets my soul in her eternal way.</LINE>
<LINE>He kneels</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Rise! Rise, Helvetius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I&#8217;ll see both your hands</LINE>
<LINE>Set to my pardon first.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Mine shall bring hers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, sir, I honour you for your goodness chiefly,</LINE>
<LINE>Y'are my most worthy father; you speak like him.</LINE>
<LINE>The first voice was not his. My joy and reverence Strive which should be most seen. Let our hands, sir, Raise you from earth thus high, and may it prove</LINE>
<LINE>The Lady and Govianus raise him up The first ascent of your immortal rising Never to fall again!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">A spring of blessings</LINE>
<LINE>Keep ever with thee, and the fruit thy lord&#8217;s.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I ha&#8217; lost an enemy and have found a father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The home of Anselmus.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Votarius, Camilla, Leonella, Anselmus, Bellarius)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Votarius, sadly.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All&#8217;s gone; there&#8217;s nothing but the prodigal left</LINE>
<LINE>I have played away my soul at one short game</LINE>
<LINE>Where e&#8217;en the winner loses. Pursuing sin, how often did I shun thee! How swift art thou afoot, beyond man&#8217;s goodness, Which has a lazy pace! So was I catched. A curse upon the cause! Man in these days Is not content to have his lady honest And so rest pleased with her without more toil, But he must have her tried, forsooth, and tempted. And when she proves a queen then he lies quiet: Like one that has a watch of curious making, Thinking to be more cunning than the workman, Never gives over tampering with the wheels Till either spring be weakened, balance bowed, Or some wrong pin put in, and so spoils all. How could I curse myself! Most business else Delight in the dispatch, that&#8217;s the best grace to&#8217;t; Only this work of blind, repented lust Hangs shame and sadness on his master&#8217;s cheek, Yet wise men take no warning.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Wife.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Nor can I now;</LINE>
<LINE>Her very sight strikes my repentance backward;</LINE>
<LINE>It cannot stand against her. Chamber thoughts And words that have sport in &#8216;em, they're for ladies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My best and dearest servant!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Worthiest mistress!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leonella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Who&#8217;s that? My woman! She&#8217;s myself.</LINE>
<LINE>Proceed, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Not if you love your honour, madam.</LINE>
<LINE>I came to give you warning my lord&#8217;s come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Alas, poor vessels, how this tempest</LINE>
<LINE>tosses &#8216;em! They're driven both asunder in a twinkling.</LINE>
<LINE>Down goes the sails here, and the main mast yonder.</LINE>
<LINE>Here rides a bark with better fortune yet; I fear no tossing, come what weather will, I have a trick to hold out water still.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>His very name shoots like a fever through me.</LINE>
<LINE>Now hot, now cold. Which cheek shall I turn toward him,</LINE>
<LINE>For fear he should read guiltiness in my looks? I would he would keep from home like a wise man; 'Tis no place for him now. I would not see him Of any friend alive! It is not fit</LINE>
<LINE>We two should come together; we have abused</LINE>
<LINE>Each other mightily: he used me ill To employ me thus, and I ha&#8217; used him worse! I&#8217;m too mUch even with him.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Yonder&#8217;s a sight on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My loved and honoured lord! Most welcome, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They kiss.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, there&#8217;s a kiss! Methinks my lord</LINE>
<LINE>might taste Dissimulation rank in&#8216;t, if he had wit. He takes but of the breath of his friend&#8217;s lip. A second kiss is hers, but that she keeps For her first friend. we women have no cunning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You parted strangely from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That&#8217;s forgotten!</LINE>
<LINE>Votarius! I make speed to be in thine arms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You never come too soon, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Anselmus and Votarius converse apart.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How goes business?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray think upon some other subject, sir. What news at court?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Pish, answer me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, sir, would you have me work by wonders,</LINE>
<LINE>To strike fire out of ice? Y'are a strange lord, sir. Put me to possible things and find &#8216;em finished At your return to me; I can say no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see by this thou didst not try her thoroughly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, sir, not thoroughly! By this light he lives not</LINE>
<LINE>That could make trial of a woman better.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear thou wast too slack.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Good faith, you wrong me, sir.</LINE>
<LINE>She never found it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Then I've a jewel;</LINE>
<LINE>And nothing shall be thought too precious for her. I may advance my forehead and boast purely.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks I see her worth with clear eyes now. O, when a man&#8217;s opinion is at peace 'Tis a fine life to marry! No state&#8217;s like it.</LINE>
<LINE>To his Wife My worthy lady, freely I confess</LINE>
<LINE>To thy wronged heart. My passion had alate</LINE>
<LINE>Put rudeness on me, which I now put off. I will no more seem so unfashionable For pleasure and the chamber of the lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I&#8217;m glad you're changed so well, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Thank himself for&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Wife and Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This comes like physic when the party&#8217;s dead.</LINE>
<LINE>Flows kindness now, when &#8216;tis so ill-deserved? This is the fortune still. Well, for this trick I&#8217;ll save my husband and his friend a labour; I&#8217;ll never marry as long as I&#8217;m honest,</LINE>
<LINE>For commonly queens have the kindest husbands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Leonella; manet Votarius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not like his company now; &#8216;tis irksome; His eye offends me. Methinks &#8216;tis not kindly we two should live together in one house. And &#8216;tis impossible to remove me hence.</LINE>
<LINE>I must not give way first. She&#8217;s my mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>And that&#8217;s a degree kinder than a wife.</LINE>
<LINE>Women are always better to their friends</LINE>
<LINE>Than to their husbands, and more true to them.</LINE>
<LINE>Then let the worst give place, whom she'as least need on</LINE>
<LINE>He that can best be spared, and that&#8217;s her husband.</LINE>
<LINE>I do not like his overboldness with her;</LINE>
<LINE>He&#8217;s too familiar with the face I love.</LINE>
<LINE>I fear the sickness of affection.</LINE>
<LINE>I feel a grudging on&#8217;t; I shall grow jealous</LINE>
<LINE>E&#8217;en of that pleasure which she has by law,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall go near with her.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Bellarius, passing over the stage.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Life, &#8216;tis Bellarius, my rank enemy!</LINE>
<LINE>Mine eye snatched so much sight of him. What&#8217;s his business?</LINE>
<LINE>His face half-darkened, stealing through the house</LINE>
<LINE>With a whoremaster&#8217;s pace. I like it not!</LINE>
<LINE>This lady will be served like a great woman,</LINE>
<LINE>With more attendants, I perceive, than one.</LINE>
<LINE>She has her shift of friends. Mine enemy one!</LINE>
<LINE>Do we both shun each other&#8217;s company</LINE>
<LINE>In all assemblies public, at all meetings,</LINE>
<LINE>And drink to one another in one mistress? My very thought&#8217;s my poison. Tis high time To seek for help. Where is our head physician,</LINE>
<LINE>A doctor of my making and that lecher&#8217;s?</LINE>
<LINE>O, woman! When thou once leav&#8217;st to be good,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou car&#8217;st not who stands next thee. Every sin</LINE>
<LINE>Is a companion for thee, for thy once-cracked honesty</LINE>
<LINE>Is like the breaking of whole money;</LINE>
<LINE>It never comes to good, but wastes away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Votarius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">We miss you, sir, within.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I missed you more without. Would you had come</LINE>
<LINE>sooner, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, what&#8217;s the business?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">You should ha&#8217; seen a fellow,</LINE>
<LINE>A common bawdy-house ferret, one Bellarius, Steal through this room, his whorish, barren face Three-quarters muffled. He is somewhere hid</LINE>
<LINE>About the house, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Which way took the villain,</LINE>
<LINE>That marriage felon, one that robs the mind Twenty times worse than any highway-striker? Speak! Which way took he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Marry, my lord, I think—</LINE>
<LINE>Let me see, which way Was&#8217;t, now? Up yon stairs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The way to chambering! Did not I say still All thy temptations were too faint and lazy? Thou dids&#8216;t not play &#8216;em home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">To tell you true, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>I found her yielding ere I left her last, And wavering in her faith.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Did I not think so!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That makes me suspect him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, partial man,</LINE>
<LINE>Coulds&#8216;t thou hide this from me, so dearly sought for, And rather waste thy pity upon her? Thou'rt not so kind as my heart praised thee to me. Hark!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Sound of footsteps, above.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tis his footing, certain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Are you chambered?</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll fetch you from aloft!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">He takes my work,</LINE>
<LINE>And toils to bring me ease. This use I&#8217;ll make on him: His care shall watch to keep all strange thieves out, Whiles I familiarly go in and rob him, Like one that knows the house. But how has rashness and my jealousy used me: Out of my vengeance to mine enemy Confessed her yielding! I have locked myself From mine own liberty with that key. Revenge Does no man good but to his greater harm. Suspect and malice, like a mingled cup, Made me soon drunk. I knew not what I spoke, And that may get me pardon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Anselmus, a dagger in his hand, with Leonella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Confess, thou mystical panderess! Run, Votarius, To the back gate; the guilty slave leaped out And scaped me so.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Votarius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This strumpet locked him up</LINE>
<LINE>In her own chamber.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold, my lord! I might.</LINE>
<LINE>He is my husband, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, soul of cunning,</LINE>
<LINE>Came that arch-subtlety from thy lady&#8217;s counsel Or thine own sudden craft? Confess to me How oft thou hast been a bawd to their close actions, Or all thy light goes out!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, believe me.</LINE>
<LINE>In troth I love a man too well myself To bring him to my mistress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Leave thy sporting!</LINE>
<LINE>Or my next offer makes thy heart weep blood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, spare that strength, my lord, and I&#8217;ll reveal A secret that concerns you, for this does not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Back, back my fury, then!</LINE>
<LINE>It shall not touch thy breast. Speak freely, what is&#8216;t?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Votarius and my lady are false gamesters; They use foul play, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Thou liest!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Reward me then</LINE>
<LINE>For all together: if it prove not so, I&#8217;ll never bestow time to ask your pity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Votarius and thy lady! 'Twill ask days ere it be settled in belief. So rise! Go get thee to thy chamber.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">A pox on you</LINE>
<LINE>You hindered me of better business, thank you. H&#8217;as frayed a secret from me. Would he were whipped! Faith, from a woman a thing&#8217;s quickly slipped.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The royal court.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Tyrant, Sophonirus, Memphonius, Helvetius, Guard, Nobles)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter The Tyrant with Sophonirus, Memphonius and other Nobles. A flourish.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My joys have all false hearts! There&#8217;s nothing</LINE>
<LINE>true to me</LINE>
<LINE>That&#8217;s either kind or pleasant. I&#8217;m hardly dealt withal. I must not miss her. I want her sight too long.</LINE>
<LINE>Where&#8217;s this old fellow?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here&#8217;s one, my lord, of threescore and seventeen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Push! That old limber ass puts in his head still. Helvetius! Where is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not yet returned, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Your lordship lies!</LINE>
<LINE>Here comes the kingdom&#8217;s father. Who amongst you</LINE>
<LINE>Dares say this worthy man has not made speed? I would fain hear that fellow!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll not be he.</LINE>
<LINE>I like the standing of my head too well To have it mended.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Thy sight quickens me.</LINE>
<LINE>I find a better health when thou art present</LINE>
<LINE>Than all times else can bring me. Is the answer As pleasing as thyself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Of what, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Of what? Fie, no! He did not say so, did he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O no, my lord, not he spoke no such word.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll say as he would ha&#8216;t, for I&#8216;d be loath</LINE>
<LINE>To have my body used like butcher&#8217;s meat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When comes she to our bed?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Who, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark! You heard that plain amongst you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my lord, as plain as my wife&#8217;s tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>That drowns a saunce bell.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Let me alone to lay about for honour: I&#8217;ll shift for one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">When comes the lady, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>That Govianus keeps?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, that&#8217;s my daughter!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, is it so? Have you unlocked your memory? What says she to us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How thou tempt&#8217;st us!</LINE>
<LINE>What didst thou say to her, being sent from us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>More than was honest, yet it was but little.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How cruelly thou work&#8217;st upon our patience, Having advantage 'cause thou art her father!</LINE>
<LINE>But be not bold too far: if duty leave thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Respect will fall from us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Have I kept life</LINE>
<LINE>So long till it looks white upon my head, Been threescore years a courtier, and a flatterer not above threescore hours, which time&#8217;s repented Amongst my greatest follies, and am I at these days</LINE>
<LINE>Fit for no place but bawd to mine own flesh? You'll prefer all your old courtiers to good services. If your lust keep but hot some twenty winters, we are like to have a virtuous world of wives, Daughters and sisters, besides kinswomen</LINE>
<LINE>And cousin-Germans removed up and down, Where'er you please to have &#8216;em! Are white hairs A colour fit for pandars and flesh-brokers, Which are the honoured ornaments of age,</LINE>
<LINE>To which e&#8217;en kings owe reverence as they're men</LINE>
<LINE>And greater in their goodness than their greatness? And must I take my pay all in base money? I was a lord born, set by all court grace, And am I thrust now to a squire&#8217;s place?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How comes the moon to change so in this man,</LINE>
<LINE>That was at full but now in all performance, And swifter than my wishes? I beshrew that virtue that busied herself with him: she might have found Some other work. The man was fit for me</LINE>
<LINE>Before she spoiled him. She has wronged my heart in&#8216;t</LINE>
<LINE>And marred me a good workman. Now his art fails him,</LINE>
<LINE>What makes the man at court? This is no place</LINE>
<LINE>For fellows of no parts. He lives not here</LINE>
<LINE>That puts himself from action when we need him.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I take off all thy honours and bestow &#8216;em</LINE>
<LINE>On any of this rank that will deserve &#8216;em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, that&#8217;s I. Trouble your grace no further. I&#8217;ll undertake to bring her to your bed With some ten words. Marry, they're special charms; No lady can withstand &#8216;em. A witch taught me &#8216;em</LINE>
<LINE>If you doubt me, I&#8217;ll leave my wife in pawn For my true loyalty, and your majesty May pass away the time till I return. I have a care in all things.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That may thrive best</LINE>
<LINE>Which the least hope looks after; but, however,</LINE>
<LINE>Force shall help nature: I&#8217;ll be too sure now.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy willingness may be fortunate; we employ thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then I&#8217;ll go fetch my wife, and take my journey.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay! We require no pledge; we think thee honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Troth, the worse luck for me! We</LINE>
<LINE>had both been made by&#8216;t: It was the way to make my wife great, too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll teach you to be wide and</LINE>
<LINE>strange to me!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'lt feel thyself light shortly. I&#8217;ll not leave thee A title to put on but the bare name</LINE>
<LINE>That men must call thee by, and know thee miserable.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis miserable, king, to be of thy making and leave a better workman. If thy honours only keep life in baseness, take &#8216;em to thee And give &#8216;em to the hungry; there&#8217;s one gapes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One that will swallow you, sir, for that jest.</LINE>
<LINE>And all your titles after.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">The devil follow &#8216;em!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s room enough for him too. Leave me, thou king,</LINE>
<LINE>As poor as truth&#8212;the gentlewoman I now serve</LINE>
<LINE>And never will forsake her for her plainness—</LINE>
<LINE>That shall not alter me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">No? Our guard within there!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Guard.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GUARD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bear that old fellow to our castle prisoner. Give charge he be kept close.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Close prisoner,</LINE>
<LINE>Why, my heart thanks thee. I shall have more time And liberty to virtue in one hour</LINE>
<LINE>Than all these threescore years I was a courtier. So by imprisonment I sustain great loss; Heaven opens to that man the world keeps close.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Helvetius, with Guard.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I&#8217;ll not go to prison to try that.</LINE>
<LINE>Give me the open world; there&#8217;s a good air.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would fain send death after him, but I dare not. He knows I dare not; that would give just cause Of her unkindness everlasting to me. His life may thank his daughter. Sophonirus,</LINE>
<LINE>Here, take this jewel, bear it as a token</LINE>
<LINE>To our heart&#8217;s saint. 'Twill do thy words no harm;</LINE>
<LINE>Speech may do much, but wealth&#8217;s a greater charm</LINE>
<LINE>Than any made of words. And, to be sure,</LINE>
<LINE>If one or both should fail, I provide farther.</LINE>
<LINE>Call forth those resolute fellows whom our clemency</LINE>
<LINE>Saved from a death of shame in time of war</LINE>
<LINE>For field offences; give &#8216;em charge from us</LINE>
<LINE>They arm themselves with speed, beset the house</LINE>
<LINE>Of Govianus round, that if thou fail&#8217;st,</LINE>
<LINE>Or stay&#8217;st beyond the time thou leav&#8217;st with them,</LINE>
<LINE>They may with violence break in themselves And seize her for our use.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Tyrant and his court. Manet Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">They're not so saucy</LINE>
<LINE>To seize her for their own, I hope, As there are many knaves will begin first</LINE>
<LINE>And bring their lords the bottom. I have been served so</LINE>
<LINE>A hundred times myself by a scurvy page That I kept once but my wife loved him, And I could not help it</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A flourish. Exit Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>


<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 3</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The house of Govianus&#8217;s imprisonment.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Govianus, Lady Luscinda, Servant, Sophonirus, First Fellow, Second Fellow)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Govianus with his Lady and a Servant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">An old lord come from the court.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He should be wise, by&#8217;s years. He will not dare To come about such business; &#8216;tis not man&#8217;s work. Art sure he desired conference with thy lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sure, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Faith, thou'rt mistook; &#8216;tis with me, certain.</LINE>
<LINE>Let&#8217;s do the man no wrong. Go, know it truly, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This&#8217; a strange humour; we must know</LINE>
<LINE>things twice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Servant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There&#8217;s no man is so dull but he will weigh The work he undertakes, and set about it E&#8217;en in the best sobriety of his judgment,</LINE>
<LINE>With all his senses watchful. Then his guilt</LINE>
<LINE>Does equal his for whom &#8216;tis undertaken.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Servant.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What says he now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">E&#8217;en as he said at first, sir!</LINE>
<LINE>'Has business to my lady from the king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Still from the king! He will not come near, will he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, when he knows he shall, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I cannot think it:</LINE>
<LINE>Let him be tried!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Small trial will serve him, I warrant you, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sure honesty has left man; has fear forsook him? Yes, faith, there is no fear where there&#8217;s no grace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What way shall I devise to gI&#8217;m his answer?</LINE>
<LINE>Denial is not strong enough to serve, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, &#8216;t must have other helps.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I see he dares! O Patience! I shall lose a friend of thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I bring thee, precious lady, this dear stone,</LINE>
<LINE>And commendations from the king my master.</LINE>
<LINE>Govianus unsheathes his sword</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I set before thee, panderous lord, this steel,</LINE>
<LINE>And much good do&#8216;t thy heart! Fall to, and spare not!</LINE>
<LINE>He stabs Sophonirus</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Las, what have you done, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, sent a bawd</LINE>
<LINE>Home to his lodging; nothing else, sweetheart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, you have killed me, sir, and there&#8217;s an</LINE>
<LINE>end.</LINE>
<LINE>But you'll get nothing by the hand, my lord, When all your cards are counted. There be gamesters not far off, will set upon the winner And make a poor lord on you ere th'ave left you. I&#8217;m fetched in like a fool to pay the reckoning, Yet you'll save nothing by&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What riddle&#8217;s this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There she stands by thee now, who yet ere midnight must lie by the king&#8217;s side.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Who speaks that lie?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One hour will make it true! She cannot &#8217;scape</LINE>
<LINE>No more than I from death. Y'ave a great game on&#8217;t,</LINE>
<LINE>And you look well about you, that&#8217;s my comfort.</LINE>
<LINE>The house is round beset with armed men</LINE>
<LINE>That know their time, when to break in and seize on her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">'Tis boldly done to trouble me</LINE>
<LINE>When I've such business to despatch. Within, there!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Servant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Look out, and tell me what thou see&#8217;st.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Servant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SOPH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How quickly now my death will be revenged, Before the king&#8217;s first sleep! I depart laughing To think upon the deed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Sophonirus dies.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">'Tis thy banquet.</LINE>
<LINE>Down, villain, to thy everlasting weeping,</LINE>
<LINE>That canst rejoice so in the rape of virtue,</LINE>
<LINE>And sing light tunes in tempests, when near shipwrecked,</LINE>
<LINE>And have no plank to save us!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Servant.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now, sir, quickly!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which way soe&#8217;er I cast mine eye, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Out of all parts o' th' house, I may see fellows</LINE>
<LINE>Gathered in companies, and all whispering, Like men for treachery busy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">'Tis confirmed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Their eyes still fixed upon the doors and windows.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think thou&#8217;st never done; thou lov&#8217;st to talk on&#8217;t.</LINE>
<LINE>Tis fine discourse; prithee, find other business.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I&#8217;m gone. I&#8217;m a man quickly sneaped.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Servant.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>H&#8217;as flattered me with safety for this hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you leisure to stand idle? Why, my lord, It is for me they come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">For thee, my glory,</LINE>
<LINE>The riches of my youth. It is for thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then is your care so cold? Will you be robbed,</LINE>
<LINE>And have such warning of the thieves? Come on, sir, Fall to your business! Lay your hands about you! Do not think scorn to work. A resolute captain Will rather fling the treasure of his bark Into whales&#8217; throats than pirates should be gorged</LINE>
<LINE>with&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>Be not less man than he. Thou art master yet, And all&#8217;s at thy disposing. Take thy time; Prevent mine enemy! Away with me! Let me no more be seen! I&#8217;m like that treasure, Dangerous to him that keeps it. Rid thy hands on&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot lose thee so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Shall I be taken,</LINE>
<LINE>And lost the cruel&#8217;st way? Then wouldst thou curse That love that sent forth pity to my life. Too late thou wouldst!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, this extremity!</LINE>
<LINE>Hast thou no way to &#8217;scape &#8216;em but in soul? Must I meet peace in thy destruction, Or will it ne&#8217;er come at me? Tis a most miserable way to get it. I had rather be content to live without it Than pay so dear for&#8216;t and yet lose it too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, you do nothing; there&#8217;s no valour in you; Y'are the worst friend to a lady in affliction That ever love made his companion. For honour&#8217;s sake despatch me! Thy own thoughts Should stir thee to this act more than my weakness. The sufferer should not do&#8216;t. I speak thy part, Dull and forgetful man, and all to help thee. Is it thy mind to have me seized upon And borne with violence to the tyrant&#8217;s bed, There forced unto the lust of all his days?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, no! Thou liv&#8217;st no longer, now I think on&#8217;t; I take thee at all hazard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, stay! Hold, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lady, what had you made me done now!</LINE>
<LINE>You never cease till you prepare me cruel 'gainst my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And then you turn&#8216;t upon my hand and mock me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cowardly flesh!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou show&#8217;st thy faintness still. I felt thee shake, E&#8217;en when the storm came near thee. Thou'rt the same. But &#8216;twas not for thy fear I put death by.</LINE>
<LINE>I had forgot a chief and worthy business, Whose strange neglect would have made me forgotten Where I desire to be remembered most. I will be ready straight, sir.</LINE>
<LINE>She kneels in prayer</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, poor lady!</LINE>
<LINE>Why might not she expire now in that prayer, Since she must die, and never try worse ways? 'Tis not so happy, for we often see Condemned men sick to death, yet &#8216;tis their fortune To recover to their execution And rise again in health to set in shame. What if I steal a death unseen of her now, And close up all my miseries with mine eyes? O, fie! And leave her here alone! That were unmanly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, be now as sudden as you please, sir; I am ready to your hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">But that&#8217;s not ready.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis the hardest work that ever man was put to; I know not which way to begin to come to&#8217;t. Believe me, I shall never kill thee well. I shall but shame myself. It were but folly,</LINE>
<LINE>Dear soul, to boast of more than I can perform.</LINE>
<LINE>I shall not have the power to do thee right in&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou deserv&#8217;st death with speed, a quick despatch,</LINE>
<LINE>The pain but of a twinkling, and so sleep.</LINE>
<LINE>If I do&#8216;t, I shall make thee live too long,</LINE>
<LINE>And so spoil all that way. I prithee excuse me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I should not be disturbed, and you did well, sir. I have prepared myself for rest and silence, And took leave of words. I am like one Removing from her house, that locks up all,</LINE>
<LINE>And rather than she would displace her goods,</LINE>
<LINE>Makes shift with anything for the time she stays.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A knock.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Then look not for more speech: th'extremity speaks Enough to serve us both had we no tongues!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Knocking within.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Within.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Lord Sophonirus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Which hand shall I take?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Art thou yet ignorant? There is no way</LINE>
<LINE>But through my bosom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Must I lose thee then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Th'are but thine enemies that tell thee so.</LINE>
<LINE>His lust may part me from thee, but death, never; Thou canst not lose me there, for, dying thine,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou dost enjoy me still. Kings cannot rob thee.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Knocking within.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Within.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Do you hear, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Is it yet time, or no?</LINE>
<LINE>Honour remember thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I must! Come, prepare thyself!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never more dearly welcome!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Govianus runs at her, and falls by the way in a swound.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Alas, sir!</LINE>
<LINE>My lord! My love! O, thou poor-spirited man!</LINE>
<LINE>He&#8217;s gone before me. Did I trust to thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And has thou served me so? Left all the work</LINE>
<LINE>Upon my head, and stole away so smoothly?</LINE>
<LINE>There was not equal suffering shown in this;</LINE>
<LINE>And yet I cannot blame thee. Every man</LINE>
<LINE>Would seek his rest. Eternal peace sleep with thee!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>She takes up the sword of Govianus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Thou art my servant now. Come, thou hast lost A fearful master, but art now preferred Unto the service of a resolute lady, One that knows how to employ thee and scorns death As much as great men fear it. Where&#8217;s hell&#8217;s ministers?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A great knocking.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The tyrant&#8217;s watch and guard? 'Tis of much worth When with this key the prisoner can slip forth.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>The Lady kills herself. A great knock again.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Awakening.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now! What noise is this? I heard doors</LINE>
<LINE>beaten.</LINE>
<LINE>Where are my servants? Let men knock so loud Their master cannot sleep!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Within.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>And we'll break in, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Ha! Where&#8217;s my sword?</LINE>
<LINE>I had forgot my business. O, &#8216;tis done, And never was beholding to my hand! Was I so hard to thee? So respectless of thee</LINE>
<LINE>To put all this to thee, why, it was more than I was able to perform myself with all the courage that I could take to me. It tired me. I was fain to fall and rest; And hast thou, valiant woman, overcome Thy honour&#8217;s enemies with thine own white hand, Where virgin-victory sits, all without help? Eternal praise go with thee! Spare not now; Make all the haste you can. I&#8217;ll plant this bawd Against the door, the fittest place for him, That when with ungoverned weapons they rush in, Blinded with fury, they may take his death Into the purple number of their deeds, And wipe it off from mine. He places the corpse ofSophonirus against the door. A knocking within</LINE>
<LINE>How now, forbear!</LINE>
<LINE>My lord&#8217;s at hand!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Within.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>I hope the king&#8217;s officers are above &#8216;em all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Fellows, well-weaponed. They stab Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Life, what do you do! Take heed! Bless the old man!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My Lord, all-ass, my lord, he&#8217;s gone!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have no eyes to pierce through inch boards &#8216;twas his own folly; the king must be served,</LINE>
<LINE>And shall. The best is we shall ne&#8217;er be hanged for&#8216;t,</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s such a number guilty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Poor my lord!</LINE>
<LINE>He went some twice ambassador, and behaved himself so wittily in all his actions.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Seeing the Lady&#8217;s body.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My lord! What&#8217;s she?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Let me see!</LINE>
<LINE>What should she be? Now I remember her.</LINE>
<LINE>O, she was a worthy creature</LINE>
<LINE>Before destruction grew so inward with her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, for her worthiness, that&#8217;s no work of ours. You have a lady, sir; the king commands her</LINE>
<LINE>To court with speed, and we must force her thither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, she'll never strive with you; she was born e&#8217;en with the spirit of meekness. Is&#8216;t for the king?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For his own royal and most gracious lust, or let me ne&#8217;er be trusted.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Take her, then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Spoke like an honest subject, by my troth.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8216;d do the like myself to serve my prince. Where is she, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Look but upon yon face,</LINE>
<LINE>Then do but tell me where you think she is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Life, she&#8217;s not here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">She&#8217;s yonder.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, she&#8217;s gone</LINE>
<LINE>Where we shall ne&#8217;er come at her, I see that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>No, nor thy master neither. Now I praise Her resolution. 'Tis a triumph to me when I see those about her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>
 
<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How came this, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>The king must know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">From yon old fellow&#8217;s prattling.</LINE>
<LINE>All your intents he revealed largely to her,</LINE>
<LINE>And she was troubled with a foolish pride To stand upon her honour, and so died. 'Twas a strange trick of her. Few of your ladies</LINE>
<LINE>In ordinary will believe it. They abhor it.</LINE>
<LINE>They&#8217;ll sooner kill themselves with lust than for it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. FEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have done the king good service to kill him. More than we were aware on; but this news Will make a mad court. 'Twill be a hard office To be a flatterer now. His grace will run</LINE>
<LINE>Into so many moods there'll be no finding on him:</LINE>
<LINE>As good seek a wild hare without a hound now.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Speaks to corpse of Sophonirus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>A vengeance of your babbling! These old fellows</LINE>
<LINE>Will harken after secrets as their lives,</LINE>
<LINE>But keep &#8216;em in e&#8217;en as they keep their wives.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have watched fairly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Fellows. Manet Govianus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What a comfort &#8216;tis</LINE>
<LINE>To see &#8216;em gone without her! Faith, she told me Her everlasting sleep would bring me joy, Yet I was still unwilling to believe her, Her life was so sweet to me: like some man</LINE>
<LINE>In time of sickness that would rather wish</LINE>
<LINE>(To please his fearful flesh) his former health</LINE>
<LINE>Restored to him than death; when, after trial,</LINE>
<LINE>If it were possible, ten thousand worlds</LINE>
<LINE>Could not entice him to return again</LINE>
<LINE>And walk upon the earth from whence he flew;</LINE>
<LINE>So stood my wish, joyed in her life and breath,</LINE>
<LINE>Now gone, there is no heav&#8217;n but after death.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, thou delicious treasure of mankind:</LINE>
<LINE>To him that knows what virtuous woman is,</LINE>
<LINE>And can discreetly love her. The whole world</LINE>
<LINE>Yields not a jewel like her, ransack rocks</LINE>
<LINE>And caves beneath the deep. O, thou fair spring</LINE>
<LINE>Of honest and religious desires,</LINE>
<LINE>Fountain of weeping honour, I will kiss thee</LINE>
<LINE>After death&#8217;s marble lip! Thou'rt cold enough</LINE>
<LINE>To lie entombed now by my father&#8217;s side</LINE>
<LINE>Without offense in kindred. There I&#8217;ll place thee</LINE>
<LINE>With one I loved the dearest next to thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Help me to mourn, all that love chastity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 4</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The home of Anselmus.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Votarius, Anselmus’s Wife, Leonella, Bellairius)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Votarius with Anselmus&#8217;s Wife.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee forgive me, madam; come, thou shalt!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'faith, &#8216;twas strangely done, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I confess it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is that enough to help it, sir? 'Tis easy to draw a lady&#8217;s honour in suspicion,</LINE>
<LINE>But not so soon recovered and confirmed</LINE>
<LINE>To the first faith again from whence you brought it. Your wit was fetched out about other business, or such forgetfulness had never seized you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twas but an overflowing, a spring tide</LINE>
<LINE>In my affection, raised by too much love;</LINE>
<LINE>And that&#8217;s the worst words you can give it, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Jealous of me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Life, you'd a' sworn yourself, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>Had you been in my body, and changed cases, To see a fellow with a guilty pace</LINE>
<LINE>Glide through the room, his face three-quarters nighted,</LINE>
<LINE>As if a deed of darkness had hung on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I tell you twice, &#8216;twas my bold woman&#8217;s friend. He&#8217;ll take her impudence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, I have done, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Y'ave done too late, sir. Who shall do the rest now?</LINE>
<LINE>Confessed me yielding! Was thy way too free?</LINE>
<LINE>Why, didst thou long to be restrained? Pray, speak, sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A man cannot cozen you of the sin of weakness, Or borrow it of a woman for one hour, But how he&#8217;s wondered at. Where, search your lives, we shall ne&#8217;er find it from you; we can suffer you</LINE>
<LINE>To play away our days in idleness, And hide your imperfections with our loves, Or the most part of you would appear strange creatures; And now &#8216;tis but our chance to make an offer,</LINE>
<LINE>And snatch at folly, running, yet to see</LINE>
<LINE>How earnest y&#8217;are against us, as if we had robbed you Or the best gift your natural mother left you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis worth a kiss, i&#8217;faith, and thou shalt ha&#8216;t,</LINE>
<LINE>Were there not one more left for my lord&#8217;s supper. And now, sir, I've bethought myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That&#8217;s happy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You say We&#8217;re weak; but the best wits on you all Are glad of our advice, for aught I see, And hardly thrive without us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I&#8217;ll say so too,</LINE>
<LINE>To give you encouragement and advance your virtues 'Tis not good always to keep down a woman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, sir, since y'ave begun to make my lord A doubtful man of me, keep on that course, And ply his faith still with that poor belief That I&#8217;m inclining unto wantonness. Take heed you pass no further now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why, dost think</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll be twice mad together in one moon? That were too much for any freeman&#8217;s son After his father&#8217;s funeral.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Well, then thus, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Upholding still the same, as being emboldened</LINE>
<LINE>By some loose glance of mine, you shall attempt</LINE>
<LINE>(After y'ave placed my lord in some near closet) To thrust yourself into my chamber rudely, As if the game went forward to your thinking, Then leave the rest to me. I&#8217;ll so reward thee</LINE>
<LINE>With bitterness of words—but prithee pardon &#8216;em—</LINE>
<LINE>My lord shall swear me into honesty</LINE>
<LINE>Enough to serve his mind all his life after.</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, for a need, I&#8217;ll draw some rapier forth,</LINE>
<LINE>That shall come near my hand as &#8216;twere by chance,</LINE>
<LINE>And set a lively face upon my rage,</LINE>
<LINE>But fear thou nothing. I too dearly love thee</LINE>
<LINE>To let harm touch thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, it likes me rarely!</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll choose a precious time for&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Votarius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go thy ways; I&#8217;m glad I had it for thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leonella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, my lord entreats your company.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pshaw, ye!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Pshaw, ye! My lord entreats your company.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What now?</LINE>
<LINE>Are ye so short-heeled?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am as my betters are, then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How come you by such impudence alate, minion?</LINE>
<LINE>Y'are not content to entertain your playfellow</LINE>
<LINE>In your own chamber closely, which I think</LINE>
<LINE>Is large allowance for a lady&#8217;s woman.</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s many a good knight&#8217;s daughter is in service</LINE>
<LINE>And cannot get such favor of her mistress</LINE>
<LINE>But what she has by stealth; she and the chambermaid</LINE>
<LINE>Are glad of one between &#8216;em; and must you Give such bold freedom to your long-nosed fellow That eveiy room must take a taste of him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Does that offend your ladyship?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How think you, forsooth?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then he shall do&#8216;t again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">And again, madam!</LINE>
<LINE>So often till it please your ladyship; And when you like it, he shall do&#8216;t no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I know no difference, virtuous madam,</LINE>
<LINE>But in love all have privilege alike.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Y'are a bold queen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">And are not you, my mistress?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This&#8217; well, i&#8217;faith!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You spare not your own flesh no more than I; Hell take me and I spare you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, the wrongs</LINE>
<LINE>That ladies do their honours when they make Their slaves familiar with their weaknesses! They're ever thus rewarded for that deed; They stand in fear e&#8217;en of the groom they feed. I must be forced to speak my woman fair now, And be first friends with her. Nay, all too little. She may undo me at her pleasure else; She knows the way so well, myself not better, My wanton folly made a key for her To all the private treasure of my heart; She may do what she list.</LINE>
<LINE>Aloud</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pish!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, I am not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, what care I and you be!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, forgive me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have nothing to say to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, thou shalt wear this jewel for my sake. A kiss and friends; we'll never quarrel more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, choose you, faith; the best is, and</LINE>
<LINE>you do.</LINE>
<LINE>You know who'll have the worst on&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>True; myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Little thinks she I have set her forth already. I please my lord, yet keep her in awe too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One thing I had forgot; I prithee, wench,</LINE>
<LINE>Steal to Votarius closely, and remember him To wear some privy armour then about him, That I may feign a fury without fear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Armour! When, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">See now, I chid thee</LINE>
<LINE>When I least thought upon thee: thou'rt my best hand.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot be without thee. Thus then, sirrah:</LINE>
<LINE>To bear away suspicion from the thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>Of ruder-list'ning servants about house,</LINE>
<LINE>I have advised Votarius at fit time</LINE>
<LINE>Boldly to force his way into my chamber,</LINE>
<LINE>The admittance being denied him, and the passage</LINE>
<LINE>Kept strict by thee, my necessary woman.</LINE>
<LINE>(La! There I should ha&#8217; missed thy help again!)</LINE>
<LINE>At which attempt I&#8217;ll take occasion</LINE>
<LINE>To dissemble such an anger that the world</LINE>
<LINE>Shall ever after swear us to their thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>As clear and free from any fleshly knowledge, As nearest kindred are, or ought to be, Or what can more express it, if that failed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You know I&#8217;m always at your service, madam, But why some privy armour?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Marry, sweetheart,</LINE>
<LINE>The best is yet forgotten; thou shalt hang A weapon in some corner of the chamber, Yonder, or there—</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Or anywhere. Why, i&#8217;faith, madam,</LINE>
<LINE>Do you think I&#8217;m to learn how to hang a weapon? As much as I&#8217;m uncapable of what follows,</LINE>
<LINE>I've all your mind without books. Think it done, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, my good wench; I&#8217;ll never call thee worse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Wife.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, y&#8217;are like to ha&#8216;t again, and you do, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Bellairius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, art alone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Cuds me, what make you here, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>You're a bold long-nosed fellow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">So my lady says.</LINE>
<LINE>Faith, she and I have had a bout for you, sir, But she got nothing by&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Did I not say still</LINE>
<LINE>Thou wouldst be too adventurous!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Ne'er a whit, sir.</LINE>
<LINE>I made her glad to seek my friendship first.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my faith, that showed well. If you come off</LINE>
<LINE>So brave a conqueress, to&#8217;t again and spare not, I know not which way you should get more honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She trusts me now to cast a mist, forsooth, Before the servants&#8217; eyes. I must remember</LINE>
<LINE>Votarius to come once with privy armour</LINE>
<LINE>Into her chamber, when with feigned fury</LINE>
<LINE>And rapier drawn, which I must lay a purpose</LINE>
<LINE>Ready for her dissemblance, she will seem</LINE>
<LINE>T'act wonders for her juggling honesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wish no riper vengeance! Canst conceive me?</LINE>
<LINE>Votarius is my enemy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That&#8217;s stale news, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark what I say to thee; forget of purpose That privy armour; do not bless his soul With so much warning, nor his hated body</LINE>
<LINE>With such sure safety. Here express thy love:</LINE>
<LINE>Lay some empoisoned weapon next her hand,</LINE>
<LINE>That in that play he may be lost forever.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8216;d have him kept no longer; away with him!</LINE>
<LINE>One touch will set him flying! Let him go!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bribe me but with a kiss, it shall be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The royal court.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Tyrant, First Nobleman, Memphonius, First Soldier, Second Soldier, Third Soldier, Fourth Soldier)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Tyrant, wondrous discontentedly. Nobles afar off.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. NOBLE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Begone, or never see life more!</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll send thee far enough from court.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit First Noble.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Memphonius!</LINE>
<LINE>Where&#8217;s he now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Ever at your highness&#8217; service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How ar&#8217;st thou be so near, when we have threatened Death to thy fellow! Have we lost our power? Or thou thy fear? Leave us in time of grace; 'Twill be too late anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside, leaving.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>I think &#8216;tis so with thee already</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dead! And I so healthful! There&#8217;s no equality in this. Stay!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is that fellow brought the first report to us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He waits without.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I charge thee give command</LINE>
<LINE>That he be executed speedily,</LINE>
<LINE>As thou&#8216;t stand firm thyself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now by my faith</LINE>
<LINE>His tongue has helped his neck to a sweet bargain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Memphonius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Her own fair hand so cruel! Did she choose Destruction before me? Was I no better?</LINE>
<LINE>How much am I exalted to my face,</LINE>
<LINE>And where I would be graced, how little worthy!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s few kings know how rich they are in goodness,</LINE>
<LINE>Or what estate they have in grace and virtue.</LINE>
<LINE>There is so much deceit in glozers&#8217; tongues</LINE>
<LINE>The truth is taken from us; we know nothing</LINE>
<LINE>But what is for their purpose. That&#8217;s our stint;</LINE>
<LINE>We are allowed no more. O, wretched greatness!</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll cause a sessions for my flatterers</LINE>
<LINE>And have &#8216;em all hanged up. 'Tis done too late.</LINE>
<LINE>O she&#8217;s destroyed, married to death and silence,</LINE>
<LINE>Which nothing can divorce, riches nor laws,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor all the violence that this fame can raise.</LINE> 
<LINE>I've lost the comfort of her sight forever.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot call this life that flames within me,</LINE>
<LINE>But everlasting torment lighted up</LINE>
<LINE>To show my soul her beggary! A new joy</LINE>
<LINE>Is come to visit me in spite of death!</LINE>
<LINE>It takes me of that sudden, I&#8217;m ashamed</LINE>
<LINE>Of my provision, but a friend will bear. Within there!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The men I wished for, for secrecy and employment. Go, give order that Govianus be released.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>4. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Released, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Set free. And then I trust he will fly the kingdom, And never know my purpose. Run, sir!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Fourth Soldier.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>To First Soldier.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE offset="9">You!</LINE>
<LINE>Bring me the keys of the cathedral straight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Are you so holy now? Do you curse all day And go to pray at midnight?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit First Soldier.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Provide you, sirs, close lanthorns and a pickaxe. Away, be speedy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Lanthorns and a pickaxe?</LINE>
<LINE>Life, does he mean to bury himself alive, too?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Second and Third Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Death nor the marble prison my love sleeps in Shall keep her body locked up from mine arms; I must not be so cozened; though her life</LINE>
<LINE>Was like a widow&#8217;s state, made o'er in policy</LINE>
<LINE>To defeat me and my too confident heart. 'Twas a most cruel wisdom to herself, As much to me that loved her. What, returned?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter First Soldier.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here be the keys, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I thank thy speed.</LINE>
<LINE>Here come the rest full-furnished.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Second and Third Soldiers.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Follow me</LINE>
<LINE>And wealth shall follow you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Tyrant.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Wealth! By this light,</LINE>
<LINE>We go to rob a church! I hold my life The money will ne&#8217;er thrive; that&#8217;s a sure saw: "What&#8217;s got from grace is ever spent in law."</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt. Enter Mr. Goughe (as Memphonius).</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What strange fits grow upon him! Here alate His soul has got a very dreadful leader, What should he make in the cathedral now, The hour so deep in night? All his intents Are contrary to men; in spirit or blood He waxes heavy in his noble mind. His moods are such they cannot bear the weight, Nor will not long, if there be truth in whispers. The honorable father of the state, Noble Helvetius, all the lords agree By some close policy shortly to set free.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 3</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Within the cathedral.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Tyrant, First Soldier, Second Soldier, Third Soldier, Fourth Soldier)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Tyrant with Soldiers at a farther door, which opened, brings him to the tomb where the Lady lies buried. The tomb is here discovered, richly set forth.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Softly, softly!</LINE>
<LINE>Let&#8217;s give this place the peace that it requires.</LINE>
<LINE>The vaults e&#8217;en chide our steps with murmuring sounds, For making bold so late. It must be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear nothing but the whorish ghost of a queen I kept once. She swore she would so haunt me I should never pray in quiet for her, and I have kept myself from</LINE>
<LINE>church this fifteen year to prevent her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The monument woos me! I must run and kiss it. Now trust me if the tears do not e&#8217;en stand Upon the marble. What slow springs have I!</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas weeping to itself before I came.</LINE>
<LINE>How pity strikes e&#8217;en through insensible things</LINE>
<LINE>And makes them shame our dullness!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou house of silence, and the calms of rest</LINE>
<LINE>After tempestuous life, I claim of thee</LINE>
<LINE>A mistress, one of the most beauteous sleepers</LINE>
<LINE>That ever lay so cold, not yet due to thee By natural death, but cruelly forced hither Many a year before the world could spare her. we miss her 'mongst the glories of our court</LINE>
<LINE>When they be numbered up. All thy still strength,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou grey-eyed monument, shall not keep her from us.</LINE>
<LINE>To Second Soldier Strike, villain! Though the echo rail us all Into ridiculous deafness! Pierce the jaws Of this cold ponderous creature.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="9">Sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Why strik&#8217;st thou not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall not hold the axe fast, I&#8217;m afraid, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O shame of men! A soldier and so fearful!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tis out of my element to be in a church, sir. Give me the open field and turn me loose, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True, there thou hast room enough to run away!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To First Soldier.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Take thou the axe from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I beseech your grace,</LINE>
<LINE>Twill come to a worse hand. You'll find us all Of one mind for the church, I can assure you, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>3. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I love not to disquiet ghosts</LINE>
<LINE>Of any people living. That&#8217;s my humour, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O slaves of one opinion!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Second Soldier.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Give me&#8216;t from thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou man made out of fear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offest="7">By my faith,</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;m glad I&#8217;m rid on&#8217;t. I that was ne&#8217;er before in a cathedral</LINE>
<LINE>And have the batt'ring of a lady&#8217;s tomb</LINE>
<LINE>Lie hard upon my conscience at first coming!</LINE>
<LINE>I should get much by that! It shall be a warning to me;</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll ne&#8217;er come here again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Striking at the tomb. No? Wilt not yield? Art thou so loath to part from her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Life, what means he?</LINE>
<LINE>Has he no feeling with him? By this light, if I be not afraid to stay any longer. I&#8217;m a stone-cutter! Very few will go nigh to turn me of some religion or other, and so</LINE>
<LINE>make me forfeit my lieutenantship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, have we got the mastery? Help, you vassals! Freeze you in idleness and can see us sweat?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We sweat with fear as much as work can make us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Remove the stone, that I may see my mistress.</LINE>
<LINE>Set to your hands, you villains, and that nimbly, Or the same axe shall make you all fly open!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, good my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I must not be delayed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is ten thousand times worse than entering</LINE>
<LINE>upon a breech. Tis the first stone that ever I took off from any lady; marry, I have brought &#8216;em many: fair diamonds, sapphires, rubies—</LINE>
<LINE>They lift off the stone</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O blessed object!</LINE>
<LINE>I never shall be weary to behold thee; I could eternally stand thus and see thee. Why, &#8216;tis not possible death should look so fair, Life is not more illustrious when health smiles on&#8217;t. She&#8217;s only pale, the colour of the court, And most attractive; mistresses most strive for&#8216;t, And their lascivious servants best effect it. Where be these lazy hands again?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ALL SOLDIERS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take up her body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Her body!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She&#8217;s dead, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">True; if she were alive</LINE>
<LINE>Such slaves as you should not come near to touch her. Do&#8216;t, and with all best reverence. Place her here.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Holds out his arms.</STAGEDIR>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not only, sir, with reverence, but with fear. You shall have more than your own asking once. I am afraid of nothing but she'll rise At the first jog and save us all a labour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then we were best take her up, and never</LINE>
<LINE>touch her!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Life, how can that be? Does fear make thee mad? I've took up many a woman in my days, But never with less pleasure; I protest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, the moon rises! What reflection</LINE>
<LINE>Is thrown about this sanctified building,</LINE>
<LINE>E&#8217;en in a twinkling! How the monuments glister</LINE>
<LINE>As if death&#8217;s palaces were all massy silver</LINE>
<LINE>And scorned the name of marble! Art thou cold?</LINE>
<LINE>I have no faith in&#8216;t yet; I believe none.</LINE>
<LINE>Madam! 'Tis I, sweet lady. Prithee speak!</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis thy love calls on thee—thy king, thy servant. No? Not a word? All prisoners to pale silence? I&#8217;ll prove a kiss.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here&#8217;s fine chill venery!</LINE>
<LINE>'Twould make a pander&#8217;s heels ache; I&#8217;ll be sworn</LINE>
<LINE>All my teeth chatter in my head to see&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>B&#8216;th' mass, thou'rt cold indeed! Beshrew thee for&#8216;t! Unkind to thine own blood? Hard-hearted lady! What injury hast thou offered to the youth And pleasure of thy days! Refuse the court</LINE>
<LINE>And steal to this hard lodging! Was that wisdom?</LINE>
<LINE>O, I could chide thee with mine eye brimfull,</LINE>
<LINE>And weep out my forgiveness when I ha&#8217; done.</LINE>
<LINE>Nothing hurt thee but want of woman&#8217;s counsel.</LINE>
<LINE>Hads&#8216;t thou but asked th'opinion of most ladies,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'dst never come to this! They would have told thee</LINE>
<LINE>How dear a treasure life and youth had been.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis that they fear to lose; the very name</LINE>
<LINE>Can make more gaudy tremblers in a minute</LINE>
<LINE>Than heaven or sin or hell. Those are last thought on.</LINE>
<LINE>And where got&#8217;st thou such boldness from the rest</LINE>
<LINE>Of all thy timorous sex to do a deed here Upon thyself would plunge the world&#8217;s best soldier And make him twice bethink him and again, And yet give over? Since thy life has left me, I&#8217;ll clasp the body for the spirit that dwelt in&#8216;t, And love the house still for the mistress&#8217; sake. Thou art mine now, spite of destruction And Govianus, and I will possess thee. I once read of a Herod, whose affection Pursued a virgin&#8217;s love as I did thine, Who, for the hate she owed him, killed herself, As thou too rashly didst, without all pity. Yet he preserved her body dead in honey And kept her long after her funeral. But I&#8217;ll unlock the treasure-house of art With keys of gold and bestow all on thee. Here, slaves, receive her humbly from our arms. Upon your knees, you villains! All&#8217;s too little If you should sweep the pavement with your lips.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What strange brooms he invents!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">So reverently</LINE>
<LINE>Bear her before us gently to our palace. Place you the stone again where first we found it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt with body. Manet First Soldier.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Life, must this on now to deceive all comers, And cover emptiness? 'Tis for all the world</LINE>
<LINE>Like a great city-pie brought to a table</LINE>
<LINE>Where there be many hands that lay about;</LINE>
<LINE>The lid&#8217;s shut close when all the meat&#8217;s picked out,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet stands to make a show and cozen people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 4</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>Within the cathedral, before the Lady&#8217;s tomb.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Govianus, Page, Lady ???)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Govianus in black, a book in his hand, his Page carrying a torch before him.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Already mine eyes melts. The monument</LINE>
<LINE>No sooner stood before it but a tear Ran swiftly from me to express her duty. Temple of honour, I salute thee early,</LINE>
<LINE>The time that my griefs rise! Chamber of peace,</LINE>
<LINE>Where wounded virtue sleeps locked from the world,</LINE>
<LINE>I bring to be acquainted with thy silence</LINE>
<LINE>Sorrows that love no noise: they dwell all inward,</LINE>
<LINE>Where truth and love in every man should dwell.</LINE>
<LINE>Be ready, boy! Give me the strain again.</LINE>
<LINE>'Twill show well here, whilst in my grief&#8217;s devotion</LINE>
<LINE>At every rest mine eye lets fall a bead</LINE>
<LINE>To keep the number perfect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Govianus kneels at the tomb, wondrous passionately. His Page sings.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAGE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>The Song.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE type="lyric">If ever pity were well-placed On true desert and virtuous honour, It could ne&#8217;er be better graced.</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Freely then, bestow&#8216;t upon her.</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Never lady earned her fame In virtue&#8217;s war with greater strife. To preserve her constant name She gave up beauty, youth and life.</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">There she sleeps</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">And here he weeps,</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">The lord unto so rare a wife.</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">Weep, weep and mourn! Lament, You virgins that pass by her.</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">For if praise come by death again</LINE>
<LINE type="lyric">I doubt few will lie nigh her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art an honest boy. Tis done like one That has a feeling of his master&#8217;s passions. And the unmatched worth of his dead mistress. Thy better years shall find me good to thee When understanding ripens in thy soul, Which truly makes the man, and not long time. Prithee withdraw a little, and attend me At cloister door.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PAGE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">It shall be done, my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>The Page withdraws</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Eternal maid of honour, whose chaste body Lies here like virtue&#8217;s close and hidden seed, To spring forth glorious to eternity At the everlasting harvest—</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Within.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE offest="5">I am not here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s that? Who is not here? I&#8217;m forced to</LINE>
<LINE>question it-</LINE>
<LINE>Some idle sounds the beaten vaults send forth.</LINE>
<LINE>On a sudden, in a kind of noise like a wind, the doors clattering, the tombstone flies open, and a great light appears in the midst of the tomb; his Lady as went out, standing just before him all in white, stuck with jewels, and a great crucifix on her breast.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Lady, Rich Robinson.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Mercy look to me! Faith, I fly to thee!</LINE>
<LINE>Keep a strong watch about me! (Now thy friendship!)</LINE>
<LINE>O</LINE>
<LINE>To have my breast shake and my hair stand stiff.</LINE>
<LINE>If this be horror, let it never die!</LINE>
<LINE>Come all the pains of hell in that shape to me,</LINE>
<LINE>This fever for felicity of man,</LINE>
<LINE>Or all the pleasures of ten thousand ages.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dear lord, I come to tell you all my wrongs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome! Who wrongs the spirit of my love? Thou art above the injuries of blood; They cannot reach thee now. What dares offend thee? No life that has the weight of flesh upon&#8217;t And treads as I do can now wrong my mistress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The peace that death allows me is not mine. The monument is robbed! Behold, I&#8217;m gone,</LINE>
<LINE>My body taken up!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Govianus lifts up the stone.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'Tis gone indeed! What villain dares so fearfully run in debt To black eternity?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">He that dares do more—</LINE>
<LINE>The Tyrant!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All the miseries below Reward his boldness!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I am now at court</LINE>
<LINE>In his own private chamber. There he woos me And plies his suit to me with as serious pains As if the short flame of mortality Were lighted up again in my cold breast,</LINE>
<LINE>Folds me within his arms and often sets</LINE>
<LINE>A sinful kiss upon my senseless lip,</LINE>
<LINE>Weeps when he sees the paleness of my cheek,</LINE>
<LINE>And will send privately for a hand of art</LINE>
<LINE>That may dissemble life upon my face</LINE>
<LINE>To please his lustful eye.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O piteous wrongs!</LINE>
<LINE>Inhuman injuries without grace or mercy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I leave &#8216;em to thy thought, dearest of men.</LINE>
<LINE>My rest is lost! Thou must restore&#8216;t again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, fly me not so soon!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Farewell, true lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Lady.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot spare thee yet. I&#8217;ll make myself</LINE>
<LINE>Over to death too, and we'll walk together Like loving spirits: I prithee let&#8217;s do so. She&#8217;s snatched away by fate and I talk sickly; I must dispatch this business upon earth</LINE>
<LINE>Before I take that journey.</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll to my brother for his aid or counsel. So wronged! O heav&#8217;n, put armour on my spirit! Her body I will place in her first rest Or in th'attempt lock death into my breast.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act 5</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 1</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The home of Anselmus.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Votarius, Anselmus, Leonella, Bellarius, Anselmus's Wife, Govianus)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Votarius with Anselmus, the husband.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall stand here, my lord, unseen and hear all.</LINE>
<LINE>Do I deal now like a right friend with you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Like a most faithful.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall have her mind e&#8217;en as it comes to me,</LINE>
<LINE>Though I undo her by&#8216;t. Your friendship, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Is the sweet mistress that I only serve. I prize the roughness of a man&#8217;s embrace Before the soft lips of a hundred ladies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And that&#8217;s an honest mind of thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Lock yourself, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Into that closet, and be sure none see you!</LINE>
<LINE>Trust not a creature. We'll have all run clear, E&#8217;en as the heart affords it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">'Tis a match, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Troth, he says true there. 'Tis a match indeed. He does not know the strength of his own words, For if he did there were no mast'ring on him.</LINE>
<LINE>H&#8217;as cleft the pin in two with a blind man&#8217;s eyes. Though I shoot wide, I&#8217;ll cozen him of the game.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Votarius. Enter Leonella above, in a gallery, with her love Bellarius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Doest thou see thine enemy walk?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would I did not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee rest quiet, man; I have fee'd one for him— A trusty catchpole, too, that will be sure on him. Thou know&#8217;st this gallery well; &#8216;tis at thy use now; 'T'as been at mine full often. Thou may&#8217;st sit Like a most private gallant in yon corner, See all the play, and ne&#8217;er be seen thyself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore I chose it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Thou shalt see my lady</LINE>
<LINE>Play her part naturally, more to the life Than she&#8217;s aware on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">There must I be pleased.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'rt one of the actors; thou&#8216;t be missed anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, a woman&#8217;s action&#8217;s always ready. Yet I&#8217;ll down, now I think on&#8217;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not yet where I should plant belief, I am so strangely tossed between two tales, I&#8217;m told by my wife&#8217;s woman the deed&#8217;s done, And in Votarius&#8217; tongue &#8216;tis yet to come; The castle is but upon yielding yet. 'Tis not delivered up. Well, we shall find The mystery shortly. I will entertain The patience of a prisoner i&#8216;th' meantime.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do: &#8216;tis time, i&#8217;faith.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Descendet Leonella. Reenter Anselmus.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Anselmus locks himself in. Enter Anselmus&#8217;s Wife with Leonella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is all set ready, wench?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pish, madam, all!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell me not so. She lives not for a lady That has less peace than I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nay, good sweet madam,</LINE>
<LINE>You would not think how much this passion alters you. It drinks up all the beauty of your cheek;</LINE>
<LINE>I promise you, madam, you have lost much blood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let it draw death upon me, for till then I shall be mistress of no true content. Who could endure hourly temptation And bear it as I do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Nay, that&#8217;s most certain—</LINE>
<LINE>Unless it were myself again: I can do&#8216;t. I suffer the like daily; you should complain, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which way? Were that wisdom? Prithee, wench, to whom?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To him that makes all whole again—my lord!</LINE>
<LINE>To one that, if he be a kind good husband,</LINE>
<LINE>Will let you bear no more than you are able.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou know&#8217;st not what thou speak&#8217;st. Why, my lord&#8217;s he That gives him the house-freedom, all his boldness, Keeps him a purpose here to war with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now I hold wiser of my lord than so.</LINE>
<LINE>He knows the world; he would not be so idle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I speak sad truth to thee. I am not private</LINE>
<LINE>In mine own chamber, such his impudence is. Nay, my repenting-time is scarce blessed from him; He will offend my prayers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Out upon him</LINE>
<LINE>I believe, madam, he&#8217;s of no religion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He serves my lord, and that&#8217;s enough for him, And he preys upon poor ladies like myself. There&#8217;s all the gentleman&#8217;s devotion!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, the devil of hell give him his blessing!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray watch the door, and suffer none to trouble us, Unless it be my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'Twas finely spoke, that!</LINE>
<LINE>My lord indeed is the most trouble to her. Now I must show a piece of service here.</LINE>
<LINE>How do I spend my days! Life, shall I never</LINE>
<LINE>Get higher than a lady&#8217;s doorkeeper? I must be married as my lady is, first, And then my maid may do as much for me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O miserable time! Except my lord Do wake in honourable pity to me, And rid this vicious gamester from his house, Whom I have checked so often, here I vow I&#8217;ll imitate my noble sister&#8217;s fate, Late mistress to the worthy Govianus, And cast away my life as she did hers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Votarius to the door within.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Back! Y'are too forward, sir! There&#8217;s no coming</LINE>
<LINE>for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, Mistress Len, my lady&#8217;s smock-woman! Am I no farther in your duty yet?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Duty! Look for&#8216;t of them you keep under, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You'll let me in?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Who would you speak withal?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With the best lady you make curtsy to.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She will not speak with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Have you her mind?</LINE>
<LINE>I scorn to take her answer of her broker.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What&#8217;s there? How now, sir! What&#8217;s your business?</LINE>
<LINE>We see your boldness plain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I came to see you, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, then! Though &#8216;twas impudence too much When I was private.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Madam!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Life, he was bom</LINE>
<LINE>To beggar all my patience!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I&#8217;m bold</LINE>
<LINE>Still to prefer my love. Your woman hears me not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where&#8217;s modesty and honour? Have I not thrice</LINE>
<LINE>Answered thy lust?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>By'r lady, I think oftener.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And ar&#8217;st thou yet look with temptation on us?</LINE>
<LINE>Since nothing will prevail, come death! Come vengeance! I will forget the weakness of my kind And force thee from my chamber.</LINE>
<LINE>She thrusts at Votarius with the sword</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">How now, lady!</LINE>
<LINE>'Uds life! You prick me, madam!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Prithee, peace!</LINE>
<LINE>I will not hurt thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Aloud</LINE>
<LINE>Will you yet be gone, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEON.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s upon going, I think</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam! Heart, you deal false with me. O, I feel it!</LINE>
<LINE>Y'are a most treacherous lady! This thy glory?</LINE>
<LINE>My breast is all afire! O!—</LINE>
<LINE>Votarius dies</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! I believe her constancy too late,</LINE>
<LINE>Confirmed e&#8217;en in the blood of my best friend.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>He seizes the sword from his Wife.</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Bellarius.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Take thou my vengeance, thou bold, perjurious strumpet, That dust accuse thy virtuous lady falsely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Kills Leonella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O deadly poison after a sweet banquet! What make I here? I had forgot my part! I am an actor too, and ne&#8217;er thought on&#8217;t. The blackness of this season cannot miss me. To Anselmus. Sirrah! You, lord!</LINE>
<LINE>Bellarius draws a sword</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Is he there? Welcome, ruin!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is a life due to me in that bosom For this poor gentlewoman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">And art thou then receiver?</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;ll pay thee largely, slave, for thy last &#8217;scape.</LINE>
<LINE>They make a dangerous pass at one another. The wife purposely runs between, and is killed</LINE>
<LINE>by them both</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>WIFE.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I come, Votarius!</LINE>
<LINE>Dies</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Hold, if manhood guide thee!</LINE>
<LINE>O what has fury done?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">What has it done now?</LINE>
<LINE>Why, killed an honourable whore, that&#8217;s all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Villain! I&#8217;ll seal that lie upon thy heart.</LINE>
<LINE>A constant lady!</LINE>
<LINE>He kneels at his Wife&#8217;s side</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Go to the devil, as could be!</LINE>
<LINE>Heart! Must I prick you forward? Either up, Or, sir, I&#8217;ll take my chance. Thou couldst kill her Without repenting that deserved more pity!</LINE>
<LINE>And spend&#8217;st thy time and tears upon a queen—</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Slave!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That was deceived once in her own deceit,</LINE>
<LINE>They fight, and each is mortally stabbed As I am now. The poison I prepared Upon that weapon for mine enemy&#8217;s bosom</LINE>
<LINE>Is bold to take acquaintance of my blood too,</LINE>
<LINE>And serves us both to make up death withal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I ask no more of destiny but to fall</LINE>
<LINE>Close by the chaste side of my virtuous mistress. If all the treasure of my weeping strength</LINE>
<LINE>Be left so wealthy but to purchase that,</LINE>
<LINE>I have the dear wish of a great man&#8217;s spirit. Yet favor me, O yet.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Touches Wife.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I thank thee, fate; I expire cheerfully, and give death a smile.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Anselmus swoons and appears to die.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O rage! I pity now mine enemy&#8217;s flesh.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Govianus with Servants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where should he be?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">My lady, sir, will tell you.</LINE>
<LINE>She&#8217;s in her chamber here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SERV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Seeing bodies. O my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace!—My honorable brother—madam—all! So many dreadful deeds, and not one tongue Left to proclaim &#8216;em)</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Yes, here! If a voice</LINE>
<LINE>Some minute long may satisfy your ear,</LINE>
<LINE>I've that time allowed it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Tis enough.</LINE>
<LINE>Bestow it quickly, ere death snatch it from thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BEL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That lord your brother made his friend Votarius To tempt his lady. She was won to lust,</LINE>
<LINE>The act revealed here by her serving-woman.</LINE>
<LINE>But that wise, close adulteress, stored with art</LINE>
<LINE>To prey upon the weakness of that lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Dissembled a great rage upon her love,</LINE>
<LINE>And indeed killed him, which so won her husband</LINE>
<LINE>He slew this right discoverer in his fury,</LINE>
<LINE>Who, being my mistress, I was moved in heart</LINE>
<LINE>To take some pains with him, and h'as paid me for&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>As for the cunning lady, I commend her;</LINE>
<LINE>She performed that which never woman tried:</LINE>
<LINE>She ran upon two weapons, and so died.</LINE>
<LINE>Now you have all, I hope I shall sleep quiet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Dies.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, thunder that awakes me e&#8217;en from death, And makes me curse my confidence with cold lips, I feel his words in flames about my soul; H&#8217;as more than killed me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Brother!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I repent the smile</LINE>
<LINE>That I bestowed on destiny! A whore!</LINE>
<LINE>Speaks to Body of Wife I fling thee thus from my believing breast With all the strength I have. My rage is great, Although my veins grow beggars. Now I sue</LINE>
<LINE>To die far from thee! May we never meet!</LINE>
<LINE>Were my soul bid to joy&#8217;s eternal banquet, And were assured to find thee there a guest, I&#8216;d sup with torments, and refuse that feast. O thou beguiler of man&#8217;s easy trust!</LINE>
<LINE>'The serpent&#8217;s wisdom is in women&#8217;s lust.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Dies.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is death so long a-coming to mankind It must be met half ways? 'Las, the full time Is to eternity but a minute. Was that so long to stay? O cruel speed!</LINE>
<LINE>There&#8217;s few men pay their debts before their day.</LINE>
<LINE>If they be ready at their time, &#8216;tis well—</LINE>
<LINE>And but a few that are so. What strange haste</LINE>
<LINE>Was made among these people! My heart weeps for&#8216;t.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Servants.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Go, bear these bodies to a place more comely.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Servants take out bodies.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Brother, I came for thy advice, but I Find thee so ill a counsellor to thyself That I repent my pains, and depart sighing. The body of my love is still at court; I am not well to think on&#8217;t. The poor spirit Was with me once again about it, troth; And I can put off no more for shame, Though I desire to have it haunt me still And never to give over, &#8216;tis so pleasing. I must to court: I've plighted my faith to&#8217;t; 'T'as opened me the way to the revenge. Tyrant, I&#8217;ll run thee on a dangerous shelf, Though I be forced to fly this land myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene 2</SCENETITLE>
<SCENELOCATION>The royal court.</SCENELOCATION>
<SCENEPERSONAE>(Tyrant, Lady Luscinda, First Soldier, Second Soldier, Third Soldier, Fourth Soldier, Govianus)</SCENEPERSONAE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Tyrant with Attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In vain my spirit wrestles with my blood;</LINE>
<LINE>Affection will be mistress here on earth.</LINE>
<LINE>The house is hers, the soul is but a tenant. I ha&#8217; tasked myself but with the abstinence Of one poor hour, yet cannot conquer that. I cannot keep from sight of her so long.</LINE>
<LINE>I starve mine eye too much. Go, bring her forth,</LINE>
<LINE>As we have caused her body to be decked</LINE>
<LINE>In all the glorious riches of our palace.</LINE>
<LINE>Our mind has felt a famine for the time;</LINE>
<LINE>All comfort has been dear and scarce with us.</LINE>
<LINE>The times are altered since.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Sounds of music within.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Strike on, sweet harmony! </LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Soldiers with the Lady.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>A braver world comes toward us.</LINE>
<LINE>They bring the body in a chair, dressed up in black velvet, which sets out the paleness of the hands and face, and a fair chain of pearl 'cross her breast, and the crucifix above it. He stands silent awhile, letting the music play, beckoning the soldiers that bring her in to make obeisance to her, and he himself makes a low honour to the body and kisses the hand.</LINE>
<LINE>A song within, in voices Song</LINE>
<LINE>O, what is beauty, that&#8217;s so much adored? A flattering glass that cozens her beholders, One night of death makes it look pale and horrid: The dainty preserved flesh, how soon it moulders! To love it living, it bewitcheth many, But after life is seldom heard of any.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By this hand, mere idolatry! I make curtsy To my damnation. I have learnt so much, Though I could never know the meaning yet Of all my Latin prayers, nor ne&#8217;er sought for&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How pleasing art thou to us even in death! I love thee yet, above all women living, And shall do sev'n year hence. I can see nothing to be mended in thee But the too constant paleness of thy cheek. I&#8216;d give the kingdom but to purchase there The breadth of a red rose in natural colour, And think it the best bargain that ever king made yet. But fate&#8217;s my hindrance, And I must only rest content with art; And that I&#8217;ll have in spite on&#8217;t. Is he come, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Dull! The fellow that we sent</LINE>
<LINE>For a court schoomaster, a picture drawer, A lady&#8217;s forenoon tutor. Is he come, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>1. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not yet returned, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">The fool belike</LINE>
<LINE>Makes his choice carefully, for so we charged him,</LINE>
<LINE>To fit our close deeds with some private hand.</LINE>
<LINE>It is no shame for thee, most silent mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>To stand in need of art, when youth</LINE>
<LINE>And all thy warm friends has forsook thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Women alive are glad to seek her friendship</LINE>
<LINE>To make up the fair number of their graces, Or else the reckoning would fall short sometimes, And servants would look out for better wages.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Third Soldier with Govianus, disguised.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>2. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He&#8217;s come, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Depart then.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Soldiers. Manet Third Soldier.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Is that he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>3. SOLD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The privatest I could get, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O heaven, marry patience to my spirit! Give me a sober fury, I beseech thee, A rage that may not overcharge my blood And do myself most hurt! 'Tis strange to me To see thee here at court, and gone from hence. Didst thou make haste to leave the world for this? And kept in the worst comer? O, who dares play with destiny but he That wears security so thick upon him The thought of death and hell cannot pierce through?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twas circumspectly carried.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Third Soldier</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Leave us; go.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To Govianus.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Be nearer, sir; thou'rt much commended to us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is the hand, my lord, commends the workman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou speak&#8217;st both modesty and truth in that.</LINE>
<LINE>We need that art that thou art master of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My king is master both of that and me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look on yon face and tell me what it wants.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which, that, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That! What wants it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Troth, my lord</LINE>
<LINE>Some thousand years&#8217; sleep and a marble pillow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What&#8217;s that?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Observe it still! All the best arts Hath the most fools and drunkards to their masters</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aloud.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Thy apprehension has too gross a film</LINE>
<LINE>To be employed at court. What colour wants she?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my troth, all, sir; I see none she has,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor none she cares for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE offset="4">I am overmatched here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A lower chamber with less noise were kindlier For her, poor woman, whatsoe'er she was.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But how if we be pleased to have it thus,</LINE>
<LINE>And thee well hired to do what we command?</LINE>
<LINE>Is not your work for money?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, my lord;</LINE>
<LINE>I would not trust at court and I could choose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let but thy art hide death upon her face, That now looks fearfully on us, and but strive</LINE>
<LINE>To give our eye delight in that pale part</LINE>
<LINE>Which draws so many pities from these springs,</LINE>
<LINE>And thy reward for&#8216;t shall outlast thy end,</LINE>
<LINE>And reach to thy friend&#8217;s fortunes, and his friend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say you so, my lord? I&#8217;ll work out my heart then But I&#8217;ll show art enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">About it, then!</LINE>
<LINE>I never wished so seriously for health After long sickness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>Aside.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>A religious trembling shakes me by the hand, And bids me put by such unhallowed business, But revenge calls for&#8216;t, and it must go forward.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis time the spirit of my love took rest; Poor soul, &#8216;tis weary, much abused and toiled.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Govianus paints the face of the body</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Could I now send for one to renew heat Within her bosom, that were a fine workman;</LINE>
<LINE>I should but too much love him. But alas,</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis as unpossible for living fire</LINE>
<LINE>To take hold there as for dead ashes to burn back again</LINE>
<LINE>Into those hard tough bodies whence they fell.</LINE>
<LINE>Life is removed from her now, as the warmth</LINE>
<LINE>Of the bright sun from us when it makes winter</LINE>
<LINE>And kills with unkind coldness. So is&#8216;t yonder; An everlasting frost hangs now upon her. And in such a season men will force A heat into their bloods with exercise</LINE>
<LINE>In spite of extreme weather, so shall we</LINE>
<LINE>By art force beauty on yon lady&#8217;s face; Though death sit frowning on&#8217;t a storm of hail To beat it off, our pleasure shall prevail.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Hast done so soon?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">That&#8217;s as your grace</LINE>
<LINE>Gives approbation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">O, she lives again!</LINE>
<LINE>She'll presently speak to me. Keep her up; I&#8217;ll have her swoon no more; there&#8217;s treachery in&#8216;t. Does she not feel warm to thee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Very little, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The heat wants cherishing then. Our arms and lips</LINE>
<LINE>Shall labour life into her. Wake, sweet mistress!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>He kisses the lips of the body.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'Tis I that call thee at the door of life. Ha! I talk so long to death, I&#8217;m sick myself. Methinks an evil scent still follows me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Maybe &#8216;tis nothing but the colour, sir, That I laid on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Is that so strong?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Yes, faith, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas the best poison I could get for money.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Govianus throws off his disguise.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Govianus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="3">O, thou sacrilegious villain!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou thief of rest, robber of monuments! Cannot the body after funeral</LINE>
<LINE>Sleep in the grave for thee? Must it be raised</LINE>
<LINE>Only to please the wickedness of thine eye?</LINE>
<LINE>Does all things end with death, and not thy lust?</LINE>
<LINE>Hast thou devised a new way to damnation,</LINE>
<LINE>More dreadful than the soul of any sin</LINE>
<LINE>Did ever pass yet between earth and hell?</LINE>
<LINE>Dost strive to be particularly plagued Above all ghosts beside? Is thy pride such</LINE>
<LINE>Thou scorn&#8217;st a partner in thy torments too?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What fury gave thee boldness to attempt</LINE>
<LINE>This deed? For which I&#8217;ll doom thee with a death</LINE>
<LINE>Beyond the Frenchmen&#8217;s tortures.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">I smile at thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Draw all the death that ever mankind suffered Unto one head, to help thine own invention, And make my end as rare as this thy sin,</LINE>
<LINE>And full as fearful to the eyes of women!</LINE>
<LINE>My spirit shall fly singing to his lodging</LINE>
<LINE>In midst of that rough weather. Doom me, Tyrant.</LINE>
<LINE>Had I feared death, I&#8216;d never appeared noble</LINE>
<LINE>To seal this act upon me, which e&#8217;en honours me</LINE>
<LINE>Unto my mistress&#8217; spirit. It loves me for&#8216;t.</LINE>
<LINE>I told my heart &#8216;twould prove destruction to&#8217;t.</LINE>
<LINE>Who, hearing &#8216;twas for her, charged me to do&#8216;t.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy glories shall be shortened! Who&#8217;s within there?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter the Ghost, in the same form as the Lady is dressed in the chair.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I called not thee, thou enemy to firmness, Mortality&#8217;s earthquake!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Welcome to mine eyes</LINE>
<LINE>As is the day spring from the morning&#8217;s womb Unto that wretch whose nights are tedious!</LINE>
<LINE>As liberty to captives, health to labourers,</LINE>
<LINE>And life still to old people, never weary on&#8217;t;</LINE>
<LINE>So welcome art thou to me. The deed&#8217;s done,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou queen of spirits; he has his end upon him.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy body shall return to rise again,</LINE>
<LINE>For thy abuser falls, and has no power</LINE>
<LINE>To vex thee farther now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LADY.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">My truest love!</LINE>
<LINE>Life ever honoured here, and blessed above.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, if there be a hell for flesh and spirit, 'Us built within this bosom.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Nobles.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My lords, treason!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now death, I&#8217;m for thee. Welcome!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Your king&#8217;s poisoned!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The King of heaven be praised for&#8216;t!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Lay hold on him—</LINE>
<LINE>On Govianus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">E&#8217;en with the best loves</LINE>
<LINE>And truest hearts that ever subjects owed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How&#8217;s that? I charge you all, lay hands on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look you, my lord, your will shall be obeyed:</LINE>
<LINE>Here comes another; we'll have his hand too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Helvetius.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall have both mine, if that work go forward, Beside my voice and knee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="6">Helvetius!</LINE>
<LINE>Then my destruction was confirmed amongst &#8216;em;</LINE>
<LINE>Premeditation wrought it. O my torments!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ALL</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Live Govianus long our virtuous king!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A flourish.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TYR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That thunder strikes me dead.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>The Tyrant dies.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">I cannot better</LINE>
<LINE>Reward my joys than with astonished silence, For all the wealth of words is not of power</LINE>
<LINE>To make up thanks for you, my honoured lords!</LINE>
<LINE>I&#8217;m like a man plucked up from many waters, That never looked for help, and am here placed Upon this cheerful mountain, where prosperity</LINE>
<LINE>Shoots forth her richest beam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Long-injured lord,</LINE>
<LINE>The tyranny of his actions grew so weighty,</LINE>
<LINE>His life so vicious—</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">To which this is witness-</LINE>
<LINE>Monster in sin!—this, the disquieted body Of my too resolute child in honour&#8217;s war.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MEMP.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>—That he became as hateful to our minds—</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>HELV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As death&#8217;s unwelcome to a house of riches,</LINE>
<LINE>Or what can more express it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GOV.</SPEAKER>
<LINE offset="5">Well, he&#8217;s gone;</LINE>
<LINE>And all the kingdom&#8217;s evils perish with him! And since the body of that virtuous lady Is taken from her rest, in memory</LINE>
<LINE>Of her admired mistress, &#8216;tis our will</LINE>
<LINE>It receive honour dead, as it took part</LINE>
<LINE>With us in all afflictions when it lived.</LINE>
<LINE>Here place her in this throne, crown her our queen,</LINE>
<LINE>The first and last that ever we make ours,</LINE>
<LINE>Her constancy strikes so much firmness in us.</LINE>
<LINE>That honour done, let her be solemnly borne Unto the house of peace from whence she came, As Queen of Silence.</LINE>
<LINE>The Spirit enters again and stays to go out with the body, as if it were attending it</LINE>
<LINE>O welcome, blessed spirit! Thou need&#8217;st not mistrust me; I have a care</LINE>
<LINE>As jealous as thine own. We'll see it done,</LINE>
<LINE>And not believe report; our zeal is such</LINE>
<LINE>We cannot reverence chastity too much.</LINE>
<LINE>Lead on! I would those ladies that fill honour&#8217;s rooms</LINE>
<LINE>Might all be borne so honest to their tombs.</LINE>
<LINE>Recorders or other solemn music plays them out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<AUTHORDETAILS>
<AUTHOR>PlayShakespeare.com</AUTHOR>
<AUTHORURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com</AUTHORURL>
<COPYRIGHT>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</COPYRIGHT>
<VERSION>3.1</VERSION>
<LICENSE>GFDL License 1.3</LICENSE>
<LICENSEURL>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</LICENSEURL>
<TERMSURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com/about-us</TERMSURL>
</AUTHORDETAILS>

</PLAY>

