<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Comedy of Errors">The Comedy of Errors</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="A Comedy of Errors">

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LUCE.">Luce</persname>
<persdescription>Luce, also known as Nell, is a maid at Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s. She has little patience with loud ruffians at the gate, whom she consigns to the stocks.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LUC.">Luciana</persname>
<persdescription>Luciana is Adriana&#8217;s sister, and dwells with her and Antipholus of Epheseus. She can preach on the natural submission of women to men as well as anyone, and tries to calm her sister down when she grows impatient with her husband. However, she does not scruple to tell her brother-in-law off, nor to insult the servants. She also advises Antipholus of Syracuse to at least pretend to still love his wife if he doesn&#8217;t. She is unnerved to suddenly find herself courted by him, and to swear him swear that he is unmarried. Convinced that he is mad, she becomes both pitying and terrified of him. She defends her sister&#8217;s actions to the Abbess, and recommends to Adriana to beg the Duke for help. Once all the confusions are sorted out, it is understood that she will be properly wooed by Antipholus of Syracuse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ADR.">Adriana</persname>
<persdescription>Adriana is Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s wife, and a proto-feminist distraught that her husband is paying attention to another woman and irritated that men are not as bound as women are, nor women as free as men. She does not think her sister has much right to judge her opinions, as Luciana lacks a husband to grieve her and therefore doesn&#8217;t actually know what she&#8217;s talking about. She feels deeply wronged by her husband&#8217;s constant desertions, though he swears that his interactions with the Courtesan are entirely respectable. She pleads with her husband to come home for lunch, disturbed as she is by his jesting and pretense that he doesn&#8217;t know her. Grieved by the news that Antipholus of Syracuse has been flirting with her sister, she bursts into a fine flurry of insults at him. She is soon convinced that he is mad, however, and fetches Doctor Pinch to cure him. When her husband escapes into the priory, she attempts to reason with the Abbess to have him sent forth, but is denied, and she must sue to the Duke instead, though she somewhat overstates her case. Of wealthy birth, she married Antipholus of Ephesus at the Duke&#8217;s entreaty. She is emotional, and giving to beating her servants.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ABB.">Aemilia</persname>
<persdescription>Abbess Aemilia is an abbess in Ephesus, highly respected by all. She was shipwrecked years ago and lost her husband, as well as her twin sons, in the wreck. She approves of the concept that wives should chide their husbands for spending time with other women, but also chides the wives for complaining too much. She refuses to have the sanctuary of her house breached, insisting that she will treat Adriana&#8217;s husband&#8217;s madness herself. Discovering the identity of the man in her care, she rushes outside to explain everything to the Duke and see her husband again for the first time in decades. She holds a great feast at the abbey to celebrate the reunion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PINCH.">Doctor Pinch</persname>
<persdescription>Pinch is a conjurer and exorcist hired by Adriana to cure Antipholus of Epheseus of his madness. He is extremely lean, bearded, with deep-set eyes and a yellow cast to his face. Determining that both the Ephesan Antipholus and his servant Dromio are possessed, he reveals that his cure for this is affliction is to have them tied up and left in a dark room. This is an unfortunate decision, as when they break free they set his beard on fire and poke him with a pair of scissors.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANG.">Angelo</persname>
<persdescription>Angelo is a goldsmith in Syracuse, the maker of a fine gold chain commissioned by Antipholus of Ephesus. He is not happy at being denied lunch at Antipholus&#8217;s. He is waiting to be paid for the chain to be able to settle his debt with the Second Merchant. He is chary of his reputation and confused by Antipholus of Syracuse&#8217;s actions, though finally convinced of the man&#8217;s unfortunate madness. He bears witness to all he knows before the Duke.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BALTH.">Balthazar</persname>
<persdescription>Balthazar is a merchant of Ephesus and a friend of the local Antipholus. When they are locked out of Antipholus&#8217;s house, he manages to calm the man down and prevent him from making a scandal by breaking down his own door.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="S. DRO.">Dromio of Syracuse</persname>
<persdescription>Dromio of Syracuse is Antiopholus of Syracuse&#8217;s slave. A quick-witted fellow, he has a good relationship with his master: despite the latter&#8217;s tendency to beat him, they often enter into flights of repartee where Antipholus gives Dromio free range to exercise his wit. He is deeply confused by the misunderstandings of the day, and wishes for a place to pray, being quickly convinced that he and his master are under a spell. At Adriana&#8217;s entreaty he keeps the gate to the house closed while she and his master dine, and uses a rude tongue against those who hope to come in. He is terrified of the fat kitchen-maid who lays claim to him, and runs to his master for safety, convinced she is a witch. He finds a ship for them to flee on, but also has to run for money from Adriana when Antipholus (of Ephesus) is arrested. Returning with the money to find Antipholus (of Syracuse) denying any knowledge of this, he is even more ready to believe that the courtesan is a devil when she comes to speak to them. Though with his master he begins to walk about with his sword drawn, he becomes slightly reconciled to the place, until they are suddenly on the verge of being tied up as madmen, at which point he hurries Antipholus (of Syracuse) into a nearby priory. He is greatly relieved when all the confusion is cleared up and he discovers that he will not have to marry Nell the kitchen-maid. His humor can be of a low sort, racist and scatological by turns, but he is a kind man, insisting that his twin of Ephesus take precedence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="E. DRO.">Dromio of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Dromio of Ephesus is Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s slave. He has the misfortune of having both a master and a mistress given to beating him, though he may find some consolation in the love of Nell the kitchen-maid. He endures them patiently, though he is not afraid to run away when need be to escape the blows, nor to complain of how beatings is all he has ever known from his master. He is completely flummoxed by the misunderstandings of the day, not understanding the cause of the number of beatings he receives, nor for that matter why he finds himself tied up as a madman. He is freed when Antipholus (of Ephesus) chews through their ropes, and they join to torment the exorcist, Dromio pricking him with a pair of scissors. From here on he no longer considers himself to be bound to Antipholus of Ephesus, merely to be his servant. He is charmed to meet his brother, delicately complimenting him and insisting that they be equals.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="S. ANT.">Antipholus of Syracuse</persname>
<persdescription>Antipholus of Syracuse is Egeon&#8217;s son. Separated from his twin at birth, at the age of eighteen he decided to travel the world to find him, and has been searching for him these last seven years. He is attended by Dromio of Syracuse. He is a cautious traveler, terrified of the possibility of magic, and weary of the inhabitants of Ephesus, since he has heard that they are all sorcerers. Though he allows his Dromio a fair bit of leeway in terms of mockery, and likes to play straight man to his wit, Antipholus of Syracuse has his limits, and is not restrained in the use of his fists when he thinks his slave has gone too far, particularly if it concerns money. He soon becomes convinced that he is someway or other be-spelled, especially when a beautiful woman begins to call him husband and bid him to come home, and he allows himself to be entranced, though he finds the woman&#8217;s sister far more attractive than she, and begins to woo her. Rejected, he decides that things have gone too far and that it would be best to leave before nightfall. He is confused when a passing goldsmith gives him a necklace made specially for him and refuses to take money for it at once, and the occurrence merely reaffirms his decision to leave. As every person he meets on the street greets him, and Dromio (of Syracuse) arrives speaking of having seen him arrested, and a courtesan comes snuggling up to him and asking for a ring back, he grows completely panicked and begins to wander about with his sword drawn. Coming across the goldsmith again, who swears that he has denied to pay for the chain, challenged to a fight by a merchant for forswearing himself, and seeing his supposed wife announce to all and sundry that he is mad, he is thoroughly discombobulated and runs into a priory for sanctuary, where he discovers that the Abbess is his long-lost mother, that his father is in town and about to be executed, and that his twin brother also lives in town and that he has been being confused with him all day long. Discovering this, he promises to renew his wooing of Luciana, this time more lawfully.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="E. ANT.">Antipholus of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Antipholus of Ephesus was brought up in Corinth, never knowing his father, and brought to Ephesus by Duke Menaphon of Corinth. Duke Solinus of Ephesus, Menaphon&#8217;s nephew, became his patron, and he served worthily in his wars. The Duke arranged for his marriage to a wealthy lady, Adriana, and he became one of the richest and best-known merchants in Ephesus, known for his honor and good credit. His marriage is not entirely a success, though: he spends a great deal of time with a Courtesan, often dining with her, though he insists that he&#8217;s not up to anything illicit with her. His wife chides him endlessly for this, and this merely drives him further from her. He is not prepared, however, to return home to find his own door locked against him and his wife denying him entry. Enraged, he is only barely prevented from knocking down his own door, and decides to give an expensive necklace he commissioned for his wife to the courtesan instead. Meeting the goldsmith Angelo after lunch, he is confused to be told that he has already received the necklace, and to find himself arrested for non-payment. Soon finding himself also declared mad and possessed, he is incapable of resisting when he is tied up and thrust into a dark room, but he chews his way through the ropes binding him and escapes, tormenting the exorcist Dr. Pinch by setting his beard on fire before finding the Duke to call for justice against his wife, whom he is certain is at the base of all his ills. Finding himself called &#8216;son&#8217; by an old man about to be executed, he is even further discombobulated, but it is soon revealed that he has a twin brother who&#8217;s been taken for him all day, that the local Abbess is his mother and the old man his father. He immediately offers to pay Egeon&#8217;s ransom, but the Duke rejects the need for it. He is a choleric man, much given to beating his slave Dromio of Ephesus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EGE.">Egeon</persname>
<persdescription>Egeon is an old man of Syracuse who sneaks into the city to seek for his lost twin son Antipholus. A great traveller, he has not had the easiest of lives, having lost his wife and one of his sons in a tempest, and then having the remaining son vanish in his quest to find his brother. Recognised as a Syracusian and captured, he is sentenced to be beheaded unless he can pay a ransom of a thousand marks. His pleas to Duke Solinus are unavailing, but the tale of his woes touches the Ephesian ruler, who allows him to roam the town to find someone who will pay the ransom for him by sundown. He is unsuccessful in this, but does find his son &#8212; who denies ever having met him. Things are soon cleared up when it is revealed that both of his twins are present in town, as is his lost wife, who just happens to be an Abbess there. Egeon is not the happiest of men, living under sentence of death as he is, and convinced at the end that his son is ashamed of him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUKE.">Solinus, Duke of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Duke (Solinus) of Ephesus rules his town with great respect for law, insisting that he cannot go against the set rules even if he wishes to, though he is willing to bend them a little on occasion. He rigidly enforces the law that requires a thousand marks from every Syracusian merchant found within the boundaries of Ephesus. He has been patron to Antipholus of Syracuse for twenty years, ever since he was brought to town by the Duke&#8217;s uncle Menaphon of Corinth and fought in the Duke&#8217;s wars, and arranged for his marriage to the rich lady Adriana. The Duke is able to pity, is intelligent enough to be the first to link Egeon&#8217;s tale to the mysterious happenings of the day, and willing to break his oath about being unable to undo the law when he so chooses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. MER.">First Merchant</persname>
<persdescription>The First Merchant warns Antipholus of Syracuse to hide his identity, given the penalty for a Syracusian to be caught in Ephesus. He leaves his traveling companion to take care of some business, though promising to join him again in the evening.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. MER.">Second Merchant</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Merchant is on the verge of a journey to Persia, and therefore needs every penny he can get. He has lent a substantial amount of money to Angelo which he now wishes to have repaid. He has not been a pressing creditor, but when money is required he is quick to hire out an officer to arrest Angelo if the latter should default. As he needs to leave quickly, he has no inclination to listen to a sparring match between Angelo and Antipholus of Ephesus and has Angelo arrested. He is shocked to hear Antipholus of Syracuse deny events that he has witnessed, and challenges him to fight, though he regrets this when he realizes that the man is mad. He testifies before the Duke to all he knows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JAIL.">Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>The Jailer has custody of Egeon, and accompanies him in his search for someone to pay his ransom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COUR.">Courtezan</persname>
<persdescription>A Courtezan counts Antipholus of Epheseus among her favored clients, and entertains him often enough to make his wife jealous. She is an excellent conversationalist, with a mix of wildness and gentleness that greatly pleases men. In return for being promised a gold chain by the Antipholus she knows, she lets him have a diamond ring of hers. When she meets him again (as she thinks) and he denies the fact, she decides he is mad, and decides to tell his wife a slightly trumped-up tale in hopes of getting the worth of the ring back, as she cannot afford to lose its worth. She bears witness of what she knows before the Duke, and receives her ring back at the end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger rushes in to warn Adriana to flee from her husband, who has broken loose from his bonds. He is clearly terrified.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OFF.">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer is a debt recovery officer, who can be hired to arrest defaulters. Once he has done so, he is at risk of having to pay the debt himself if he lets his prisoner escape. He trusts Adriana&#8217;s promise to pay when the latter has her husband tied up, and is terrified of the Syracusan Antipholus and Dromio when he sees them with swords drawn.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HEAD.">Headsman</persname>
<persdescription>The Headsman [mute role] is in charge of executing Egeon, and leads him to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A hall in Duke Solinus&#8217;s Palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Duke of Ephesus, Egeon, Jailer, Officers, Attendants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Egeon, a merchant of Syracuse, had been condemned to death by the Duke of Ephesus for daring to appear in Ephesus. Egeon tells the story of how he was separated from his wife and one of their twin sons by a storm at sea. When the son who remained with him reached the age of 18, he became inquisitive and asked to be able to try and find his bother. For five years they have searched in vain. Affected by the tale, the Duke gives Egeon a day&#8217;s reprieve from execution to try to raise a 1000 marks to pay in fine rather than being killed.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Duke of Ephesus with Egeon the merchant of Syracuse, Jailer with Officers, and other Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Proceed, Solinus, to procure my fall,</line>
<line form="verse">And by the doom of death end woes and all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Merchant of Syracuse, plead no more.</line>
<line form="verse">I am not partial to infringe our laws;</line>
<line form="verse">The enmity and discord which of late</line>
<line form="verse">Sprung from the rancorous outrage of your Duke</line>
<line form="verse">To merchants, our well-dealing countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, wanting guilders to redeem their lives,</line>
<line form="verse">Have seal&#8217;d his rigorous statutes with their bloods,</line>
<line form="verse">Excludes all pity from our threat&#8217;ning looks:</line>
<line form="verse">For since the mortal and intestine jars</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twixt thy seditious countrymen and us,</line>
<line form="verse">It hath in solemn synods been decreed,</line>
<line form="verse">Both by the Syracusians and ourselves,</line>
<line form="verse">To admit no traffic to our adverse towns:</line>
<line form="verse">Nay more, if any born at Ephesus be seen</line>
<line form="verse">At any Syracusian marts and fairs;</line>
<line form="verse">Again, if any Syracusian born</line>
<line form="verse">Come to the bay of Ephesus, he dies,</line>
<line form="verse">His goods confiscate to the Duke&#8217;s dispose,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless a thousand marks be levied</line>
<line form="verse">To quit the penalty and to ransom him.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy substance, valued at the highest rate,</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot amount unto a hundred marks,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore by law thou art condemn&#8217;d to die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yet this my comfort, when your words are done,</line>
<line form="verse">My woes end likewise with the evening sun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, Syracusian; say in brief the cause</line>
<line form="verse">Why thou departedst from thy native home,</line>
<line form="verse">And for what cause thou cam&#8217;st to Ephesus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A heavier task could not have been impos&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Than I to speak my griefs unspeakable:</line>
<line form="verse">Yet that the world may witness that my end</line>
<line form="verse">Was wrought by nature, not by vile offense,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll utter what my sorrow gives me leave.</line>
<line form="verse">In Syracuse was I born, and wed</line>
<line form="verse">Unto a woman, happy but for me,</line>
<line form="verse">And by me, had not our hap been bad:</line>
<line form="verse">With her I liv&#8217;d in joy; our wealth increas&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">By prosperous voyages I often made</line>
<line form="verse">To Epidamium, till my factor&#8217;s death,</line>
<line form="verse">And the great care of goods at random left,</line>
<line form="verse">Drew me from kind embracements of my spouse;</line>
<line form="verse">From whom my absence was not six months old</line>
<line form="verse">Before herself (almost at fainting under</line>
<line form="verse">The pleasing punishment that women bear)</line>
<line form="verse">Had made provision for her following me,</line>
<line form="verse">And soon, and safe, arrived where I was.</line>
<line form="verse">There had she not been long but she became</line>
<line form="verse">A joyful mother of two goodly sons:</line>
<line form="verse">And, which was strange, the one so like the other</line>
<line form="verse">As could not be distinguish&#8217;d but by names.</line>
<line form="verse">That very hour, and in the self-same inn,</line>
<line form="verse">A mean woman was delivered</line>
<line form="verse">Of such a burden male, twins both alike.</line>
<line form="verse">Those, for their parents were exceeding poor,</line>
<line form="verse">I bought, and brought up to attend my sons.</line>
<line form="verse">My wife, not meanly proud of two such boys,</line>
<line form="verse">Made daily motions for our home return:</line>
<line form="verse">Unwilling I agreed. Alas! Too soon</line>
<line form="verse">We came aboard.</line>
<line form="verse">A league from Epidamium had we sail&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Before the always-wind-obeying deep</line>
<line form="verse">Gave any tragic instance of our harm:</line>
<line form="verse">But longer did we not retain much hope;</line>
<line form="verse">For what obscured light the heavens did grant</line>
<line form="verse">Did but convey unto our fearful minds</line>
<line form="verse">A doubtful warrant of immediate death,</line>
<line form="verse">Which though myself would gladly have embrac&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet the incessant weepings of my wife,</line>
<line form="verse">Weeping before for what she saw must come,</line>
<line form="verse">And piteous plainings of the pretty babes,</line>
<line form="verse">That mourn&#8217;d for fashion, ignorant what to fear,</line>
<line form="verse">Forc&#8217;d me to seek delays for them and me.</line>
<line form="verse">And this it was (for other means was none):</line>
<line form="verse">The sailors sought for safety by our boat,</line>
<line form="verse">And left the ship, then sinking-ripe, to us.</line>
<line form="verse">My wife, more careful for the latter-born,</line>
<line form="verse">Had fast&#8217;ned him unto a small spare mast,</line>
<line form="verse">Such as sea-faring men provide for storms;</line>
<line form="verse">To him one of the other twins was bound,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst I had been like heedful of the other.</line>
<line form="verse">The children thus dispos&#8217;d, my wife and I,</line>
<line form="verse">Fixing our eyes on whom our care was fix&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Fast&#8217;ned ourselves at either end the mast,</line>
<line form="verse">And floating straight, obedient to the stream,</line>
<line form="verse">Was carried towards Corinth, as we thought.</line>
<line form="verse">At length the sun, gazing upon the earth,</line>
<line form="verse">Dispers&#8217;d those vapors that offended us,</line>
<line form="verse">And by the benefit of his wished light</line>
<line form="verse">The seas wax&#8217;d calm, and we discovered</line>
<line form="verse">Two ships from far, making amain to us,</line>
<line form="verse">Of Corinth that, of Epidaurus this.</line>
<line form="verse">But ere they came&#8212;O, let me say no more!</line>
<line form="verse">Gather the sequel by that went before.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, forward, old man, do not break off so,</line>
<line form="verse">For we may pity, though not pardon thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, had the gods done so, I had not now</line>
<line form="verse">Worthily term&#8217;d them merciless to us!</line>
<line form="verse">For ere the ships could meet by twice five leagues,</line>
<line form="verse">We were encount&#8217;red by a mighty rock,</line>
<line form="verse">Which being violently borne upon,</line>
<line form="verse">Our helpful ship was splitted in the midst;</line>
<line form="verse">So that, in this unjust divorce of us,</line>
<line form="verse">Fortune had left to both of us alike</line>
<line form="verse">What to delight in, what to sorrow for.</line>
<line form="verse">Her part, poor soul! Seeming as burdened</line>
<line form="verse">With lesser weight, but not with lesser woe,</line>
<line form="verse">Was carried with more speed before the wind,</line>
<line form="verse">And in our sight they three were taken up</line>
<line form="verse">By fishermen of Corinth, as we thought.</line>
<line form="verse">At length, another ship had seiz&#8217;d on us,</line>
<line form="verse">And knowing whom it was their hap to save,</line>
<line form="verse">Gave healthful welcome to their shipwrack&#8217;d guests,</line>
<line form="verse">And would have reft the fishers of their prey,</line>
<line form="verse">Had not their bark been very slow of sail;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore homeward did they bend their course.</line>
<line form="verse">Thus have you heard me sever&#8217;d from my bliss,</line>
<line form="verse">That by misfortunes was my life prolong&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">To tell sad stories of my own mishaps.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And for the sake of them thou sorrowest for,</line>
<line form="verse">Do me the favor to dilate at full</line>
<line form="verse">What have befall&#8217;n of them and thee till now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My youngest boy, and yet my eldest care,</line>
<line form="verse">At eighteen years became inquisitive</line>
<line form="verse">After his brother; and importun&#8217;d me</line>
<line form="verse">That his attendant&#8212;so his case was like,</line>
<line form="verse">Reft of his brother, but retain&#8217;d his name&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Might bear him company in the quest of him:</line>
<line form="verse">Whom whilst I labored of a love to see,</line>
<line form="verse">I hazarded the loss of whom I lov&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Five summers have I spent in farthest Greece,</line>
<line form="verse">Roaming clean through the bounds of Asia,</line>
<line form="verse">And coasting homeward, came to Ephesus;</line>
<line form="verse">Hopeless to find, yet loath to leave unsought</line>
<line form="verse">Or that, or any place that harbors men.</line>
<line form="verse">But here must end the story of my life,</line>
<line form="verse">And happy were I in my timely death,</line>
<line form="verse">Could all my travels warrant me they live.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hapless Egeon, whom the fates have mark&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To bear the extremity of dire mishap!</line>
<line form="verse">Now trust me, were it not against our laws,</line>
<line form="verse">Against my crown, my oath, my dignity,</line>
<line form="verse">Which princes, would they, may not disannul,</line>
<line form="verse">My soul should sue as advocate for thee:</line>
<line form="verse">But though thou art adjudged to the death,</line>
<line form="verse">And passed sentence may not be recall&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">But to our honor&#8217;s great disparagement,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet will I favor thee in what I can;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, merchant, I&#8217;ll limit thee this day</line>
<line form="verse">To seek thy health by beneficial help.</line>
<line form="verse">Try all the friends thou hast in Ephesus;</line>
<line form="verse">Beg thou, or borrow, to make up the sum,</line>
<line form="verse">And live: if no, then thou art doom&#8217;d to die.</line>
<line form="verse">Jailer, take him to thy custody.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JAIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hopeless and helpless doth Egeon wend,</line>
<line form="verse">But to procrastinate his liveless end.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The mart.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antipholus Erotes of Syracuse, First Merchant, Dromio of Syracuse, Dromio of Ephesus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antipholus of Syracuse is warned by a merchant not to divulge his nationality, for fear of being executed. He sends his servant, Dromio of Syracuse, to his inn with 1000 marks. He invites the merchant to dine with him, but having other engagements the latter instead promises to meet him at five. Dromio of Ephesus comes in, sent by Adriana to search for his master Antipholus of Ephesus, who is late to dinner. Antipholus of Syracuse asks about his money, but Dromio of Ephesus has no idea what he&#8217;s talking about. Antipholus of Syracuse, thinking that Dromio is trying to be funny, beats him for persisting in the jest.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus Erotes of Syracuse, First Merchant, and Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Therefore give out you are of Epidamium,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest that your goods too soon be confiscate:</line>
<line form="verse">This very day a Syracusian merchant</line>
<line form="verse">Is apprehended for arrival here;</line>
<line form="verse">And not being able to buy out his life,</line>
<line form="verse">According to the statute of the town,</line>
<line form="verse">Dies ere the weary sun set in the west.</line>
<line form="verse">There is your money that I had to keep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go bear it to the Centaur, where we host,</line>
<line form="verse">And stay there, Dromio, till I come to thee.</line>
<line form="verse">Within this hour it will be dinner-time;</line>
<line form="verse">Till that, I&#8217;ll view the manners of the town,</line>
<line form="verse">Peruse the traders, gaze upon the buildings,</line>
<line form="verse">And then return and sleep within mine inn,</line>
<line form="verse">For with long travel I am stiff and weary.</line>
<line form="verse">Get thee away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Many a man would take you at your word,</line>
<line form="verse">And go indeed, having so good a mean.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A trusty villain, sir, that very oft,</line>
<line form="verse">When I am dull with care and melancholy,</line>
<line form="verse">Lightens my humor with his merry jests.</line>
<line form="verse">What, will you walk with me about the town,</line>
<line form="verse">And then go to my inn and dine with me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am invited, sir, to certain merchants,</line>
<line form="verse">Of whom I hope to make much benefit;</line>
<line form="verse">I crave your pardon. Soon at five a&#8217; clock,</line>
<line form="verse">Please you, I&#8217;ll meet with you upon the mart,</line>
<line form="verse">And afterward consort you till bed-time:</line>
<line form="verse">My present business calls me from you now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell till then. I will go lose myself,</line>
<line form="verse">And wander up and down to view the city.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, I commend you to your own content.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He that commends me to mine own content,</line>
<line form="verse">Commends me to the thing I cannot get:</line>
<line form="verse">I to the world am like a drop of water,</line>
<line form="verse">That in the ocean seeks another drop,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, falling there to find his fellow forth</line>
<line form="verse">(Unseen, inquisitive), confounds himself.</line>
<line form="verse">So I, to find a mother and a brother,</line>
<line form="verse">In quest of them (unhappy), ah, lose myself.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Here comes the almanac of my true date.</line>
<line form="verse">What now? How chance thou art return&#8217;d so soon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Return&#8217;d so soon! Rather approach&#8217;d too late:</line>
<line form="verse">The capon burns, the pig falls from the spit;</line>
<line form="verse">The clock hath strucken twelve upon the bell:</line>
<line form="verse">My mistress made it one upon my cheek:</line>
<line form="verse">She is so hot, because the meat is cold:</line>
<line form="verse">The meat is cold, because you come not home:</line>
<line form="verse">You come not home, because you have no stomach:</line>
<line form="verse">You have no stomach, having broke your fast:</line>
<line form="verse">But we that know what &#8217;tis to fast and pray,</line>
<line form="verse">Are penitent for your default today.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stop in your wind, sir; tell me this, I pray:</line>
<line form="verse">Where have you left the money that I gave you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O&#8212;sixpence that I had a&#8217; We&#8217;n&#8217;sday last</line>
<line form="verse">To pay the saddler for my mistress&#8217; crupper?</line>
<line form="verse">The saddler had it, sir, I kept it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am not in a sportive humor now:</line>
<line form="verse">Tell me, and dally not, where is the money?</line>
<line form="verse">We being strangers here, how dar&#8217;st thou trust</line>
<line form="verse">So great a charge from thine own custody?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you jest, sir, as you sit at dinner.</line>
<line form="verse">I from my mistress come to you in post:</line>
<line form="verse">If I return, I shall be post indeed,</line>
<line form="verse">For she will score your fault upon my pate:</line>
<line form="verse">Methinks your maw, like mine, should be your clock,</line>
<line form="verse">And strike you home without a messenger.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, Dromio, come, these jests are out of season,</line>
<line form="verse">Reserve them till a merrier hour than this:</line>
<line form="verse">Where is the gold I gave in charge to thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To me, sir? Why, you gave no gold to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come on, sir knave, have done your foolishness,</line>
<line form="verse">And tell me how thou hast dispos&#8217;d thy charge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My charge was but to fetch you from the mart</line>
<line form="verse">Home to your house, the Phoenix, sir, to dinner;</line>
<line form="verse">My mistress and her sister stays for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, as I am a Christian, answer me,</line>
<line form="verse">In what safe place you have bestow&#8217;d my money;</line>
<line form="verse">Or I shall break that merry sconce of yours</line>
<line form="verse">That stands on tricks when I am undispos&#8217;d:</line>
<line form="verse">Where is the thousand marks thou hadst of me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have some marks of yours upon my pate;</line>
<line form="verse">Some of my mistress&#8217; marks upon my shoulders;</line>
<line form="verse">But not a thousand marks between you both.</line>
<line form="verse">If I should pay your worship those again,</line>
<line form="verse">Perchance you will not bear them patiently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy mistress&#8217; marks? What mistress, slave, hast thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your worship&#8217;s wife, my mistress at the Phoenix;</line>
<line form="verse">She that doth fast till you come home to dinner;</line>
<line form="verse">And prays that you will hie you home to dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, wilt thou flout me thus unto my face,</line>
<line form="verse">Being forbid? There, take you that, sir knave.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Strikes Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What mean you, sir? For God sake hold your hands!</line>
<line form="verse">Nay, and you will not, sir, I&#8217;ll take my heels.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Dromio of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon my life, by some device or other</line>
<line form="verse">The villain is  o&#8217;erraught of all my money.</line>
<line form="verse">They say this town is full of cozenage:</line>
<line form="verse">As nimble jugglers that deceive the eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Dark-working sorcerers that change the mind,</line>
<line form="verse">Soul-killing witches that deform the body,</line>
<line form="verse">Disguised cheaters, prating mountebanks,</line>
<line form="verse">And many such-like liberties of sin:</line>
<line form="verse">If it prove so, I will be gone the sooner.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll to the Centaur to go seek this slave;</line>
<line form="verse">I greatly fear my money is not safe.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The house of Antipholus of Ephesus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Adriana, Luciana, Dromio of Ephesus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Adriana impatiently awaits her husband, talking to her sister, Luciana, about men&#8217;s mastery over women. Dromio of Ephesus arrives and tells her how oddly her husband has been behaved, but is sent back to fetch him regardless. Adriana fears that her beauty is fading and that her husband is therefore turning elsewhere.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana, wife to Antipholus Sereptus of Ephesus, with Luciana, her sister.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Neither my husband nor the slave return&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">That in such haste I sent to seek his master?</line>
<line form="verse">Sure, Luciana, it is two a&#8217; clock.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Perhaps some merchant hath invited him,</line>
<line form="verse">And from the mart he&#8217;s somewhere gone to dinner.</line>
<line form="verse">Good sister, let us dine, and never fret;</line>
<line form="verse">A man is master of his liberty:</line>
<line form="verse">Time is their master, and when they see time,</line>
<line form="verse">they&#8217;ll go or come; if so, be patient, sister.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why should their liberty than ours be more?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Because their business still lies out a&#8217; door.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Look when I serve him so, he takes it ill.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, know he is the bridle of your will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s none but asses will be bridled so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, headstrong liberty is lash&#8217;d with woe:</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s nothing situate under heaven&#8217;s eye</line>
<line form="verse">But hath his bound in earth, in sea, in sky.</line>
<line form="verse">The beasts, the fishes, and the winged fowls</line>
<line form="verse">Are their males&#8217; subjects and at their controls:</line>
<line form="verse">Man, more divine, the master of all these,</line>
<line form="verse">Lord of the wide world and wild wat&#8217;ry seas,</line>
<line form="verse">Indu&#8217;d with intellectual sense and souls,</line>
<line form="verse">Of more pre-eminence than fish and fowls,</line>
<line form="verse">Are masters to their females, and their lords:</line>
<line form="verse">Then let your will attend on their accords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This servitude makes you to keep unwed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not this, but troubles of the marriage-bed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But, were you wedded, you would bear some sway.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ere I learn love, I&#8217;ll practice to obey.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How if your husband start some other where?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Till he come home again, I would forbear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Patience unmov&#8217;d! No marvel though she pause&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">They can be meek that have no other cause:</line>
<line form="verse">A wretched soul, bruis&#8217;d with adversity,</line>
<line form="verse">We bid be quiet when we hear it cry;</line>
<line form="verse">But were we burd&#8217;ned with like weight of pain,</line>
<line form="verse">As much, or more, we should ourselves complain:</line>
<line form="verse">So thou, that hast no unkind mate to grieve thee,</line>
<line form="verse">With urging helpless patience would relieve me;</line>
<line form="verse">But if thou live to see like right bereft,</line>
<line form="verse">This fool-begg&#8217;d patience in thee will be left.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, I will marry one day, but to try.</line>
<line form="verse">Here comes your man, now is your husband nigh.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker> 
<line form="verse">Say, is your tardy master now at hand?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, he&#8217;s at two hands with me, and that my two ears can witness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker> 
<line form="verse">Say, didst thou speak with him? Know&#8217;st thou his mind?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, ay, he told his mind upon mine ear. Beshrew his hand, I scarce could understand it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Spake he so doubtfully, thou couldst not feel his meaning?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, he strook so plainly, I could too well feel his blows; and withal so doubtfully, that I could scarce understand them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But say, I prithee, is he coming home?</line>
<line form="verse">It seems he hath great care to please his wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, mistress, sure my master is horn-mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Horn-mad, thou villain!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I mean not cuckold-mad&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">But sure he is stark mad:</line>
<line form="verse">When I desir&#8217;d him to come home to dinner,</line>
<line form="verse">He ask&#8217;d me for a thousand marks in gold:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;&#8217;Tis dinner-time,&#8221; quoth I: &#8220;My gold!&#8221; quoth he.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Your meat doth burn,&#8221; quoth I: &#8220;My gold!&#8221; quoth he.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Will you come?&#8221; quoth I: &#8220;My gold!&#8221; quoth he;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Where is the thousand marks I gave thee, villain?&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;The pig,&#8221; quoth I, &#8220;is burn&#8217;d&#8221; : &#8220;My gold!&#8221; quoth he.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;My mistress, sir,&#8221; quoth I: &#8220;Hang up thy mistress!</line>
<line form="verse">I know not thy mistress, out on thy mistress!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Quoth who?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Quoth my master.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;I know,&#8221; quoth he, &#8220;no house, no wife, no mistress.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">So that my arrant, due unto my tongue,</line>
<line form="verse">I thank him, I bare home upon my shoulders:</line>
<line form="verse">For, in conclusion, he did beat me there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go back again, thou slave, and fetch him home.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go back again, and be new beaten home?</line>
<line form="verse">For God&#8217;s sake send some other messenger.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Back, slave, or I will break thy pate across.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And he will bless that cross with other beating:</line>
<line form="verse">Between you I shall have a holy head.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hence, prating peasant! Fetch thy master home.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Am I so round with you, as you with me,</line>
<line form="verse">That like a football you do spurn me thus?</line>
<line form="verse">You spurn me hence, and he will spurn me hither:</line>
<line form="verse">If I last in this service, you must case me in leather.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, how impatience low&#8217;reth in your face!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His company must do his minions grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst I at home starve for a merry look:</line>
<line form="verse">Hath homely age th&#8217; alluring beauty took</line>
<line form="verse">From my poor cheek? Then he hath wasted it.</line>
<line form="verse">Are my discourses dull? Barren my wit?</line>
<line form="verse">If voluble and sharp discourse be marr&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Unkindness blunts it more than marble hard.</line>
<line form="verse">Do their gay vestments his affections bait?</line>
<line form="verse">That&#8217;s not my fault, he&#8217;s master of my state.</line>
<line form="verse">What ruins are in me that can be found,</line>
<line form="verse">By him not ruin&#8217;d? Then is he the ground</line>
<line form="verse">Of my defeatures. My decayed fair</line>
<line form="verse">A sunny look of his would soon repair.</line>
<line form="verse">But, too unruly deer, he breaks the pale,</line>
<line form="verse">And feeds from home; poor I am but his stale.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Self-harming jealousy&#8212;fie, beat it hence!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unfeeling fools can with such wrongs dispense:</line>
<line form="verse">I know his eye doth homage otherwhere,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else what lets it but he would be here?</line>
<line form="verse">Sister, you know he promis&#8217;d me a chain;</line>
<line form="verse">Would that alone a&#8217; love he would detain,</line>
<line form="verse">So he would keep fair quarter with his bed!</line>
<line form="verse">I see the jewel best enamelled</line>
<line form="verse">Will lose his beauty; yet the gold bides still</line>
<line form="verse">That others touch and, often touching, will</line>
<line form="verse">Where gold; and no man that hath a name</line>
<line form="verse">By falsehood and corruption doth it shame.</line>
<line form="verse">Since that my beauty cannot please his eye,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll weep what&#8217;s left away, and weeping die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How many fond fools serve mad jealousy?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A public place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antipholus Erotes of Syracuse, Dromio of Syracuse, Adriana, Luciana)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antipholus of Syracuse has discovered that Dromio of Syracuse did in fact deposit his money. The servant is confused at his master&#8217;s claims of his playing a bad joke, and does not understand what he has done to deserve a beating. Adriana and Luciana come in, mistaking the two for husband and servant. The Syracusian Antipholus and Dromio are amazed at what is said to them. Adriana says she sent for Antipholus by Dromio (of Ephesus) and Dromio (of Syracuse) denies he ever spoke with the woman; Antipholus feels sure, because of what Dromio of Syracuse said to him, that he must have spoken to her. Dazed to be addressed lovingly by this unknown woman, Antipholus of Ephesus allows himself to be taken home by Adriana, who gives Dromio of Syracuse orders to see that nobody disturbs them while they dine together. The fact that these ladies they have never met know their names leaves Antipholus and Dromio wondering what witchcraft is at work.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus Erotes of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The gold I gave to Dromio is laid up</line>
<line form="verse">Safe at the Centaur, and the heedful slave</line>
<line form="verse">Is wand&#8217;red forth, in care to seek me out.</line>
<line form="verse">By computation and mine host&#8217;s report,</line>
<line form="verse">I could not speak with Dromio since at first</line>
<line form="verse">I sent him from the mart! See, here he comes.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">How now, sir, is your merry humor alter&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">As you love strokes, so jest with me again.</line>
<line form="verse">You know no Centaur? You receiv&#8217;d no gold?</line>
<line form="verse">Your mistress sent to have me home to dinner?</line>
<line form="verse">My house was at the Phoenix? Wast thou mad,</line>
<line form="verse">That thus so madly thou didst answer me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What answer, sir? When spake I such a word?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Even now, even here, not half an hour since.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did not see you since you sent me hence</line>
<line form="verse">Home to the Centaur with the gold you gave me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villain, thou didst deny the gold&#8217;s receipt,</line>
<line form="verse">And toldst me of a mistress, and a dinner,</line>
<line form="verse">For which I hope thou feltst I was displeas&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am glad to see you in this merry vein.</line>
<line form="verse">What means this jest? I pray you, master, tell me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yea, dost thou jeer and flout me in the teeth?</line>
<line form="verse">Think&#8217;st thou I jest? Hold, take thou that, and that.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Beats Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hold, sir, for God&#8217;s sake! Now your jest is earnest,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon what bargain do you give it me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Because that I familiarly sometimes</line>
<line form="verse">Do use you for my fool, and chat with you,</line>
<line form="verse">Your sauciness will jest upon my love,</line>
<line form="verse">And make a common of my serious hours.</line>
<line form="verse">When the sun shines, let foolish gnats make sport,</line>
<line form="verse">But creep in crannies, when he hides his beams:</line>
<line form="verse">If you will jest with me, know my aspect,</line>
<line form="verse">And fashion your demeanor to my looks,</line>
<line form="verse">Or I will beat this method in your sconce.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Sconce call you it? So you would leave battering, I had rather have it a head. And you use these blows long, I must get a sconce for my head, and insconce it too, or else I shall seek my wit in my shoulders. But I pray, sir, why am I beaten?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Dost thou not know?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nothing, sir, but that I am beaten.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Shall I tell you why?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, sir, and wherefore; for they say, every why hath a wherefore.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why first&#8212;for flouting me, and then wherefore&#8212;</line>
<line form="prose">For urging it the second time to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Was there ever any man thus beaten out of season,</line>
<line form="prose">When in the why and the wherefore is neither rhyme nor reason?</line>
<line form="prose">Well, sir, I thank you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thank me, sir, for what?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, for this something that you gave me for nothing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I&#8217;ll make you amends next, to give you nothing for something. But say, sir, is it dinner-time?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No, sir, I think the meat wants that I have.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">In good time, sir: what&#8217;s that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Basting.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, sir, then &#8217;twill be dry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If it be, sir, I pray you eat none of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Your reason?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Lest it make you choleric, and purchase me another dry basting.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, sir, learn to jest in good time&#8212;there&#8217;s a time for all things.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I durst have denied that before you were so choleric.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">By what rule, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, by a rule as plain as the plain bald pate of Father Time himself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Let&#8217;s hear it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">There&#8217;s no time for a man to recover his hair that grows bald by nature.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">May he not do it by fine and recovery?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, to pay a fine for a periwig, and recover the lost hair of another man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why is Time such a niggard of hair, being (as it is) so plentiful an excrement?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Because it is a blessing that he bestows on beasts, and what he hath scanted men in hair he hath given them in wit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, but there&#8217;s many a man hath more hair than wit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not a man of those but he hath the wit to lose his hair.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, thou didst conclude hairy men plain dealers without wit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The plainer dealer, the sooner lost; yet he loseth it in a kind of jollity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">For what reason?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">For two&#8212;and sound ones too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, not sound, I pray you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Sure ones then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, not sure, in a thing falsing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Certain ones then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Name them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The one, to save the money that he spends in tiring; the other, that at dinner they should not drop in his porridge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You would all this time have prov&#8217;d there is no time for all things.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, and did, sir: namely, e&#8217;en no time to recover hair lost by nature.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">But your reason was not substantial, why there is no time to recover.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thus I mend it: Time himself is bald, and therefore, to the world&#8217;s end, will have bald followers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I knew &#8217;twould be a bald conclusion. But soft, who wafts us yonder?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana and Luciana.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, ay, Antipholus, look strange and frown,</line>
<line form="verse">Some other mistress hath thy sweet aspects:</line>
<line form="verse">I am not Adriana, nor thy wife.</line>
<line form="verse">The time was once, when thou unurg&#8217;d wouldst vow</line>
<line form="verse">That never words were music to thine ear,</line>
<line form="verse">That never object pleasing in thine eye,</line>
<line form="verse">That never touch well welcome to thy hand,</line>
<line form="verse">That never meat sweet-savor&#8217;d in thy taste,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless I spake, or look&#8217;d, or touch&#8217;d, or carv&#8217;d to thee.</line>
<line form="verse">How comes it now, my husband, O, how comes it,</line>
<line form="verse">That thou art then estranged from thyself?</line>
<line form="verse">Thyself I call it, being strange to me,</line>
<line form="verse">That, undividable incorporate,</line>
<line form="verse">Am better than thy dear self&#8217;s better part.</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, do not tear away thyself from me;</line>
<line form="verse">For know, my love, as easy mayst thou fall</line>
<line form="verse">A drop of water in the breaking gulf,</line>
<line form="verse">And take unmingled thence that drop again,</line>
<line form="verse">Without addition or diminishing,</line>
<line form="verse">As take from me thyself and not me too.</line>
<line form="verse">How dearly would it touch thee to the quick,</line>
<line form="verse">Shouldst thou but hear I were licentious,</line>
<line form="verse">And that this body, consecrate to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">By ruffian lust should be contaminate?</line>
<line form="verse">Wouldst thou not spit at me, and spurn at me,</line>
<line form="verse">And hurl the name of husband in my face,</line>
<line form="verse">And tear the stain&#8217;d skin off my harlot brow,</line>
<line form="verse">And from my false hand cut the wedding-ring,</line>
<line form="verse">And break it with a deep-divorcing vow?</line>
<line form="verse">I know thou canst, and therefore see thou do it.</line>
<line form="verse">I am possess&#8217;d with an adulterate blot;</line>
<line form="verse">My blood is mingled with the crime of lust:</line>
<line form="verse">For if we two be one, and thou play false,</line>
<line form="verse">I do digest the poison of thy flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">Being strumpeted by thy contagion.</line>
<line form="verse">Keep then fair league and truce with thy true bed,</line>
<line form="verse">I live dis-stain&#8217;d, thou undishonored.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Plead you to me, fair dame? I know you not:</line>
<line form="verse">In Ephesus I am but two hours old,</line>
<line form="verse">As strange unto your town as to your talk,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, every word by all my wit being scann&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Wants wit in all one word to understand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, brother, how the world is chang&#8217;d with you:</line>
<line form="verse">When were you wont to use my sister thus?</line>
<line form="verse">She sent for you by Dromio home to dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By Dromio?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By thee, and this thou didst return from him,</line>
<line form="verse">That he did buffet thee, and in his blows</line>
<line form="verse">Denied my house for his, me for his wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Did you converse, sir, with this gentlewoman?</line>
<line form="verse">What is the course and drift of your compact?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I, sir? I never saw her till this time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villain, thou liest, for even her very words</line>
<line form="verse">Didst thou deliver to me on the mart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never spake with her in all my life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How can she thus then call us by our names,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless it be by inspiration?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How ill agrees it with your gravity</line>
<line form="verse">To counterfeit thus grossly with your slave,</line>
<line form="verse">Abetting him to thwart me in my mood!</line>
<line form="verse">Be it my wrong you are from me exempt,</line>
<line form="verse">But wrong not that wrong with a more contempt.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, I will fasten on this sleeve of thine:</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art an elm, my husband, I a vine,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose weakness, married to thy stronger state,</line>
<line form="verse">Makes me with thy strength to communicate:</line>
<line form="verse">If aught possess thee from me, it is dross,</line>
<line form="verse">Usurping ivy, brier, or idle moss,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, all for want of pruning, with intrusion</line>
<line form="verse">Infect thy sap, and live on thy confusion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To me she speaks, she moves me for her theme:</line>
<line form="verse">What, was I married to her in my dream?</line>
<line form="verse">Or sleep I now and think I hear all this?</line>
<line form="verse">What error drives our eyes and ears amiss?</line>
<line form="verse">Until I know this sure uncertainty,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll entertain the offer&#8217;d fallacy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dromio, go bid the servants spread for dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O for my beads! I cross me for a sinner.</line>
<line form="verse">This is the fairy land. O spite of spites!</line>
<line form="verse">We talk with goblins, owls, and sprites;</line>
<line form="verse">If we obey them not, this will ensue:</line>
<line form="verse">they&#8217;ll suck our breath, or pinch us black and blue.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why prat&#8217;st thou to thyself, and answer&#8217;st not?</line>
<line form="verse">Dromio, thou drumble, thou snail, thou slug, thou sot!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am transformed, master, am not I?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think thou art in mind, and so am I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, master, both in mind and in my shape.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou hast thine own form.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No, I am an ape.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If thou art chang&#8217;d to aught, &#8217;tis to an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis true she rides me and I long for grass.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis so, I am an ass, else it could never be</line>
<line form="verse">But I should know her as well as she knows me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, come, no longer will I be a fool,</line>
<line form="verse">To put the finger in the eye and weep,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst man and master laughs my woes to scorn.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, sir, to dinner. Dromio, keep the gate.</line>
<line form="verse">Husband, I&#8217;ll dine above with you today,</line>
<line form="verse">And shrive you of a thousand idle pranks.</line>
<line form="verse">Sirrah, if any ask you for your master,</line>
<line form="verse">Say he dines forth, and let no creature enter.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, sister. Dromio, play the porter well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Am I in earth, in heaven, or in hell?</line>
<line form="verse">Sleeping or waking, mad or well-advis&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">Known unto these, and to myself disguis&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say as they say, and persever so,</line>
<line form="verse">And in this mist at all adventures go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master, shall I be porter at the gate?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and let none enter, lest I break your pate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, come, Antipholus, we dine too late.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Before the house of Antipholus of Ephesus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antipholus of Ephesus, Dromio of Ephesus, Angelo, Balthazar, Luce, Adriana, Dromio of Syracuse)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antipholus of Ephesus invites the merchant Balthazar and Angelo the goldsmith to dine with him, asking them to support his excuse for being late. Antipholus calls Dromio of Ephesus drunk for trying to tell him that he raved about 1000 marks and denied his wife. When Antipholus of Ephesus knocks at the door of his house, Dromio of Syracuse, keeping the door within, refuses to let him enter. Luce the servant refuses to let them in either, as does Adriana, who insults Antipholus of Ephesus when he calls her his wife. Dromio of Ephesus is surprised that the keeper of the door is called Dromio and thinks he has usurped his name as well as his job. When Antipholus of Ephesus plans to break the door door, Balthazar advises him not to but imply to dine elsewhere. Out of spite Antipholus decides they should eat at a courtesan&#8217;s, and plans to give her a chain intended for his wife.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Ephesus, his man Dromio of Ephesus, Angelo the goldsmith, and Balthazar the merchant.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Signior Angelo, you must excuse us all,</line>
<line form="verse">My wife is shrewish when I keep not hours:</line>
<line form="verse">Say that I linger&#8217;d with you at your shop</line>
<line form="verse">To see the making of her carcanet,</line>
<line form="verse">And that tomorrow you will bring it home.</line>
<line form="verse">But here&#8217;s a villain that would face me down</line>
<line form="verse">He met me on the mart, and that I beat him,</line>
<line form="verse">And charg&#8217;d him with a thousand marks in gold,</line>
<line form="verse">And that I did deny my wife and house.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou drunkard, thou, what didst thou mean by this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say what you will, sir, but I know what I know:</line>
<line form="verse">That you beat me at the mart, I have your hand to show;</line>
<line form="verse">If the skin were parchment, and the blows you gave were ink,</line>
<line form="verse">Your own handwriting would tell you what I think.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think thou art an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Marry, so it doth appear</line>
<line form="verse">By the wrongs I suffer, and the blows I bear.</line>
<line form="verse">I should kick, being kick&#8217;d, and being at that pass,</line>
<line form="verse">You would keep from my heels, and beware of an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Y&#8217; are sad, Signior Balthazar, pray God our cheer</line>
<line form="verse">May answer my good will and your good welcome here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hold your dainties cheap, sir, and your welcome dear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, Signior Balthazar, either at flesh or fish,</line>
<line form="verse">A table full of welcome makes scarce one dainty dish.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good meat, sir, is common; that every churl affords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And welcome more common, for that&#8217;s nothing but words.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Small cheer and great welcome makes a merry feast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, to a niggardly host and more sparing guest:</line>
<line form="verse">But though my cates be mean, take them in good part;</line>
<line form="verse">Better cheer may you have, but not with better heart.</line>
<line form="verse">But soft, my door is lock&#8217;d; go bid them let us in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Maud, Bridget, Marian, Cic&#8217;ly, Gillian, Ginn!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Mome, malt-horse, capon, cox-comb, idiot, patch!</line>
<line form="verse">Either get thee from the door, or sit down at the hatch;</line>
<line form="verse">Dost thou conjure for wenches, that thou call&#8217;st for such store,</line>
<line form="verse">When one is one too many? Go get thee from the door.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What patch is made our porter? My master stays in the street.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Let him walk from whence he came, lest he catch cold on &#8217;s feet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who talks within there? Ho, open the door!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Right, sir, I&#8217;ll tell you when, and You&#8217;ll tell me wherefore.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wherefore? For my dinner: I have not din&#8217;d today.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Nor today here you must not, come again when you may.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What art thou that keep&#8217;st me out from the house I owe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">The porter for this time, sir, and my name is Dromio.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O villain, thou hast stol&#8217;n both mine office and my name:</line>
<line form="verse">The one ne&#8217;er got me credit, the other mickle blame.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou hadst been Dromio today in my place,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wouldst have chang&#8217;d thy face for a name, or thy name for an ass.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Luce within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What a coil is there, Dromio?</line>
<line form="verse">Who are those at the gate?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let my master in, Luce.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Faith, no, he comes too late,</line>
<line form="verse">And so tell your master.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">O Lord, I must laugh!</line>
<line form="verse">Have at you with a proverb&#8212;Shall I set in my staff?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Have at you with another, that&#8217;s&#8212;When? Can you tell?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">If thy name be called Luce&#8212;Luce, thou hast answer&#8217;d him well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do you hear, you minion? You&#8217;ll let us in, I hope?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I thought to have ask&#8217;d you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse" offset="6">And you said no.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So come help: well strook! There was blow for blow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou baggage, let me in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Can you tell for whose sake?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master, knock the door hard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Let him knock till it ache.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You&#8217;ll cry for this, minion, if I beat the door down.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCE.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What needs all that, and a pair of stocks in the town?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Who is that at the door that keeps all this noise?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">By my troth, your town is troubled with unruly boys.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Are you there, wife? You might have come before.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Your wife, sir knave? Go get you from the door.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If you went in pain, master, this knave would go sore.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here is neither cheer, sir, nor welcome: we would fain have either.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In debating which was best, we shall part with neither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They stand at the door, master, bid them welcome hither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is something in the wind, that we cannot get in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You would say so, master, if your garments were thin.</line>
<line form="verse">Your cake here is warm within: you stand here in the cold.</line>
<line form="verse">It would make a man mad as a buck to be so bought and sold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go fetch me something: I&#8217;ll break ope the gate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Break any breaking here, and I&#8217;ll break your knave&#8217;s pate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A man may break a word with you, sir, and words are but wind:</line>
<line form="verse">Ay, and break it in your face, so he break it not behind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">It seems thou want&#8217;st breaking, out upon thee, hind!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s too much &#8220;out upon thee!&#8221;; I pray thee let me in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker> <stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir> 
<line form="verse">Ay, when fowls have no feathers, and fish have no fin.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, I&#8217;ll break in: go borrow me a crow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A crow without feather? Master, mean you so?</line>
<line form="verse">For a fish without a fin, there&#8217;s a fowl without a feather:</line>
<line form="verse">If a crow help us in, sirrah, we&#8217;ll pluck a crow together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, get thee gone, fetch me an iron crow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have patience, sir, O, let it not be so!</line>
<line form="verse">Herein you war against your reputation,</line>
<line form="verse">And draw within the compass of suspect</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; unviolated honor of your wife.</line>
<line form="verse">Once this&#8212;your long experience of her wisdom,</line>
<line form="verse">Her sober virtue, years, and modesty,</line>
<line form="verse">Plead on her part some cause to you unknown;</line>
<line form="verse">And doubt not, sir, but she will well excuse</line>
<line form="verse">Why at this time the doors are made against you.</line>
<line form="verse">Be rul&#8217;d by me, depart in patience,</line>
<line form="verse">And let us to the Tiger all to dinner;</line>
<line form="verse">And about evening come yourself alone</line>
<line form="verse">To know the reason of this strange restraint.</line>
<line form="verse">If by strong hand you offer to break in</line>
<line form="verse">Now in the stirring passage of the day,</line>
<line form="verse">A vulgar comment will be made of it;</line>
<line form="verse">And that supposed by the common rout</line>
<line form="verse">Against your yet ungalled estimation,</line>
<line form="verse">That may with foul intrusion enter in,</line>
<line form="verse">And dwell upon your grave when you are dead;</line>
<line form="verse">For slander lives upon succession,</line>
<line form="verse">Forever hous&#8217;d where it gets possession.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You have prevail&#8217;d. I will depart in quiet,</line>
<line form="verse">And in despite of mirth mean to be merry.</line>
<line form="verse">I know a wench of excellent discourse,</line>
<line form="verse">Pretty and witty; wild, and yet, too, gentle;</line>
<line form="verse">There will we dine. This woman that I mean,</line>
<line form="verse">My wife (but, I protest, without desert)</line>
<line form="verse">Hath oftentimes upbraided me withal:</line>
<line form="verse">To her will we to dinner.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Angelo.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Get you home</line>
<line form="verse">And fetch the chain; by this I know &#8217;tis made.</line>
<line form="verse">Bring it, I pray you, to the Porpentine,</line>
<line form="verse">For there&#8217;s the house. That chain will I bestow</line>
<line form="verse">(Be it for nothing but to spite my wife)</line>
<line form="verse">Upon mine hostess there. Good sir, make haste.</line>
<line form="verse">Since mine own doors refuse to entertain me,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll knock elsewhere, to see if they&#8217;ll disdain me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll meet you at that place some hour hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do so. This jest shall cost me some expense.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Before the house of Antipholus of Ephesus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Luciana, Antipholus of Syracuse, Dromio of Syracuse, Angelo)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Luciana tells Antipholus of Syracuse he should at least pretend he loves his wife, but he protests he has no wife and makes love to her instead. Dromio of Syracuse reports that a fat kitchen wench claimed him as her own, and told him of marks on his arms and shoulders, which made him fear she was a witch. Antipholus gives orders for Dromio to pack, planning to leave as soon as possible. Angelo the goldsmith, finding Antipholus of Syracuse in the street, gives him the chain, which Antipholus protests he has not ordered, but the goldsmith says he has ordered it 20 times. Angelo says he will come for the money when they meet at supper, though Antipholus remarks he had better take it at once. Antipholus thinks it an odd place where people give strangers chains of gold on the street.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Luciana with Antipholus of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And may it be that you have quite forgot</line>
<line form="verse">A husband&#8217;s office? Shall, Antipholus,</line>
<line form="verse">Even in the spring of love, thy love-springs rot?</line>
<line form="verse">Shall love, in building, grow so ruinous?</line>
<line form="verse">If you did wed my sister for her wealth,</line>
<line form="verse">Then for her wealth&#8217;s sake use her with more kindness:</line>
<line form="verse">Or if you like elsewhere, do it by stealth,</line>
<line form="verse">Muffle your false love with some show of blindness:</line>
<line form="verse">Let not my sister read it in your eye;</line>
<line form="verse">Be not thy tongue thy own shame&#8217;s orator:</line>
<line form="verse">Look sweet, speak fair, become disloyalty;</line>
<line form="verse">Apparel vice like virtue&#8217;s harbinger;</line>
<line form="verse">Bear a fair presence, though your heart be tainted;</line>
<line form="verse">Teach sin the carriage of a holy saint;</line>
<line form="verse">Be secret-false: what need she be acquainted?</line>
<line form="verse">What simple thief brags of his own attaint?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis double wrong, to truant with your bed,</line>
<line form="verse">And let her read it in thy looks at board:</line>
<line form="verse">Shame hath a bastard fame, well managed;</line>
<line form="verse">Ill deeds is doubled with an evil word.</line>
<line form="verse">Alas, poor women, make us but believe</line>
<line form="verse">(Being compact of credit) that you love us;</line>
<line form="verse">Though others have the arm, show us the sleeve:</line>
<line form="verse">We in your motion turn, and you may move us.</line>
<line form="verse">Then, gentle brother, get you in again;</line>
<line form="verse">Comfort my sister, cheer her, call her wife:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis holy sport to be a little vain,</line>
<line form="verse">When the sweet breath of flattery conquers strife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet mistress&#8212;what your name is else, I know not,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor by what wonder you do hit of mine&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Less in your knowledge and your grace you show not</line>
<line form="verse">Than our earth&#8217;s wonder, more than earth divine.</line>
<line form="verse">Teach me, dear creature, how to think and speak:</line>
<line form="verse">Lay open to my earthy gross conceit,</line>
<line form="verse">Smoth&#8217;red in errors, feeble, shallow, weak,</line>
<line form="verse">The folded meaning of your words&#8217; deceit.</line>
<line form="verse">Against my soul&#8217;s pure truth why labor you,</line>
<line form="verse">To make it wander in an unknown field?</line>
<line form="verse">Are you a god? Would you create me new?</line>
<line form="verse">Transform me then, and to your pow&#8217;r I&#8217;ll yield.</line>
<line form="verse">But if that I am I, then well I know</line>
<line form="verse">Your weeping sister is no wife of mine,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor to her bed no homage do I owe:</line>
<line form="verse">Far more, far more, to you do I decline.</line>
<line form="verse">O, train me not, sweet mermaid, with thy note,</line>
<line form="verse">To drown me in thy sister&#8217;s flood of tears.</line>
<line form="verse">Sing, siren, for thyself, and I will dote;</line>
<line form="verse">Spread  o&#8217;er the silver waves thy golden hairs,</line>
<line form="verse">And as a bed I&#8217;ll take them, and there lie,</line>
<line form="verse">And in that glorious supposition think</line>
<line form="verse">He gains by death that hath such means to die:</line>
<line form="verse">Let Love, being light, be drowned if she sink!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, are you mad, that you do reason so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not mad, but mated&#8212;how, I do not know.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is a fault that springeth from your eye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For gazing on your beams, fair sun, being by.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gaze when you should, and that will clear your sight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As good to wink, sweet love, as look on night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why call you me love? Call my sister so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy sister&#8217;s sister.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">That&#8217;s my sister.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">No;</line>
<line form="verse">It is thyself, mine own self&#8217;s better part:</line>
<line form="verse">Mine eye&#8217;s clear eye, my dear heart&#8217;s dearer heart,</line>
<line form="verse">My food, my fortune, and my sweet hope&#8217;s aim,</line>
<line form="verse">My sole earth&#8217;s heaven, and my heaven&#8217;s claim.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All this my sister is, or else should be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Call thyself sister, sweet, for I am thee:</line>
<line form="verse">Thee will I love and with thee lead my life;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast no husband yet, nor I no wife.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me thy hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">O soft, sir, hold you still;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll fetch my sister to get her good will.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, how now, Dromio, where run&#8217;st thou so fast?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Do you know me, sir? Am I Dromio? Am I your man? Am I myself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thou art Dromio, thou art my man, thou art thyself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I am an ass, I am a woman&#8217;s man, and besides myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What woman&#8217;s man, and how besides thyself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, besides myself, I am due to a woman: one that claims me, one that haunts me, one that will have me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What claim lays she to thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, such claim as you would lay to your horse, and she would have me as a beast; not that, I being a beast, she would have me, but that she, being a very beastly creature, lays claim to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What is she?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A very reverent body: ay, such a one as a man may not speak of without he say &#8220;Sir-reverence.&#8221; I have but lean luck in the match, and yet is she a wondrous fat marriage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How dost thou mean a fat marriage?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, she&#8217;s the kitchen wench and all grease, and I know not what use to put her to but to make a lamp of her and run from her by her own light. I warrant, her rags and the tallow in them will burn a Poland winter: if she lives till doomsday, she&#8217;ll burn a week longer than the whole world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What complexion is she of?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Swart, like my shoe, but her face nothing like so clean kept: for why? She sweats, a man may go over shoes in the grime of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That&#8217;s a fault that water will mend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No, sir, &#8217;tis in grain, Noah&#8217;s flood could not do it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What&#8217;s her name?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nell, sir; but her name and three quarters, that&#8217;s an ell and three quarters, will not measure her from hip to hip.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Then she bears some breadth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No longer from head to foot than from hip to hip: she is spherical, like a globe; I could find out countries in her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">In what part of her body stands Ireland?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, in her buttocks, I found it out by the bogs.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where Scotland?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I found it by the barrenness, hard in the palm of the hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">In her forehead, arm&#8217;d and reverted, making war against her heir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where England?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I look&#8217;d for the chalky cliffs, but I could find no whiteness in them. But I guess, it stood in her chin, by the salt rheum that ran between France and it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where Spain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Faith, I saw it not; but I felt it hot in her breath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where America, the Indies?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">O, sir, upon her nose, all  o&#8217;er embellish&#8217;d with rubies, carbuncles, sapphires, declining their rich aspect to the hot breath of Spain, who sent whole armadoes of carrects to be ballast at her nose.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where stood Belgia, the Netherlands?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">O, sir, I did not look so low. To conclude, this drudge or diviner laid claim to me, call&#8217;d me Dromio, swore I was assur&#8217;d to her, told me what privy marks I had about me, as the mark of my shoulder, the mole in my neck, the great wart on my left arm, that I, amaz&#8217;d, ran from her as a witch.</line>
<line form="verse">And I think, if my breast had not been made of faith, and my heart of steel,</line>
<line form="verse">She had transform&#8217;d me to a curtal dog, and made me turn i&#8217; th&#8217; wheel.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go hie thee presently, post to the road,</line>
<line form="verse">And if the wind blow any way from shore,</line>
<line form="verse">I will not harbor in this town tonight.</line>
<line form="verse">If any bark put forth, come to the mart,</line>
<line form="verse">Where I will walk till thou return to me.</line>
<line form="verse">If every one knows us, and we know none,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis time, I think, to trudge, pack, and be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As from a bear a man would run for life,</line>
<line form="verse">So fly I from her that would be my wife.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s none but witches do inhabit here,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore &#8217;tis high time that I were hence.</line>
<line form="verse">She that doth call me husband, even my soul</line>
<line form="verse">Doth for a wife abhor. But her fair sister,</line>
<line form="verse">Possess&#8217;d with such a gentle sovereign grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Of such enchanting presence and discourse,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath almost made me traitor to myself;</line>
<line form="verse">But lest myself be guilty to self-wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll stop mine ears against the mermaid&#8217;s song.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Angelo with the chain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master Antipholus&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Ay, that&#8217;s my name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know it well, sir. Lo here&#8217;s the chain.</line>
<line form="verse">I thought to have ta&#8217;en you at the Porpentine;</line>
<line form="verse">The chain unfinish&#8217;d made me stay thus long.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is your will that I shall do with this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What please yourself, sir; I have made it for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Made it for me, sir! I bespoke it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not once, nor twice, but twenty times you have.</line>
<line form="verse">Go home with it, and please your wife withal,</line>
<line form="verse">And soon at supper-time I&#8217;ll visit you,</line>
<line form="verse">And then receive my money for the chain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you, sir, receive the money now,</line>
<line form="verse">For fear you ne&#8217;er see chain nor money more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You are a merry man, sir, fare you well.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What I should think of this, I cannot tell:</line>
<line form="verse">But this I think, there&#8217;s no man is so vain</line>
<line form="verse">That would refuse so fair an offer&#8217;d chain.</line>
<line form="verse">I see a man here needs not live by shifts,</line>
<line form="verse">When in the streets he meets such golden gifts.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll to the mart and there for Dromio stay:</line>
<line form="verse">If any ship put out, then straight away.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A public place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Second Merchant, Angelo, Officer, Antipholus of Ephesus, Dromio of Ephesus, Dromio of Syracuse)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>A second merchant asks Angelo for the money the goldsmith owes him; Angelo explains that he himself is waiting for a payment from Antipholus of Ephesus, and will be able to pay at five o&#8217;clock. Antipholus and Dromio of Ephesus come from the courtesan&#8217;s, and Antipholus sends Dromio to find a rope for whipping the servants back at his house. Antipholus chides Angelo for not bringing the chain he promised to give the courtesan. Angelo thinks Antipholus is joking and asks for his money. Antipholus tells him to get it from his wife, as he hasn&#8217;t the sum with him, and to take the chain to her. Angelo asks for the chain, which Antipholus says he hasn&#8217;t got, and the two fall into an argument about who has it. The second merchant orders Angelo to be arrested, and Angelo orders Antipholus of Ephesus to be arrested, both being very angry at this disgrace. Dromio of Syracuse comes to say he has found the ship and has loaded their goods aboard. Antipholus accuses him of being drunk, since he sent the other Dromio for rope&#8217;s end, and tells him to go to Adriana to bail him out. Angelo and Antipholus are taken away, Dromio wonderingly obeys.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Second Merchant, Angelo the goldsmith, and an Officer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You know since Pentecost the sum is due,</line>
<line form="verse">And since I have not much importun&#8217;d you,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor now I had not, but that I am bound</line>
<line form="verse">To Persia, and want guilders for my voyage:</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore make present satisfaction,</line>
<line form="verse">Or I&#8217;ll attach you by this officer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Even just the sum that I do owe to you</line>
<line form="verse">Is growing to me by Antipholus,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the instant that I met with you</line>
<line form="verse">He had of me a chain. At five a&#8217;clock</line>
<line form="verse">I shall receive the money for the same:</line>
<line form="verse">Pleaseth you walk with me down to his house,</line>
<line form="verse">I will discharge my bond, and thank you too.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Ephesus, Dromio of Ephesus from the Courtezan&#8217;s.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That labor may you save; see where he comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">While I go to the goldsmith&#8217;s house, go thou</line>
<line form="verse">And buy a rope&#8217;s end; that will I bestow</line>
<line form="verse">Among my wife and her confederates,</line>
<line form="verse">For locking me out of my doors by day.</line>
<line form="verse">But soft, I see the goldsmith. Get thee gone,</line>
<line form="verse">Buy thou a rope, and bring it home to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I buy a thousand pound a year! I buy a rope!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A man is well holp up that trusts to you:</line>
<line form="verse">I promised your presence and the chain,</line>
<line form="verse">But neither chain nor goldsmith came to me:</line>
<line form="verse">Belike you thought our love would last too long</line>
<line form="verse">If it were chain&#8217;d together, and therefore came not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Saving your merry humor, here&#8217;s the note</line>
<line form="verse">How much your chain weighs to the utmost charect,</line>
<line form="verse">The fineness of the gold, and chargeful fashion,</line>
<line form="verse">Which doth amount to three odd ducats more</line>
<line form="verse">Than I stand debted to this gentleman.</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you see him presently discharg&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">For he is bound to sea, and stays but for it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am not furnish&#8217;d with the present money:</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, I have some business in the town.</line>
<line form="verse">Good signior, take the stranger to my house,</line>
<line form="verse">And with you take the chain, and bid my wife</line>
<line form="verse">Disburse the sum on the receipt thereof.</line>
<line form="verse">Perchance I will be there as soon as you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then you will bring the chain to her yourself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, bear it with you, lest I come not time enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, sir, I will. Have you the chain about you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And if I have not, sir, I hope you have:</line>
<line form="verse">Or else you may return without your money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, come, I pray you, sir, give me the chain:</line>
<line form="verse">Both wind and tide stays for this gentleman,</line>
<line form="verse">And I, to blame, have held him here too long.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Lord! You use this dalliance to excuse</line>
<line form="verse">Your breach of promise to the Porpentine:</line>
<line form="verse">I should have chid you for not bringing it,</line>
<line form="verse">But like a shrew you first begin to brawl.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The hour steals on, I pray you, sir, dispatch.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You hear how he importunes me&#8212;the chain!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, give it to my wife, and fetch your money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, come, you know I gave it you even now.</line>
<line form="verse">Either send the chain, or send me by some token.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, now you run this humor out of breath.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, where&#8217;s the chain? I pray you let me see it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My business cannot brook this dalliance.</line>
<line form="verse">Good sir, say whe&#8217;r You&#8217;ll answer me or no:</line>
<line form="verse">If not, I&#8217;ll leave him to the officer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I answer you? What should I answer you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The money that you owe me for the chain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I owe you none, till I receive the chain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You know I gave it you half an hour since.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You gave me none, you wrong me much to say so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You wrong me more, sir, in denying it.</line>
<line form="verse">Consider how it stands upon my credit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, officer, arrest him at my suit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do, and charge you in the Duke&#8217;s name to obey me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This touches me in reputation.</line>
<line form="verse">Either consent to pay this sum for me</line>
<line form="verse">Or I attach you by this officer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Consent to pay thee that I never had!</line>
<line form="verse">Arrest me, foolish fellow, if thou dar&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here is thy fee, arrest him, officer.</line>
<line form="verse">I would not spare my brother in this case,</line>
<line form="verse">If he should scorn me so apparently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do arrest you, sir: you hear the suit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do obey thee, till I give thee bail.</line>
<line form="verse">But, sirrah, you shall buy this sport as dear</line>
<line form="verse">As all the metal in your shop will answer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, sir, I shall have law in Ephesus,</line>
<line form="verse">To your notorious shame, I doubt it not.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Syracuse from the bay.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master, there&#8217;s a bark of Epidamium</line>
<line form="verse">That stays but till her owner comes aboard,</line>
<line form="verse">And then, sir, she bears away. Our fraughtage, sir,</line>
<line form="verse">I have convey&#8217;d aboard, and I have bought</line>
<line form="verse">The oil, the balsamum, and aqua-vitae.</line>
<line form="verse">The ship is in her trim, the merry wind</line>
<line form="verse">Blows fair from land: they stay for nought at all</line>
<line form="verse">But for their owner, master, and yourself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now? A madman? Why, thou peevish sheep,</line>
<line form="verse">What ship of Epidamium stays for me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A ship you sent me to, to hire waftage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou drunken slave, I sent thee for a rope,</line>
<line form="verse">And told thee to what purpose and what end.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You sent me for a rope&#8217;s end as soon:</line>
<line form="verse">You sent me to the bay, sir, for a bark.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will debate this matter at more leisure,</line>
<line form="verse">And teach your ears to list me with more heed.</line>
<line form="verse">To Adriana, villain, hie thee straight:</line>
<line form="verse">Give her this key, and tell her, in the desk</line>
<line form="verse">That&#8217;s cover&#8217;d  o&#8217;er with Turkish tapestry</line>
<line form="verse">There is a purse of ducats; let her send it.</line>
<line form="verse">Tell her I am arrested in the street,</line>
<line form="verse">And that shall bail me. Hie thee, slave, be gone!</line>
<line form="verse">On, officer, to prison till it come.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt all but Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To Adriana! That is where we din&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Where Dowsabel did claim me for her husband:</line>
<line form="verse">She is too big, I hope, for me to compass.</line>
<line form="verse">Thither I must, although against my will,</line>
<line form="verse">For servants must their masters&#8217; minds fulfill.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A room in the house of Antipholus of Ephesus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Adriana, Luciana, Dromio of Syracuse)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Luciana tells Adriana of Antipholus of Syracuse&#8217;s protestation of love to her, and Adriana rails against him, though acknowledging she loves him in her heart. Dromio of Syracuse comes in for gold, and though Adriana is surprised her husband is in debt, she gives him the money to bring to Antipholus.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana and Luciana.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, Luciana, did he tempt thee so?</line>
<line form="verse">Mightst thou perceive austerely in his eye</line>
<line form="verse">That he did plead in earnest? Yea or no?</line>
<line form="verse">Look&#8217;d he or red or pale, or sad or merrily?</line>
<line form="verse">What observation mad&#8217;st thou in this case</line>
<line form="verse">Of his heart&#8217;s meteors tilting in his face?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">First he denied you had in him no right.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He meant he did me none: the more my spite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then swore he that he was a stranger here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And true he swore, though yet forsworn he were.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then pleaded I for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">And what said he?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That love I begg&#8217;d for you, he begg&#8217;d of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With what persuasion did he tempt thy love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With words that in an honest suit might move.</line>
<line form="verse">First he did praise my beauty, then my speech.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Didst speak him fair?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Have patience, I beseech.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I cannot, nor I will not, hold me still,</line>
<line form="verse">My tongue, though not my heart, shall have his will.</line>
<line form="verse">He is deformed, crooked, old, and sere,</line>
<line form="verse">Ill-fac&#8217;d, worse bodied, shapeless every where;</line>
<line form="verse">Vicious, ungentle, foolish, blunt, unkind,</line>
<line form="verse">Stigmatical in making, worse in mind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who would be jealous then of such a one?</line>
<line form="verse">No evil lost is wail&#8217;d when it is gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, but I think him better than I say,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet would herein others&#8217; eyes were worse:</line>
<line form="verse">Far from her nest the lapwing cries away;</line>
<line form="verse">My heart prays for him, though my tongue do curse.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, go: the desk, the purse! Sweat now, make haste!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How hast thou lost thy breath?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">By running fast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where is thy master, Dromio? Is he well?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, he&#8217;s in Tartar limbo, worse than hell:</line>
<line form="verse">A devil in an everlasting garment hath him;</line>
<line form="verse">One whose hard heart is button&#8217;d up with steel;</line>
<line form="verse">A fiend, a fairy, pitiless and rough;</line>
<line form="verse">A wolf, nay worse, a fellow all in buff;</line>
<line form="verse">A back-friend, a shoulder-clapper, one that countermands</line>
<line form="verse">The passages of alleys, creeks, and narrow lands;</line>
<line form="verse">A hound that runs counter, and yet draws dry-foot well;</line>
<line form="verse">One that before the judgment carries poor souls to hell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, man, what is the matter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do not know the matter, he is &#8217;rested on the case.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, is he arrested? Tell me at whose suit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know not at whose suit he is arrested well;</line>
<line form="verse">But &#8217;a&#8217;s in a suit of buff which &#8217;rested him, that can I tell.</line>
<line form="verse">Will you send him, mistress, redemption, the money in his desk?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go fetch it, sister.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Luciana.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="4">This I wonder at,</line>
<line form="verse">That he unknown to me should be in debt.</line>
<line form="verse">Tell me, was he arrested on a band?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not on a band but on a stronger thing:</line>
<line form="verse">A chain, a chain! Do you not hear it ring?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, the chain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, no, the bell, &#8217;tis time that I were gone:</line>
<line form="verse">It was two ere I left him, and now the clock strikes one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The hours come back! That did I never hear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O yes, if any hour meet a sergeant, &#8217;a turns back for very fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As if Time were in debt! How fondly dost thou reason!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Time is a very bankrout and owes more than he&#8217;s worth to season.</line>
<line form="verse">Nay, he&#8217;s a thief too: have you not heard men say,</line>
<line form="verse">That Time comes stealing on by night and day?</line>
<line form="verse">If &#8217;a be in debt and theft, and a sergeant in the way,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath he not reason to turn back an hour in a day?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Luciana.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, Dromio, there&#8217;s the money, bear it straight,</line>
<line form="verse">And bring thy master home immediately.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, sister, I am press&#8217;d down with conceit&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Conceit, my comfort and my injury.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A public place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antipholus of Syracuse, Dromio of Syracuse, Courtezan)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antipholus of Syracuse, having been in the market place, is surprised to be greeted by all. Dromio of Syracuse enters with the money to bail him, but Antipholus knows nothing of any arrest. He asks about his ship, and Dromio tells him, saying he told him a short time before. The courtesan enters, sees the chain, and asks for it in exchange for the ring she gave Antipholus of Ephesus, according to their bargain. Antipholus of Syracuse thinks she is a witch, and will have nothing to do with her. Cheated out of her ring, she thinks Antipholus of Syracuse is crazy, and goes to tell the wife of Antipholus of Ephesus she was cheated by him.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s not a man I meet but doth salute me</line>
<line form="verse">As if I were their well-acquainted friend,</line>
<line form="verse">And every one doth call me by my name:</line>
<line form="verse">Some tender money to me, some invite me;</line>
<line form="verse">Some other give me thanks for kindnesses;</line>
<line form="verse">Some offer me commodities to buy.</line>
<line form="verse">Even now a tailor call&#8217;d me in his shop,</line>
<line form="verse">And show&#8217;d me silks that he had bought for me,</line>
<line form="verse">And therewithal took measure of my body.</line>
<line form="verse">Sure these are but imaginary wiles,</line>
<line form="verse">And Lapland sorcerers inhabit here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Master, here&#8217;s the gold you sent me for. What, have you got the picture of old Adam new apparell&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What gold is this? What Adam dost thou mean?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not that Adam that kept the Paradise, but that Adam that keeps the prison; he that goes in the calve&#8217;s-skin that was kill&#8217;d for the Prodigal; he that came behind you, sir, like an evil angel, and bid you forsake your liberty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I understand thee not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No? Why, &#8217;tis a plain case: he that went like a base-viol in a case of leather; the man, sir, that when gentlemen are tir&#8217;d, gives them a sob and &#8217;rests them; he, sir, that takes pity on decay&#8217;d men and gives them suits of durance; he that sets up his rest to do more exploits with his mace than a morris-pike.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What, thou mean&#8217;st an officer?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, sir, the sergeant of the band: he that brings any man to answer it that breaks his band; one that thinks a man always going to bed and says, &#8220;God give you good rest!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, sir, there rest in your foolery. Is there any ships puts forth tonight? May we be gone?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, sir, I brought you word an hour since that the bark Expedition put forth tonight, and then were you hind&#8217;red by the sergeant to tarry for the hoy Delay. Here are the angels that you sent for to deliver you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The fellow is distract, and so am I,</line>
<line form="verse">And here we wander in illusions:</line>
<line form="verse">Some blessed power deliver us from hence!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Courtezan.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well met, well met, Master Antipholus.</line>
<line form="verse">I see, sir, you have found the goldsmith now.</line>
<line form="verse">Is that the chain you promis&#8217;d me today?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sathan, avoid, I charge thee tempt me not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Master, is this Mistress Sathan?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is the devil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, she is worse, she is the devil&#8217;s dam, and here she comes in the habit of a light wench; and thereof comes that the wenches say, &#8220;God damn me,&#8221; that&#8217;s as much to say, &#8220;God make me a light wench.&#8221; It is written, they appear to men like angels of light, light is an effect of fire, and fire will burn: ergo, light wenches will burn. Come not near her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your man and you are marvellous merry, sir.</line>
<line form="verse">Will you go with me? We&#8217;ll mend our dinner here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Master, if you do, expect spoon-meat, or bespeak a long spoon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, Dromio?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, he must have a long spoon that must eat with the devil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Avoid then, fiend, what tell&#8217;st thou me of supping?</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art, as you are all, a sorceress:</line>
<line form="verse">I conjure thee to leave me and be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Give me the ring of mine you had at dinner,</line>
<line form="verse">Or, for my diamond, the chain you promis&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And I&#8217;ll be gone, sir, and not trouble you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Some devils ask but the parings of one&#8217;s nail,</line>
<line form="verse">A rush, a hair, a drop of blood, a pin,</line>
<line form="verse">A nut, a cherry-stone;</line>
<line form="verse">But she, more covetous, would have a chain.</line>
<line form="verse">Master, be wise, and if you give it her,</line>
<line form="verse">The devil will shake her chain, and fright us with it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you, sir, my ring, or else the chain;</line>
<line form="verse">I hope you do not mean to cheat me so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Avaunt, thou witch! Come, Dromio, let us go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Fly pride,&#8221; says the peacock: mistress, that you know.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Antipholus of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now out of doubt Antipholus is mad,</line>
<line form="verse">Else would he never so demean himself.</line>
<line form="verse">A ring he hath of mine worth forty ducats,</line>
<line form="verse">And for the same he promis&#8217;d me a chain:</line>
<line form="verse">Both one and other he denies me now.</line>
<line form="verse">The reason that I gather he is mad,</line>
<line form="verse">Besides this present instance of his rage,</line>
<line form="verse">Is a mad tale he told today at dinner,</line>
<line form="verse">Of his own doors being shut against his entrance.</line>
<line form="verse">Belike his wife, acquainted with his fits,</line>
<line form="verse">On purpose shut the doors against his way.</line>
<line form="verse">My way is now to hie home to his house,</line>
<line form="verse">And tell his wife that, being lunatic,</line>
<line form="verse">He rush&#8217;d into my house, and took perforce</line>
<line form="verse">My ring away. This course I fittest choose,</line>
<line form="verse">For forty ducats is too much to lose.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antipholus of Ephesus, Officer, Dromio of Ephesus, Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan, Pinch, Antipholus of Syracuse, Dromio of Syracuse)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Dromio of Ephesus with a rope meets Antipholus of Ephesus with the officers, delivers the rope, and receives a beating for not bringing money, while he denies he was sent for any. Adriana, Luciana, the courtesan, and the schoolmaster Pinch enter, and Pinch attempts to exorcise Antipholus, receiving a beating for his pains. Antipholus, seconded by Dromio, tells a story of being shut out of his house at dinner, though Adriana says he dined with her. Adriana, seconded by Luciana, tells how she gave the money to Dromio (of Syracuse) but Dromio of Ephesus denies ever having got it. Master and servant are tied up as madmen. Antipholus accuses Adriana of having Pinch with her when she shut him out. Antipholus and Dromio are taken away, after Adriana promises to discharge the debt. Inquiring of the officer, Adriana finds that the money was for the chain, which the courtesan claims was promised her in exchange for her ring. Antipholus and Dromio of Syracuse enter with drawn swords and the others flee, thinking they are loose again and out to kill them. Antipholus and Dromio are glad that witches fear swords, but Antipholus says he will not stay any longer in town, though Dromio feels except for the fat woman claiming him he would be willing to stay and turn witch himself.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Ephesus with the Officer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fear me not, man, I will not break away;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll give thee, ere I leave thee, so much money,</line>
<line form="verse">To warrant thee, as I am &#8217;rested for.</line>
<line form="verse">My wife is in a wayward mood today,</line>
<line form="verse">And will not lightly trust the messenger,</line>
<line form="verse">That I should be attach&#8217;d in Ephesus;</line>
<line form="verse">I tell you, &#8217;twill sound harshly in her ears.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Dromio of Ephesus with a rope&#8217;s end.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Here comes my man: I think he brings the money.</line>
<line form="verse">How now, sir? Have you that I sent you for?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s that, I warrant you, will pay them all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">But where&#8217;s the money?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, sir, I gave the money for the rope.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Five hundred ducats, villain, for a rope?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll serve you, sir, five hundred at the rate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To what end did I bid thee hie thee home?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">To a rope&#8217;s end, sir, and to that end am I return&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And to that end, sir, I will welcome you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Beats Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Good sir, be patient.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, &#8217;tis for me to be patient: I am in adversity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Good now, hold thy tongue.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, rather persuade him to hold his hands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thou whoreson, senseless villain!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I would I were senseless, sir, that I might not feel your blows.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thou art sensible in nothing but blows, and so is an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I am an ass indeed; you may prove it by my long ears. I have serv&#8217;d him from the hour of my nativity to this instant, and have nothing at his hands for my service but blows. When I am cold, he heats me with beating; when I am warm, he cools me with beating. I am wak&#8217;d with it when I sleep, rais&#8217;d with it when I sit, driven out of doors with it when I go from home, welcom&#8217;d home with it when I return; nay, I bear it on my shoulders, as a beggar wont her brat; and I think when he hath lam&#8217;d me, I shall beg with it from door to door.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan, and a schoolmaster call&#8217;d Pinch.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come go along, my wife is coming yonder.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Mistress, <latin xml:lang="la">respice finem</latin>, respect your end, or rather, the prophecy like the parrot, &#8220;beware the rope&#8217;s end.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Wilt thou still talk?</line>
</speech>
<stagedir type="fight">Beats Dromio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How say you now? Is not your husband mad?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His incivility confirms no less.</line>
<line form="verse">Good Doctor Pinch, you are a conjurer,</line>
<line form="verse">Establish him in his true sense again,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will please you what you will demand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alas, how fiery, and how sharp, he looks!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mark, how he trembles in his ecstasy!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Give me your hand, and let me feel your pulse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is my hand, and let it feel your ear.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Strikes Pinch.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I charge thee, Sathan, hous&#8217;d within this man,</line>
<line form="verse">To yield possession to my holy prayers,</line>
<line form="verse">And to thy state of darkness hie thee straight:</line>
<line form="verse">I conjure thee by all the saints in heaven!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peace, doting wizard, peace! I am not mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O that thou wert not, poor distressed soul!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You minion, you, are these your customers?</line>
<line form="verse">Did this companion with the saffron face</line>
<line form="verse">Revel and feast it at my house today,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst upon me the guilty doors were shut,</line>
<line form="verse">And I denied to enter in my house?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O husband, God doth know you din&#8217;d at home,</line>
<line form="verse">Where would you had remain&#8217;d until this time,</line>
<line form="verse">Free from these slanders and this open shame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Din&#8217;d at home? Thou villain, what sayest thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, sooth to say, you did not dine at home.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were not my doors lock&#8217;d up, and I shut out?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Perdie, your doors were lock&#8217;d, and you shut out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And did not she herself revile me there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sans fable, she herself revil&#8217;d you there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Did not her kitchen maid rail, taunt, and scorn me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Certes she did, the kitchen vestal scorn&#8217;d you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And did not I in rage depart from thence?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In verity you did, my bones bears witness,</line>
<line form="verse">That since have felt the vigor of his rage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t good to soothe him in these contraries?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is no shame; the fellow finds his vein,</line>
<line form="verse">And yielding to him, humors well his frenzy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou hast suborn&#8217;d the goldsmith to arrest me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alas, I sent you money to redeem you,</line>
<line form="verse">By Dromio here, who came in haste for it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Money by me? Heart and good will you might,</line>
<line form="verse">But surely, master, not a rag of money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Went&#8217;st not thou to her for a purse of ducats?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He came to me, and I deliver&#8217;d it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I am witness with her that she did.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God and the rope-maker bear me witness</line>
<line form="verse">That I was sent for nothing but a rope!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mistress, both man and master is possess&#8217;d:</line>
<line form="verse">I know it by their pale and deadly looks.</line>
<line form="verse">They must be bound and laid in some dark room.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say wherefore didst thou lock me forth today?</line>
<line form="verse">And why dost thou deny the bag of gold?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did not, gentle husband, lock thee forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And, gentle master, I receiv&#8217;d no gold;</line>
<line form="verse">But I confess, sir, that we were lock&#8217;d out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dissembling villain, thou speak&#8217;st false in both.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dissembling harlot, thou art false in all,</line>
<line form="verse">And art confederate with a damned pack</line>
<line form="verse">To make a loathsome abject scorn of me;</line>
<line form="verse">But with these nails I&#8217;ll pluck out these false eyes</line>
<line form="verse">That would behold in me this shameful sport.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter three or four, and offer to bind him; he strives.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, bind him, bind him, let him not come near me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">More company! The fiend is strong within him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay me, poor man, how pale and wan he looks!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, will you murder me? Thou jailer, thou,</line>
<line form="verse">I am thy prisoner. Wilt thou suffer them</line>
<line form="verse">To make a rescue?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Masters, let him go:</line>
<line form="verse">He is my prisoner, and you shall not have him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PINCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go bind this man, for he is frantic too.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They offer to bind Dromio of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What wilt thou do, thou peevish officer?</line>
<line form="verse">Hast thou delight to see a wretched man</line>
<line form="verse">Do outrage and displeasure to himself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He is my prisoner; if I let him go,</line>
<line form="verse">The debt he owes will be requir&#8217;d of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will discharge thee ere I go from thee:</line>
<line form="verse">Bear me forthwith unto his creditor,</line>
<line form="verse">And knowing how the debt grows, I will pay it.</line>
<line form="verse">Good Master Doctor, see him safe convey&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Home to my house. O most unhappy day!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O most unhappy strumpet!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master, I am here ent&#8217;red in bond for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Out on thee, villain, wherefore dost thou mad me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Will you be bound for nothing? Be mad, good master,</line>
<line form="verse">Cry &#8220;The devil!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God help, poor souls, how idlely do they talk!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go bear him hence. Sister, go you with me.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Manent Officer, Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Say now, whose suit is he arrested at?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">One Angelo, a goldsmith. Do you know him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know the man; what is the sum he owes?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Two hundred ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Say, how grows it due?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Due for a chain your husband had of him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He did bespeak a chain for me, but had it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When as your husband all in rage today</line>
<line form="verse">Came to my house, and took away my ring&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">The ring I saw upon his finger now&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Straight after did I meet him with a chain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It may be so, but I did never see it.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, jailer, bring me where the goldsmith is,</line>
<line form="verse">I long to know the truth hereof at large.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Syracuse, with his rapier drawn, and Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God for thy mercy! They are loose again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And come with naked swords: let&#8217;s call more help</line>
<line form="verse">To have them bound again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Away, they&#8217;ll kill us.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt omnes but Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio of Syracuse as fast as may be, frighted.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I see these witches are afraid of swords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She that would be your wife now ran from you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come to the Centaur, fetch our stuff from thence;</line>
<line form="verse">I long that we were safe and sound aboard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Faith, stay here this night, they will surely do us no harm. You saw they speak us fair, give us gold: methinks they are such a gentle nation that, but for the mountain of mad flesh that claims marriage of me, I could find in my heart to stay here still, and turn witch.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not stay tonight for all the town:</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore away, to get our stuff aboard.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A street before an abbey.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Second Merchant, Angelo, Antipholus of Syracuse. Dromio of Syracuse, Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan, Lady Abbess, Duke of Ephesus, Egeon, Headsman, Officers, Messenger, Antipholus of Ephesus, Dromio of Ephesus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The merchant and Angelo, meeting Antipholus and Dromio of Syracuse, fight over the chain. Adriana, Luciana, the courtesan and others come, and Antipholus and Dromio take refuge in the priory, from whence the lady abbess refuses to deliver them. The Duke and Egeon enter, prepared for Egeon&#8217;s execution. A messenger brings tidings of the escape of Antipholus and Dromio of Ephesus, who have beaten up the servants and burnt Pinch&#8217;s beard. Antipholus and Dromio of Ephesus enter seeking justice against Adriana. The Duke tries to unravel the mystery of the conflicting testimonies. Egeon is denied by Antipholus and Dromio of Ephesus. The abbess enters with the other Antipholus and Dromio, and all is explained. It turns out that the Abbess is Egeon&#8217;s long-lost wife. The Duke pardons Egeon, and all ends well.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Second Merchant and Angelo the goldsmith.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sorry, sir, that I have hind&#8217;red you,</line>
<line form="verse">But I protest he had the chain of me,</line>
<line form="verse">Though most dishonestly he doth deny it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How is the man esteem&#8217;d here in the city?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of very reverent reputation, sir,</line>
<line form="verse">Of credit infinite, highly belov&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Second to none that lives here in the city:</line>
<line form="verse">His word might bear my wealth at any time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak softly, yonder, as I think, he walks.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio of Syracuse again.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis so; and that self chain about his neck,</line>
<line form="verse">Which he forswore most monstrously to have.</line>
<line form="verse">Good sir, draw near to me, I&#8217;ll speak to him.</line>
<line form="verse">Signior Antipholus, I wonder much</line>
<line form="verse">That you would put me to this shame and trouble,</line>
<line form="verse">And, not without some scandal to yourself,</line>
<line form="verse">With circumstance and oaths so to deny</line>
<line form="verse">This chain which now you wear so openly.</line>
<line form="verse">Beside the charge, the shame, imprisonment,</line>
<line form="verse">You have done wrong to this my honest friend,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, but for staying on our controversy,</line>
<line form="verse">Had hoisted sail and put to sea today.</line>
<line form="verse">This chain you had of me, can you deny it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think I had, I never did deny it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, that you did, sir, and forswore it too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who heard me to deny it or forswear it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These ears of mine thou know&#8217;st did hear thee;</line>
<line form="verse">Fie on thee, wretch, &#8217;tis pity that thou liv&#8217;st</line>
<line form="verse">To walk where any honest men resort.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou art a villain to impeach me thus:</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll prove mine honor and mine honesty</line>
<line form="verse">Against thee presently, if thou dar&#8217;st stand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I dare, and do defy thee for a villain.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">They draw.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan, and others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hold, hurt him not for God sake! He is mad.</line>
<line form="verse">Some get within him, take his sword away:</line>
<line form="verse">Bind Dromio too, and bear them to my house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Run, master, run, for God&#8217;s sake take a house!</line>
<line form="verse">This is some priory, in, or we are spoil&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio of Syracuse to the priory.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Abbess Aemilia.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be quiet, people. Wherefore throng you hither?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To fetch my poor distracted husband hence.</line>
<line form="verse">Let us come in, that we may bind him fast,</line>
<line form="verse">And bear him home for his recovery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I knew he was not in his perfect wits.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sorry now that I did draw on him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How long hath this possession held the man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This week he hath been heavy, sour, sad,</line>
<line form="verse">And much different from the man he was;</line>
<line form="verse">But till this afternoon his passion</line>
<line form="verse">Ne&#8217;er brake into extremity of rage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hath he not lost much wealth by wrack of sea?</line>
<line form="verse">Buried some dear friend? Hath not else his eye</line>
<line form="verse">Stray&#8217;d his affection in unlawful love&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">A sin prevailing much in youthful men,</line>
<line form="verse">Who give their eyes the liberty of gazing?</line>
<line form="verse">Which of these sorrows is he subject to?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To none of these, except it be the last,</line>
<line form="verse">Namely, some love that drew him oft from home.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You should for that have reprehended him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, so I did.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Ay, but not rough enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As roughly as my modesty would let me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Haply, in private.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And in assemblies too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, but not enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It was the copy of our conference:</line>
<line form="verse">In bed he slept not for my urging it;</line>
<line form="verse">At board he fed not for my urging it;</line>
<line form="verse">Alone, it was the subject of my theme;</line>
<line form="verse">In company I often glanced it;</line>
<line form="verse">Still did I tell him it was vild and bad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And thereof came it that the man was mad.</line>
<line form="verse">The venom clamors of a jealous woman</line>
<line form="verse">Poisons more deadly than a mad dog&#8217;s tooth.</line>
<line form="verse">It seems his sleeps were hind&#8217;red by thy railing,</line>
<line form="verse">And thereof comes it that his head is light.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou say&#8217;st his meat was sauc&#8217;d with thy upbraidings:</line>
<line form="verse">Unquiet meals make ill digestions,</line>
<line form="verse">Thereof the raging fire of fever bred,</line>
<line form="verse">And what&#8217;s a fever but a fit of madness?</line>
<line form="verse">Thou say&#8217;st his sports were hind&#8217;red by thy brawls:</line>
<line form="verse">Sweet recreation barr&#8217;d, what doth ensue</line>
<line form="verse">But moody and dull melancholy,</line>
<line form="verse">Kinsman to grim and comfortless despair,</line>
<line form="verse">And at her heels a huge infectious troop</line>
<line form="verse">Of pale distemperatures and foes to life?</line>
<line form="verse">In food, in sport, and life-preserving rest</line>
<line form="verse">To be disturb&#8217;d, would mad or man or beast:</line>
<line form="verse">The consequence is then, thy jealous fits</line>
<line form="verse">Hath scar&#8217;d thy husband from the use of wits.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She never reprehended him but mildly,</line>
<line form="verse">When he demean&#8217;d himself rough, rude, and wildly.</line>
<line form="verse">Why bear you these rebukes, and answer not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She did betray me to my own reproof.</line>
<line form="verse">Good people, enter and lay hold on him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, not a creature enters in my house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then let your servants bring my husband forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Neither. He took this place for sanctuary,</line>
<line form="verse">And it shall privilege him from your hands</line>
<line form="verse">Till I have brought him to his wits again,</line>
<line form="verse">Or lose my labor in assaying it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will attend my husband, be his nurse,</line>
<line form="verse">Diet his sickness, for it is my office,</line>
<line form="verse">And will have no attorney but myself,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore let me have him home with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be patient, for I will not let him stir</line>
<line form="verse">Till I have us&#8217;d the approved means I have,</line>
<line form="verse">With wholesome syrups, drugs, and holy prayers,</line>
<line form="verse">To make of him a formal man again:</line>
<line form="verse">It is a branch and parcel of mine oath,</line>
<line form="verse">A charitable duty of my order,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore depart, and leave him here with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not hence, and leave my husband here;</line>
<line form="verse">And ill it doth beseem your holiness</line>
<line form="verse">To separate the husband and the wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be quiet and depart, thou shalt not have him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Complain unto the Duke of this indignity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come go: I will fall prostrate at his feet,</line>
<line form="verse">And never rise until my tears and prayers</line>
<line form="verse">Have won his Grace to come in person hither,</line>
<line form="verse">And take perforce my husband from the abbess.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By this I think the dial points at five.</line>
<line form="verse">Anon I&#8217;m sure the Duke himself in person</line>
<line form="verse">Comes this way to the melancholy vale,</line>
<line form="verse">The place of death and sorry execution,</line>
<line form="verse">Behind the ditches of the abbey here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon what cause?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To see a reverent Syracusian merchant,</line>
<line form="verse">Who put unluckily into this bay</line>
<line form="verse">Against the laws and statutes of this town,</line>
<line form="verse">Beheaded publicly for his offense.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">See where they come, we will behold his death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Kneel to the Duke before he pass the abbey.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Duke of Ephesus attended and Egeon the merchant of Syracuse, bare-head, with the Headsman and other Officers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yet once again proclaim it publicly,</line>
<line form="verse">If any friend will pay the sum for him,</line>
<line form="verse">He shall not die, so much we tender him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Justice, most sacred Duke, against the abbess!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She is a virtuous and a reverend lady,</line>
<line form="verse">It cannot be that she hath done thee wrong.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">May it please your Grace, Antipholus my husband,</line>
<line form="verse">Who I made lord of me and all I had,</line>
<line form="verse">At your important letters&#8212;this ill day</line>
<line form="verse">A most outrageous fit of madness took him,</line>
<line form="verse">That desp&#8217;rately he hurried through the street&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">With him his bondman, all as mad as he&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Doing displeasure to the citizens</line>
<line form="verse">By rushing in their houses, bearing thence</line>
<line form="verse">Rings, jewels, any thing his rage did like.</line>
<line form="verse">Once did I get him bound, and sent him home,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst to take order for the wrongs I went,</line>
<line form="verse">That here and there his fury had committed.</line>
<line form="verse">Anon, I wot not by what strong escape,</line>
<line form="verse">He broke from those that had the guard of him,</line>
<line form="verse">And with his mad attendant and himself,</line>
<line form="verse">Each one with ireful passion, with drawn swords,</line>
<line form="verse">Met us again, and madly bent on us</line>
<line form="verse">Chas&#8217;d us away; till raising of more aid,</line>
<line form="verse">We came again to bind them. Then they fled</line>
<line form="verse">Into this abbey, whither we pursu&#8217;d them,</line>
<line form="verse">And here the abbess shuts the gates on us,</line>
<line form="verse">And will not suffer us to fetch him out,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor send him forth, that we may bear him hence.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, most gracious Duke, with thy command</line>
<line form="verse">Let him be brought forth, and borne hence for help.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Long since thy husband serv&#8217;d me in my wars,</line>
<line form="verse">And I to thee engag&#8217;d a prince&#8217;s word,</line>
<line form="verse">When thou didst make him master of thy bed,</line>
<line form="verse">To do him all the grace and good I could.</line>
<line form="verse">Go some of you, knock at the abbey-gate,</line>
<line form="verse">And bid the Lady Abbess come to me:</line>
<line form="verse">I will determine this before I stir.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O mistress, mistress, shift and save yourself!</line>
<line form="verse">My master and his man are both broke loose,</line>
<line form="verse">Beaten the maids a-row, and bound the doctor,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose beard they have sing&#8217;d off with brands of fire,</line>
<line form="verse">And ever as it blaz&#8217;d, they threw on him</line>
<line form="verse">Great pails of puddled mire to quench the hair;</line>
<line form="verse">My master preaches patience to him, and the while</line>
<line form="verse">His man with scissors nicks him like a fool;</line>
<line form="verse">And sure (unless you send some present help)</line>
<line form="verse">Between them they will kill the conjurer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peace, fool, thy master and his man are here,</line>
<line form="verse">And that is false thou dost report to us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mistress, upon my life, I tell you true;</line>
<line form="verse">I have not breath&#8217;d almost since I did see it.</line>
<line form="verse">He cries for you, and vows, if he can take you,</line>
<line form="verse">To scorch your face, and to disfigure you.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Cry within.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Hark, hark, I hear him, mistress; fly, be gone!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come stand by me, fear nothing. Guard with halberds!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay me, it is my husband! Witness you,</line>
<line form="verse">That he is borne about invisible:</line>
<line form="verse">Even now we hous&#8217;d him in the abbey here,</line>
<line form="verse">And now he&#8217;s there, past thought of human reason.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antipholus of Ephesus and Dromio of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Justice, most gracious Duke, O, grant me justice,</line>
<line form="verse">Even for the service that long since I did thee,</line>
<line form="verse">When I bestrid thee in the wars, and took</line>
<line form="verse">Deep scars to save thy life; even for the blood</line>
<line form="verse">That then I lost for thee, now grant me justice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unless the fear of death doth make me dote,</line>
<line form="verse">I see my son Antipholus and Dromio.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Justice, sweet prince, against that woman there!</line>
<line form="verse">She whom thou gav&#8217;st to me to be my wife;</line>
<line form="verse">That hath abused and dishonored me,</line>
<line form="verse">Even in the strength and height of injury:</line>
<line form="verse">Beyond imagination is the wrong</line>
<line form="verse">That she this day hath shameless thrown on me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Discover how, and thou shalt find me just.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This day, great Duke, she shut the doors upon me,</line>
<line form="verse">While she with harlots feasted in my house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A grievous fault! Say, woman, didst thou so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, my good lord. Myself, he, and my sister</line>
<line form="verse">Today did dine together: so befall my soul</line>
<line form="verse">As this is false he burdens me withal!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ne&#8217;er may I look on day, nor sleep on night,</line>
<line form="verse">But she tells to your Highness simple truth!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O perjur&#8217;d woman! They are both forsworn:</line>
<line form="verse">In this the madman justly chargeth them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My liege, I am advised what I say,</line>
<line form="verse">Neither disturbed with the effect of wine,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor heady-rash, provok&#8217;d with raging ire,</line>
<line form="verse">Albeit my wrongs might make one wiser mad.</line>
<line form="verse">This woman lock&#8217;d me out this day from dinner;</line>
<line form="verse">That goldsmith there, were he not pack&#8217;d with her,</line>
<line form="verse">Could witness it, for he was with me then,</line>
<line form="verse">Who parted with me to go fetch a chain,</line>
<line form="verse">Promising to bring it to the Porpentine,</line>
<line form="verse">Where Balthazar and I did dine together.</line>
<line form="verse">Our dinner done, and he not coming thither,</line>
<line form="verse">I went to seek him. In the street I met him,</line>
<line form="verse">And in his company that gentleman.</line>
<line form="verse">There did this perjur&#8217;d goldsmith swear me down</line>
<line form="verse">That I this day of him receiv&#8217;d the chain,</line>
<line form="verse">Which, God he knows, I saw not; for the which</line>
<line form="verse">He did arrest me with an officer.</line>
<line form="verse">I did obey, and sent my peasant home</line>
<line form="verse">For certain ducats; he with none return&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Then fairly I bespoke the officer</line>
<line form="verse">To go in person with me to my house.</line>
<line form="verse">By th&#8217; way we met</line>
<line form="verse">My wife, her sister, and a rabble more</line>
<line form="verse">Of vild confederates. Along with them</line>
<line form="verse">They brought one Pinch, a hungry lean-fac&#8217;d villain,</line>
<line form="verse">A mere anatomy, a mountebank,</line>
<line form="verse">A threadbare juggler and a fortune-teller,</line>
<line form="verse">A needy, hollow-ey&#8217;d, sharp-looking wretch,</line>
<line form="verse">A living dead man. This pernicious slave,</line>
<line form="verse">Forsooth, took on him as a conjurer,</line>
<line form="verse">And gazing in mine eyes, feeling my pulse,</line>
<line form="verse">And with no face, as &#8217;twere, outfacing me,</line>
<line form="verse">Cries out, I was possess&#8217;d. Then all together</line>
<line form="verse">They fell upon me, bound me, bore me thence,</line>
<line form="verse">And in a dark and dankish vault at home</line>
<line form="verse">There left me and my man, both bound together,</line>
<line form="verse">Till gnawing with my teeth my bonds in sunder,</line>
<line form="verse">I gain&#8217;d my freedom; and immediately</line>
<line form="verse">Ran hither to your Grace, whom I beseech</line>
<line form="verse">To give me ample satisfaction</line>
<line form="verse">For these deep shames and great indignities.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, in truth, thus far I witness with him:</line>
<line form="verse">That he din&#8217;d not at home, but was lock&#8217;d out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But had he such a chain of thee, or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He had, my lord, and when he ran in here,</line>
<line form="verse">These people saw the chain about his neck.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Besides, I will be sworn these ears of mine</line>
<line form="verse">Heard you confess you had the chain of him,</line>
<line form="verse">After you first forswore it on the mart,</line>
<line form="verse">And thereupon I drew my sword on you;</line>
<line form="verse">And then you fled into this abbey here,</line>
<line form="verse">From whence I think you are come by miracle.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never came within these abbey walls,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor ever didst thou draw thy sword on me;</line>
<line form="verse">I never saw the chain, so help me heaven;</line>
<line form="verse">And this is false you burden me withal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, what an intricate impeach is this!</line>
<line form="verse">I think you all have drunk of Circe&#8217;s cup.</line>
<line form="verse">If here you hous&#8217;d him, here he would have been;</line>
<line form="verse">If he were mad, he would not plead so coldly.</line>
<line form="verse">You say he din&#8217;d at home; the goldsmith here</line>
<line form="verse">Denies that saying. Sirrah, what say you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, he din&#8217;d with her there, at the Porpentine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He did, and from my finger snatch&#8217;d that ring.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis true, my liege, this ring I had of her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Saw&#8217;st thou him enter at the abbey here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As sure, my liege, as I do see your Grace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, this is strange. Go call the abbess hither.</line>
<line form="verse">I think you are all mated, or stark mad.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit one to the abbess.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most mighty Duke, vouchsafe me speak a word:</line>
<line form="verse">Haply I see a friend will save my life,</line>
<line form="verse">And pay the sum that may deliver me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak freely, Syracusian, what thou wilt.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is not your name, sir, call&#8217;d Antipholus?</line>
<line form="verse">And is not that your bondman, Dromio?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Within this hour I was his bondman, sir,</line>
<line form="verse">But he, I thank him, gnaw&#8217;d in two my cords:</line>
<line form="verse">Now am I Dromio, and his man, unbound.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sure you both of you remember me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ourselves we do remember, sir, by you;</line>
<line form="verse">For lately we were bound as you are now.</line>
<line form="verse">You are not Pinch&#8217;s patient, are you, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why look you strange on me? You know me well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never saw you in my life till now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O! Grief hath chang&#8217;d me since you saw me last,</line>
<line form="verse">And careful hours with time&#8217;s deformed hand</line>
<line form="verse">Have written strange defeatures in my face:</line>
<line form="verse">But tell me yet, dost thou not know my voice?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Neither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dromio, nor thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">No, trust me, sir, nor I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sure thou dost!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, sir, but I am sure I do not&#8212;and whatsoever a man denies, you are now bound to believe him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not know my voice! O time&#8217;s extremity,</line>
<line form="verse">Hast thou so crack&#8217;d and splitted my poor tongue</line>
<line form="verse">In seven short years, that here my only son</line>
<line form="verse">Knows not my feeble key of untun&#8217;d cares?</line>
<line form="verse">Though now this grained face of mine be hid</line>
<line form="verse">In sap-consuming winter&#8217;s drizzled snow,</line>
<line form="verse">And all the conduits of my blood froze up,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet hath my night of life some memory,</line>
<line form="verse">My wasting lamps some fading glimmer left,</line>
<line form="verse">My dull deaf ears a little use to hear:</line>
<line form="verse">All these old witnesses&#8212;I cannot err&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Tell me thou art my son Antipholus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never saw my father in my life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But seven years since, in Syracuse, boy,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou know&#8217;st we parted, but perhaps, my son,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou sham&#8217;st to acknowledge me in misery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Duke, and all that know me in the city,</line>
<line form="verse">Can witness with me that it is not so.</line>
<line form="verse">I ne&#8217;er saw Syracuse in my life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I tell thee, Syracusian, twenty years</line>
<line form="verse">Have I been patron to Antipholus,</line>
<line form="verse">During which time he ne&#8217;er saw Syracuse:</line>
<line form="verse">I see thy age and dangers make thee dote.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the abbess with Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio of Syracuse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most mighty Duke, behold a man much wrong&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">All gather to see them.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I see two husbands, or mine eyes deceive me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">One of these men is genius to the other:</line>
<line form="verse">And so of these, which is the natural man,</line>
<line form="verse">And which the spirit? Who deciphers them?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I, sir, am Dromio, command him away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I, sir, am Dromio, pray let me stay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Egeon art thou not? Or else his ghost?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O my old master, who hath bound him here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whoever bound him, I will loose his bonds,</line>
<line form="verse">And gain a husband by his liberty.</line>
<line form="verse">Speak, old Egeon, if thou be&#8217;st the man</line>
<line form="verse">That hadst a wife once call&#8217;d Aemilia,</line>
<line form="verse">That bore thee at a burden two fair sons.</line>
<line form="verse">O, if thou be&#8217;st the same Egeon, speak,</line>
<line form="verse">And speak unto the same Aemilia!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If I dream not, thou art Aemilia.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou art she, tell me, where is that son</line>
<line form="verse">That floated with thee on the fatal raft?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By men of Epidamium he and I,</line>
<line form="verse">And the twin Dromio, all were taken up;</line>
<line form="verse">But by and by rude fishermen of Corinth</line>
<line form="verse">By force took Dromio and my son from them,</line>
<line form="verse">And me they left with those of Epidamium.</line>
<line form="verse">What then became of them I cannot tell;</line>
<line form="verse">I to this fortune that you see me in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, here begins his morning story right:</line>
<line form="verse">These two Antipholus&#8217;, these two so like,</line>
<line form="verse">And these two Dromios, one in semblance&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Besides her urging of her wrack at sea&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">These are the parents to these children,</line>
<line form="verse">Which accidentally are met together.</line>
<line form="verse">Antipholus, thou cam&#8217;st from Corinth first?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, sir, not I, I came from Syracuse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, stand apart, I know not which is which.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I came from Corinth, my most gracious lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Brought to this town by that most famous warrior,</line>
<line form="verse">Duke Menaphon, your most renowned uncle.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Which of you two did dine with me today?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I, gentle mistress.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And are not you my husband?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, I say nay to that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so do I, yet did she call me so;</line>
<line form="verse">And this fair gentlewoman, her sister here,</line>
<line form="verse">Did call me brother.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Luciana.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="4">What I told you then</line>
<line form="verse">I hope I shall have leisure to make good,</line>
<line form="verse">If this be not a dream I see and hear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That is the chain, sir, which you had of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think it be, sir, I deny it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And you, sir, for this chain arrested me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think I did, sir, I deny it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ADR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I sent you money, sir, to be your bail,</line>
<line form="verse">By Dromio, but I think he brought it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, none by me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This purse of ducats I receiv&#8217;d from you,</line>
<line form="verse">And Dromio my man did bring them me.</line>
<line form="verse">I see we still did meet each other&#8217;s man,</line>
<line form="verse">And I was ta&#8217;en for him, and he for me,</line>
<line form="verse">And thereupon these errors are arose.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These ducats pawn I for my father here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It shall not need, thy father hath his life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, I must have that diamond from you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There take it, and much thanks for my good cheer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ABB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Renowned Duke, vouchsafe to take the pains</line>
<line form="verse">To go with us into the abbey here,</line>
<line form="verse">And hear at large discoursed all our fortunes;</line>
<line form="verse">And all that are assembled in this place</line>
<line form="verse">That by this sympathized one day&#8217;s error</line>
<line form="verse">Have suffer&#8217;d wrong, go keep us company,</line>
<line form="verse">And we shall make full satisfaction.</line>
<line form="verse">Thirty-three years have I but gone in travail</line>
<line form="verse">Of you, my sons, and till this present hour</line>
<line form="verse">My heavy burden ne&#8217;er delivered.</line>
<line form="verse">The Duke, my husband, and my children both,</line>
<line form="verse">And you the calendars of their nativity,</line>
<line form="verse">Go to a gossips&#8217; feast, and go with me&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">After so long grief, such nativity!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With all my heart, I&#8217;ll gossip at this feast.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt omnes. Manent the two Dromios and two brothers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Master, shall I fetch your stuff from shipboard?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dromio, what stuff of mine hast thou embark&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your goods that lay at host, sir, in the Centaur.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He speaks to me. I am your master, Dromio.</line>
<line form="verse">Come go with us, we&#8217;ll look to that anon.</line>
<line form="verse">Embrace thy brother there, rejoice with him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Antipholus of Ephesus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is a fat friend at your master&#8217;s house,</line>
<line form="verse">That kitchen&#8217;d me for you today at dinner:</line>
<line form="verse">She now shall be my sister, not my wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Methinks you are my glass, and not my brother:</line>
<line form="verse">I see by you I am a sweet-fac&#8217;d youth.</line>
<line form="verse">Will you walk in to see their gossiping?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not I, sir, you are my elder.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That&#8217;s a question; how shall we try it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>S. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll draw cuts for the senior, till then, lead thou first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>E. DRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay then thus:</line>
<line form="verse">We came into the world like brother and brother;</line>
<line form="verse">And now let&#8217;s go hand in hand, not one before another.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>
