<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?><play><title short="Double Falsehood">Double Falsehood, or The Distressed Lovers</title><playwright>William Shakespeare, Lewis Theobald</playwright><personae playtitle="Double Falsehood"><persona gender="male"><persname short="D. BERN.">Don Bernard</persname><persdescription>Don Bernard is Leonora&#8217;s father, a crusty old man who claims to have sympathy for the young and for women&#8217;s right to choose their own husbands, but shows little signs of it. He wishes Leonora would find a richer young man than Julio, and has far more consideration for the business transaction aspect of marriage than for anything as silly as love. Not very self-aware, he does not realize that he could be talking about himself when he describes his father-in-law as a blockhead. His distemper at Leonora&#8217;s continued refusals to marry Henriquez grows to violence when she still refuses at the altar; the only explanation he can come up with is that she has gone mad. He only realizes how wrong he&#8217;s been when Leonora is abducted from the convent where she&#8217;d taken refuge, and the realization brings him to tears. He is rather an old fool, but not a malicious one.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="RODER.">Roderick</persname><persdescription>Roderick is the Duke of Andalusia&#8217;s eldest son, and a decent, upright young man. He is concerned about his younger brother Henriquez&#8217;s actions, though he puts them down to youth rather than evil disposition. Their father sends him to keep an eye on the younger man. Though growing ever more suspicious of what Henriquez has been up to, he agrees to help his brother abduct Leonora from a convent. The evidence mounting against Henriquez convinces him, however, and he decides to force his brother to admit to his wrongs by publicly confronting him with the various witnesses. So long as honor is satisfied all around, he is not concerned with punishing.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="MAST.">Master of the Flocks</persname><persdescription>The Master of the Flocks hires the disguised Violante as a shepherding apprentice. He soon realizes that &#8216;Florio&#8217; is in fact a woman, and as he is a man with very precise ideas about what to do when a woman unexpectedly falls into one&#8217;s hands, he quickly intends to take advantage of the situation. He is not the most sympathetic of men, particularly when he is interrupted before he can have his way with Violante. He is coarse and rather brutal, and enjoys drinking.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="GER.">Gerald</persname><persdescription>Gerald is Henriquez&#8217;s servant. Able to arrange for a concert under a lady&#8217;s window, he is trusted to send messages, but not to know their content.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="LOP.">Lopez</persname><persdescription>Lopez is a villager, Fabian&#8217;s neighbor. He overhears Henriquez&#8217;s ravings the night after his rape of Violante, and is concerned for the young man&#8217;s sanity.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="HENR.">Henriquez</persname><persdescription>Henriquez is the Duke of Andalusia&#8217;s second son, and is in the process of sowing his wild oats, much to his father&#8217;s despair. Though wild and driven by his desires, he is not incapable of introspection. He is fully aware of the extent of his faults when he commits them, but this awareness does not alter his behavior; after raping Violante, he manages to rationalize that because she did not utter a sound, she was not truly resisting. Asked by his friend Julio to look after Leonora, he takes the opportunity to get Julio out of the way and woo the lady for himself, his passion for Violante being quite forgotten. Just as he blames Violante for not resisting vocally during her rape, he blames Leonora for causing him to fall in love with him. He obtains the consent of Don Bernard, Leonora&#8217;s father, to marry her thanks to his social rank, which he is not shy of pulling. He is a good liar when he needs to be, which is quite often. Faced with the evidence of his wrongdoing, he repents and chooses to act honorably, leaving everyone (presumably) happy.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="female"><persname short="VIOL.">Violante</persname><persaliases>	<persname short="FLO.">Florio</persname></persaliases><persdescription>Violante is a poor, young lady being wooed by Henriquez. Of humble birth, she has no desire to join the greats of this world, preferring her village. She therefore pays little attention to Henriquez&#8217;s blandishments. She is also worried that should he have his ways with her, he would then abandon her. Despite his promises to marry her, she still refuses him, and he rapes her. Though she resists him, she remains entirely silent during the act. Shamed and dishonored, she flees her father&#8217;s house, finally disguising herself as a shepherd boy named Florio, in the hopes of following Henriquez and shaming him. The disguise is not entirely successful: both the mad Julio and the Master of the Flocks realize that she is a woman, and the latter attempts to rape her, though Roderick&#8217;s arrival saves her in this instance. She enjoys singing to herself, and accompanies herself on the lute. There is no evidence of her ever being in love with Henriquez, rather wishing that he marry her to repair the crime he has committed against her and to restore her honor.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="CAM.">Camillo</persname><persdescription>Camillo is Julio&#8217;s father. He sent his son to France to perfect his education, though he does not think overmuch of his abilities. He also finds Julio&#8217;s clothes extravagant. He is full of wise advice for his son, but with his neighbors he has the reputation of being a bit nutty. Quite well-off, he is a bluff fellow with little time for the fussiness of polite society, telling Don Bernard that he considers him a liar, not to mention accusing the Duke&#8217;s son Roderick of evil practices to his face. Hearing of his son&#8217;s madness, and then of his death, he becomes despondent and looks forward only to death. He is overjoyed when Julio turns out to be alive. He is 71 years old and suffers from gout.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="female"><persname short="LEON.">Leonora</persname><persdescription>Leonora is Don Bernard&#8217;s daughter and in love with Julio. She is a good, obedient child until her father interferes in her hopes to marry Julio, at which point she begins to defy him. She is aware of her place in society and that though well-off she is not from the highest ranks of society; she worries that when Julio is sent to court it will change him and make him forget her. She is aghast at Henriquez&#8217;s betrayal of his friend and refuses to marry him, being prepared to stab herself rather than go through with the wedding ceremony. Her attempts to escape by hiding in a nunnery are defeated when she is abducted from it by Henriquez and his brother Roderick. She is a determined young woman, and far from shy.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="JUL.">Julio</persname><persdescription>Julio is Camillo&#8217;s son, who is deeply in love with Don Bernard&#8217;s daughter Leonora. An obedient son, he refuses to propose to her without his father&#8217;s approval, upon which Don Bernard&#8217;s consent depends. He is a friend of Henriquez&#8217;s &#8213; or at least believes himself to be one &#8213; and is an excellent, French-educated horseman who dresses rather too well for his station in life. Taking after his father, he is hot-blooded, emotional and passionate, and tends to overreact, never more perhaps than when he goes mad. He has little care for the court, especially when it takes him away from Leonora. Betrayed by Henriquez, he loses his wits, letting the gloomy side of his personality take over just as he loses control of his temper. He remains sensitive to music, though. He is quick to disguise himself to gain access to Leonora, and very physically affectionate when he finally gets her back. He is also generous enough to forgive Henriquez.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="FAB.">Fabian</persname><persdescription>Fabian is a villager, Lopez&#8217;s neighbor. He overhears Henriquez&#8217;s ravings the night after his rape of Violante, and is concerned for the young man&#8217;s sanity.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="CITIZ.">Citizen</persname><persdescription>A Citizen knows most of the main characters and likes them, and is quickly bribed to carry a letter from a clearly disobedient daughter. He is touched by Leonora&#8217;s plight and somewhat concerned by Julio&#8217;s fervor. This concern turns out to be justified when Julio goes mad, and the Citizen must report this to the young man&#8217;s father. He gets no thanks for delivering that particular piece of news.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="female"><persname short="MAID.">Maid</persname><persdescription>A Maid serves Violante, and lets her know that Gerald has brought her a letter.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="DUKE.">Duke Angelo</persname><persdescription>Duke Angelo is the ruler of Andalusia, and Roderick and Henriquez&#8217;s father. An old man, he is making preparations for his death and his succession. Not a fool, he is as suspicious of Henriquez as he is fond of Roderick, but this does not imply that he does not love his younger son. He is a just and honorable man, if old-fashioned and having strong views about the rights of parents. His main concern is that there should be order in the world.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="1. SHEP.">First Shepherd</persname><persdescription>The First Shepherd thinks that Julio would be a fine man were he not mad. He notes the madman&#8217;s attentiveness to music, and thinks that it may be worthwhile to pay attention to his ravings. He is not however so foolish as to not be afraid of Julio&#8217;s propensity to beating people up. He enjoys a good drink.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="2. SHEP.">Second Shepherd</persname><persdescription>The Second Shepherd is convinced that there&#8217;s always a woman to blame if a man goes mad. Julio takes him for Henriquez and attempts to murder him, or at least to pull his nose off. He is less sympathetic to the mad young man than the First Shepherd is, though he too thinks that Julio looks like he&#8217;d be an excellent fellow when sane.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="1. GENT.">First Gentleman</persname><persdescription>The First Gentleman accompanies Julio out of town when the latter goes mad, attempting to bring him to his right wits again. He is unimaginative and unromantic, and a bit of a snob about country folk&#8217;s musical abilities.</persdescription></persona> <persona gender="male"><persname short="2. GENT.">Second Gentleman</persname><persdescription>The Second Gentleman accompanies Julio out of town when the latter goes mad, attempting to bring him to his right wits again. He is very responsive to music and is far more sensitive to emotion than his friend the First Gentleman.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="SERV.">Servant to Violante</persname><persdescription>The Servant to Violante is extremely faithful to her. He finds her the shepherd&#8217;s clothing she will use as a disguise.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="male"><persname short="ATT.">Attendant</persname><persdescription>An Attendant announces Roderick&#8217;s arrival to the Duke.</persdescription></persona> <persona gender="male"><persname short="CHURCH.">A Churchman</persname><persdescription>A Churchman [mute role] comes to Don Bernard&#8217;s house to marry Henriquez and Leonora. He never quite gets to do so.</persdescription></persona><persona gender="female"><persname short="LADIES.">Ladies Attending on Leonora</persname><persdescription>Ladies attending on Leonora accompany her to her wedding and tend to her when she faints.</persdescription></persona></personae><act num="1"><acttitle>Act 1</acttitle><scene num="1"><scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle><scenelocation>The province of Andalusia in Spain. A royal palace.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Duke Angelo, Roderick)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Roderick is disturbed by the fact that his father is discussing his mortality, but as Duke Angelo has no regrets about his life, he does not see why his son should be bothered. Angelo&#8217;s only fear is that his younger son Henriquez&#8217;s behavior will tarnish the family name, but Roderick is certain that with age Henriquez will calm down. Angelo hopes that this is true, but is still bothered by the fact that Henriquez has removed himself from court. Roderick reports that Henriquez is sending his friend Julio to court to get some money for him to buy some horses. Angelo and Roderick decide to see whether they can get Julio to spy for them on his friend.</scenedescription><speech><speaker>RODER.</speaker><line form="verse">My gracious father, this unwonted strain</line><line form="verse">Visits my heart with sadness.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Why, my son?</line><line form="verse">Making my death familiar to my tongue</line><line form="verse">Digs not my grave one jot before the date.</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve worn the garland of my honors long,</line><line form="verse">And would not leave it wither&#8217;d to thy brow,</line><line form="verse">But flourishing and green; worthy the man,</line><line form="verse">Who, with my Dukedoms, heirs my better glories.</line></speech><speech><speaker>RODER.</speaker><line form="verse">This praise, which is my pride, spreads me with blushes.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Think not, that I can flatter thee, my Roderick;</line><line form="verse">Or let the scale of love o&#8217;er-poise my judgment.</line><line form="verse">Like a fair glass of retrospection, thou</line><line form="verse">Reflect&#8217;st the virtues of my early youth;</line><line form="verse">Making my old blood mend its pace with transport:</line><line form="verse">While fond Henriquez, thy irregular brother,</line><line form="verse">Sets the large credit of his name at stake,</line><line form="verse">A truant to my wishes, and his birth.</line><line form="verse">His taints of wildness hurt our nicer honor,</line><line form="verse">And call for swift reclaim.</line></speech><speech><speaker>RODER.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">I trust, my brother</line><line form="verse">Will, by the vantage of his cooler wisdom,</line><line form="verse">E&#8217;er-while redeem the hot escapes of youth,</line><line form="verse">And court opinion with a golden conduct.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Be thou a prophet in that kind suggestion!</line><line form="verse">But I, by fears weighing his unweigh&#8217;d course,</line><line form="verse">Interpret for the future from the past.</line><line form="verse">And strange misgivings, why he hath of late</line><line form="verse">By importunity, and strain&#8217;d petition,</line><line form="verse">Wrested our leave of absence from the court,</line><line form="verse">Awake suspicion. Thou art inward with him;</line><line form="verse">And, haply, from the bosom&#8217;d trust can&#8217;st shape</line><line form="verse">Some formal cause to qualify my doubts.</line></speech><speech><speaker>RODER.</speaker><line form="verse">Why he hath press&#8217;d this absence, sir, I know not;</line><line form="verse">But have his letters of a modern date,</line><line form="verse">Wherein by Julio, good Camillo&#8217;s son,</line><line form="verse">(Who, as he says, shall follow hard upon;</line><line form="verse">And whom I with the growing hour expect)</line><line form="verse">He doth sollicit the return of gold</line><line form="verse">To purchase certain horse, that like him well.</line><line form="verse">This Julio he encounter&#8217;d first in france,</line><line form="verse">And lovingly commends him to my favor;</line><line form="verse">Wishing, I would detain him some few days,</line><line form="verse">To know the value of his well-placed trust.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">O, do it, Roderick; and assay to mould him</line><line form="verse">An honest spy upon thy brother&#8217;s riots.</line><line form="verse">Make us acquainted when the youth arrives;</line><line form="verse">We&#8217;ll see this Julio, and he shall from us</line><line form="verse">Receive the secret loan his friend requires.</line><line form="verse">Bring him to court.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene><scene num="2"><scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle><scenelocation>Prospect of a village at a distance.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Camillo, Julio, Leonora, Don Bernard)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Julio&#8217;s father Camillo is trying to work out why the Duke would want Julio to go to court. Julio himself is uncertain whether he wishes to go, as it involves leaving his beloved Leonora behind. He is particularly worried as her father is expecting him to propose to her that night, with Camillo&#8217;s consent. Leonora enters and is not impressed with Julio&#8217;s unwillingness to talk to his father on the matter, and suggests that they break up. When she finds out he has been summoned to court, however, she is upset, fearing he will find someone more beautiful there. He denies the possibility, and they vow their love to one another, both swearing to remain faithful. Her father Don Bernard enters, disapproving of their public display of affection and reminding Julio that things will move no further without Camillo&#8217;s approval. Julio leaves, promising to have Camillo&#8217;s consent by morning, and Don Bernard admits his reservations about the lad to his daughter, fearing that he may be a bit feather-brained. However, he is neither opposed nor in favor of the match, so is willing to let Leonora marry Julio so long as Camillo agrees.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Camillo with a letter.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">How comes the Duke to take such notice of my son, that he must needs have him in court, and I must send him upon the view of his letter?&#8212;Horsemanship! What horsemanship has Julio? I think, he can no more but gallop a hackney, unless he practiced riding in france. It may be, he did so; for he was there a good continuance. But I have not heard him speak much of his horsemanship. That&#8217;s no matter: if he be not a good horseman, all&#8217;s one in such a case, he must bear. Princes are absolute; they may do what they will in any thing, save what they cannot do.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio.</stagedir><line form="prose">O, come on, sir; read this paper: no more ado, but read it: it must not be answer&#8217;d by my hand, nor yours, but, in gross, by your person; your sole person. Read aloud.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">Please you, to let me first o&#8217;erlook it, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">I was this other day in a spleen against your new suits: I do now think, some fate was the tailor that hath fitted them: for, this hour, they are for the palace of the Duke. Your father&#8217;s house is too dusty.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose">Hem!&#8212;to court? Which is the better, to serve a mistress, or a Duke? I am sued to be his slave, and I sue to be Leonora&#8217;s.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">You shall find your horsemanship much praised there; are you so good a horseman?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">I have been,</line><line form="verse">E&#8217;er now, commended for my seat, or mock&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Take one commendation with another, every third&#8217;s a mock. Affect not therefore to be praised. Here&#8217;s a deal of command and entreaty mixt; there&#8217;s no denying; you must go; peremptorily he enforces that.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose">What fortune soever my going shall encounter, cannot be good fortune; what I part withal unseasons any other goodness.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">You must needs go; he rather conjures than importunes.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose">No moving of my love-suit to him now?</line> </speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Great fortunes have grown out of less grounds.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose">What may her father think of me, who expects to be solicited this very night?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Those scatter&#8217;d pieces of virtue, which are in him, the court will solder together, varnish, and rectify.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">He will surely think I deal too slightly, or unmannerly, or foolishly, indeed; nay, dishonestly; to bear him in hand with my father&#8217;s consent, who yet hath not been touch&#8217;d with so much as a request to it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Well, sir, have you read it over?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">Yes, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">And consider&#8217;d it?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">As I can.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">If you are courted by good fortune, you must go.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">So it please you, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">By any means, and tomorrow: is it not there the limit of his request?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="prose">It is, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">I must bethink me of some necessaries, without which you might be unfurnish&#8217;d: and my supplies shall at all convenience follow you. Come to my closet by and by; I would there speak with you.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Camillo. Manet Julio solus.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I do not see that fervour in the maid,</line><line form="verse">Which youth and love should kindle. She consents,</line><line form="verse">As &#8217;twere to feed without an appetite;</line><line form="verse">Tells me, she is content; and plays the coy one,</line><line form="verse">Like those that subtly make their words their ward,</line><line form="verse">Keeping address at distance. This affection</line><line form="verse">Is such a feign&#8217;d one, as will break untouch&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">Die frosty, e&#8217;er it can be thaw&#8217;d; while mine,</line><line form="verse">Like to a clime beneath Hyperion&#8217;s eye,</line><line form="verse">Burns with one constant heat. I&#8217;ll straight go to her;</line><line form="verse">Pray her to regard my honor: but she greets me.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter Leonora, and maid.</stagedir><line form="verse">See, how her beauty doth enrich the place!</line><line form="verse">O, add the music of thy charming tongue,</line><line form="verse">Sweet as the lark that wakens up the morn,</line><line form="verse">And make me think it paradise indeed.</line><line form="verse">I was about to seek thee, Leonora,</line><line form="verse">And chide thy coldness, love.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">What says your father?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I have not mov&#8217;d him yet.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Then do not, Julio.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Not move him? Was it not your own command,</line><line form="verse">That his consent should ratify our loves?</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Perhaps, it was: but now I&#8217;ve chang&#8217;d my mind.</line><line form="verse">You purchase at too dear a rate, that puts you</line><line form="verse">To woo me and your father too: besides,</line><line form="verse">As he, perchance, may say, you shall not have me;</line><line form="verse">You, who are so obedient, must discharge me</line><line form="verse">Out of your fancy: then, you know, &#8217;twill prove</line><line form="verse">My shame and sorrow, meeting such repulse,</line><line form="verse">To wear the willow in my prime of youth.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Oh! Do not rack me with these ill-placed doubts;</line><line form="verse">Nor think, though age has in my father&#8217;s breast</line><line form="verse">Put out love&#8217;s flame, he therefore has not eyes,</line><line form="verse">Or is in judgment blind. You wrong your beauties,</line><line form="verse">Venus will frown if you disprize her gifts,</line><line form="verse">That have a face would make a frozen hermit</line><line form="verse">Leap from his cell, and burn his beads to kiss it;</line><line form="verse">Eyes, that are nothing but continual births</line><line form="verse">Of new desires in those that view their beams.</line><line form="verse">You cannot have a cause to doubt.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Why, Julio?</line><line form="verse">When you that dare not choose without your father,</line><line form="verse">And, where you love, you dare not vouch it; must not,</line><line form="verse">Though you have eyes, see with &#8217;em;&#8212;can I, think you,</line><line form="verse">Somewhat, perhaps, infected with your suit,</line><line form="verse">Sit down content to say, you would, but dare not?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Urge not suspicions of what cannot be;</line><line form="verse">You deal unkindly; misbecomingly,</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;m loathe to say: for all that waits on you,</line><line form="verse">Is graced, and graces. No impediment</line><line form="verse">Shall bar my wishes, but such grave delays</line><line form="verse">As reason presses patience with; which blunt not,</line><line form="verse">But rather whet our loves. Be patient, sweet.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Patient! What else? My flames are in the flint.</line><line form="verse">Haply, to lose a husband I may weep;</line><line form="verse">Never, to get one: when I cry for bondage,</line><line form="verse">Let freedom quit me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">From what a spirit comes this?</line><line form="verse">I now perceive too plain, you care not for me.</line><line form="verse">Duke, I obey thy summons, be its tenour</line><line form="verse">Whate&#8217;er it will: if war, I come thy soldier:</line><line form="verse">Or if to waste my silken hours at court,</line><line form="verse">The slave of fashion, I with willing soul</line><line form="verse">Embrace the lazy banishment for life;</line><line form="verse">Since Leonora has pronounc&#8217;d my doom.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">What do you mean? Why talk you of the Duke?</line><line form="verse">Wherefore of war, or court, or banishment?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">How this new note is grown of me, I know not;</line><line form="verse">But the Duke writes for me. Coming to move</line><line form="verse">My father in our bus&#8217;ness, I did find him</line><line form="verse">Reading this letter; whose contents require</line><line form="verse">My instant service, and repair to court.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Now I perceive the birth of these delays;</line><line form="verse">Why Leonora was not worth your suit.</line><line form="verse">Repair to court? Ay, there you shall, perhaps,</line><line form="verse">(Rather, past doubt) behold some choicer beauty,</line><line form="verse">Rich in her charms, train&#8217;d to the arts of soothing,</line><line form="verse">Shall prompt you to a spirit of hardiness,</line><line form="verse">To say, &#8220;So please you, father, I have chosen</line><line form="verse">This mistress for my own.&#8221;</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Still you mistake me:</line><line form="verse">Ever your servant I profess myself;</line><line form="verse">And will not blot me with a change, for all</line><line form="verse">That sea and land inherit.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">But when go you?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Tomorrow, love; so runs the Duke&#8217;s command;</line><line form="verse">Stinting our farewell-kisses, cutting off</line><line form="verse">The forms of parting, and the interchange</line><line form="verse">Of thousand precious vows, with haste too rude.</line><line form="verse">Lovers have things of moment to debate,</line><line form="verse">More than a prince, or dreaming statesman, know:</line><line form="verse">Such ceremonies wait on cupid&#8217;s throne.</line><line form="verse">Why heav&#8217;d that sigh?</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">O Julio, let me whisper</line><line form="verse">What, but for parting, I should blush to tell thee:</line><line form="verse">My heart beats thick with fears, lest the gay scene,</line><line form="verse">The splendors of a court, should from thy breast</line><line form="verse">Banish my image, kill my int&#8217;rest in thee,</line><line form="verse">And I be left, the scoff of maids, to drop</line><line form="verse">A widow&#8217;s tear for thy departed faith.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">O let assurance, strong as words can bind,</line><line form="verse">Tell thy pleas&#8217;d soul, I will be wond&#8217;rous faithful;</line><line form="verse">True, as the sun is to his race of light,</line><line form="verse">As shade to darkness, as desire to beauty:</line><line form="verse">And when I swerve, let wretchedness o&#8217;ertake me,</line><line form="verse">Great as e&#8217;er falsehood met, or change can merit.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Enough. I&#8217;m satisfied: and will remain</line><line form="verse">Yours, with a firm and untir&#8217;d constancy.</line><line form="verse">Make not your absence long: old men are wav&#8217;ring;</line><line form="verse">And sway&#8217;d by int&#8217;rest more than promise giv&#8217;n.</line><line form="verse">Should some fresh offer start, when you&#8217;re away,</line><line form="verse">I may be press&#8217;d to something, which must put</line><line form="verse">My faith, or my obedience, to the rack.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Fear not, but I with swiftest wing of time</line><line form="verse">Will labour my return. And in my absence,</line><line form="verse">My noble friend, and now our honor&#8217;d guest,</line><line form="verse">The lord Henriquez, will in my behalf</line><line form="verse">Hang at your father&#8217;s ear, and with kind hints,</line><line form="verse">Pour&#8217;d from a friendly tongue, secure my claim;</line><line form="verse">And play the lover for thy absent Julio.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Is there no instance of a friend turn&#8217;d false?</line><line form="verse">Take heed of that: no love by proxy, Julio.</line><line form="verse">My father&#8212;</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Don Bernard.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">What, Julio, in public? This wooing is too urgent. Is your father yet moved in the suit, who must be the prime unfolder of this business?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I have not yet, indeed, at full possess&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">My father, whom it is my service follows;</line><line form="verse">But only that I have a wife in chase.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Chase!&#8212;let chase alone; no matter for that. You may halt after her, whom you profess to pursue, and catch her too; marry, not unless your father let you slip.&#8212;Briefly, I desire you, (for she tells me, my instructions shall be both eyes and feet to her) no farther to insist in your requiring, &#8217;till, as I have formerly said, Camillo make known to me, that his good liking goes along with us; which but once breath&#8217;d, all is done; &#8217;till when, the business has no life, and cannot find a beginning.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Sir, I will know his mind, e&#8217;er I taste sleep:</line><line form="verse">At morn, you shall be learn&#8217;d in his desire.</line><line form="verse">I take my leave. O virtuous Leonora,</line><line form="verse">Repose, sweet as thy beauties, seal thy eyes;</line><line form="verse">Once more, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>. I have thy promise, love;</line><line form="verse">Remember, and be faithful.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Julio.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">His father is as unsettled, as he is wayward, in his disposition. If I thought young Julio&#8217;s temper were not mended by the metal of his mother, I should be something crazy in giving my consent to this match: and, to tell you true, if my eyes might be the directors to your mind, I could in this town look upon twenty men of more delicate choice. I speak not this altogether to unbend your affections to him: but the meaning of what I say is, that you set such price upon yourself to him, as many, and much his betters, would buy you at; (and reckon those virtues in you at the rate of their scarcity) to which if he come not up, you remain for a better mart.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="prose">My obedience, sir, is chain&#8217;d to your advice.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">&#8217;Tis well said, and wisely. I fear, your lover is a little folly-tainted; which, shortly after it proves so, you will repent.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="prose">Sir, I confess, I approve him of all the men I know; but that approbation is nothing, &#8217;till season&#8217;d by your consent.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">We shall hear soon what his father will do, and so proceed accordingly. I have no great heart to the business, neither will I with any violence oppose it: but leave it to that power which rules in these conjunctions, and there&#8217;s an end. Come, haste we homeward, girl.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene><scene num="3"><scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle><scenelocation>Outside an apartment.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Henriquez, Gerald, Violante)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Henriquez and his servants arrive at Violante&#8217;s window, waiting for some musicians. When they arrive, they serenade her at Henriquez&#8217;s request. When he tries to woo her, she reminds him that she has said no to him already, as she is a lower-class woman and mistrusts lords&#8217; promises. Henriquez is insulted by her rejection, but decides to try to be humble to gain her.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Henriquez, Gerald, and servants with lights.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Bear the lights close&#8212;where is the music, sirs?</line></speech><speech><speaker>GER.</speaker><line form="verse">Coming, my lord.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Let &#8217;em not come too near. This maid,</line><line form="verse">For whom my sighs ride on the night&#8217;s chill vapour,</line><line form="verse">Is born most humbly, though she be as fair</line><line form="verse">As nature&#8217;s richest mould and skill can make her,</line><line form="verse">Mended with strong imagination.</line><line form="verse">But what of that? Th&#8217; obscureness of her birth</line><line form="verse">Cannot eclipse the lustre of her eyes,</line><line form="verse">Which make her all one light.&#8212;Strike up, my masters;</line><line form="verse">But touch the strings with a religious softness;</line><line form="verse">Teach sound to languish through the night&#8217;s dull ear,</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Till melancholy start from her lazy couch,</line><line form="verse">And carelessness grow convert to attention.</line><stagedir type="song">Music plays.</stagedir><line form="verse">She drives me into wonder, when I sometimes</line><line form="verse">Hear her discourse; the court, whereof report,</line><line form="verse">And guess alone inform her, she will rave at,</line><line form="verse">As if she there sev&#8217;n reigns had slander&#8217;d time.</line><line form="verse">Then, when she reasons on her country state,</line><line form="verse">Health, virtue, plainness, and simplicity,</line><line form="verse">On beauties true in title, scorning art,</line><line form="verse">Freedom as well to do, as think, what&#8217;s good;</line><line form="verse">My heart grows sick of birth and empty rank,</line><line form="verse">And I become a villager in wish.</line><line form="verse">Play on&#8212;she sleeps too sound&#8212;be still, and vanish:</line><line form="verse">A gleam of day breaks sudden from her window:</line><line form="verse">O taper, graced by that midnight hand!</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Violante appears above at her window.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Who is&#8217;t, that woos at this late hour? What are you?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">One, who for your dear sake&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Watches the starless night!</line><line form="verse">My lord Henriquez, or my ear deceives me.</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;ve had my answer, and &#8217;tis more than strange</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;ll combat these repulses. Good my lord!</line><line form="verse">Be friend to your own health; and give me leave,</line><line form="verse">Securing my poor fame, nothing to pity</line><line form="verse">What pangs you swear you suffer. &#8217;Tis impossible</line><line form="verse">To plant your choice affections in my shade,</line><line form="verse">At least, for them to grow there.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Why, Violante?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Alas! Sir, there are reasons numberless</line><line form="verse">To bar your aims. Be warn&#8217;d to hours more wholesome;</line><line form="verse">For, these you watch in vain. I have read stories,</line><line form="verse">(I fear, too true ones) how young lords, like you,</line><line form="verse">Have thus besung mean windows, rhymed their suff&#8217;rings</line><line form="verse">Ev&#8217;n to th&#8217; abuse of things divine, set up</line><line form="verse">Plain girls, like me, the idols of their worship,</line><line form="verse">Then left them to bewail their easie faith,</line><line form="verse">And stand the world&#8217;s contempt.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Your memory,</line><line form="verse">Too faithful to the wrongs of few lost maids,</line><line form="verse">Makes fear too general.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Let us be homely,</line><line form="verse">And let us too be chaste, doing you lords no wrong;</line><line form="verse">But crediting your oaths with such a spirit,</line><line form="verse">As you profess them: so no party trusted</line><line form="verse">Shall make a losing bargain. Home, my lord!</line><line form="verse">What you can say, is most unseasonable; what sing,</line><line form="verse">Most absonant and harsh: nay, your perfume,</line><line form="verse">Which I smell hither, cheers not my sense</line><line form="verse">Like our field-violet&#8217;s breath.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Why this dismission</line><line form="verse">Does more invite my staying.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Men of your temper</line><line form="verse">Make ev&#8217;ry thing their bramble. But I wrong</line><line form="verse">That which I am preserving, my maid&#8217;s name,</line><line form="verse">To hold so long discourse. Your virtues guide you</line><line form="verse">T&#8217; effect some nobler purpose!</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Violante.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Stay, bright maid!</line><line form="verse">Come back, and leave me with a fairer hope.</line><line form="verse">She&#8217;s gone. Who am I, that am thus contemn&#8217;d?</line><line form="verse">The second son to a prince? Yes, well, what then?</line><line form="verse">Why, your great birth forbids you to descend</line><line form="verse">To a low alliance. Her&#8217;s is the self-same stuff,</line><line form="verse">Whereof we Dukes are made; but clay more pure!</line><line form="verse">And take away my title, which is acquir&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">Not by myself, but thrown by fortune on me,</line><line form="verse">Or by the merit of some ancestor</line><line form="verse">Of singular quality, she doth inherit</line><line form="verse">Deserts t&#8217; outweigh me. I must stoop to gain her;</line><line form="verse">Throw all my gay comparisons aside,</line><line form="verse">And turn my proud additions out of service,</line><line form="verse">Rather than keep them to become my masters.</line><line form="verse">The dignities we wear, are gifts of pride;</line><line form="verse">And laugh&#8217;d at by the wise, as mere outside.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir></scene></act><act num="2"><acttitle>Act 2</acttitle><scene num="1"><scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle><scenelocation>The prospect of a village.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Fabian, Lopez, Henriquez)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Fabian and Lopez overhear Henriquez as he wrestles with his conscience after raping Violenta, trying to convince himself that her silence implied acquiescence. He is terrified of being found out and dishonored, especially as he is no longer in love with Violante but with Leonora, even though she is his friend Julio&#8217;s lady. His despair is strong enough that the two onlookers are worried he will harm himself.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Fabian and Lopez; Henriquez on the opposite side.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LOP.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose">Soft, soft you, neighbor; who comes here? Pray you, slink aside&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="prose">Ha! Is it come to this? Oh the devil, the devil, the devil!</line></speech><speech><speaker>FAB.</speaker><line form="prose">Lo you now! For want of the discreet ladle of a cool understanding, will this fellow&#8217;s brains boil over.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">To have enjoy&#8217;d her, I would have given&#8212;what?</line><line form="verse">All that at present I could boast my own,</line><line form="verse">And the reversion of the world to boot,</line><line form="verse">Had the inheritance been mine: and now,</line><line form="verse">(Just doom of guilty joys!) I grieve as much</line><line form="verse">That I have rifled all the stores of beauty,</line><line form="verse">Those charms of innocence and artless love,</line><line form="verse">As just before I was devour&#8217;d with sorrow,</line><line form="verse">That she refus&#8217;d my vows, and shut the door</line><line form="verse">Upon my ardent longings.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LOP.</speaker><line form="prose">Love! Love! Downright love! I see by the foolishness of it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="prose">Now then to recollection&#8212;was&#8217;t not so? A promise first of marriage&#8212;not a promise only, for &#8217;twas bound with surety of a thousand oaths&#8212;and those not light ones neither.</line><line form="verse">Yet I remember too, those oaths could not prevail;</line><line form="verse">Th&#8217; unpractis&#8217;d maid trembled to meet my love:</line><line form="verse">By force alone I snatch&#8217;d th&#8217; imperfect joy,</line><line form="verse">Which now torments my memory. Not love,</line><line form="verse">But brutal violence prevail&#8217;d; to which</line><line form="verse">The time, and place, and opportunity,</line><line form="verse">Were accessaries most dishonorable.</line><line form="verse">Shame, shame upon it!</line></speech><speech><speaker>FAB.</speaker><line form="verse">What a heap of stuff&#8217;s this&#8212;I fancy, this fellow&#8217;s head would make a good peddler&#8217;s pack, neighbor.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="prose">Hold, let me be severe to myself, but not unjust. Was it a rape then? No. Her shrieks, her exclamations then had drove me from her. True, she did not consent; as true, she did resist; but still in silence all.</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Twas but the coyness of a modest bride,</line><line form="verse">Not the resentment of a ravish&#8217;d maid.</line><line form="verse">And is the man yet born, who would not risk</line><line form="verse">The guilt, to meet the joy? The guilt! That&#8217;s true&#8212;</line><line form="prose">But then the danger; the tears, the clamours of the ruin&#8217;d maid, pursuing me to court. That, that, I fear will (as it already does my conscience) something shatter my honor. What&#8217;s to be done? But now I have no choice. Fair Leonora reigns confest the tyrant queen of my revolted heart, and Violante seems a short usurper there. Julio&#8217;s already by my arts remov&#8217;d.&#8212;O friendship!</line><line form="verse">How wilt thou answer that? Oh, that a man</line><line form="verse">Could reason down this fever of the blood,</line><line form="verse">Or sooth with words the tumult in his heart!</line><line form="verse">Then, Julio, I might be, indeed, thy friend.</line><line form="verse">They, they only should condemn me,</line><line form="verse">Who born devoid of passion ne&#8217;er have prov&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">The fierce disputes &#8217;twixt virtue and desire.</line><line form="verse">While they, who have, like me,</line><line form="verse">The loose escapes of youthful nature known,</line><line form="verse">Must wink at mine, indulgent to their own.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Henriquez.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LOP.</speaker><line form="prose">This man is certainly mad, and may be mischievous. Prithee, neighbor, let&#8217;s follow him; but at some distance, for fear of the worst.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt after Henriquez.</stagedir></scene><scene num="2"><scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle><scenelocation>An apartment.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Violante, Maid, Gerald)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Shamed and feeling unable to tell anyone about what has happened to her, Violante receives a letter from Henriquez announcing his departure for court and his suggestion that they forget what has occurred. Utterly betrayed, she decides to leave her father&#8217;s house and wander the world at random.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Violante alone.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Whom shall I look upon without a blush?</line><line form="verse">There&#8217;s not a maid, whose eye with virgin gaze</line><line form="verse">Pierces not to my guilt. What will&#8217;t avail me,</line><line form="verse">To say I was not willing;</line><line form="verse">Nothing; but that I publish my dishonor,</line><line form="verse">And wound my fame anew.&#8212;O misery,</line><line form="verse">To seem to all one&#8217;s neighbors rich, yet know</line><line form="verse">One&#8217;s self necessitous and wretched.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter maid, and afterwards Gerald with a letter.</stagedir><speech><speaker>MAID.</speaker><line form="verse">Madam, here&#8217;s Gerald, Lord Henriquez&#8217; servant;</line><line form="verse">He brings a letter to you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">A letter to me! How I tremble now!</line><line form="verse">Your lord&#8217;s for court, good Gerald, is he not?</line></speech><speech><speaker>GER.</speaker><line form="verse">Not so, lady.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">O my presaging heart! When goes he then?</line></speech><speech><speaker>GER.</speaker><line form="verse">His business now steers him some other course.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Whither, I pray you? How my fears torment me!</line></speech><speech><speaker>GER.</speaker><line form="verse">Some two months progress.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Whither, whither, sir,</line><line form="verse">I do beseech you? Good heav&#8217;ns, I lose all patience.</line><line form="verse">Did he deliberate this? Or was the business</line><line form="verse">But then conceiv&#8217;d, when it was born?</line></speech><speech><speaker>GER.</speaker><line form="prose">Lady, I know not that; nor is it in the command I have to wait your answer. For the perusing the letter I commend you to your leisure.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Gerald.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">To hearts like mine suspense is misery.</line><line form="verse">Wax, render up thy trust: be the contents</line><line form="verse">Prosp&#8217;rous, or fatal, they are all my due.</line><stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir><line form="verse"><recite>Our prudence should now teach us to forget,</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>What our indiscretion has committed. I</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>Have already made one step towards this</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>Wisdom, by prevailing on myself to bid you</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>Farewell.</recite></line><line form="verse">O, wretched and betray&#8217;d! Lost Violante!</line><line form="verse">Heart-wounded with a thousand perjur&#8217;d vows,</line><line form="verse">Poison&#8217;d with studied language, and bequeath&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">To desperation. I am now become</line><line form="verse">The tomb of my own honor: a dark mansion,</line><line form="verse">For death alone to dwell in. I invite thee,</line><line form="verse">Consuming desolation, to this temple,</line><line form="verse">Now fit to be thy spoil: the ruin&#8217;d fabric,</line><line form="verse">Which cannot be repair&#8217;d, at once o&#8217;erthrow.</line><line form="verse">What must I do? But that&#8217;s not worth my thought:</line><line form="verse">I will commend to hazard all the time</line><line form="verse">That I shall spend hereafter: farewel, my father,</line><line form="verse">Whom I&#8217;ll no more offend: and men, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>,</line><line form="verse">Whom I&#8217;ll no more believe: and maids, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>,</line><line form="verse">Whom I&#8217;ll no longer shame. The way I go,</line><line form="verse">As yet I know not. Sorrow be my guide.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Violante.</stagedir></scene><scene num="3"><scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle><scenelocation>Prospect of a village. Before Don Bernard&#8217;s house.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Henriquez, Don Bernard, Leonora, Camillo)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Henriquez is still agonizing over his betrayal of Julio and of Violante, but decides that gaining Leonora would be worth it. Don Bernard brings Leonora out; he strongly favors Henriquez&#8217; suit, though Leonora protests that she has pledged herself to Julio. She begs her father not to make her marry Henriquez, but he considers her a fool for that wish and threatens to disown her if she does not agree to marry the Duke&#8217;s son in two days. She walks out, and Henriquez follows her. Don Bernard recalls that Leonora&#8217;s mother was much the same, and married him not out of love but to annoy her father. Camillo comes in to find Bernard; Julio has told his father of his love for Leonora, and on reflection Camillo has come to make the case for his son to Don Bernard. Don Bernard puts Camillo off, however, by claiming that Leonora has fallen in love with Henriquez. Camillo refuses to believe him and goes off to find Leonora and hear her version of this, and Don Bernard resolves to lock her up from company to avoid this.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Henriquez.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Where were the eyes, the voice, the various charms,</line><line form="verse">Each beauteous particle, each nameless grace,</line><line form="verse">Parents of glowing love? All these in her,</line><line form="verse">It seems, were not: but a disease in me,</line><line form="verse">That fancied graces in her. Who ne&#8217;er beheld</line><line form="verse">More than a hawthorne, shall have cause to say</line><line form="verse">The cedar&#8217;s a tall tree; and scorn the shade,</line><line form="verse">The lov&#8217;d bush once had lent him. Soft! Mine honor</line><line form="verse">Begins to sicken in this black reflection.</line><line form="verse">How can it be, that with my honor safe</line><line form="verse">I should pursue Leonora for my wife?</line><line form="verse">That were accumulating injuries,</line><line form="verse">To Violante first, and now to Julio;</line><line form="verse">To her a perjur&#8217;d wretch, to him perfidious;</line><line form="verse">And to myself in strongest terms accus&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">Of murd&#8217;ring Honor willfully, without which</line><line form="verse">My dog&#8217;s the creature of the nobler kind.</line><line form="verse">But Pleasure is too strong for Reason&#8217;s curb;</line><line form="verse">And Conscience sinks o&#8217;erpower&#8217;d with Beauty&#8217;s sweets.</line><line form="verse">Come, Leonora, auth&#8217;ress of my crime,</line><line form="verse">Appear, and vindicate thy empire here;</line><line form="verse">Aid me to drive this ling&#8217;ring Honor hence,</line><line form="verse">And I am wholly thine.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter to him, Don Bernard and Leonora.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">Fie, my good lord; why would you wait without?</line><line form="verse">If you suspect your welcome, I have brought</line><line form="verse">My Leonora to assure you of it.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Henriquez salutes Leonora.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">O kiss, sweet as the odours of the spring,</line><line form="verse">But cold as dews that dwell on morning flow&#8217;rs!</line><line form="verse">Say, Leonora, has your father conquer&#8217;d?</line><line form="verse">Shall duty then at last obtain the prize,</line><line form="verse">Which you refus&#8217;d to love? And shall Henriquez</line><line form="verse">Owe all his happiness to good Bernardo?</line><line form="verse">Ah! No; I read my ruin in your eyes:</line><line form="verse">That sorrow, louder than a thousand tongues,</line><line form="verse">Pronounces my despair.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Come, Leonora,</line><line form="verse">You are not now to learn, this noble lord,</line><line form="verse">(Whom but to name, restores my failing age,)</line><line form="verse">Has with a lover&#8217;s eye beheld your beauty;</line><line form="verse">Through which his heart speaks more than language can;</line><line form="verse">It offers joy and happiness to you,</line><line form="verse">And honor to our house. Imagine then</line><line form="verse">The birth and qualities of him that loves you;</line><line form="verse">Which when you know, you cannot rate too dear.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">My father, on my knees I do beseech you</line><line form="verse">To pause one moment on your daughter&#8217;s ruin.</line><line form="verse">I vow, my heart ev&#8217;n bleeds, that I must thank you</line><line form="verse">For your past tenderness; and yet distrust</line><line form="verse">That which is yet behind. Consider, sir,</line><line form="verse">Whoe&#8217;er&#8217;s th&#8217; occasion of another&#8217;s fault,</line><line form="verse">Cannot himself be innocent. O, give not</line><line form="verse">The censuring world occasion to reproach</line><line form="verse">Your harsh commands; or to my charge lay that</line><line form="verse">Which most I fear, the fault of disobedience.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Prithee, fear neither the one, nor the other: I tell thee, girl, there&#8217;s more fear than danger. For my own part, as soon as thou art married to this noble lord, my fears will be over.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Sir, I should be the vainest of my sex,</line><line form="verse">Not to esteem myself unworthy far</line><line form="verse">Of this high honor. Once there was a time,</line><line form="verse">When to have heard my lord Henriquez&#8217; vows,</line><line form="verse">Might have subdued my unexperienc&#8217;d heart,</line><line form="verse">And made me wholly his.&#8212;But that&#8217;s now past:</line><line form="verse">And my firm-plighted faith by your consent</line><line form="verse">Was long since given to the injur&#8217;d Julio.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Why then, by my consent e&#8217;en take it back again. Thou, like a simple wench, hast given thy affections to a fellow, that does not care a farthing for them. One, that has left thee for a jaunt to court; as who should say, &#8220;I&#8217;ll get a place now; &#8217;tis time enough to marry, when I&#8217;m turn&#8217;d out of it.&#8221;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">So, surely, it should seem, most lovely maid;</line><line form="verse">Julio, alas, feels nothing of my passion:</line><line form="verse">His love is but th&#8217; amusement of an hour,</line><line form="verse">A short relief from business, or ambition,</line><line form="verse">The sport of youth, and fashion of the age.</line><line form="verse">O! Had he known the hopes, the doubts, the ardours,</line><line form="verse">Or half the fond varieties of passion,</line><line form="verse">That play the tyrant with my tortur&#8217;d soul;</line><line form="verse">He had not left thee to pursue his fortune:</line><line form="verse">To practice cringes in a slavish circle,</line><line form="verse">And barter real bliss for unsure honor.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Oh, the opposing wind,</line><line form="verse">Should&#8217;ring the tide, makes here a fearful billow:</line><line form="verse">I needs must perish in it.&#8212;Oh, my lord,</line><line form="verse">Is it then possible, you can forget</line><line form="verse">What&#8217;s due to your great name, and princely birth,</line><line form="verse">To friendship&#8217;s holy law, to faith repos&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">To truth, to honor, and poor injur&#8217;d Julio?</line><line form="verse">O think, my lord, how much this Julio loves you;</line><line form="verse">Recall his services, his well-tried faith;</line><line form="verse">Think too, this very hour, where&#8217;er he be,</line><line form="verse">Your favor is the envy of the court,</line><line form="verse">And secret triumph of his grateful heart.</line><line form="verse">Poor Julio, how securely thou depend&#8217;st</line><line form="verse">Upon the faith and honor of thy master;</line><line form="verse">Mistaken youth! This very hour he robs thee</line><line form="verse">Of all thy heart holds dear. &#8217;Tis so Henriquez</line><line form="verse">Repays the merits of unhappy Julio.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Weeps.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">My slumb&#8217;ring honor catches the alarm.</line><line form="verse">I was to blame to parley with her thus:</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">She&#8217;s shown me to myself. It troubles me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">Mad; mad. Stark mad, by this light.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">I but begin to be so. I conjure you,</line><line form="verse">By all the tender interests of nature,</line><line form="verse">By the chaste love &#8217;twixt you, and my dear mother,</line><line form="verse">(O holy heav&#8217;n, that she were living now!)</line><line form="verse">Forgive and pity me.&#8212;Oh, sir, remember,</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve heard my mother say a thousand times,</line><line form="verse">Her father would have forced her virgin choice;</line><line form="verse">But when the conflict was &#8217;twixt love and duty,</line><line form="verse">Which should be first obey&#8217;d, my mother quickly</line><line form="verse">Paid up her vows to love, and married you.</line><line form="verse">You thought this well, and she was praised for this;</line><line form="verse">For this her name was honor&#8217;d, disobedience</line><line form="verse">Was ne&#8217;er imputed to her, her firm love</line><line form="verse">Conquer&#8217;d whate&#8217;er oppos&#8217;d it, and she prosper&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">Long time your wife. My case is now the same;</line><line form="verse">You are the father, which you then condemn&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">I, what my mother was; but not so happy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Go to, you&#8217;re a fool. No doubt, you have old stories enough to undo you. What, you can&#8217;t throw yourself away but by precedent, ha? You will needs be married to one, that will none of you? You will be happy no body&#8217;s way but your own, forsooth. But, d&#8217;ye mark me, spare your tongue for the future; (and that&#8217;s using you hardly too, to bid you spare what you have a great deal too much of) go, go your ways, and d&#8217;ye hear, get ready within these two days to be married to a husband you don&#8217;t deserve. Do it, or, by my dead father&#8217;s soul, you are no acquaintance of mine.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">She weeps: be gentler to her, good Bernardo.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Then woe the day. I&#8217;m circled round with fire;</line><line form="verse">No way for my escape, but through the flames.</line><line form="verse">Oh, can I e&#8217;er resolve to live without</line><line form="verse">A father&#8217;s blessing, or abandon Julio?</line><line form="verse">With other maids, the choice were not so hard;</line><line form="verse">Int&#8217;rest, that rules the world, has made at last</line><line form="verse">A merchandize of hearts: and virgins now</line><line form="verse">Choose as they&#8217;re bid, and wed without esteem.</line><line form="verse">By nobler springs shall my affections move;</line><line form="verse">Nor own a master, but the man I love.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Leonora.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Go thy ways, contradiction. Follow her, my lord; follow her, in the very heat. This obstinacy must be combated by importunity as obstinate.</line><stagedir type="exit">Exit Henriquez after her.</stagedir><line form="prose">The girl says right; her mother was just such another. I remember, two of us courted her at the same time. She lov&#8217;d neither of us, but she chose me purely to spight that surly old blockhead my father-in-law. Who comes here, Camillo? Now the refusing part will lie on my side.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Camillo.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">My worthy neighbor, I am much in fortune&#8217;s favor to find you thus alone. I have a suit to you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Please to name it, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Sir, I have long held you in singular esteem: and what I shall now say, will be a proof of it. You know, sir, I have but one son.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Ay, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">And the fortune I am blest withal, you pretty well know what it is.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">&#8217;Tis a fair one, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Such as it is, the whole reversion is my son&#8217;s. He is now engaged in his attendance on our master, the Duke. But e&#8217;er he went, he left with me the secret of his heart, his love for your fair daughter. For your consent, he said, &#8217;twas ready. I took a night, indeed, to think upon it, and now have brought you mine; and am come to bind the contract with half my fortune in present, the whole some time hence, and, in the mean while, my hearty blessing. Ha? What say you to&#8217;t, Don Bernard?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Why, really, neighbor,&#8212;I must own, I have heard something of this matter.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Heard something of it? No doubt, you have.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Yes, now I recollect it well.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Was it so long ago then?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Very long ago, neighbor. On Tuesday last.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">What, am I mock&#8217;d in this business, Don Bernard?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Not mock&#8217;d, good Camillo, not mock&#8217;d: but in love-matters, you know, there are abundance of changes in half an hour. Time, time, neighbor, plays tricks with all of us.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Time, sir! What tell you me of time? Come, I see how this goes. Can a little time take a man by the shoulder, and shake off his honor? Let me tell you, neighbor, it must either be a strong wind, or a very mellow honesty that drops so easily. Time, quoth&#8217;a?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Look&#8217;e, Camillo; will you please to put your indignation in your pocket for half a moment, while I tell you the whole truth of the matter. My daughter, you must know, is such a tender soul, she cannot possibly see a Duke&#8217;s younger son without falling desperately in love with him. Now, you know, neighbor, when greatness rides post after a man of my years, &#8217;tis both prudence, and good breeding, to let one&#8217;s self be overtaken by it. And who can help all this? I profess, it was not my seeking, neighbor.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">I profess, a fox might earth in the hollowness of your heart, neighbor, and there&#8217;s an end. If I were to give a bad conscience its true likeness, it should be drawn after a very near neighbor to a certain poor neighbor of yours.&#8212;Neighbor! With a pox!</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Nay, you are so nimble with me, you will hear nothing.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Sir, if I must speak nothing, I will hear nothing. As for what you have to say, if it comes from your heart, &#8217;tis a lie before you speak it. I&#8217;ll to Leonora; and if I find her in the same story, why, I shall believe your wife was true to you, and your daughter is your own. Fare you well.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit, as into Don Bernard&#8217;s house.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="prose">Ay, but two words must go to that bargain. It happens, that I am at present of opinion my daughter shall receive no more company to day; at least, no such visits as yours.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Don Bernard, following him.</stagedir></scene><scene num="4"><scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle><scenelocation>Another prospect of Don Bernard&#8217;s house.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Leonora, Citizen, Don Bernard)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Leonora waits at her window for someone to pass by; finally, a citizen with a face she trusts passes by, and she calls to him. She throws him some money and a letter, asking him to deliver it to Julio.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Leonora, above.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">How tediously I&#8217;ve waited at the window,</line><line form="verse">Yet know not one that passes. Should I trust</line><line form="verse">My letter to a stranger, whom I think</line><line form="verse">To bear an honest face, (in which sometimes</line><line form="verse">We fancy we are wond&#8217;rous skillful) then</line><line form="verse">I might be much deceiv&#8217;d. This late example</line><line form="verse">Of base Henriquez, bleeding in me now,</line><line form="verse">From each good aspect takes away my trust:</line><line form="verse">For his face seem&#8217;d to promise truth and honor.</line><line form="verse">Since nature&#8217;s gifts in noblest forms deceive,</line><line form="verse">Be happy you, that want &#8217;em!&#8212;Here comes one;</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve seen him, though I know him not; he has</line><line form="verse">An honest face too&#8212;that&#8217;s no matter. Sir!&#8212;</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Citizen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">To me?</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">As you were of a virtuous matron born,</line><line form="verse">(There is no doubt, you are) I do conjure you</line><line form="verse">Grant me one boon. Say, do you know me, sir?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">Ay, Leonora, and your worthy father.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">I have not time to press the suit I&#8217;ve to you</line><line form="verse">With many words; nay, I should want the words,</line><line form="verse">Though I had leisure: but for love of justice,</line><line form="verse">And as you pity misery&#8212;but I wander</line><line form="verse">Wide from my subject. Know you Julio, sir?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">Yes, very well; and love him too, as well.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Oh, there an angel spake! Then I conjure you,</line><line form="verse">Convey this paper to him: and believe me,</line><line form="verse">You do heav&#8217;n service in&#8217;t, and shall have cause</line><line form="verse">Not to repent your pains. I know not what</line><line form="verse">Your fortune is;&#8212;pardon me, gentle sir,</line><line form="verse">That I am bold to offer this.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Throws down a purse with money.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir><line form="verse">Leonora.&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">I trust to you; heav&#8217;n put it in your heart</line><line form="verse">To work me some relief.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">Doubt it not, lady. You have mov&#8217;d me so,</line><line form="verse">That though a thousand dangers barr&#8217;d my way,</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;d dare &#8217;em all to serve you.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Citizen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Thanks from a richer hand than mine requite you!</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir><line form="verse">Why, daughter&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">I come:&#8212;Oh, Julio, feel but half my grief,</line><line form="verse"> and thou wilt outfly time to bring relief.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Leonora from the window.</stagedir></scene></act><act num="3"><acttitle>Act 3</acttitle><scene num="1"><scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle><scenelocation>The prospect of a village.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Citizen, Julio)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Julio receives his letter from Leonora, which reveals Henriquez&#8217;s treachery, and works himself into a frenzy until the Citizen succeeds in calming him down. Desperate to see his lady-love, he proposes to borrow some clothes from the Citizen so that he can see Leonora in disguise, and the Citizen agrees to help.</scenedescription>     <stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio with a letter, and citizen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">When from the window she did bow and call,</line><line form="verse">Her passions shook her voice; and from her eyes</line><line form="verse">Mistemper and distraction, with strange wildness</line><line form="verse">Bespoke concern above a common sorrow.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Poor Leonora! Treacherous, damn&#8217;d Henriquez!</line><line form="verse">She bids me fill my memory with her danger;</line><line form="verse">I do, my Leonora; yes, I fill</line><line form="verse">The region of my thought with nothing else;</line><line form="verse">Lower, she tells me here, that this affair</line><line form="verse">Shall yield a testimony of her love:</line><line form="verse">And prays, her letter may come safe and sudden.</line><line form="verse">This pray&#8217;r the heav&#8217;ns have heard, and I beseech &#8217;em,</line><line form="verse">To hear all pray&#8217;rs she makes.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Have patience, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">O my good friend, methinks, I am too patient.</line><line form="verse">Is there a treachery, like this in baseness,</line><line form="verse">Recorded any where? It is the deepest:</line><line form="verse">None but itself can be its parallel:</line><line form="verse">And from a friend, profess&#8217;d! Friendship? Why, &#8217;tis</line><line form="verse">A word forever maim&#8217;d; in human nature</line><line form="verse">It was a thing the noblest; and &#8217;mong beasts,</line><line form="verse">It stood not in mean place: things of fierce nature</line><line form="verse">Hold amity and concordance. Such a villany</line><line form="verse">A writer could not put down in his scene,</line><line form="verse">Without taxation of his auditory</line><line form="verse">For fiction most enormous.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">These upbraidings</line><line form="verse">Cool time, while they are vented.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">I am counsel&#8217;d.</line><line form="verse">For you, evermore, thanks. You&#8217;ve done much for us;</line><line form="verse">So gently press&#8217;d to &#8217;t, that I may persuade me</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;ll do a little more.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Put me t&#8217; employment</line><line form="verse">That&#8217;s honest, though not safe, with my best spirits</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll give&#8217;t accomplishment.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">No more but this;</line><line form="verse">For I must see Leonora: and to appear</line><line form="verse">Like Julio, as I am, might haply spoil</line><line form="verse">Some good event ensuing. Let me crave</line><line form="verse">Th&#8217; exchange of habit with you: some disguise,</line><line form="verse">May bear me to my love, unmark&#8217;d, and secret.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">You shall not want. Yonder&#8217;s the house before us:</line><line form="verse">Make haste to reach it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Still I thank you, sir.</line><line form="verse">O Leonora! Stand but this rude shock;</line><line form="verse">Hold out thy faith against the dread assault</line><line form="verse">Of this base lord, the service of my life</line><line form="verse">Shall be devoted to repay thy constancy.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene><scene num="2"><scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle><scenelocation>Don Bernard&#8217;s house.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Leonora, Julio, Henriquez, Don Bernard, Churchman, Ladies Attending on Leonora)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Leonora has waited for a reply from Julio, but receiving none is frantic, worrying that Julio has given her up to Henriquez. Julio enters in disguise, however, and they reassure each other of their love, though as they hear the musicians tuning for Leonora&#8217;s wedding ceremony they realize there is little time for them to decide what to do. Julio threatens to kill Henriquez, but Leonora points out that this would not improve matters. Julio has no better thoughts, but Leonora has considered matters, and hides him behind a tapestry, warning him not to emerge, no matter what. She threatens to kill herself if he disobeys. The doors open to show the large hall and chapel where the wedding is to take place. Henriquez tells Leonora to cheer up, but she launches into a diatribe against him and fidelity. Don Bernard accuses her of madness. Despite her speech, however, Don Bernard grabs her and forces her to take hands with Henriquez  but at that moment Julio steps out from behind the arras and makes his claim. Henriquez pulls rank, reminding Julio that he was sent to court at his command, and that it is treason for him to return without permission, but Julio replies that the injury Henriquez has done him is stronger than allegiance. Julio attempts to seize Julio, but Henriquez has him thrown out by the servants. Leonora faints, and as the men crowd around her to revive her they find a suicide note she had written in case she needed to kill herself to avoid marrying Henriquez, as well as the dagger with which she planned to do the deed. They have her carried to her chamber, and Henriquez assures Don Benard that with Julio gone, Leonora will soon come around.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Leonora.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve hoped to th&#8217; latest minute hope can give:</line><line form="verse">He will not come: h&#8217;as not receiv&#8217;d my letter:</line><line form="verse">May be, some other view has from our home</line><line form="verse">Repeal&#8217;d his chang&#8217;d eye: for what business can</line><line form="verse">Excuse a tardiness thus willfull? None.</line><line form="verse">Well then, it is not business.&#8212;Oh! That letter,&#8212;</line><line form="verse">I say, is not deliver&#8217;d; or he&#8217;s sick;</line><line form="verse">Or, O suggestion, wherefore wilt thou fright me?</line><line form="verse">Julio does to Henriquez on mere purpose,</line><line form="verse">On plotted purpose, yield me up; and he</line><line form="verse">Hath chose another mistress. All presumptions</line><line form="verse">Make pow&#8217;rful to this point: his own protraction,</line><line form="verse">Henriquez left behind;&#8212;that strain lack&#8217;d jealousy,</line><line form="verse">Therefore lack&#8217;d love. So sure as life shall empty</line><line form="verse">It self in death, this new surmise of mine</line><line form="verse">Is a bold certainty. &#8217;Tis plain, and obvious,</line><line form="verse">Henriquez would not, durst not, thus infringe</line><line form="verse">The law of friendship; thus provoke a man,</line><line form="verse">That bears a sword, and wears his flag of youth</line><line form="verse">As fresh as he: he durst not: &#8217;tis contrivance,</line><line form="verse">Gross-dawbing &#8217;twixt them both. But I&#8217;m o&#8217;erheard.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Going.</stagedir><stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio, disguised.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Stay, Leonora; has this outward veil</line><line form="verse">Quite lost me to thy knowledge?</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">O my Julio!</line><line form="verse">Thy presence ends the stern debate of doubt,</line><line form="verse">And cures me of a thousand heartsick fears,</line><line form="verse">Sprung from thy absence: yet awakes a train</line><line form="verse">Of other sleeping terrors. Do you weep?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">No, Leonora; when I weep, it must be</line><line form="verse">The substance of mine eye. Would I could weep;</line><line form="verse">For then mine eye would drop upon my heart,</line><line form="verse">And &#8217;suage the fire there.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">You are full possess&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">How things go here. First, welcome heartily;</line><line form="verse">Welcome to th&#8217; ending of my last good hour:</line><line form="verse">Now summer bliss and gawdy days are gone,</line><line form="verse">My lease in &#8217;em &#8217;s expir&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Not so, Leonora.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Yes, Julio, yes; an everlasting storm</line><line form="verse">Is come upon me, which I can&#8217;t bear out.</line><line form="verse">I cannot stay much talk; we have lost leisure;</line><line form="verse">And thus it is: your absence hath giv&#8217;n breeding</line><line form="verse">To what my letter hath declar&#8217;d, and is</line><line form="verse">This instant on th&#8217; effecting, hark!</line><stagedir type="action">Flourish within.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="8">The music</line><line form="verse">Is now on tuning, which must celebrate</line><line form="verse">This bus&#8217;ness so discordant. Tell me then,</line><line form="verse">What you will do.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">I know not what: advise me.</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll kill the traitor.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">O! Take heed: his death</line><line form="verse">Betters our cause no whit. No killing, Julio.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">My blood stands still; and all my faculties</line><line form="verse">Are by enchantment dull&#8217;d. You gracious pow&#8217;rs,</line><line form="verse">The guardians of sworn faith, and suff&#8217;ring virtue,</line><line form="verse">Inspire prevention of this dreaded mischief!</line><line form="verse">This moment is our own; let&#8217;s use it, love,</line><line form="verse">And fly o&#8217;th&#8217; instant from this house of woe.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Alas! Impossible: my steps are watch&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">There&#8217;s no escape for me. You must stay too.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">What! Stay, and see thee ravish&#8217;d from my arms?</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll force thy passage. Wear I not a sword?</line><line form="verse">Ne&#8217;er on man&#8217;s thigh rode better. If I suffer</line><line form="verse">The traitor play his part; if I not do</line><line form="verse">Manhood and justice, honor; let me be deem&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">A tame, pale, coward, whom the night owl&#8217;s hoot</line><line form="verse">May turn to aspen leaf: some man take this,</line><line form="verse">Give me a distaff for it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Patience, Julio;</line><line form="verse">And trust to me: I have fore-thought the means</line><line form="verse">To disappoint these nuptials.</line><stagedir type="song">Music within.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="7">Hark! Again;</line><line form="verse">These are the bells knoll for us. See, the lights</line><line form="verse">Move this way, Julio. Quick, behind yon arras,</line><line form="verse">And take thy secret stand. Dispute it not;</line><line form="verse">I have my reasons, you anon shall know them:</line><line form="verse">There you may mark the passages of the night.</line><line form="verse">Yet, more:&#8212;I charge you by the dearest ties,</line><line form="verse">Whate&#8217;er you see, or hear, whate&#8217;er shall hap,</line><line form="verse">In your concealment rest a silent statue.</line><line form="verse">Nay, hide thee straight,&#8212;or, see, I&#8217;m arm&#8217;d and vow</line><stagedir type="action">Shews a dagger.</stagedir><line form="verse">To fall a bleeding sacrifice before thee.</line><stagedir type="action">Thrusts him out, to the arras.</stagedir><line form="verse">I dare not tell thee of my purpose, Julio,</line><line form="verse">Lest it should wrap thee in such agonies,</line><line form="verse">Which my love could not look on.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Scene opens to a large hall: an altar prepared with tapers. Enter at one door servants with lights, Henriquez, Don Bernard, and Churchman. At another, Ladies Attending on Leonora. Henriquez runs to her.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Why, Leonora, wilt thou with this gloom</line><line form="verse">Darken my triumph; suff&#8217;ring discontent,</line><line form="verse">And wan displeasure, to subdue that cheek</line><line form="verse">Where love should sit enthron&#8217;d? Behold your slave;</line><line form="verse">Nay, frown not; for each hour of growing time</line><line form="verse">Shall task me to thy service, &#8217;till by merit</line><line form="verse">Of dearest love I blot the low-born Julio</line><line form="verse">From thy fair mind.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">So I shall make it foul;</line><line form="verse">This counsel is corrupt.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Come, you will change.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Why would you make a wife of such a one,</line><line form="verse">That is so apt to change? This foul proceeding</line><line form="verse">Still speaks against itself, and vilifies</line><line form="verse">The purest of your judgment. For your birth&#8217;s sake</line><line form="verse">I will not dart my hoarded curses at you,</line><line form="verse">Nor give my meanings language: for the love</line><line form="verse">Of all good things together, yet take heed,</line><line form="verse">And spurn the tempter back.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">I think, you&#8217;re mad. Perverse, and foolish, wretch!</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">How may I be obedient, and wise too?</line><line form="verse">Of my obedience, sir, I cannot strip me;</line><line form="verse">Nor can I then be wise: grace against grace!</line><line form="verse">Ungracious, if I not obey a father;</line><line form="verse">Most perjur&#8217;d, if I do. Yet, lord, consider,</line><line form="verse">Or e&#8217;er too late, or e&#8217;er that knot be tied,</line><line form="verse">Which may with violence damnable be broken,</line><line form="verse">No other way dissever&#8217;d: yet consider,</line><line form="verse">You wed my body, not my heart, my lord;</line><line form="verse">No part of my affection. Sounds it well,</line><line form="verse">That Julio&#8217;s love is lord Henriquez&#8217; wife;</line><line form="verse">Have you an ear for this harsh sound?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">No shot of reason can come near the place,</line><line form="verse">Where my love&#8217;s fortified. The day shall come,</line><line form="verse">Wherein you&#8217;ll chide this backwardness, and bless</line><line form="verse">Our fervour in this course.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">No, no, Henriquez,</line><line form="verse">When you shall find what prophet you are prov&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;ll prophesie no more.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Have done this talking,</line><line form="verse">If you will cleave to your obedience, do&#8217;t;</line><line form="verse">If not, unbolt the portal, and be gone;</line><line form="verse">My blessing stay behind you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Sir, your pardon:</line><line form="verse">I will not swerve a hair&#8217;s breadth from my duty;</line><line form="verse">It shall first cost me dear.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Well then, to th&#8217; point:</line><line form="verse">Give me your hand. My honor&#8217;d lord, receive</line><line form="verse">My daughter of me,&#8212;nay, no dragging back,</line><line form="verse">But with my curses; whom I frankly give you,</line><line form="verse">And wish you joy and honor.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">As Don Bernard goes to give Leonora to Henriquez, Julio advances from the arras, and steps between.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Hold, Don Bernard,</line><line form="verse">Mine is the elder claim.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">What are you, sir?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">A wretch, that&#8217;s almost lost to his own knowledge,</line><line form="verse">Struck through with injuries.&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Ha! Julio? Hear you,</line><line form="verse">Were you not sent on our commands to court?</line><line form="verse">Order&#8217;d to wait your fair dismission thence?</line><line form="verse">And have you dared, knowing you are our vassal,</line><line form="verse">To steal away unpriviledg&#8217;d, and leave</line><line form="verse">My business and your duty unaccomplish&#8217;d?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Ungen&#8217;rous lord! The circumstance of things</line><line form="verse">Should stop the tongue of question. You have wrong&#8217;d me;</line><line form="verse">Wrong&#8217;d me so basely, in so dear a point,</line><line form="verse">As stains the cheek of honor with a blush;</line><line form="verse">Cancells the bonds of service; bids allegiance</line><line form="verse">Throw to the wind all high respects of birth,</line><line form="verse">Title, and eminence; and, in their stead,</line><line form="verse">Fills up the panting heart with just defiance.</line><line form="verse">If you have sense of shame, or justice, lord,</line><line form="verse">Forego this bad intent; or with your sword</line><line form="verse">Answer me like a man, and I shall thank you.</line><line form="verse">Julio once dead, Leonora may be thine;</line><line form="verse">But, living, she&#8217;s a prize too rich to part with.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Vain man! The present hour is fraught with business</line><line form="verse">Of richer moment. Love shall first be serv&#8217;d:</line><line form="verse">Then, if your courage hold to claim it of me,</line><line form="verse">I may have leisure to chastise this boldness.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Nay, then I&#8217;ll seize my right.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">What, here, a brawl?</line><line form="verse">My servants,&#8212;turn this boist&#8217;rous sworder forth;</line><line form="verse">And see he come not to disturb our joys.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Hold, dogs!&#8212;Leonora,&#8212;coward, base, Henriquez!</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Julio is seized, and dragged out by the servants.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">She dies upon me; help!</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Leonora swoons; as they endeavour to recover her, a paper drops from her.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Throng not about her;</line><line form="verse">But give her air.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">What paper&#8217;s that? Let&#8217;s see it.</line><line form="verse">It is her own handwriting.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Bow her head:</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis but her fright; she will recover soon.</line><line form="verse">What learn you by that paper, good my lord?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">That she would do the violence to herself,</line><line form="verse">Which nature hath anticipated on her.</line><line form="verse">What dagger means she? Search her well, I pray you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">Here is the dagger.&#8212;Oh, the stubborn sex,</line><line form="verse">Rash ev&#8217;n to madness!</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Bear her to her chamber:</line><line form="verse">Life flows in her again.&#8212;Pray, bear her hence:</line><line form="verse">And tend her, as you would the world&#8217;s best treasure.</line><stagedir type="action">Women carry Leonora off.</stagedir><line form="verse">Don Bernard, this wild tumult soon will cease,</line><line form="verse">The cause remov&#8217;d; and all return to calmness.</line><line form="verse">Passions in women are as short in working,</line><line form="verse">As strong in their effect. Let the priest wait:</line><line form="verse">Come, go we in: my soul is all on fire;</line><line form="verse">And burns impatient of this forc&#8217;d delay.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt; and the scene closes.</stagedir></scene><scene num="3"><scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle><scenelocation>Prospect of a village at a distance.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Roderick, Camillo, Violante, Citizen, Don Bernard, Servant)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Roderick is concerned about things, considering that Julio has left court in secret and Roderick knows that he was friendly with Henriquez. He goes to find Camillo in the hopes of discovering what&#8217;s going on. Camillo, however, accuses him of colluding with Henriquez in stealing Leonora from Julio. Roderick insists he knew nothing of all this. Violante comes by and hides to listen to the conversation between the two men. She hears Camillo admit amazement that anyone related to Henriquez should be an honest man and Roderick disclaim his brotherhood. A Citizen arrives to inform them that Julio has left town, apparently insane. Don Bernard arrives as well, distraught over how things have turned out, and Camillo threatens him with his sword. Roderick steps between them, arguing that they have both lost children and therefore should be reconciled by their losses. They agree, and Roderick suggests that they spread out to find those who are missing. They do so. Violante comments on the difference between Roderick and his brother, but finds new hope in her despair: Henriquez is not yet married, and hence all is not yet lost for her. She resolves to follow Henriquez and shame him into marrying her, thus restoring her honor. A faithful servant comes to warn her that her father is having her searched for; she tests his honesty and trustworthiness, and asks him to procure her a shepherd&#8217;s clothes.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Roderick.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Julio&#8217;s departure thus in secret from me,</line><line form="verse">With the long doubtful absence of my brother,</line><line form="verse">(Who cannot suffer, but my father feels it)</line><line form="verse">Have trusted me with strong suspicions,</line><line form="verse">And dreams, that will not let me sleep, nor eat,</line><line form="verse">Nor taste those recreations health demands:</line><line form="verse">But, like a whirlwind, hither have they snatch&#8217;d me,</line><line form="verse">Perforce, to be resolv&#8217;d. I know my brother</line><line form="verse">Had Julio&#8217;s father for his host: from him</line><line form="verse">Enquiry may befriend me.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter Camillo.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="6">Old sir, I&#8217;m glad</line><line form="verse">To &#8217;ve met you thus. What ails the man? Camillo,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Ha?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Is&#8217;t possible, you should forget your friends?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Friends! What are those?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Why, those that love you, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">You&#8217;re none of those, sure, if you be lord Roderick.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Yes, I am that lord Roderick, and I lie not,</line><line form="verse">If I protest, I love you passing well.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">You lov&#8217;d my son too passing well, I take it:</line><line form="verse">One, that believ&#8217;d too suddenly his court-creed.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">All is not well.</line><line form="verse" offset="4">&#8212;Good old man, do not rail.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">My lord, my lord, you&#8217;ve dealt dishonorably.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Good sir, I am so far from doing wrongs</line><line form="verse">Of that base strain, I understand you not.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Indeed! You know not neither, o&#8217; my conscience,</line><line form="verse">How your most virtuous brother, noble Henriquez,</line><line form="verse">(You look so like him, lord, you are the worse for&#8217;t;</line><line form="verse">Rots upon such dissemblers!) under color</line><line form="verse">Of buying coursers, and I know not what,</line><line form="verse">Bought my poor boy out of possession</line><line form="verse">Ev&#8217;n of his plighted faith. Was not this honor?</line><line form="verse">And this a constant friend?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">I dare not say so.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Now you have robb&#8217;d him of his love, take all;</line><line form="verse">Make up your malice, and dispatch his life too.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">If you would hear me, sir,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Your brave old father</line><line form="verse">Would have been torn in pieces with wild horses,</line><line form="verse">E&#8217;er he had done this treachery. On my conscience,</line><line form="verse">Had he but dreamt you two durst have committed</line><line form="verse">This base, unmanly crime,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Why, this is madness.&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve done; I&#8217;ve eas&#8217;d my heart; now you may talk.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Then as I am a gentleman, believe me,</line><line form="verse">(For I will lie for no man) I&#8217;m so far</line><line form="verse">From being guilty of the least suspicion</line><line form="verse">Of sin that way, that fearing the long absence</line><line form="verse">Of Julio and my brother might beget</line><line form="verse">Something to start at, hither have I travell&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">To know the truth of you.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Violante behind.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">My servant loiters; sure, he means me well.</line><line form="verse">Camillo, and a stranger? These may give me</line><line form="verse">Some comfort from their talk. I&#8217;ll step aside:</line><line form="verse">And hear what fame is stirring.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Violante retires.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Why this wond&#8217;ring?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Can there be one so near in blood as you are</line><line form="verse">To that Henriquez, and an honest man?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">While he was good, I do confess my nearness;</line><line form="verse">But, since his fall from honor, he&#8217;s to me</line><line form="verse">As a strange face I saw but yesterday,</line><line form="verse">And as soon lost.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">I ask your pardon, lord;</line><line form="verse">I was too rash and bold.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">No harm done, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">But is it possible, you should not hear</line><line form="verse">The passage &#8217;twixt Leonora and your brother?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">None of all this.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter a Citizen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">How now?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">I bear you tidings, sir, which I could wish</line><line form="verse">Some other tongue deliver&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Whence, I pray you?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">From your son, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Prithee, where is he?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CITIZ.</speaker><line form="verse">That&#8217;s more than I know now, sir.</line><line form="verse">But this I can assure you, he has left</line><line form="verse">The city raging mad; heav&#8217;n comfort him!</line><line form="verse">He came to that curst marriage&#8212;the fiends take it!</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Prithee, be gone, and bid the bell knoll for me:</line><line form="verse">I have had one foot in the grave some time.</line><line form="verse">Nay, go, good friend; thy news deserve no thanks.</line><line form="verse">How does your lordship?</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Citizen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">That&#8217;s well said, old man.</line><line form="verse">I hope, all shall be well yet.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">It had need;</line><line form="verse">For &#8217;tis a crooked world. Farewell, poor boy!</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Don Bernard.</stagedir><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">This comes of forcing women where they hate:</line><line form="verse">It was my own sin; and I am rewarded.</line><line form="verse">Now I am like an aged oak, alone,</line><line form="verse">Left for all tempests. I would cry, but cannot:</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;m dried to death almost with these vexations.</line><line form="verse">Lord! What a heavy load I have within me!</line><line form="verse">My heart,&#8212;my heart,&#8212;my heart&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Has this ill weather</line><line form="verse">Met with thee too?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line offest="4">O wench, that I were with thee!</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">You do not come to mock at me now?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Ha?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Do not dissemble; thou may&#8217;st find a knave</line><line form="verse">As bad as thou art, to undo thee too:</line><line form="verse">I hope to see that day before I die yet.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">It needeth not, Camillo; I am knave</line><line form="verse">Sufficient to myself. If thou wilt rail,</line><line form="verse">Do it as bitterly as thou canst think of;</line><line form="verse">For I deserve it. Draw thy sword, and strike me;</line><line form="verse">And I will thank thee for&#8217;t. I&#8217;ve lost my daughter;</line><line form="verse">She&#8217;s stol&#8217;n away; and whither gone, I know not.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">She has a fair blessing in being from you, sir.</line><line form="verse">I was too poor a brother for your greatness;</line><line form="verse">You must be grafted into noble stocks,</line><line form="verse">And have your titles rais&#8217;d. My state was laugh&#8217;d at:</line><line form="verse">And my alliance scorn&#8217;d. I&#8217;ve lost a son too;</line><line form="verse">Which must not be put up so.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Offers to draw.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Hold; be counsel&#8217;d.</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;ve equal losses; urge no farther anger.</line><line form="verse">Heav&#8217;n, pleas&#8217;d now at your love, may bring again,</line><line form="verse">And, no doubt, will, your children to your comforts:</line><line form="verse">In which adventure my foot shall be foremost.</line><line form="verse">And one more will I add, my honor&#8217;d father;</line><line form="verse">Who has a son to grieve for too, though tainted.</line><line form="verse">Let your joint sorrow be as balm to heal</line><line form="verse">These wounds of adverse fortune.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Come, Camillo,</line><line form="verse">Do not deny your love, for charity;</line><line form="verse">I ask it of you. Let this noble lord</line><line form="verse">Make brothers of us, whom our own cross fates</line><line form="verse">Could never join. What I have been, forget;</line><line form="verse">What I intend to be, believe and nourish:</line><line form="verse">I do confess my wrongs; give me your hand.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Heav&#8217;n make thee honest&#8212;there.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">&#8217;Tis done like good men.</line><line form="verse">Now there rests nought, but that we part, and each</line><line form="verse">Take sev&#8217;ral ways in quest of our lost friends:</line><line form="verse">Some of my train o&#8217;er the wild rocks shall wait you.</line><line form="verse">Our best search ended, here we&#8217;ll meet again,</line><line form="verse">And tell the fortunes of our separate travels.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir><stagedir type="action">Violante comes forward.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">I would, your brother had but half your virtue!</line><line form="verse">Yet there remains a little spark of hope</line><line form="verse">That lights me to some comfort. The match is cross&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">The parties separate; and I again</line><line form="verse">May come to see this man that has betray&#8217;d me;</line><line form="verse">And wound his conscience for it: home again</line><line form="verse">I will not go, whatever fortune guides me;</line><line form="verse">Though ev&#8217;ry step I went, I trod upon</line><line form="verse">Dangers as fearful and as pale as death.</line><line form="verse">No, no, Henriquez; I will follow thee</line><line form="verse">Where there is day. Time may beget a wonder.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter a servant.</stagedir><line form="verse">O, are you come? What news?</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="prose">None, but the worst. Your father makes mighty offers yonder by a cryer, to any one can bring you home again.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="prose">Art thou corrupted?</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="prose">No.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="prose">Wilt thou be honest?</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="prose">I hope, you do not fear me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Indeed, I do not. Thou hast an honest face;</line><line form="verse">And such a face, when it deceives, take heed,</line><line form="verse">Is curst of all heav&#8217;n&#8217;s creatures.</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">I&#8217;ll hang first.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Heav&#8217;n bless thee from that end! I&#8217;ve heard a man</line><line form="verse">Say more than this; and yet that man was false.</line><line form="verse">Thou&#8217;lt not be so, I hope.</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">By my life, mistress,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Swear not; I credit thee. But prithee though,</line><line form="verse">Take heed, thou dost not fail: I do not doubt thee:</line><line form="verse">Yet I have trusted such a serious face,</line><line form="verse">And been abused too.</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">If I fail your trust,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">I do thee wrong to hold thy honesty</line><line form="verse">At distance thus: thou shalt know all my fortunes.</line><line form="verse">Get me a shepherd&#8217;s habit.</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Well; what else?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">And wait me in the evening, where I told thee;</line><line form="verse">There thou shalt know my farther ends. Take heed&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>SERV.</speaker><line form="verse">D&#8217;ye fear me still?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">No; this is only counsel:</line><line form="verse">My life and death I have put equally</line><line form="verse">Into thy hand: let not rewards, nor hopes,</line><line form="verse">Be cast into the scale to turn thy faith.</line><line form="verse">Be honest but for virtue&#8217;s sake, that&#8217;s all;</line><line form="verse">He, that has such a treasure, cannot fall.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene></act><act num="4"><acttitle>Act 4</acttitle><scene num="1"><scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle><scenelocation>A wide plain, with a prospect of mountains in the distance.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(First Shepherd, Second Shepherd, Master of the Flocks, Julio, Violante, Roderick, Henriquez)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>The Master of the Flocks and two shepherds discuss the madman who has recently come to live nearby them, mentioning his apparent love of music. The madman enters and turns out to be Julio, ranting about treachery. The shepherds send the Master&#8217;s boy, who is actually Violante in disguise, to talk to Julio in the hopes of finding out more about what brought him here. Julio almost notices that the shepherd boy is a woman, along with guessing that &#8220;he&#8221; has suffered in love, and counsels Violante to kill herself. The shepherds grab him to stop him harming anyone, but he fights them off, thinking one of them is Henriquez. Julio goes off, cursing Henriquez, and the injured shepherds go off to a tavern. The Master of the Flocks pans to meet them there, but first, having guessed that Violante is a woman, decides to have his way with her. She pleads with him, but he has no patience for that. Just as he is about to rape her, Roderick interrupts and she manages to escape. Roderick asks the Master some questions, but the curmudgeonly fellow refuses even to tell him the way. The nobleman is shocked at this lack of manners. It turns out that he is in the area looking for his brother, who is in the area because Leonora has cloistered herself in a nunnery nearby. Henriquez finds his brother, and insists that he must have the lady, and abduct her from the nunnery; Roderick agrees to help if only to try and make Henriquez behave honorably. He comes up with the plan of pretending to be carrying a body to burial and asking to spend the night at the nunnery, thus gaining access to Leonora. Roderick insists that she is to be treated honorably, and Henriquez agrees.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Master of the Flocks, three or four Shepherds, and Violante in boy&#8217;s clothes.</stagedir><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Well, he&#8217;s as sweet a man, heav&#8217;n comfort him! As ever these eyes look&#8217;d on.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">If he have a mother, I believe, neighbors, she&#8217;s a woe-woman for him at this hour.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">Why should he haunt these wild unpeopled mountains,</line><line form="verse">Where nothing dwells but hunger, and sharp winds?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">His melancholy, sir, that&#8217;s the main devil does it. Go to, I fear he has had too much foul play offer&#8217;d him.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">How gets he meat?</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Why, now and then he takes our victuals from us, though we desire him to eat; and instead of a short grace, beats us well and soundly, and then falls to.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">Where lies he?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Ev&#8217;n where the night o&#8217;ertakes him.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Now will I be hang&#8217;d, an&#8217; some fair-snouted skittish woman, or other, be not at the end of this madness.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Well, if he lodg&#8217;d within the sound of us, I knew our music would allure him. How attentively he stood, and how he fix&#8217;d his eyes, when your boy sung his love-ditty. Oh, here he comes again.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">Let him alone; he wonders strangely at us.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Not a word, sirs, to cross him, as you love your shoulders.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">He seems much disturb&#8217;d: I believe the mad fit is upon him.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Horsemanship!&#8212;Hell&#8212;Riding shall be abolish&#8217;d:</line><line form="verse">Turn the barb&#8217;d steed loose to his native wildness;</line><line form="verse">It is a beast too noble to be made</line><line form="verse">The property of man&#8217;s baseness. What a letter</line><line form="verse">Wrote he to&#8217;s brother? What a man was I?</line><line form="verse">Why, Perseus did not know his seat like me;</line><line form="verse">The Parthian, that rides swift without the rein,</line><line form="verse">Match&#8217;d not my grace and firmness. Shall this lord</line><line form="verse">Die, when men pray for him? Think you &#8217;tis meet?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">I don&#8217;t know what to say: neither I, nor all the confessors in Spain, can unriddle this wild stuff.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I must to court! Be usher&#8217;d into grace,</line><line form="verse">By a large list of praises ready penn&#8217;d!</line><line form="verse">O devil! What a venomous world is this,</line><line form="verse">When commendations are the baits to ruin!</line><line form="verse">All these good words were gyves and fetters, sir,</line><line form="verse">To keep me bolted there: while the false sender</line><line form="verse">Play&#8217;d out the game of treach&#8217;ry.&#8212;Hold; come hither;</line><line form="verse">You have an aspect, sir, of wond&#8217;rous wisdom,</line><line form="verse">And, as it seems, are travell&#8217;d deep in knowledge;</line><line form="verse">Have you e&#8217;er seen the Phoenix of the Earth,</line><line form="verse">The Bird of Paradise?</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">In troth, not I, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I have; and known her haunts, and where she built</line><line form="verse">Her spicy nest: &#8217;till, like a credulous fool,</line><line form="verse">I shew&#8217;d the treasure to a friend in trust,</line><line form="verse">And he hath robb&#8217;d me of her.&#8212;Trust no friend:</line><line form="verse">Keep thy heart&#8217;s counsels close.&#8212;Hast thou a mistress?</line><line form="verse">Give her not out in words; nor let thy pride</line><line form="verse">Be wanton to display her charms to view;</line><line form="verse">Love is contagious: and a breath of praise,</line><line form="verse">Or a slight glance, has kindled up its flame,</line><line form="verse">And turn&#8217;d a friend a traitor. &#8217;Tis in proof;</line><line form="verse">And it has hurt my brain.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Marry, now there is some moral in his madness, and we may profit by it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">See, he grows cool, and pensive.</line><line form="verse">Go towards him, boy, but do not look that way.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Alas! I tremble&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Oh, my pretty youth!</line><line form="verse">Come hither, child; did not your song imply</line><line form="verse">Something of love?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Ha&#8212;ha&#8212;goes it there? Now if the boy be witty, we shall trace something.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Yes, sir, it was the subject.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Sit here then: come, shake not, good pretty soul,</line><line form="verse">Nor do not fear me; I&#8217;ll not do thee wrong.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Why do you look so on me?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">I have reasons.</line><line form="verse">It puzzles my philosophy, to think</line><line form="verse">That the rude blast, hot sun, and dashing rains</line><line form="verse">Have made no fiercer war upon thy youth;</line><line form="verse">Nor hurt the bloom of that vermilion cheek.</line><line form="verse">You weep too, do you not?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Sometimes, I do.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I weep sometimes too. You&#8217;re extremely young.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Indeed, I&#8217;ve seen more sorrows far than years.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Yet all these have not broken your complexion.</line><line form="verse">You have a strong heart, and you are the happier.</line><line form="verse">I warrant, you&#8217;re a very loving woman.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">A woman, sir?</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="4">I fear, h&#8217;as found me out.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="verse">He takes the boy for a woman. Mad, again!</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">You&#8217;ve met some disappointment; some foul play</line><line form="verse">Has cross&#8217;d your love. I read it in your face.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">You read a truth then.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Where can lie the fault?</line><line form="verse">Is&#8217;t in the man, or some dissembling knave,</line><line form="verse">He put in trust? Ho! Have I hit the cause?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">You&#8217;re not far off.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">This world is full of coz&#8217;ners, very full;</line><line form="verse">Young virgins must be wary in their ways.</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve known a Duke&#8217;s son do as great a knavery.</line><line form="verse">Will you be rul&#8217;d by me?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Yes.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="8">Kill yourself.</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Twill be a terror to the villain&#8217;s conscience,</line><line form="verse">The longest day he lives.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">By no means. What?</line><line form="verse">Commit self-murder!</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Yes; I&#8217;ll have it so.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">I fear, his fit is returning. Take heed of all hands. &#8212;Sir,&#8212;do you want any thing?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Thou liest; thou can&#8217;st not hurt me: I am proof</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Gainst farther wrongs. Steal close behind me, lady.</line><line form="verse">I will avenge thee.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">Thank the heav&#8217;ns, I&#8217;m free.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">O treach&#8217;rous, base Henriquez! Have I caught thee?</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="verse">Help! Help! Good neighbors; he will kill me else.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Julio seizes on the Shepherd.</stagedir><stagedir type="exit">Violante runs out.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Here thou shalt pay thy heart-blood for the wrongs</line><line form="verse">Thou&#8217;st heap&#8217;d upon this head. Faith-breaker! Villain!</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll suck thy life-blood.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="verse">Good sir, have patience; this is no Henriquez.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">They rescue the Shepherd.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Well; let him slink to court, and hide a coward;</line><line form="verse">Not all his father&#8217;s guards shall shield him there.</line><line form="verse">Or if he prove too strong for mortal arm,</line><line form="verse">I will sollicit ev&#8217;ry saint in heav&#8217;n</line><line form="verse">To lend me vengeance.&#8212;I&#8217;ll about it straight.&#8212;</line><line form="verse">The wrathful elements shall wage this war;</line><line form="verse">Furies shall haunt him; vultures gnaw his heart;</line><line form="verse">And nature pour forth all her stores of plagues,</line><line form="verse">To join in punishment of trust betray&#8217;d.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Julio.</stagedir><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Go thy ways, and a vengeance go with thee!&#8212;Pray, feel my nose; is it fast, neighbors?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">&#8217;Tis as well as may be.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">He pull&#8217;d at it, as he would have drag&#8217;d a bullock backward by the tail. An&#8217;t had been some men&#8217;s nose that I know, neighbors, who knows where it had been now? He has given me such a devilish dash o&#8217;er the mouth, that I feel, I shall never whistle to my sheep again. Then they&#8217;ll make holiday.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="prose">Come, shall we go? For, I fear, if the youth return, our second course will be much more against our stomachs.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">Walk you afore; I will but give my boy</line><line form="verse">Some short instructions, and I&#8217;ll follow straight.</line><line form="verse">We&#8217;ll crash a cup together.</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. SHEP.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Pray, do not linger.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">I will not, sirs;&#8212;this must not be a boy;</line><line form="verse">His voice, mein, gesture, ev&#8217;rything he does,</line><line form="verse">Savour of soft and female delicacy.</line><line form="verse">He but puts on this seeming, and his garb</line><line form="verse">Speaks him of such a rank, as well persuades me,</line><line form="verse">He plays the swain, rather to cloak some purpose,</line><line form="verse">Than forced to&#8217;t by a need: I&#8217;ve waited long</line><line form="verse">To mark the end he has in his disguise;</line><line form="verse">But am not perfect in&#8217;t. The madman&#8217;s coil</line><line form="verse">Has driv&#8217;n him shaking hence. These fears betray him.</line><line form="verse">If he prove right, I&#8217;m happy. O, he&#8217;s here.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter Violante.</stagedir><line form="prose">Come hither, boy; where did you leave the flock, child?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="prose">Grazing below, sir.&#8212;What does he mean, to stroke one o&#8217;the cheek so? I hope, I&#8217;m not betray&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">Have you learnt the whistle yet, and when to fold?</line><line form="verse">And how to make the dog bring in the strayers?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Time, sir, will furnish me with all these rules;</line><line form="verse">My will is able, but my knowledge weak, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">That&#8217;s a good child: why dost thou blush, my boy?</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis certainly a woman.</line><line form="verse" offset="7">Speak, my boy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Heav&#8217;n! How I tremble.&#8212;&#8217;Tis unusual to me</line><line form="verse">To find such kindness at a master&#8217;s hand,</line><line form="verse">That am a poor boy, ev&#8217;ry way unable,</line><line form="verse">Unless it be in pray&#8217;rs to merit it.</line><line form="verse">Besides, I&#8217;ve often heard old people say,</line><line form="verse">Too much indulgence makes boys rude and saucy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">Are you so cunning!</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="6">How his eyes shake fire,</line><line form="verse">And measure ev&#8217;ry piece of youth about me!</line><stagedir type="speak">To the Master.</stagedir><line form="verse">The ewes want water, sir: shall I go drive &#8217;em</line><line form="verse">Down to the cisterns? Shall I make haste, sir?</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">Would I were five miles from him&#8212;how he gripes me!</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">Come, come, all this is not sufficient, child,</line><line form="verse">To make a fool of me. This is a fine hand,</line><line form="verse">A delicate fine hand,&#8212;never change color;</line><line form="verse">You understand me,&#8212;and a woman&#8217;s hand.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">You&#8217;re strangely out: yet if I were a woman,</line><line form="verse">I know, you are so honest and so good,</line><line form="verse">That though I wore disguises for some ends,</line><line form="verse">You would not wrong me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Come, you&#8217;re made for love;</line><line form="verse">Will you comply? I&#8217;m madder with this talk.</line><line form="verse">There&#8217;s nothing you can say, can take my edge off.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Oh, do but quench these foul affections in you,</line><line form="verse">That, like base thieves, have rob&#8217;d you of your reason,</line><line form="verse">And I will be a woman; and begin</line><line form="verse">So sad a story, that if there be aught</line><line form="verse">Of humane in you, or a soul that&#8217;s gentle,</line><line form="verse">You cannot choose but pity my lost youth.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">No stories now.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">Kill me directly, sir;</line><line form="verse">As you have any goodness, take my life.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir><line form="verse">Hoa! Shepherd, will you hear, sir?</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="verse">What bawling rogue is that, i&#8217;th&#8217; devil&#8217;s name?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Blessings upon him, whatsoe&#8217;er he be!</line></speech><stagedir type="exit" actor="VIOL.">Runs out.</stagedir><stagedir type="enter">Enter Roderick.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="prose">Good even, my friend; I thought, you all had been asleep in this country.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">You had lied then; for you were waking, when you thought so.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="prose">I thank you, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">I pray, be cover&#8217;d; &#8217;tis not so much worth, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="prose">Was that thy boy ran crying?</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">Yes; what then?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="prose">Why dost thou beat him so?</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">To make him grow.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="prose">A pretty med&#8217;cine! Thou can&#8217;st not tell me the way to the next nunnery?</line></speech><speech><speaker>MAST.</speaker><line form="prose">How do you know that?&#8212;Yes, I can tell you; but the question is, whether I will or no; and, indeed, I will not. Fare you well.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Master.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">What a brute fellow&#8217;s this! Are they all thus?</line><line form="verse">My brother Henriquez tells me by his letters,</line><line form="verse">The mistress of his soul not far from hence</line><line form="verse">Hath taken sanctuary: from which he prays</line><line form="verse">My aid to bring her back.&#8212;From what Camillo</line><line form="verse">Hinted, I wear some doubts.&#8212;Here &#8217;tis appointed</line><line form="verse">That we should meet; it must be here; &#8217;tis so.</line><line form="verse">He comes.</line><stagedir type="enter">Enter Henriquez.</stagedir><line form="verse">Now, brother, what&#8217;s this post-haste business</line><line form="verse">You hurry me about?&#8212;Some wenching matter&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">My letter told you, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis true, it tells me, that you&#8217;ve lost a mistress</line><line form="verse">Whom your heart bleeds for; but the means to win her</line><line form="verse">From her close life, I take it, is not mention&#8217;d.</line><line form="verse">You&#8217;re ever in these troubles.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Noble brother,</line><line form="verse">I own, I have too freely giv&#8217;n a scope</line><line form="verse">To youth&#8217;s intemp&#8217;rate heat, and rash desires:</line><line form="verse">But think not, that I would engage your virtues</line><line form="verse">To any cause, wherein my constant heart</line><line form="verse">Attended not my eye. &#8217;Till now my passions</line><line form="verse">Reign&#8217;d in my blood; ne&#8217;er pierc&#8217;d into my mind;</line><line form="verse">But I&#8217;m a convert grown to purest thoughts:</line><line form="verse">And must in anguish spend my days to come,</line><line form="verse">If I possess not her: so much I love.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">The means? She&#8217;s in a cloister, is she not?</line><line form="verse">Within whose walls to enter as we are,</line><line form="verse">Will never be: few men, but friars, come there;</line><line form="verse">Which we shall never make.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">If that would do it,</line><line form="verse">I would make anything.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Are you so hot?</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll serve him, be it but to save his honor.</line><line form="verse">To feign a corpse&#8212;By th&#8217; mass, it shall be so.</line><line form="verse">We must pretend, we do transport a body</line><line form="verse">As &#8217;twere to&#8217;s funeral: and coming late by,</line><line form="verse">Crave a night&#8217;s leave to rest the herse i&#8217;th&#8217; convent.</line><line form="verse">That be our course; for to such charity</line><line form="verse">Strict zeal and custom of the house give way.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">And, opportune, a vacant herse pass&#8217;d by</line><line form="verse">From rites but new perform&#8217;d: this for a price</line><line form="verse">We&#8217;ll hire, to put our scheme in act. Ho! Gerald&#8212;</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Gerald, whom Henriquez whispers; then Gerald goes out.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">When we&#8217;re once lodg&#8217;d, the means of her conveyance,</line><line form="verse">By safe and secret force, with ease we&#8217;ll compass</line><line form="verse">But, brother, know my terms. If that your mistress</line><line form="verse">Will to the world come back, and she appear</line><line form="verse">An object worthy in our father&#8217;s eye,</line><line form="verse">Woo her, and win her; but if his consent</line><line form="verse">Keep not pace with your purpose&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="8">Doubt it not.</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve look&#8217;d not with a common eye; but chose</line><line form="verse">A noble virgin, who to make her so,</line><line form="verse">Has all the gifts of heav&#8217;n and earth upon her.</line><line form="verse">If ever woman yet could be an angel,</line><line form="verse">She is the nearest.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Well; a lover&#8217;s praise</line><line form="verse">Feasts not a common ear.&#8212;Now to our plot;</line><line form="verse">We shall bring night in with us.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene><scene num="2"><scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle><scenelocation>The prospect of the mountains.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Julio, Two Gentlemen, Violante)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Two gentlemen try to convince Julio that he would be better off if he left the wildness. They hear Violante playing the lute and singing sad love songs. Julio remarks that he often hears her, and that the music brings peace to his soul. Violante comes in, commenting to herself on how preferable nature is to the court. She reflects painfully on her past, leaving Julio deeply sorry for her. She cries out against Henriquez and pities herself by name, and Julio recognizes her. He goes to her, and they decide to go together to a cave to mutually mope.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio, and two Gentlemen.</stagedir><speech><speaker>1. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">Good sir, compose yourself.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">O Leonora,</line><line form="verse">That heav&#8217;n had made thee stronger than a woman,</line><line form="verse">How happy had I been!</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">He&#8217;s calm again:</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll take this interval to work upon him.</line><line form="verse">These wild and solitary places, sir,</line><line form="verse">But feed your pain; let better reason guide you;</line><line form="verse">And quit this forlorn state, that yields no comfort.</line></speech><stagedir type="song">Lute sounds within.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Ha! Hark, a sound from heav&#8217;n! Do you hear nothing?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">Yes, sir; the touch of some sweet instrument:</line><line form="verse">Here&#8217;s no inhabitant.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">No, no, the better.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">This is a strange place to hear music in.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I&#8217;m often visited with these sweet airs.</line><line form="verse">The spirit of some hapless man that died,</line><line form="verse">And left his love hid in a faithless woman,</line><line form="verse">Sure haunts these mountains.</line><stagedir type="song" actor="VIOL.">Violante sings within.</stagedir><line type="lyric">Fond echo! Forego thy light strain,</line><line type="lyric">And heedfully hear a lost maid;</line><line type="lyric">Go, tell the false ear of the swain</line><line type="lyric">How deeply his vows have betray&#8217;d.</line><line type="lyric">Go, tell him, what sorrows I bear;</line><line type="lyric">See, yet if his heart feel my woe:</line><line type="lyric">&#8217;Tis now he must heal my despair,</line><line type="lyric">Or death will make pity too slow.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">See, how his soul strives in him! This sad strain</line><line form="verse">Has search&#8217;d him to the heart.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Excellent sorrow!</line><line form="verse">You never lov&#8217;d?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">No.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Peace; and learn to grieve then.</line><stagedir type="song" actor="VIOL.">Violante sings within.</stagedir><line type="lyric">Go, tell him, what sorrows I bear;</line><line type="lyric">See, yet if his heart feel my woe:</line><line type="lyric">&#8217;Tis now he must heal my despair,</line><line type="lyric">Or death will make pity too slow.</line><line form="verse">Is not this heav&#8217;nly?</line></speech><speech><speaker>1. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">I never heard the like, sir.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll tell you, my good friends; but pray, say nothing;</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;m strangely touch&#8217;d with this. The heav&#8217;nly sound</line><line form="verse">Diffuses a sweet peace through all my soul.</line><line form="verse">But yet I wonder, what new, sad, companion</line><line form="verse">Grief has brought hither to out-bid my sorrows.</line><line form="verse">Stand off, stand off, stand off&#8212;Friends, it appears.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Violante.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">How much more grateful are these craggy mountains,</line><line form="verse">And these wild trees, than things of nobler natures;</line><line form="verse">For these receive my plaints, and mourn again</line><line form="verse">In many echoes to me. All good people</line><line form="verse">Are fall&#8217;n asleep forever. None are left,</line><line form="verse">That have the sense, and touch of tenderness</line><line form="verse">For virtue&#8217;s sake: no, scarce their memory:</line><line form="verse">From whom I may expect counsel in fears,</line><line form="verse">Ease to complainings, or redress of wrongs.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">This is a moving sorrow, but say nothing.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">What dangers have I run, and to what insults</line><line form="verse">Expos&#8217;d this ruin of myself? Oh! Mischief</line><line form="verse">On that soul-spotted hind, my vicious master!</line><line form="verse">Who would have thought, that such poor worms as they,</line><line form="verse">(Whose best feed is coarse bread; whose bev&#8217;rage, water)</line><line form="verse">Should have so much rank blood? I shake all over,</line><line form="verse">And blush to think what had become of me,</line><line form="verse">If that good man had not reliev&#8217;d me from him.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Since she is not Leonora, she is heav&#8217;nly.</line><line form="verse">When she speaks next, listen as seriously,</line><line form="verse">As women do that have their loves at sea,</line><line form="verse">What wind blows ev&#8217;ry morning.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">I cannot get this false man&#8217;s memory</line><line form="verse">Out of my mind. You maidens, that shall live</line><line form="verse">To hear my mournful tale, when I am ashes,</line><line form="verse">Be wise; and to an oath no more give credit,</line><line form="verse">To tears, to vows, (false both!) or any thing</line><line form="verse">A man shall promise, than to clouds, that now</line><line form="verse">Bear such a pleasing shape, and now are nothing.</line><line form="verse">For they will cozen, (if they may be cozen&#8217;d,)</line><line form="verse">The very gods they worship. Valour, justice,</line><line form="verse">Discretion, honesty, and all they covet,</line><line form="verse">To make them seeming saints, are but the wiles</line><line form="verse">By which these syrens lure us to destruction.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Do not you weep now? I could drop myself</line><line form="verse">Into a fountain for her.</line></speech><speech><speaker>2. GENT.</speaker><line form="verse">She weeps extremely.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Let her weep; &#8217;tis well:</line><line form="verse">Her heart will break else. Great sorrows live in tears.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">O false Henriquez!&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Ha!</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">And oh, thou fool,</line><line form="verse">Forsaken Violante! Whose belief</line><line form="verse">And childish love have made thee so&#8212;go, die;</line><line form="verse">For there is nothing left thee now to look for,</line><line form="verse">That can bring comfort, but a quiet grave.</line><line form="verse">There all the miseries I long have felt,</line><line form="verse">And those to come, shall sweetly sleep together.</line><line form="verse">Fortune may guide that false Henriquez hither,</line><line form="verse">To weep repentance o&#8217;er my pale, dead coarse,</line><line form="verse">And cheer my wand&#8217;ring spirit with those lov&#8217;d obsequies.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Going.</stagedir><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Stay, lady, stay: can it be possible,</line><line form="verse">That you are Violante?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">That lost name,</line><line form="verse">Spoken by one, that needs must know my fortunes,</line><line form="verse">Has taken much fear from me. Who are you, sir?</line><line form="verse">For, sure, I am that hopeless Violante.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">And I, as far from any earthly comfort</line><line form="verse">That I know yet, the much-wrong&#8217;d Julio!</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Julio!</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">I once was thought so. If the curst Henriquez</line><line form="verse">Had pow&#8217;r to change you to a boy, why, lady,</line><line form="verse">Should not that mischief make me any thing,</line><line form="verse">That have an equal share in all the miseries</line><line form="verse">His crimes have flung upon us?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Well I know it:</line><line form="verse">And pardon me, I could not know your virtues,</line><line form="verse">Before your griefs. Methought, when last we met,</line><line form="verse">The accent of your voice struck on my ear</line><line form="verse">Like something I had known, but floods of sorrow</line><line form="verse">Drown&#8217;d the remembrance. If you&#8217;ll please to sit,</line><line form="verse">(Since I have found a suff&#8217;ring true companion,)</line><line form="verse">And give me hearing, I will tell you something</line><line form="verse">Of Leonora, that may comfort you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">Blessing upon thee! Henceforth, I protest</line><line form="verse">Never to leave thee, if heav&#8217;n say amen.</line><line form="verse">But, soft! Let&#8217;s shift our ground, guide our sad steps</line><line form="verse">To some remoter gloom, where, undisturb&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">We may compare our woes; dwell on the tale</line><line form="verse">Of mutual injuries, &#8217;till our eyes run o&#8217;er,</line><line form="verse">And we infect each other, with fresh sorrows.</line><line form="verse">Talk&#8217;d you of comfort? &#8217;Tis the food of fools,</line><line form="verse">And we will none on&#8217;t; but indulge despair:</line><line form="verse" offset="2">So, worn with griefs, steal to the cave of death,</line><line form="verse" offset="2">And in a sigh give up our latest breath.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene></act><act num="5"><acttitle>Act 5</acttitle><scene num="1"><scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle><scenelocation>Another part of the prospect of the mountains.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Roderick, Leonora, Henriquez, Violante)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Roderick and Henriquez lead in Leonora, veiled, whom they have just kidnapped from the nunnery. Roderick introduces himself to her and explains why they have abducted her, and she castigates him for helping out such an unworthy brother. Henriquez woos her, but she rejects him, and Roderick begins to see that there may be more to this story than he thought. He sends Leonora to a lodge to restore herself; as they are leaving, he is taken aside by Violante. He recognizes her as the shepherd&#8217;s boy, but she reveals to himself as a woman Henriquez has wronged. She lets him know that Julio is nearby. He suggests that she appeal to the Duke his father, and goes off to find Julio.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Roderick, Leonora veiled, Henriquez, attendants as mourners.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Rest certain, lady, nothing shall betide you,</line><line form="verse">But fair, and noble usage. Pardon me,</line><line form="verse">That hitherto a course of violence</line><line form="verse">Has snatch&#8217;d you from that seat of contemplation</line><line form="verse">To which you gave your afterlife.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Where am I?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Not in the nunnery; never blush, nor tremble;</line><line form="verse">Your honor has as fair a guard, as when</line><line form="verse">Within a cloister. Know then, what is done,</line><line form="verse">(Which, I presume, you understand not truly,)</line><line form="verse">Has this use, to preserve the life of one</line><line form="verse">Dying for love of you: my brother, and your friend:</line><line form="verse">Under which color we desir&#8217;d to rest</line><line form="verse">Our herse one night within your hallow&#8217;d walls,</line><line form="verse">Where we surpriz&#8217;d you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Are you that lord Roderick,</line><line form="verse">So spoken of for virtue, and fair life,</line><line form="verse">And dare you lose these to be advocate</line><line form="verse">For such a brother, such a sinful brother,</line><line form="verse">Such an unfaithful, treacherous, brutal brother?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">This is a fearful charge.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Looks at Henriquez.</stagedir><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">If you would have me</line><line form="verse">Think, you still bear respect for virtue&#8217;s name;</line><line form="verse">As you would wish, your daughters, thus distress&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">Might find a guard, protect me from Henriquez;</line><line form="verse">And I am happy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">Come, sir, make your answer;</line><line form="verse">For as I have a soul, I am asham&#8217;d on&#8217;t.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">O Leonora, see! Thus self-condemn&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">I throw me at your feet, and sue for mercy.</line><line form="verse">If I have err&#8217;d, impute it to my love;</line><line form="verse">The tyrant god that bows us to his sway,</line><line form="verse">Rebellious to the laws of reas&#8217;ning men;</line><line form="verse">That will not have his votaries actions scann&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">But calls it justice, when we most obey him.</line><line form="verse">He but commanded, what your eyes inspir&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">Whose sacred beams, darted into my soul,</line><line form="verse">Have purg&#8217;d the mansion from impure desires,</line><line form="verse">And kindled in my heart a vestal&#8217;s flame.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">Rise, rise, my lord; this well-dissembled passion</line><line form="verse">Has gain&#8217;d you nothing but a deeper hate.</line><line form="verse">Should I imagine, he can truly love me,</line><line form="verse">That, like a villain, murders my desires?</line><line form="verse">Or should I drink that wine, and think it cordial,</line><line form="verse">When I see poison in&#8217;t?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Draw this way, lady;</line><line form="verse">I am not perfect in your story yet;</line><line form="verse">But see you&#8217;ve had some wrongs, that want redress.</line><line form="verse">Only you must have patience to go with us</line><line form="verse">To yon small lodge, which meets the sight from hence,</line><line form="verse">Where your distress shall find the due respect:</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Till when, your griefs shall govern me as much,</line><line form="verse">As nearness and affection to my brother.</line><line form="verse">Call my attendants yours; and use them freely;</line><line form="verse">For as I am a gentleman, no pow&#8217;r,</line><line form="verse">Above your own will, shall come near your person.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">As they are going out, Violante enters and plucks Roderick by the sleeve; the rest go out.</stagedir><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Your ear a moment&#8212;scorn not my tender youth.</line></speech><speech><speaker>RODER.</speaker><line form="verse">Look to the lady there.&#8212;I follow straight.</line><line form="verse">What ails this boy? Why dost thou single me?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">The due observance of your noble virtue,</line><line form="verse">Vow&#8217;d to this mourning virgin, makes me bold</line><line form="verse">To give it more employment.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Art not thou</line><line form="verse">The surly Shepherd&#8217;s boy, that, when I call&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">To know the way, ran crying by me?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Yes, sir.</line><line form="verse">And I thank heav&#8217;n and you for helping me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">How did I help thee, boy?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">I do but seem so, sir; and am indeed</line><line form="verse">A woman; one your brother once has lov&#8217;d;</line><line form="verse">Or, heav&#8217;n forgive him else, he li&#8217;d extremely.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Weep not, good maid; O this licentious brother!</line><line form="verse">But how came you a wand&#8217;rer on these mountains?</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">That, as we pass, an&#8217;t please you, I&#8217;ll discover.</line><line form="verse">I will assure you, sir, these barren mountains</line><line form="verse">Hold many wonders of your brother&#8217;s making.</line><line form="verse">Here wanders hapless Julio, worthy man!</line><line form="verse">Besides himself with wrongs&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">That once again&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">Sir, I said, Julio.&#8212;Sleep weigh&#8217;d down his eyelids,</line><line form="verse">Oppress&#8217;d with watching, just as you approach&#8217;d us.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">O brother! We shall sound the depths of falsehood.</line><line form="verse">If this be true, no more but guide me to him:</line><line form="verse">I hope, a fair end will succeed all yet.</line><line form="verse">If it be he, by your leave, gentle brother,</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll see him serv&#8217;d first.&#8212;Maid, you have o&#8217;erjoy&#8217;d me.</line><line form="verse">Thou shalt have right too: make thy fair appeal</line><line form="verse">To the good Duke, and doubt not but thy tears</line><line form="verse">Shall be repaid with interest from his justice.</line><line form="verse">Lead me to Julio.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir></scene><scene num="2"><scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle><scenelocation>An apartment in the lodge.</scenelocation><scenepersonae>(Duke Angelo, Don Bernard, Camillo, Gentleman, Roderick, Leonora, Henriquez, Julio)</scenepersonae><scenedescription>Camillo, Don Bernard and the Duke discuss their respective wayward children. Don Bernard is so weepy that he wishes he had Leonora back no matter the circumstances. News comes that Roderick is arriving, with a hearse in his train. He brings in Henriquez and Leonora. The Duke and Don Bernard are overjoyed, but Camillo reminds them of how he has been injured. The Duke lectures Leonora on how she ought to obey her father, and, believing Julio to be dead, she agrees to marry Henriquez so long as she is first allowed to mourn Julio properly. Violante nervously approaches, but keep hanging back until she is noticed. Roderick tells Henriquez it is his former, mistreated page, to Henriquez&#8217;s confusion, as he never had such a page. Violante approaches and, still pretending to be a boy, accuses Henriquez of promising to treat him well and advance him, only to cast &#8220;him&#8221; off for no good reason. The duke only asks for a witness to this to do &#8220;him&#8221; justice. Violante promises to produce one. In her absence Henriquez still insists this is a set-up, but Roderick produces a letter he argues proves that the pageboy was in his service; he begins reading it  it is the letter that Henriquez sent to Violante telling her he was forgetting her. Henriquez interrupts before his brother gets too far, and admits that he wrote the letter, but argues it must have been stolen from him and is now being used as blackmail against him. Accompanied by the disguised Julio, Violante comes back, now dressed as a woman, and Henriquez recognizes her. Though she gives up her claim on him since he no longer loves her, she still begs that he leave her a virtuous woman. He is so moved that he falls in love with her and proposes to marry her, begs Leonora&#8217;s forgiveness, and pledges not to marry until he has found Julio to apologize. Julio throws off his disguise and he and Leonora fall into each other&#8217;s arms  to the extent that Camillo cannot actually recognize his son. There is forgiveness all around and the whole company leaves for court, where the weddings will take place.</scenedescription><stagedir type="enter">Enter Duke, Don Bernard, and Camillo.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Ay, then your grace had had a son more; he, a daughter; and I, an heir: but let it be as &#8217;tis, I cannot mend it; one way or other, I shall rub it over, with rubbing to my grave, and there&#8217;s an end on&#8217;t.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Our sorrows cannot help us, gentlemen.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Hang me, sir, if I shed one tear more. By Jove, I&#8217;ve wept so long, I&#8217;m as blind as justice. When I come to see my hawks (which I held a toy next to my son) if they be but house-high, I must stand aiming at them like a gunner.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Why, he mourns like a man. Don Bernard, you</line><line form="verse">Are still like April, full of show&#8217;rs and dews:</line><line form="verse">And yet I blame you not: for I myself</line><line form="verse">Feel the self-same affections.&#8212;Let them go;</line><line form="verse">They&#8217;re disobedient children.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Ay, my lord;</line><line form="verse">Yet they may turn again.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Let them e&#8217;en have their swing: they&#8217;re young and wanton; the next storm we shall have them gallop homeward, whining as pigs do in the wind.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">Would I had my daughter any way.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Would&#8217;st thou have her with bairn, man, tell me that?</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">I care not, if an honest father got it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">You might have had her so in this good time, had my son had her: now you may go seek your fool to stop a gap with.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">You say, that Rod&#8217;rick charg&#8217;d you here should wait him:</line><line form="verse">He has o&#8217;erslip&#8217;d the time, at which his letters</line><line form="verse">Of speed request that I should also meet him.</line><line form="verse">I fear, some bad event is usher&#8217;d in</line><line form="verse">By this delay:&#8212;How now?</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Attendant.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ATT.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">So please your grace,&#8212;</line><line form="verse">Lord Roderick makes approach.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">I thank thee, fellow,</line><line form="verse">For thy so timely news: comes he alone?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ATT.</speaker><line form="verse">No, sir, attended well; and in his train</line><line form="verse">Follows a herse with all due rites of mourning.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Gentleman.</stagedir><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Heav&#8217;n send, Henriquez live!</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">&#8217;Tis my poor Julio.&#8212;</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Roderick, hastily.</stagedir><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">O welcome, welcome,</line><line form="verse">Welcome, good Rod&#8217;rick! Say, what news?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Do you bring joy or grief, my lord? For me,</line><line form="verse">Come what can come, I&#8217;ll live a month or two</line><line form="verse">If the gout please; curse my physician once more,</line><line form="verse">And then,&#8212;</line><line form="verse" offset="2">Under this stone</line><line form="verse" offset="2">Lies sev&#8217;nty one.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Signior, you do express a manly patience.</line><line form="verse">My noble father, something I have brought</line><line form="verse">To ease your sorrows: my endeavours have not</line><line form="verse">Been altogether barren in my journey.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">It comes at need, boy; but I hop&#8217;d it from thee.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Leonora veiled, Henriquez behind, and attendants.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">The company I bring, will bear me witness</line><line form="verse">The busiest of my time has been employ&#8217;d</line><line form="verse">On this good task. Don Bernard finds beneath</line><line form="verse">This veil his daughter: you, my royal father,</line><line form="verse">Behind that lady find a wand&#8217;ring son.</line><line form="verse">How I met with them, and how brought them hither,</line><line form="verse">More leisure must unfold.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">My father here!</line><line form="verse">And Julio&#8217;s! O confusion! Low as earth</line><stagedir type="speak">To the Duke.</stagedir><line form="verse">I bow me for your pardon.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">O my girl!</line><line form="verse">Thou bring&#8217;st new life.&#8212;</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Embraces Leonora.</stagedir><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><stagedir type="speak">To Roderick.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="6">And you, my son, restore me</line><line form="verse">One comfort here that has been missing long.</line><stagedir type="speak">To Henriquez.</stagedir><line form="verse">I hope, thy follies thou hast left abroad.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">Ay, ay; you&#8217;ve all comforts but I; you have ruin&#8217;d me, kill&#8217;d my poor boy; cheated and ruin&#8217;d him; and I have no comfort.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Be patient, signior; time may guide my hand</line><line form="verse">To work you comfort too.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">I thank your lordship;</line><line form="verse">Would grandsire time had been so kind to&#8217;ve done it;</line><line form="verse">We might have joy&#8217;d together like good fellows.</line><line form="verse">But he&#8217;s so full of business, good old man,</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis wonder, he could do the good he has done.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">Nay, child, be comforted. These tears distract me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Hear your good father, lady.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="8">Willingly.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">The voice of parents is the voice of gods:</line><line form="verse">For to their children they are heav&#8217;n&#8217;s lieutenants:</line><line form="verse">Made fathers, not for common uses merely</line><line form="verse">Of procreation; (beasts and birds would be</line><line form="verse">As noble then as we are) but to steer</line><line form="verse">The wanton freight of youth through storms and dangers,</line><line form="verse">Which with full sails they bear upon: and streighten</line><line form="verse">The moral line of life, they bend so often.</line><line form="verse">For these are we made fathers; and for these,</line><line form="verse">May challenge duty on our children&#8217;s part.</line><line form="verse">Obedience is the sacrifice of angels,</line><line form="verse">Whose form you carry.</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">Hear the Duke, good wench.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><stagedir type="speak">To the Duke.</stagedir><line form="verse">I do most heedfully. My gracious lord,</line><line form="verse">Let me be so unmanner&#8217;d to request,</line><line form="verse">He would not farther press me with persuasions</line><line form="verse">O&#8217; th&#8217; instant hour: but have the gentle patience</line><line form="verse">To bury this keen suit, &#8217;till I shake hands</line><line form="verse">With my old sorrows,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Why dost look at me?</line><line form="verse">Alas! I cannot help thee.</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">And but weep</line><line form="verse">A farewell to my murder&#8217;d Julio,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Blessing be with thy soul, whene&#8217;er it leaves thee!</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">For such sad rites must be perform&#8217;d, my lord,</line><line form="verse">E&#8217;er I can love again. Maids, that have lov&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">If they be worth that noble testimony,</line><line form="verse">Wear their loves here, my lord; here, in their hearts;</line><line form="verse">Deep, deep within; not in their eyes, or accents;</line><line form="verse">Such may be slip&#8217;d away; or with two tears</line><line form="verse">Wash&#8217;d out of all remembrance: mine, no physic,</line><line form="verse">But time, or death, can cure.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">You make your own conditions, and I seal them</line><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">Thus on your virtuous hand.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Well, wench, thy equal</line><line form="verse">Shall not be found in haste; I give thee that:</line><line form="verse">Thou art a right one, ev&#8217;ry inch. Thy father</line><line form="verse">(For, without doubt, that snuff never begot thee,)</line><line form="verse">Was some choice fellow, some true gentleman;</line><line form="verse">I give thy mother thanks for&#8217;t&#8212;there&#8217;s no harm done.</line><line form="verse">Would I were young again, and had but thee,</line><line form="verse">A good horse under me, and a good sword,</line><line form="verse">And thus much for inheritance.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Violante offers, once or twice, to shew herself, but goes back.</stagedir><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">What boy&#8217;s that,</line><line form="verse">Has offer&#8217;d twice or thrice to break upon us?</line><line form="verse">I&#8217;ve noted him, and still he falls back fearful.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">A little boy, sir, like a shepherd?</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Yes.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis your page, brother; one that was so, late.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">My page! What page?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Ev&#8217;n so he says, your page;</line><line form="verse">And more, and worse, you stole him from his friends,</line><line form="verse">And promis&#8217;d him preferment.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">I, preferment!</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">And on some slight occasion let him slip</line><line form="verse">Here on these mountains, where he had been starv&#8217;d,</line><line form="verse">Had not my people found him, as we travell&#8217;d.</line><line form="verse">This was not handsome, brother.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">You are merry.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">You&#8217;ll find it sober truth.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">If so, &#8217;tis ill.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis fiction all, sir;&#8212;brother, you must please</line><line form="verse">To look some other fool to put these tricks on;</line><line form="verse">They are too obvious:&#8212;please your grace, give leave</line><line form="verse">T&#8217; admit the boy; if he know me, and say,</line><line form="verse">I stole him from his friends, and cast him off,</line><line form="verse">Know me no more. Brother, pray do not wrong me.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Violante.</stagedir><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Here is the boy. If he deny this to you,</line><line form="verse">Then I have wrong&#8217;d you.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Hear me; what&#8217;s thy name, boy?</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse">Florio, an&#8217;t like your grace.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">A pretty child.</line><line form="verse">Where wast thou born?</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">On t&#8217;other side the mountains.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">What are thy friends?</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">A father, sir; but poor.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">How camest thou hither? How, to leave thy father?</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Pointing to Henriquez.</stagedir><line form="verse">That noble gentleman pleas&#8217;d once to like me,</line><line form="verse">And, not to lie, so much to dote upon me,</line><line form="verse">That with his promises he won my youth,</line><line form="verse">And duty, from my father: him I follow&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">How say you now, brother?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Ay, my lord, how say you?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">As I have life and soul, &#8217;tis all a trick, sir.</line><line form="verse">I never saw the boy before.</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="8">O sir,</line><line form="verse">Call not your soul to witness in a wrong:</line><line form="verse">And &#8217;tis not noble in you, to despise</line><line form="verse">What you have made thus. If I lie, let justice</line><line form="verse">Turn all her rods upon me.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Fie, Henriquez;</line><line form="verse">There is no trace of cunning in this boy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">A good boy!&#8212;Be not fearful: speak thy mind, child.</line><line form="verse">Nature, sure, meant thou should&#8217;st have been a wench;</line><line form="verse">And then&#8217;t had been no marvel he had bobb&#8217;d thee.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Why did he put thee from him?</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">That to me</line><line form="verse">Is yet unknown, sir; for my faith, he could not;</line><line form="verse">I never did deceive him: for my service,</line><line form="verse">He had no just cause; what my youth was able,</line><line form="verse">My will still put in act, to please my master:</line><line form="verse">I cannot steal; therefore that can be nothing</line><line form="verse">To my undoing: no, nor lie; my breeding,</line><line form="verse">Though it be plain, is honest.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Weep not, child.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="prose">This lord has abused men, women, and children already: what farther plot he has, the devil knows.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">If thou can&#8217;st bring a witness of thy wrong,</line><line form="verse">(Else it would be injustice to believe thee,</line><line form="verse">He having sworn against it) thou shalt have,</line><line form="verse">I bind it with my honor, satisfaction</line><line form="verse">To thine own wishes.</line></speech><speech><speaker alias="VIOL.">FLO.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">I desire no more, sir.</line><line form="verse">I have a witness, and a noble one,</line><line form="verse">For truth and honesty.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Go, bring him hither.</line></speech><stagedir type="exit">Exit Violante.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">This lying boy will take him to his heels,</line><line form="verse">And leave me slander&#8217;d.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">No; I&#8217;ll be his voucher.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">Nay then &#8217;tis plain, this is confederacy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">That he has been an agent in your service,</line><line form="verse">Appears from this. Here is a letter, brother,</line><line form="verse">(Produc&#8217;d, perforce, to give him credit with me)</line><line form="verse">The writing, yours; the matter, love; for so,</line><line form="verse">He says, he can explain it.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Then, belike,</line><line form="verse">A young he-bawd.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">This forgery confounds me!</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Read it, Roderick.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir><line form="verse"><recite>Our prudence should now teach us to</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>forget, what our indiscretion has com-</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>mitted. I have already made one step</recite></line><line form="verse"><recite>towards this wisdom&#8212;</recite></line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">Hold, sir.&#8212;My very words to Violante!</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Go on.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="2">My gracious father, give me pardon;</line><line form="verse">I do confess, I some such letter wrote</line><line form="verse">(The purport all too trivial for your ear,)</line><line form="verse">But how it reach&#8217;d this young dissembler&#8217;s hands,</line><line form="verse">Is what I cannot solve. For on my soul,</line><line form="verse">And by the honors of my birth and house,</line><line form="verse">The minion&#8217;s face &#8217;till now I never saw.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Run not too far in debt on protestation.</line><line form="verse">Why should you do a child this wrong?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Go to;</line><line form="verse">Your friendships past warrant not this abuse:</line><line form="verse">If you provoke me thus, I shall forget</line><line form="verse">What you are to me. This is a mere practice,</line><line form="verse">And villany to draw me into scandal.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">No more; you are a boy.&#8212;Here comes a witness,</line><line form="verse">Shall prove you so: no more.</line></speech><stagedir type="enter">Enter Julio, disguis&#8217;d; Violante, as a woman.</stagedir><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Another rascal!</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">Hold&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Seeing Violante.</stagedir><line form="verse">Ha!</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">What&#8217;s here?</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="verse">By all my sins, the injur&#8217;d Violante.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Now, sir, whose practice breaks?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><stagedir type="speak">To Henriquez.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="9">Is this a page?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">One that has done him service,</line><line form="verse">And he has paid her for&#8217;t; but broke his covenant.</line></speech><speech><speaker>VIOL.</speaker><line form="verse">My lord, I come not now to wound your spirit.</line><line form="verse">Your pure affection dead, which first betray&#8217;d me,</line><line form="verse">My claim die with it! Only let me not</line><line form="verse">Shrink to the grave with infamy upon me:</line><line form="verse">Protect my virtue, though it hurt your faith;</line><line form="verse">And my last breath shall speak Henriquez noble.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">What a fierce conflict shame, and wounded honor,</line><line form="verse">Raise in my breast!&#8212;But honor shall o&#8217;ercome.&#8212;</line><line form="verse">She looks as beauteous, and as innocent,</line><line form="verse">As when I wrong&#8217;d her.&#8212;Virtuous Violante!</line><line form="verse">Too good for me! Dare you still love a man,</line><line form="verse">So faithless as I am? I know you love me.</line><line form="verse">Thus, thus, and thus, I print my vow&#8217;d repentance:</line><line form="verse">Let all men read it here. My gracious father,</line><line form="verse">Forgive, and make me rich with your consent,</line><line form="verse">This is my wife; no other would I choose,</line><line form="verse">Were she a queen.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Here&#8217;s a new change. Bernard looks dull upon&#8217;t.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">And fair Leonora, from whose virgin arms</line><line form="verse">I forc&#8217;d my wrong&#8217;d friend Julio, O forgive me.</line><line form="verse">Take home your holy vows, and let him have &#8217;em</line><line form="verse">That has deserv&#8217;d them. O that he were here!</line><line form="verse">That I might own the baseness of my wrong,</line><line form="verse">And purpos&#8217;d recompence. My Violante,</line><line form="verse">You must again be widow&#8217;d: for I vow</line><line form="verse">A ceaseless pilgrimage, ne&#8217;er to know joy,</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Till I can give it to the injur&#8217;d Julio.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">This almost melts me:&#8212;but my poor lost boy&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">I&#8217;ll stop that voyage, brother.&#8212;Gentle lady,</line><line form="verse">What think you of this honest man?</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="9">Alas!</line><line form="verse">My thoughts, my lord, were all employ&#8217;d within!</line><line form="verse">He has a face makes me remember something</line><line form="verse">I have thought well of; how he looks upon me!</line><line form="verse">Poor man, he weeps.&#8212;Ha! Stay; it cannot be&#8212;</line><line form="verse">He has his eye, his features, shape, and gesture.&#8212;</line><line form="verse">Would, he would speak.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><stagedir type="action">Throws off his disguise.</stagedir><line form="verse" offset="5">Leonora,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="7">Yes, &#8217;tis he.</line><stagedir type="action">They embrace.</stagedir><line form="verse">O ecstacy of joy!&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="5">Now, what&#8217;s the matter?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">Let &#8217;em alone; they&#8217;re almost starv&#8217;d for kisses.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Stand forty foot off; no man trouble &#8217;em.</line><line form="verse">Much good may&#8217;t do your hearts!&#8212;What is he, lord,</line><line form="verse">What is he?</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">A certain son of yours.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">The devil he is.</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse">If he be the devil, that devil must call you father.</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">By your leave a little, ho,&#8212;are you my Julio?</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">My duty tells me so, sir,</line><line form="verse">Still on my knees. But love engross&#8217;d me all;</line><line form="verse">O Leonora, do I once more hold thee?</line></speech><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">Nay, to&#8217;t again: I will not hinder a kiss,</line><stagedir type="action">Leaps.</stagedir><line form="verse">&#8217;Tis he&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>LEON.</speaker><line form="verse">The righteous pow&#8217;rs at length have crown&#8217;d our loves.</line><line form="verse">Think, Julio, from the storm that&#8217;s now o&#8217;erblown,</line><line form="verse">Though sour affliction combat hope awhile,</line><line form="verse">When lovers swear true faith, the list&#8217;ning angels</line><line form="verse">Stand on the golden battlements of heav&#8217;n,</line><line form="verse">And waft their vows to the eternal throne.</line><line form="verse">Such were our vows, and so are they repaid.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">E&#8217;en as you are, we&#8217;ll join your hands together.</line><line form="verse">A providence above our pow&#8217;r rules all.</line><stagedir type="speak">To Henriquez.</stagedir><line form="verse">Ask him forgiveness, boy.</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">He has it, sir:</line><line form="verse">The fault was love&#8217;s, not his.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="6">Brave, gen&#8217;rous Julio!</line><line form="verse">I knew thy nobleness of old, and priz&#8217;d it,</line><line form="verse">&#8217;Till passion made me blind&#8212;once more, my friend,</line><line form="verse">Share in a heart, that ne&#8217;er shall wrong thee more.</line><line form="verse">And, brother,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>ROD.</speaker><line form="verse" offset="4">This embrace cuts off excuses.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">I must, in part, repair my son&#8217;s offence:</line><line form="verse">At your best leisure, Julio, know our court.</line><line form="verse">And, Violante, (for I know you now)</line><line form="verse">I have a debt to pay: your good old father,</line><line form="verse">Once, when I chas&#8217;d the boar, preserv&#8217;d my life:</line><line form="verse">For that good deed, and for your virtue&#8217;s sake,</line><line form="verse">Though your descent be low, call me your father.</line><line form="verse">A match drawn out of honesty, and goodness,</line><line form="verse">Is pedigree enough. Are you all pleas&#8217;d?</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Gives her to Henriquez.</stagedir><speech><speaker>CAM.</speaker><line form="verse">All.</line></speech><speech><speaker>HENR.</speaker><line form="verse">All, sir,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>D. BERN.</speaker><line form="verse">All, sir,&#8212;</line></speech><speech><speaker>JUL.</speaker><line form="verse">All.</line></speech><speech><speaker>DUKE.</speaker><line form="verse">And I not least. We&#8217;ll now return to court:</line><line form="verse">(And that short travel, and your loves compleated,</line><line form="verse">Shall, as I trust, for life restrain these wand&#8217;rings.)</line><line form="verse">There, the solemnity, and grace, I&#8217;ll do</line><line form="verse">Your sev&#8217;ral nuptials, shall approve my joy;</line><line form="verse" offset="2">And make griev&#8217;d lovers, that your story read,</line><line form="verse" offset="2">Wish, true love&#8217;s wand&#8217;rings may like yours succeed.</line></speech><stagedir type="action">Curtain falls.</stagedir></scene></act><sourcedetails><source>PlayShakespeare.com</source><sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl><copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright><version>3.1a</version><license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license></sourcedetails></play>