<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Edward III">The Reign of King Edward the Third</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="Edward III">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING OF BOHEMIA.">King of Bohemia</persname>
<persdescription>The King of Bohemia is an ally of King John, and brings his forces to the French King&#8217;s aid. He is killed during the battle of Cr&#233;cy. Historically, this is best explained by the fact that he was blind.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LORRAIN.">Duke of Lorraine</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Lorraine is a high-ranking French aristocrat, King John&#8217;s ambassador both to England and Scotland. He is quick to anger and foolhardy enough to draw his sword in the presence of King Edward, but shows more diplomacy with the Scottish King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PHILLIP.">Philip</persname>
<persdescription>Philip is the younger son of King John of France. He is a brave lad with a taste for battle and a blunt appreciation of realities, considering possession nine-tenths of the law. Confident of French victory, he sends Prince Edward a religious book as a consolation before battle, being certain that Edward will not live out the day. Philip is somewhat disquieted by the evil presages just before battle, but is quickly ready to reassure the common men. He is horrified at being defeated by such a smaller force. He is captured in battle. Historically, he was 14 years old at this time, and won the moniker &#8216;The Brave&#8217; for his deeds in the battle of Poitiers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CHARLES.">Charles</persname>
<persdescription>Charles of Normandy is the eldest son of King John of France. Proud and insulting, he can find excuses to get out of keeping one&#8217;s promises, but once he has given his word he will hold to it even against his father&#8217;s displeasure. Ready to call an old man a dotard to his face, he also sends a message to Prince Edward advises him to run away before a battle. Charles is a brave man. Historically, he escaped the battlefield at Poitiers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING JOHN.">John de Valois, King of France</persname>
<persdescription>John de Valois, King of France, was named King after the last son of King Philip le Bew (le Bel) died. Haughty, overly self-assured, and rather a snob, he is nevertheless a genuinely brave man when he has his back to the wall. His own arrogance puts him in that position perhaps more often than strictly necessary, but his defiance of Edward&#8217;s invasion does make some rather good points. Beaten time and again in battle, he is overly optimistic about the likelihood of a French victory, bouncing back from defeat and misinterpreting prophecies to suit his hopes. He has the instincts of a good leader, he insists on reassuring his troops no matter how he feels himself when his confidence is shaken by more portents. Unfortunately, he cannot back up either these instincts or his quite genuine qualities with any military abilities. He is also wrathful, choleric, and authoritarian, willing to break all the rules of chivalry when he is in a temper with no care for the honor of his lords. He refuses to the end to admit that Edward has any justice on his side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GOBIN.">Gobin de Grey</persname>
<persdescription>Gobin de Grey is a French prisoner who shows the English a ford over the river Somme, in return for which he receives both his liberty and rather a lot of money.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOUNTFORD.">Earl of Mountford</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Mountford is a claimant to the Dukedom of Brittany, which the Earl of Salisbury has been helping him to conquer. In thanks for the English help, he swears allegiance to King Edward once his campaign is successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ARTOIS.">Robert of Artois</persname>
<persdescription>Robert Earl of Artois is a Frenchman who has had to flee from France; arriving in England and being named Earl of Richmond by King Edward, he convinces the latter that he has a better claim to the French throne than does King John. Regarded as a traitor by the French, he becomes one of Edward&#8217;s war leaders, following the King to Scotland before going on to France and accompanying the Prince of Wales to the battle of Poitiers, where he captures the French King&#8217;s son Phillip. He is a brave man who is fond of Prince Edward and horrified that King Edward will do nothing to help his own son when the latter is in a bit of a fix.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="VILLIERS.">Villiers</persname>
<persdescription>Villiers is a French Lord, a prisoner of the Earl of Salisbury. He is freed in return for a safe-conduct for the Earl. He is a deeply honorable man who is horrified at the idea of being prevented from keeping his word.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="COPLAND.">Sir John Copland</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Copland is an English esquire who captures King David of Scots in battle but refuses to hand him over to Queen Philippa, as he insists that he will only give the prisoner to the King in person.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOUNTAGUE.">Sir William Mountague</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Mountague is a young English knight from the North of the country who rushes to report to King Edward that the peace with Scotland has been breached and that his aunt the Countess of Salisbury is besieged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LODOWICK.">Lodowick</persname>
<persdescription>Lodowick is a confidant of King Edward&#8217;s, well-read and literate, and who knows the King better than many do. Asked by the monarch to write a love letter on his behalf, he is unable to get anywhere, as the King is being a backseat driver and literary critic throughout. His attempts at writing a formal and fashionable epistle do not please the King at all. He puts up with being used as a go-between even though he is perfectly well aware that the Countess is unlikely to reciprocate the King&#8217;s feelings.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PERCY.">Lord Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Percy is a nobleman from the North of England who travels to France to inform King Edward that his enemy King David of Scotland has been captured in battle thanks to the Queen&#8217;s efforts in fighting the Scots.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AUDLEY.">Lord Audley</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Audley is an old English nobleman who accompanies the Prince of Wales to the war. He is taken aback by the King&#8217;s refusal to send any aid to the Prince when the latter is in danger. Unafraid of death, he is able to stiffen the backs of those much younger than himself. He is mortally wounded at the battle of Poitiers. Honorable and generous, his final thoughts are for those dependent on him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SALISBURY.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury is an English nobleman, the husband of the Countess of Salisbury, and never does find out what King Edward&#8217;s plans for his wife were. He is off in France fighting to allow the Earl of Mountford to rule over Brittany. Eager to join King Edward in his war against the French, he arranges for a safe-condct for himself and his men from his prisoner Villiers in exchange for the latter&#8217;s freedom. Convinced by King John that the Prince of Wales is dead, he brings this false report to King Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DERBY.">Earl of Derby</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Derby is an English nobleman whom King Edward sends off to convince the earl of Hainault and the Emperor of Germany to provide aid to the English war against France. He is confused at the King&#8217;s distraction over the Countess of Salisbury, and distraught at the thought of Prince Edward&#8217;s death in battle. He is a compassionate man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WARWICK.">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Warwick is one of King Edward&#8217;s noblemen, an old man who is the Countess of Salisbury&#8217;s father. Deeply honorable, he is horrified when the King tricks him into swearing to convince his daughter to sleep with the lustful monarch, but makes a rather half-hearted attempt at doing so. He is greatly relieved when she&#8217;ll have none of it. Warwick is named Warden of the North to defend England against the Scots while King Edward is off beating up the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PRINCE EDWARD.">Prince Edward</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Edward is King Edward&#8217;s son, the Prince of Wales, and history&#8217;s Black Prince &#8212; also, therefore, the father of Richard II. A young man who looks a good deal like his mother Queen Philippa, he is the ideal knight, a brave and brilliant fighter who in his very first battle beats a far superior force and kills the King of Bohemia. Deeply patriotic, he bridles at insults to England or the English, and absolutely refuses to act in any way that risks ruining their reputation. Scornful and proud, he does not take well to being mocked, but is a true friend to those he loves, such as Audley. Victory makes him thirsty for more.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COUNTESS.">Countess of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Countess of Salisbury, Warwick&#8217;s daughter and Salisbury&#8217;s wife, is an English noblewoman who has the misfortune of being captured by the Scottish King and of being rather good-looking, attracting the attentions of not only Earl Douglas and King David but also of King Edward. Though a well-brought-up, well-behaved, and respectable lady, she has a sarcastic edge to her tongue when need be, and does not refrain from mocking the Scots when they are on the verge of running away. A loyal subject, she nevertheless absolutely refuses to entertain the idea of cheating on her husband with the King, out-arguing him on the subject and in the end out-maneuvering him completely into giving up his importuning. She is both brave and extremely clever.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="QUEEN PHILLIP.">Philippa</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Philippa is King Edward&#8217;s wife, a brave woman who is not afraid, even while heavily pregnant, to take charge of the war against the Scots. She is proud and does not like having her authority put into question. However, she is merciful, and often pleads with her husband to pardon others, as she is at times the only one who can calm him down. In particular she saves the lives of the six rich Citizens of Calais.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DOUGLAS.">Earl Douglas</persname>
<persdescription>Earl Douglas is a Scottish lord who is rather taken with the Countess of Salisbury, but has no intention of staying to be captured by the English when they come to deliver her, and instead runs away as fast as he can.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING DAVID.">David, King of Scotland</persname>
<persdescription>King David of Scots is, despite his brave promises to the French, a bit of a wimp. He is more concerned with who should get the Countess of Salisbury than with checking whether the English might be coming to deliver her, and runs away as soon as he hears that they&#8217;re on their way. Trying to attack England in Edward&#8217;s absence, he ends up being captured by the English.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING EDWARD.">Edward III</persname>
<persdescription>Edward III is the King of England, a passionate man used to getting his own way. A proud man, he is insulted at the idea of being forced to do homage to the French King when he can claim the throne of France for himself. He does not act quite as nobly as he ought to, and is easily distracted from his wars by a pretty lady; in fact, he is quite able and willing to make a fool of himself over one. His attempts to woo the Countess of Salisbury provoke a burst of both lyricism and literary criticism from him, neither of which suit him, along with distracting him from his job. Luckily for England, as well as his own reputation, he recovers. He knows the value of propaganda, and quarters his arms with those of France even before fighting for the throne of that country begins. He is a proud but tough father to his son Prince Edward, refusing to give him any help on the battlefield so that he will not learn to expect any. Though generous by nature, Edward can also be cruel and vindictive, as in his plan to slaughter the six richest men of Calais in retribution for the city&#8217;s earlier refusal to surrender. His wife Queen Philippa is able to sway him on this, however. Edward is not an overly complicated man, being direct and generally acting as honor dictates, but his temper and desires can get in the way of that on occasion &#8212; and as he is not overly complicated, he follows them where they lead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. SCOT. MESS.">First Scottish Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>First Scottish Messenger warns King David of the approach of an enemy army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. SCOT. MESS.">Second Scottish Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Second Scottish Messenger informs King David that the Scots have suddenly been attacked.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="POL. CAPTAIN.">Polish Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Polish Captain leads forces to the aid of King John of France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. MARINER.">French Mariner</persname>
<persdescription>A French Mariner comes to tell King John that he has spotted the English fleet, and that King Edward has had the gall to quarter his arms with those of France. Sent back to the battle, he returns to inform the King that the French have lost, and many of their ships have been sunk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. FRENCH.">First Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Frenchman is a cautious man who thinks it much more prudent to save as many of his personal belongings and store them (and himself) in a safe place when armies are on the march. He prefers not to fight on the French side as he believes that Edward is in the right.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. FRENCH.">Second Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Frenchman is a cautious man who thinks it best to get out of the path of war when armies are marching.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. FRENCH.">Third Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Frenchman is an overly optimistic man who has not heard of the approaching English and does not see them as being worth fleeing from. He soon learns better.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. FRENCH.">Fourth Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Frenchman witnesses the devastation caused by the English invasion and rushes about warning all those he meets to get to safety while they can.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FRENCHWOMAN.">Frenchwoman</persname>
<persdescription>A Frenchwoman has heard of prophecies suggesting that the war is going to be devastating, and cautiously thinks she should get herself and her children out of the path of war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. HERALD.">First Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The First Herald [mute role] carries in the coat of armor that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. HERALD.">Second Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Herald [mute role] carries in the helmet that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. HERALD.">Third Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Herald [mute role] carries in the lance that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. HERALD.">Fourth Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Herald [mute role] carries in the shield that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="POOR.">Poor Inhabitant of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>A Poor Inhabitant of Calais is one of several kicked out of the town as he is far too weak to help in the defense of the city. He is saved from starving to death by King Edward&#8217;s generosity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FIVE POOR.">Five Poor Inhabitants of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>Five Poor Inhabitants of Calais [mute roles] are kicked out of the town as he is far too weak to help in the defense of the city. They are saved from starving to death by King Edward&#8217;s generosity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. FR. HERALD.">First French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The First French Herald is sent by King John to offer terms to Prince Edward to avoid a battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. FR. HERALD.">Second French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Second French Herald is sent by Charles of Normandy to Prince Edward to suggest that he should take the opportunity to flee before battle becomes inevitable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. FR. HERALD.">Third French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Third French Herald is sent by Prince Philip of France to offer Prince Edward a consoling religious book.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. FR. CAPTAIN.">First French Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The First French Captain comes to inform King Edward that the burgesses of Calais have decided to surrender, and has his own opinion about trusting in monarchs.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. FR. CAPTAIN.">Second French Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The Second French Captain captures the Earl of Salisbury as he tries to make his way to Prince Edward, and brings him to King John.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. ESQUIRE.">First English Esquire</persname>
<persdescription>The First English Esquire helps rescue Audley from the French. He is concerned by Audley&#8217;s wounds.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. ESQUIRE.">Second English Esquire</persname>
<persdescription>The Second English Esquire helps rescue Audley from the French. He does not like the idea of Audley dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ENG. HERALD.">English Herald</persname>
<persdescription>An English Herald announces to King Edward and Queen Philippa that Prince Edward has won at Poitiers and captured King John.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. CIT. CAL.">First Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who along with five others accepts to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man. He begs Edward to keep his word to spare the city, pointing out that the two-days&#8217; truce is not yet over.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. CIT. CAL.">Second Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who along with five others accepts to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man, and swears to the truth of this on the peril of his immortal soul.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. CIT. CAL.">Third Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who accepts with five others to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. CIT. CAL.">Fourth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fourth Citizen of Calais is one of the six richest men of Calais who accept to sacrifice themselves for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="5. CIT. CAL.">Fifth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fifth Citizen of Calais is one of the six rich men of Calais who accept to sacrifice themselves for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="6. CIT. CAL.">Sixth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. CIT. CAL.">All Citizens of Calais</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Sixth Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who accepts to sacrifice himself along with five others for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. A room of state in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Edward, Derby, Prince Edward, Audley, Artois, Lords, Lorraine, Mountague)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Robert of Artois, exiled from France, is created Earl of Richmond by King Edward. In return, Artois lays out a genealogy that permits Edward to claim the throne of France. The Duke of Lorraine arrives from France to request Edward to do homage to King John for the Duchy of Guyenne – an idea Edward finds laughable. Mutual threats are exchanged, and war between France and England declared. Meanwhile, Edward receives news that despite a truce, the Scots have invaded England and trapped the Countess of Salisbury in her castle. Edward sends his son and noblemen to prepare for the invasion of France while he takes care of the Scots. The Prince of Wales is delighted.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward, Derby, Prince Edward, Audley, and Artois.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Robert of Artois, banished though thou be</line>
<line form="verse">From France, thy native Country, yet with us</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt retain as great a Seigniorie:</line>
<line form="verse">For we create thee Earl of Richmond here.</line>
<line form="verse">And now go forwards with our pedigree:</line>
<line form="verse">Who next succeeded Phillip le Bew?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Three sons of his, which all successfully</line>
<line form="verse">Did sit upon their father&#8217;s regal throne,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet died, and left no issue of their loins.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But was my mother sister unto those?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She was, my lord; and only Isabel</line>
<line form="verse">Was all the daughters that this Phillip had,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom afterward your father took to wife;</line>
<line form="verse">And from the fragrant garden of her womb</line>
<line form="verse">Your gracious self, the flower of Europe&#8217;s hope,</line>
<line form="verse">Derived is inheritor to France.</line>
<line form="verse">But note the rancor of rebellious minds:</line>
<line form="verse">When thus the lineage of le Bew was out,</line>
<line form="verse">The French obscured your mother&#8217;s privilege,</line>
<line form="verse">And, though she were the next of blood, proclaimed</line>
<line form="verse">John, of the house of Valois, now their king:</line>
<line form="verse">The reason was, they say, the realm of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Replete with princes of great parentage,</line>
<line form="verse">Ought not admit a governor to rule,</line>
<line form="verse">Except he be descended of the male;</line>
<line form="verse">And that&#8217;s the special ground of their contempt,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherewith they study to exclude your grace:</line>
<line form="verse">But they shall find that forged ground of theirs</line>
<line form="verse">To be but dusty heaps of brittle sand.</line>
<line form="verse">Perhaps it will be thought a heinous thing,</line>
<line form="verse">That I, a Frenchman, should discover this;</line>
<line form="verse">But heaven I call to record of my vows:</line>
<line form="verse">It is not hate nor any private wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">But love unto my country and the right,</line>
<line form="verse">Provokes my tongue, thus lavish in report.</line>
<line form="verse">You are the lineal watchman of our peace,</line>
<line form="verse">And John of Valois indirectly climbs;</line>
<line form="verse">What then should subjects but embrace their King?</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, where in may our duty more be seen,</line>
<line form="verse">Than striving to rebate a tyrant&#8217;s pride</line>
<line form="verse">And place the true shepherd of our commonwealth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This counsel, Artois, like to fruitful showers,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath added growth unto my dignity;</line>
<line form="verse">And, by the fiery vigor of thy words,</line>
<line form="verse">Hot courage is engendered in my breast,</line>
<line form="verse">Which heretofore was raked in ignorance,</line>
<line form="verse">But now doth mount with golden wings of fame,</line>
<line form="verse">And will approve fair Isabel&#8217;s descent,</line>
<line form="verse">Able to yoke their stubborn necks with steel,</line>
<line form="verse">That spurn against my sovereignty in France.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Sound a horn.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">A messenger?&#8212;Lord Audley, know from whence.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Audley, and returns.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Duke of Lorraine, having crossed the seas,</line>
<line form="verse">Entreats he may have conference with your highness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Admit him, lords, that we may hear the news.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt lords. King takes his State. Re-enter lords; with Lorraine, attended.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Say, Duke of Lorraine, wherefore art thou come?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The most renowned prince, King John of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Doth greet thee, Edward, and by me commands,</line>
<line form="verse">That, for so much as by his liberal gift</line>
<line form="verse">The Guyen Dukedom is entailed to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou do him lowly homage for the same.</line>
<line form="verse">And, for that purpose, here I summon thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Repair to France within these forty days,</line>
<line form="verse">That there, according as the custom is,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mayst be sworn true liegeman to our King;</line>
<line form="verse">Or else thy title in that province dies,</line>
<line form="verse">And he himself will repossess the place.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">See, how occasion laughs me in the face!</line>
<line form="verse">No sooner minded to prepare for France,</line>
<line form="verse">But straight I am invited,&#8212;nay, with threats,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon a penalty, enjoined to come:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twere but a childish part to say him nay.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Lorraine, return this answer to thy lord:</line>
<line form="verse">I mean to visit him as he requests;</line>
<line form="verse">But how? Not servilely disposed to bend,</line>
<line form="verse">But like a conqueror to make him bow.</line>
<line form="verse">His lame unpolished shifts are come to light;</line>
<line form="verse">And truth hath pulled the vizard from his face,</line>
<line form="verse">That set a gloss upon his arrogance.</line>
<line form="verse">Dare he command a fealty in me?</line>
<line form="verse">Tell him, the Crown that he usurps, is mine,</line>
<line form="verse">And where he sets his foot, he ought to kneel.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis not a petty dukedom that I claim,</line>
<line form="verse">But all the whole dominions of the realm;</line>
<line form="verse">Which if with grudging he refuse to yield,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll take away those borrowed plumes of his,</line>
<line form="verse">And send him naked to the wilderness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then, Edward, here, in spite of all thy lords,</line>
<line form="verse">I do pronounce defiance to thy face.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Defiance, Frenchman? We rebound it back,</line>
<line form="verse">Even to the bottom of thy master&#8217;s throat.</line>
<line form="verse">And, be it spoke with reverence of the king,</line>
<line form="verse">My gracious father, and these other lords,</line>
<line form="verse">I hold thy message but as scurrilous,</line>
<line form="verse">And him that sent thee, like the lazy drone,</line>
<line form="verse">Crept up by stealth unto the eagle&#8217;s nest;</line>
<line form="verse">From whence we&#8217;ll shake him with so rough a storm,</line>
<line form="verse">As others shall be warned by his harm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bid him leave of the lion&#8217;s case he wears,</line>
<line form="verse">Least, meeting with the lion in the field,</line>
<line form="verse">He chance to tear him piecemeal for his pride.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The soundest counsel I can give his grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Is to surrender ere he be constrained.</line>
<line form="verse">A voluntary mischief hath less scorn,</line>
<line form="verse">Than when reproach with violence is borne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Degenerate traitor, viper to the place</line>
<line form="verse">Where thou was fostered in thine infancy,</line>
<line form="verse">Bearest thou a part in this conspiracy?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">He draws his sword.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lorraine, behold the sharpness of this steel:</line>
<stagedir type="action">Drawing his.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Fervent desire that sits against my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Is far more thorny pricking than this blade;</line>
<line form="verse">That, with the nightingale, I shall be scared,</line>
<line form="verse">As oft as I dispose myself to rest,</line>
<line form="verse">Until my colours be displayed in France:</line>
<line form="verse">This is my final answer; so be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is not that, nor any English brave,</line>
<line form="verse">Afflicts me so, as doth his poisoned view,</line>
<line form="verse">That is most false, should most of all be true.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lorraine, and Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, lord, our fleeting bark is under sail;</line>
<line form="verse">Our gage is thrown, and war is soon begun,</line>
<line form="verse">But not so quickly brought unto an end.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Mountague.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">But wherefore comes Sir William Mountague?</line>
<line form="verse">How stands the league between the Scot and us?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOUNTAGUE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cracked and dissevered, my renowned lord.</line>
<line form="verse">The treacherous King no sooner was informed</line>
<line form="verse">Of your with drawing of your army back,</line>
<line form="verse">But straight, forgetting of his former oath,</line>
<line form="verse">He made invasion on the bordering Towns:</line>
<line form="verse">Barwick is won, Newcastle spoiled and lost,</line>
<line form="verse">And now the tyrant hath begirt with siege</line>
<line form="verse">The castle of Rocksborough, where enclos&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The Countess Salisbury is like to perish.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That is thy daughter, Warwick, is it not?</line>
<line form="verse">Whose husband hath in Britain served so long</line>
<line form="verse">About the planting of Lord Mountford there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ignoble David, hast thou none to grieve</line>
<line form="verse">But silly Ladies with thy threatening arms?</line>
<line form="verse">But I will make you shrink your snaily horns!</line>
<line form="verse">First, therefore, Audley, this shall be thy charge,</line>
<line form="verse">Go levy footmen for our wars in France;</line>
<line form="verse">And, Ned, take muster of our men at arms:</line>
<line form="verse">In every shire elect a several band.</line>
<line form="verse">Let them be Soldiers of a lusty spirit,</line>
<line form="verse">Such as dread nothing but dishonor&#8217;s blot;</line>
<line form="verse">Be wary, therefore, since we do commence</line>
<line form="verse">A famous war, and with so mighty a nation.</line>
<line form="verse">Derby, be thou ambassador for us</line>
<line form="verse">Unto our father in law, the Earl of Henalt:</line>
<line form="verse">Make him acquainted with our enterprise,</line>
<line form="verse">And likewise will him, with our own allies</line>
<line form="verse">That are in Flanders, to solicit to</line>
<line form="verse">The Emperor of Almaigne in our name.</line>
<line form="verse">Myself, whilst you are jointly thus employed,</line>
<line form="verse">Will, with these forces that I have at hand,</line>
<line form="verse">March, and once more repulse the traitorous Scot.</line>
<line form="verse">But, Sirs, be resolute: we shall have wars</line>
<line form="verse">On every side; and, Ned, thou must begin</line>
<line form="verse">Now to forget thy study and thy books,</line>
<line form="verse">And ure thy shoulders to an armor&#8217;s weight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As cheerful sounding to my youthful spleen</line>
<line form="verse">This tumult is of war&#8217;s increasing broils,</line>
<line form="verse">As, at the coronation of a king,</line>
<line form="verse">The joyful clamours of the people are,</line>
<line form="verse">When &#8220;Ave, Caesar!&#8221; they pronounce aloud.</line>
<line form="verse">Within this school of honor I shall learn</line>
<line form="verse">Either to sacrifice my foes to death,</line>
<line form="verse">Or in a rightful quarrel spend my breath.</line>
<line form="verse">Then cheerfully forward, each a several way;</line>
<line form="verse">In great affairs &#8217;tis nought to use delay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Roxborough. Before the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Countess of Salisbury, David, Douglas, Lorraine, First Scottish Messenger, Second Scottish Messenger, King Edward, Warwick, Artois)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Countess of Salisbury laments and frets over her captivity and her fears that the King will not come to rescue her. She overhears King David of Scots making plans with the Duke of Lorraine, promising to keep the English busy so that they have no leisure to attack France. Lorraine leaves, and the King and the Earl of Douglas begin disputing over who should have the Countess and her jewels as booty. But at that moment a messenger runs in to announce that the English are on their way; the Earl immediately announces his intention to flee. The Countess jeers at the Scots as they run away. The Countess&#8217;s nephew Montague, arriving with the English forces, informs her that the King himself is at the head of the army. She is immediately worried about greeting him appropriately. Edward, coming in with Warwick, is quite smitten with the Countess. He wants to leave to pursue the Scots immediately, but the Countess persuades him to stay for dinner.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Countess.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alas, how much in vain my poor eyes gaze</line>
<line form="verse">For succour that my sovereign should send!</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, cousin Mountague, I fear thou wants</line>
<line form="verse">The lively spirit, sharply to solicit</line>
<line form="verse">With vehement suit the king in my behalf:</line>
<line form="verse">Thou dost not tell him, what a grief it is</line>
<line form="verse">To be the scornful captive of a Scot,</line>
<line form="verse">Either to be wooed with broad untuned oaths,</line>
<line form="verse">Or forced by rough insulting barbarism;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou doest not tell him, if he here prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">How much they will deride us in the north,</line>
<line form="verse">And, in their wild, uncivil, skipping gigs,</line>
<line form="verse">Bray forth their conquest and our overthrow</line>
<line form="verse">Even in the barren, bleak, and fruitless air.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter David and Douglas, Lorraine.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I must withdraw, the everlasting foe</line>
<line form="verse">Comes to the wall; I&#8217;ll closely step aside,</line>
<line form="verse">And list their babble, blunt and full of pride.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord of Lorraine, to our brother of France</line>
<line form="verse">Commend us, as the man in Christendom</line>
<line form="verse">That we most reverence and entirely love.</line>
<line form="verse">Touching your embassage, return and say,</line>
<line form="verse">That we with England will not enter parley,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor never make fair weather, or take truce;</line>
<line form="verse">But burn their neighbor towns, and so persist</line>
<line form="verse">With eager roads beyond their city York.</line>
<line form="verse">And never shall our bonny riders rest,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor rusting canker have the time to eat</line>
<line form="verse">Their light borne snaffles nor their nimble spurs,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor lay aside their Jacks of Gymould mayle,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor hang their staves of grained Scottish ash</line>
<line form="verse">In peaceful wise upon their city walls,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor from their buttoned tawny leathern belts</line>
<line form="verse">Dismiss their biting whinyards, till your King</line>
<line form="verse">Cry out, &#8220;Enough! Spare England now for pity!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Farewell, and tell him that you leave us here</line>
<line form="verse">Before this castle; say, you came from us,</line>
<line form="verse">Even when we had that yielded to our hands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I take my leave, and fairly will return</line>
<line form="verse">Your acceptable greeting to my king.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lorraine.</stagedir>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, Douglas, to our former task again,</line>
<line form="verse">For the division of this certain spoil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOUGLAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My liege, I crave the lady, and no more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, soft ye, sir; first I must make my choice,</line>
<line form="verse">And first I do bespeak her for myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOUGLAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then, my liege, let me enjoy her jewels.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Those are her own, still liable to her,</line>
<line form="verse">And who inherits her, hath those with all.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter First Scottish Messenger in haste.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SCOT. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My liege, as we were pricking on the hills,</line>
<line form="verse">To fetch in booty, marching hitherward,</line>
<line form="verse">We might descry a might host of men;</line>
<line form="verse">The sun, reflecting on the armour, shewed</line>
<line form="verse">A field of plate, a wood of picks advanced.</line>
<line form="verse">Bethink your highness speedily herein:</line>
<line form="verse">An easy march within four hours will bring</line>
<line form="verse">The hindmost rank unto this place, my liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dislodge, dislodge! It is the king of England.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOUGLAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Jemmy, my man, saddle my bonny black.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Meanst thou to fight, Douglas? We are too weak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOUGLAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know it well, my liege, and therefore fly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Coming forward.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">My lords of Scotland, will ye stay and drink?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She mocks at us, Douglas; I cannot endure it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say, good my lord, which is he must have the Lady,</line>
<line form="verse">And which her jewels? I am sure, my lords,</line>
<line form="verse">Ye will not hence, till you have shared the spoils.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She heard the messenger, and heard our talk;</line>
<line form="verse">And now that comfort makes her scorn at us.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Second Scottish Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SCOT. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Arm, my good lord! O, we are all surprised!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">After the French ambassador, my liege,</line>
<line form="verse">And tell him, that you dare not ride to York;</line>
<line form="verse">Excuse it that your bonny horse is lame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING DAVID.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She heard that too; intolerable grief!</line>
<line form="verse">Woman, farewell! Although I do not stay...</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Scots.</stagedir>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis not for fear, and yet you run away.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">O happy comfort, welcome to our house!</line>
<line form="verse">The confident and boisterous boasting Scot,</line>
<line form="verse">That swore before my walls they would not back</line>
<line form="verse">For all the armed power of this land,</line>
<line form="verse">With faceless fear that ever turns his back,</line>
<line form="verse">Turned hence against the blasting north-east wind</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the bare report and name of arms.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Mountague.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O Summer&#8217;s day! See where my Cousin comes!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOUNTAGUE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How fares my Aunt? We are not Scots;</line>
<line form="verse">Why do you shut your gates against your friends?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well may I give a welcome, cousin, to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">For thou comst well to chase my foes from hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOUNTAGUE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The king himself is come in person hither;</line>
<line form="verse">Dear aunt, descend, and gratulate his highness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How may I entertain his majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">To shew my duty and his dignity?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit, from above.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward, Warwick, Artois, with others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, are the stealing Foxes fled and gone,</line>
<line form="verse">Before we could uncouple at their heels?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They are, my liege; but, with a cheerful cry,</line>
<line form="verse">Hot hounds and hardy chase them at the heels.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Countess.</stagedir>
<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is the countess, Warwick, is it not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Even she, my liege; whose beauty tyrants fear,</line>
<line form="verse">As a May blossom with pernicious winds,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath sullied, withered, overcast, and done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hath she been fairer, Warwick, than she is?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious King, fair is she not at all,</line>
<line form="verse">If that herself were by to stain herself,</line>
<line form="verse">As I have scene her when she was herself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What strange enchantment lurked in those her eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">When they excelled this excellence they have,</line>
<line form="verse">That now her dim decline hath power to draw</line>
<line form="verse">My subject eyes from persing majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">To gaze on her with doting admiration?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In duty lower than the ground I kneel,</line>
<line form="verse">And for my dull knees bow my feeling heart,</line>
<line form="verse">To witness my obedience to your highness,</line>
<line form="verse">With many millions of a subject&#8217;s thanks</line>
<line form="verse">For this your royal presence, whose approach</line>
<line form="verse">Hath driven war and danger from my gate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lady, stand up; I come to bring thee peace,</line>
<line form="verse">How ever thereby I have purchased war.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No war to you, my liege; the Scots are gone,</line>
<line form="verse">And gallop home toward Scotland with their hate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Least, yielding here, I pine in shameful love,</line>
<line form="verse">Come, we&#8217;ll pursue the Scots;&#8212;Artois, away!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A little while, my gracious sovereign, stay,</line>
<line form="verse">And let the power of a mighty king</line>
<line form="verse">Honor our roof; my husband in the wars,</line>
<line form="verse">When he shall hear it, will triumph for joy;</line>
<line form="verse">Then, dear my liege, now niggard not thy state:</line>
<line form="verse">Being at the wall, enter our homely gate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pardon me, countess, I will come no near;</line>
<line form="verse">I dreamed tonight of treason, and I fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Far from this place let ugly treason lie!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No farther off, than her conspiring eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Which shoots infected poison in my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Beyond repulse of wit or cure of art.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, in the sun alone it doth not lie,</line>
<line form="verse">With light to take light from a mortal eye;</line>
<line form="verse">For here two day stars that mine eyes would see</line>
<line form="verse">More than the sun steals mine own light from me,</line>
<line form="verse">Contemplative desire, desire to be</line>
<line form="verse">In contemplation, that may master thee!</line>
<line form="verse">Warwick, Artois, to horse and let&#8217;s away!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What might I speak to make my sovereign stay?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What needs a tongue to such a speaking eye,</line>
<line form="verse">That more persuades than winning Oratory?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let not thy presence, like the April sun,</line>
<line form="verse">Flatter our earth and suddenly be done.</line>
<line form="verse">More happy do not make our outward wall</line>
<line form="verse">Than thou wilt grace our inner house withal.</line>
<line form="verse">Our house, my liege, is like a country swain,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose habit rude and manners blunt and plain</line>
<line form="verse">Presageth nought, yet inly beautified</line>
<line form="verse">With bounties, riches and faire hidden pride.</line>
<line form="verse">For where the golden ore doth buried lie,</line>
<line form="verse">The ground, undecked with nature&#8217;s tapestry,</line>
<line form="verse">Seems barren, sere, unfertile, fructless, dry;</line>
<line form="verse">And where the upper turf of earth doth boast</line>
<line form="verse">His pied perfumes and party coloured coat,</line>
<line form="verse">Delve there, and find this issue and their pride</line>
<line form="verse">To spring from ordure and corruption&#8217;s side.</line>
<line form="verse">But, to make up my all too long compare,</line>
<line form="verse">These ragged walls no testimony are,</line>
<line form="verse">What is within; but, like a cloak, doth hide</line>
<line form="verse">From weather&#8217;s Waste the under garnished pride.</line>
<line form="verse">More gracious then my terms can let thee be,</line>
<line form="verse">Intreat thyself to stay a while with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As wise, as fair; what fond fit can be heard,</line>
<line form="verse">When wisdom keeps the gate as beauty&#8217;s guard?&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">It shall attend, while I attend on thee:</line>
<line form="verse">Come on, my lords; here will I host tonight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Roxborough. The gardens of the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lodowick, King Edward, Countess of Salisbury, Warwick)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lodowick considers the King&#8217;s behavior, and, concluding that he is in love with the Countess, infers that war-making is off the schedule for a while. The besotted King asks Lodowick to write a love letter to the Countess for him. As it turns out, the King is rather a backseat driver when it comes to writing, and particularly objects to any references to chastity, as this is scarcely what he has in mind. The King is quite unimpressed by Lodowick&#8217;s efforts and dismisses him, but before he can begin to write himself the Countess comes in and he begins rather crassly to woo her. She makes the mistake of promising to give him whatever he wants before she knows what it is, but defends herself quite spiritedly when she finds out what his intentions are, and walks out. This resistance is unexpected, and Edward swears to himself that he will have her. He begins to work on her father, Warwick, instead, tricking him into swearing to force his daughter to acquiesce. He is horrified but, having sworn, makes himself go through with it. When the Countess responds to his half-hearted attempt with outrage, he is delighted. </scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lodowick.</stagedir>
 
<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I might perceive his eye in her eye lost,</line>
<line form="verse">His ear to drink her sweet tongue&#8217;s utterance,</line>
<line form="verse">And changing passion, like inconstant clouds</line>
<line form="verse">That rack upon the carriage of the winds,</line>
<line form="verse">Increase and die in his disturbed cheeks.</line>
<line form="verse">Lo, when she blushed, even then did he look pale,</line>
<line form="verse">As if her cheeks by some enchanted power</line>
<line form="verse">Attracted had the cherry blood from his:</line>
<line form="verse">Anon, with reverent fear when she grew pale,</line>
<line form="verse">His cheeks put on their scarlet ornaments;</line>
<line form="verse">But no more like her oriental red,</line>
<line form="verse">Than brick to coral or live things to dead.</line>
<line form="verse">Why did he then thus counterfeit her looks?</line>
<line form="verse">If she did blush, twas tender modest shame,</line>
<line form="verse">Being in the sacred presence of a King;</line>
<line form="verse">If he did blush, twas red immodest shame,</line>
<line form="verse">To veil his eyes amiss, being a king;</line>
<line form="verse">If she looked pale, twas silly woman&#8217;s fear,</line>
<line form="verse">To bear herself in presence of a king;</line>
<line form="verse">If he looked pale, it was with guilty fear,</line>
<line form="verse">To dote amiss, being a mighty king.</line>
<line form="verse">Then, Scottish wars, farewell; I fear twill prove</line>
<line form="verse">A lingering English siege of peevish love.</line>
<line form="verse">Here comes his highness, walking all alone.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She is grown more fairer far since I came hither,</line>
<line form="verse">Her voice more silver every word than other,</line>
<line form="verse">Her wit more fluent. What a strange discourse</line>
<line form="verse">Unfolded she of David and his Scots!</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Even thus,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;he spake,&#8221; and then spoke broad,</line>
<line form="verse">With epithites and accents of the Scot,</line>
<line form="verse">But somewhat better than the Scot could speak:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;And thus,&#8221; quoth she, and answered then herself&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">For who could speak like her but she herself&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Breathes from the wall an angel&#8217;s note from heaven</line>
<line form="verse">Of sweet defiance to her barbarous foes.</line>
<line form="verse">When she would talk of peace, methinks, her tongue</line>
<line form="verse">Commanded war to prison; when of war,</line>
<line form="verse">It wakened Caesar from his Roman grave,</line>
<line form="verse">To hear war beautified by her discourse.</line>
<line form="verse">Wisdom is foolishness but in her tongue,</line>
<line form="verse">Beauty a slander but in her fair face,</line>
<line form="verse">There is no summer but in her cheerful looks,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor frosty winter but in her disdain.</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot blame the Scots that did besiege her,</line>
<line form="verse">For she is all the treasure of our land;</line>
<line form="verse">But call them cowards, that they ran away,</line>
<line form="verse">Having so rich and fair a cause to stay.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Art thou there, Lodowick? Give me ink and paper.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And bid the lords hold on their play at chess,</line>
<line form="verse">For we will walk and meditate alone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my sovereign.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lodowick.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This fellow is well read in poetry,</line>
<line form="verse">And hath a lusty and persuasive spirit;</line>
<line form="verse">I will acquaint him with my passion,</line>
<line form="verse">Which he shall shadow with a veil of lawn,</line>
<line form="verse">Through which the queen of beauties queen shall see</line>
<line form="verse">Her self the ground of my infirmity.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lodowick.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hast thou pen, ink, and paper ready, Lodowick?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ready, my liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then in the summer arbor sit by me,</line>
<line form="verse">Make it our counsel house or cabinet:</line>
<line form="verse">Since green our thoughts, green be the conventicle,</line>
<line form="verse">Where we will ease us by disburdening them.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, Lodowick, invocate some golden muse,</line>
<line form="verse">To bring thee hither an enchanted pen,</line>
<line form="verse">That may for sighs set down true sighs indeed,</line>
<line form="verse">Talking of grief, to make thee ready groan;</line>
<line form="verse">And when thou writest of tears, encouch the word</line>
<line form="verse">Before and after with such sweet laments,</line>
<line form="verse">That it may raise drops in a Tartar&#8217;s eye,</line>
<line form="verse">And make a flintheart Scythian pitiful;</line>
<line form="verse">For so much moving hath a Poet&#8217;s pen:</line>
<line form="verse">Then, if thou be a poet, move thou so,</line>
<line form="verse">And be enriched by thy sovereign&#8217;s love.</line>
<line form="verse">For, if the touch of sweet concordant strings</line>
<line form="verse">Could force attendance in the ears of hell,</line>
<line form="verse">How much more shall the strains of poets&#8217; wit</line>
<line form="verse">Beguile and ravish soft and humane minds?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To whom, my lord, shall I direct my stile?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To one that shames the fair and sots the wise;</line>
<line form="verse">Whose bod is an abstract or a brief,</line>
<line form="verse">Contains each general virtue in the world.</line>
<line form="verse">Better than beautiful thou must begin,</line>
<line form="verse">Devise for fair a fairer word than fair,</line>
<line form="verse">And every ornament that thou wouldest praise,</line>
<line form="verse">Fly it a pitch above the soar of praise.</line>
<line form="verse">For flattery fear thou not to be convicted;</line>
<line form="verse">For, were thy admiration ten times more,</line>
<line form="verse">Ten times ten thousand more the worth exceeds</line>
<line form="verse">Of that thou art to praise, thy praises worth.</line>
<line form="verse">Begin; I will to contemplate the while:</line>
<line form="verse">Forget not to set down, how passionate,</line>
<line form="verse">How heart sick, and how full of languishment,</line>
<line form="verse">Her beauty makes me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Write I to a woman?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What beauty else could triumph over me,</line>
<line form="verse">Or who but women do our love lays greet?</line>
<line form="verse">What, thinkest thou I did bid thee praise a horse?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of what condition or estate she is,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twere requisite that I should know, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of such estate, that hers is as a throne,</line>
<line form="verse">And my estate the footstool where she treads:</line>
<line form="verse">Then mayst thou judge what her condition is</line>
<line form="verse">By the proportion of her mightiness.</line>
<line form="verse">Write on, while I peruse her in my thoughts.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Her voice to music or the nightingale&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">To music every summer leaping swain</line>
<line form="verse">Compares his sunburnt lover when she speaks;</line>
<line form="verse">And why should I speak of the nightingale?</line>
<line form="verse">The nightingale sings of adulterate wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">And that, compared, is too satyrical;</line>
<line form="verse">For sin, though sin, would not be so esteemed,</line>
<line form="verse">But, rather, virtue sin, sin virtue deemed.</line>
<line form="verse">Her hair, far softer than the silk worm&#8217;s twist,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a flattering glass, doth make more fair</line>
<line form="verse">The yellow Amber:&#8212;like a flattering glass</line>
<line form="verse">Comes in too soon; for, writing of her eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say that like a glass they catch the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">And thence the hot reflection doth rebound</line>
<line form="verse">Against the breast, and burns my heart within.</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, what a world of descant makes my soul</line>
<line form="verse">Upon this voluntary ground of love!&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Come, Lodowick, hast thou turned thy ink to gold?</line>
<line form="verse">If not, write but in letters capital</line>
<line form="verse">My mistress&#8217; name, and it will gild thy paper:</line>
<line form="verse">Read, lord, read;</line>
<line form="verse">Fill thou the empty hollows of mine ears</line>
<line form="verse">With the sweet hearing of thy poetry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have not to a period brought her praise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Her praise is as my love, both infinite,</line>
<line form="verse">Which apprehend such violent extremes,</line>
<line form="verse">That they disdain an ending period.</line>
<line form="verse">Her beauty hath no match but my affection;</line>
<line form="verse">Hers more than most, mine most and more than more:</line>
<line form="verse">Hers more to praise than tell the sea by drops,</line>
<line form="verse">Nay, more than drop the massy earth by sands,</line>
<line form="verse">And sand by sand print them in memory:</line>
<line form="verse">Then wherefore talkest thou of a period</line>
<line form="verse">To that which craves unended admiration?</line>
<line form="verse">Read, let us hear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;More fair and chaste than is the queen of shades,&#8221;&#8212;</recite></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That line hath two faults, gross and palpable:</line>
<line form="verse">Comparest thou her to the pale queen of night,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, being set in dark, seems therefore light?</line>
<line form="verse">What is she, when the sun lifts up his head,</line>
<line form="verse">But like a fading taper, dim and dead?</line>
<line form="verse">My love shall brave the eye of heaven at noon,</line>
<line form="verse">And, being unmasked, outshine the golden sun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is the other fault, my sovereign lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Read o&#8217;er the line again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;More fair and chaste&#8221;&#8212;</recite></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did not bid thee talk of chastity,</line>
<line form="verse">To ransack so the treasure of her mind;</line>
<line form="verse">For I had rather have her chased than chaste.</line>
<line form="verse">Out with the moon line, I will none of it;</line>
<line form="verse">And let me have her likened to the sun:</line>
<line form="verse">Say she hath thrice more splendour than the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">That her perfections emulate the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">That she breeds sweets as plenteous as the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">That she doth thaw cold winter like the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">That she doth cheer fresh summer like the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">The she doth dazzle gazers like the sun;</line>
<line form="verse">And, in this application to the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">Bid her be free and general as the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">Who smiles upon the basest weed that grows</line>
<line form="verse">As lovingly as on the fragrant rose.</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s see what follows that same moonlight line.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;More fair and chaste than is the queen of shades,</line>
<line form="verse">More bold in constance&#8221;&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">In constance! Than who?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Than Judith was.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O monstrous line! Put in the next a sword,</line>
<line form="verse">And I shall woo her to cut of my head.</line>
<line form="verse">Blot, blot, good Lodowick! Let us hear the next.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s all that yet is done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I thank thee then; thou hast done little ill,</line>
<line form="verse">But what is done, is passing, passing ill.</line>
<line form="verse">No, let the captain talk of boisterous war,</line>
<line form="verse">The prisoner of emured dark constraint,</line>
<line form="verse">The sick man best sets down the pangs of death,</line>
<line form="verse">The man that starves the sweetness of a feast,</line>
<line form="verse">The frozen soul the benefit of fire,</line>
<line form="verse">And every grief his happy opposite:</line>
<line form="verse">Love cannot sound well but in lover&#8217;s tongues;</line>
<line form="verse">Give me the pen and paper, I will write.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Countess.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">But soft, here comes the treasurer of my spirit.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Lodowick, thou knowst not how to draw a battle;</line>
<line form="verse">These wings, these flankers, and these squadrons</line>
<line form="verse">Argue in thee defective discipline:</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shouldest have placed this here, this other here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pardon my boldness, my thrice gracious lords;</line>
<line form="verse">Let my intrusion here be called my duty,</line>
<line form="verse">That comes to see my sovereign how he fares.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, draw the same, I tell thee in what form.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lodowick.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sorry I am to see my liege so sad:</line>
<line form="verse">What may thy subject do to drive from thee</line>
<line form="verse">Thy gloomy consort, sullome melancholy?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, lady, I am blunt and cannot straw</line>
<line form="verse">The flowers of solace in a ground of shame:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Since I came hither, Countess, I am wronged.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now God forbid that any in my house</line>
<line form="verse">Should think my sovereign wrong! Thrice gentle King,</line>
<line form="verse">Acquaint me with your cause of discontent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How near then shall I be to remedy?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As near, my liege, as all my woman&#8217;s power</line>
<line form="verse">Can pawn itself to buy thy remedy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If thou speakst true, then have I my redress:</line>
<line form="verse">Engage thy power to redeem my Joys,</line>
<line form="verse">And I am joyful, Countess; else I die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my Liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Swear, Countess, that thou wilt.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By heaven, I will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then take thyself a little way a side,</line>
<line form="verse">And tell thyself, a king doth dote on thee;</line>
<line form="verse">Say that within thy power it doth lie</line>
<line form="verse">To make him happy, and that thou hast sworn</line>
<line form="verse">To give him all the joy within thy power:</line>
<line form="verse">Do this, and tell me when I shall be happy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All this is done, my thrice dread sovereign:</line>
<line form="verse">That power of love, that I have power to give,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast with all devout obedience;</line>
<line form="verse">Employ me how thou wilt in proof thereof.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou hear&#8217;st me say that I do dote on thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If on my beauty, take it if thou canst;</line>
<line form="verse">Though little, I do prize it ten times less;</line>
<line form="verse">If on my virtue, take it if thou canst,</line>
<line form="verse">For virtue&#8217;s store by giving doth augment;</line>
<line form="verse">Be it on what it will, that I can give</line>
<line form="verse">And thou canst take away, inherit it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is thy beauty that I would enjoy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, were it painted, I would wipe it off</line>
<line form="verse">And dispossess myself, to give it thee.</line>
<line form="verse">But, sovereign, it is soldered to my life:</line>
<line form="verse">Take one and both; for, like an humble shadow,</line>
<line form="verse">It haunts the sunshine of my summer&#8217;s life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But thou mayst lend it me to sport with all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As easy may my intellectual soul</line>
<line form="verse">Be lent away, and yet my body live,</line>
<line form="verse">As lend my body, palace to my soul,</line>
<line form="verse">Away from her, and yet retain my soul.</line>
<line form="verse">My body is her bower, her court, her abbey,</line>
<line form="verse">And she an angel, pure, divine, unspotted:</line>
<line form="verse">If I should leave her house, my lord, to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">I kill my poor soul and my poor soul me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Didst thou not swear to give me what I would?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did, my liege, so what you would I could.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I wish no more of thee than thou mayst give:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor beg I do not, but I rather buy&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">That is, thy love; and for that love of thine</line>
<line form="verse">In rich exchange I tender to thee mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But that your lips were sacred, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">You would profane the holy name of love.</line>
<line form="verse">That love you offer me you cannot give,</line>
<line form="verse">For Caesar owes that tribute to his queen;</line>
<line form="verse">That love you beg of me I cannot give,</line>
<line form="verse">For Sara owes that duty to her lord.</line>
<line form="verse">He that doth clip or counterfeit your stamp</line>
<line form="verse">Shall die, my lord; and will your sacred self</line>
<line form="verse">Commit high treason against the King of Heaven,</line>
<line form="verse">To stamp his image in forbidden metal,</line>
<line form="verse">Forgetting your allegiance and your oath?</line>
<line form="verse">In violating marriage sacred law,</line>
<line form="verse">You break a greater honor than yourself:</line>
<line form="verse">To be a king is of a younger house</line>
<line form="verse">Than to be married; your progenitour,</line>
<line form="verse">Sole reigning Adam on the universe,</line>
<line form="verse">By God was honored for a married man,</line>
<line form="verse">But not by him anointed for a king.</line>
<line form="verse">It is a penalty to break your statutes,</line>
<line form="verse">Though not enacted with your highness&#8217; hand:</line>
<line form="verse">How much more, to infringe the holy act,</line>
<line form="verse">Made by the mouth of God, sealed with his hand?</line>
<line form="verse">I know, my sovereign, in my husband&#8217;s love,</line>
<line form="verse">Who now doth loyal service in his wars,</line>
<line form="verse">Doth but so try the wife of Salisbury,</line>
<line form="verse">Whither she will hear a wanton&#8217;s tale or no,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest being therein guilty by my stay,</line>
<line form="verse">From that, not from my liege, I turn away.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whether is her beauty by her words dying,</line>
<line form="verse">Or are her words sweet chaplains to her beauty?</line>
<line form="verse">Like as the wind doth beautify a sail,</line>
<line form="verse">And as a sail becomes the unseen wind,</line>
<line form="verse">So do her words her beauties, beauties words.</line>
<line form="verse">O, that I were a honey gathering bee,</line>
<line form="verse">To bear the comb of virtue from this flower,</line>
<line form="verse">And not a poison sucking envious spider,</line>
<line form="verse">To turn the juice I take to deadly venom!</line>
<line form="verse">Religion is austere and beauty gentle;</line>
<line form="verse">Too strict a guardian for so fair a ward!</line>
<line form="verse">O, that she were, as is the air, to me!</line>
<line form="verse">Why, so she is, for when I would embrace her,</line>
<line form="verse">This do I, and catch nothing but myself.</line>
<line form="verse">I must enjoy her; for I cannot beat</line>
<line form="verse">With reason and reproof fond love a way.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Warwick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here comes her father: I will work with him,</line>
<line form="verse">To bear my colours in this field of love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How is it that my sovereign is so sad?</line>
<line form="verse">May I with pardon know your highness grief;</line>
<line form="verse">And that my old endeavor will remove it,</line>
<line form="verse">It shall not cumber long your majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A kind and voluntary gift thou proferest,</line>
<line form="verse">That I was forward to have begged of thee.</line>
<line form="verse">But, O thou world, great nurse of flattery,</line>
<line form="verse">Why dost thou tip men&#8217;s tongues with golden words,</line>
<line form="verse">And peise their deeds with weight of heavy lead,</line>
<line form="verse">That fair performance cannot follow promise?</line>
<line form="verse">O, that a man might hold the heart&#8217;s close book</line>
<line form="verse">And choke the lavish tongue, when it doth utter</line>
<line form="verse">The breath of falsehood not charactered there!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Far be it from the honor of my age,</line>
<line form="verse">That I should owe bright gold and render lead;</line>
<line form="verse">Age is a cynic, not a flatterer.</line>
<line form="verse">I say again, that if I knew your grief,</line>
<line form="verse">And that by me it may be lessened,</line>
<line form="verse">My proper harm should buy your Highness&#8217; good.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These are the vulgar tenders of false men,</line>
<line form="verse">That never pay the duty of their words.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wilt not stick to swear what thou hast said;</line>
<line form="verse">But, when thou knowest my grief&#8217;s condition,</line>
<line form="verse">This rash disgorged vomit of thy word</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wilt eat up again, and leave me helpless.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By heaven, I will not, though your majesty</line>
<line form="verse">Did bid me run upon your sword and die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say that my grief is no way medicinable</line>
<line form="verse">But by the loss and bruising of thine honour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If nothing but that loss may vantage you,</line>
<line form="verse">I would accompt that loss my vantage too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thinkst that thou canst unswear thy oath again?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I cannot; nor I would not, if I could.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But, if thou dost, what shall I say to thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What may be said to any perjured villain,</line>
<line form="verse">That breaks the sacred warrant of an oath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What wilt thou say to one that breaks an oath?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That he hath broke his faith with God and man,</line>
<line form="verse">And from them both stands excommunicate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What office were it, to suggest a man</line>
<line form="verse">To break a lawful and religious vow?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An office for the devil, not for man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That devil&#8217;s office must thou do for me,</line>
<line form="verse">Or break thy oath, or cancel all the bonds</line>
<line form="verse">Of love and duty twixt thyself and me;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore, Warwick, if thou art thyself,</line>
<line form="verse">The lord and master of thy word and oath,</line>
<line form="verse">Go to thy daughter; and in my behalf</line>
<line form="verse">Command her, woo her, win her any ways,</line>
<line form="verse">To be my mistress and my secret love.</line>
<line form="verse">I will not stand to hear thee make reply:</line>
<line form="verse">Thy oath break hers, or let thy sovereign die.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O doting King! O detestable office!</line>
<line form="verse">Well may I tempt myself to wrong myself,</line>
<line form="verse">When he hath sworn me by the name of God</line>
<line form="verse">To break a vow made by the name of God.</line>
<line form="verse">What, if I swear by this right hand of mine</line>
<line form="verse">To cut this right hand off? The better way</line>
<line form="verse">Were to profane the Idol than confound it:</line>
<line form="verse">But neither will I do; I&#8217;ll keep mine oath,</line>
<line form="verse">And to my daughter make a recantation</line>
<line form="verse">Of all the virtue I have preacht to her:</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say, she must forget her husband Salisbury,</line>
<line form="verse">If she remember to embrace the king;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say, an oath may easily be broken,</line>
<line form="verse">But not so easily pardoned, being broken;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say, it is true charity to love,</line>
<line form="verse">But not true love to be so charitable;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say, his greatness may bear out the shame,</line>
<line form="verse">But not his kingdom can buy out the sin;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll say, it is my duty to persuade,</line>
<line form="verse">But not her honesty to give consent.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Countess.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">See where she comes; was never father had</line>
<line form="verse">Against his child an embassage so bad?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord and father, I have sought for you:</line>
<line form="verse">My mother and the Peers importune you</line>
<line form="verse">To keep in presence of his majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">And do your best to make his highness merry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How shall I enter in this graceless arrant?</line>
<line form="verse">I must not call her child, for where&#8217;s the father</line>
<line form="verse">That will in such a suit seduce his child?</line>
<line form="verse">Then, &#8220;wife of Salisbury&#8221;; shall I so begin?</line>
<line form="verse">No, he&#8217;s my friend, and where is found the friend</line>
<line form="verse">That will do friendship such indammagement?</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To the Countess.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Neither my daughter nor my dear friend&#8217;s wife,</line>
<line form="verse">I am not Warwick, as thou thinkst I am,</line>
<line form="verse">But an attorney from the court of hell,</line>
<line form="verse">That thus have housed my spirit in his form,</line>
<line form="verse">To do a message to thee from the king.</line>
<line form="verse">The mighty king of England dotes on thee:</line>
<line form="verse">He that hath power to take away thy life,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath power to take thy honor; then consent</line>
<line form="verse">To pawn thine honor rather than thy life:</line>
<line form="verse">Honor is often lost and got again,</line>
<line form="verse">But life, once gone, hath no recovery.</line>
<line form="verse">The sun, that withers hay, doth nourish grass;</line>
<line form="verse">The king, that would disdain thee, will advance thee.</line>
<line form="verse">The poets write that great Achilles&#8217; spear</line>
<line form="verse">Could heal the wound it made: the moral is,</line>
<line form="verse">What mighty men misdo, they can amend.</line>
<line form="verse">The lion doth become his bloody jaws,</line>
<line form="verse">And grace his forragement by being mild,</line>
<line form="verse">When vassel fear lies trembling at his feet.</line>
<line form="verse">The king will in his glory hide thy shame;</line>
<line form="verse">And those that gaze on him to find out thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Will lose their eyesight, looking in the sun.</line>
<line form="verse">What can one drop of poison harm the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose huge vastures can digest the ill</line>
<line form="verse">And make it loose his operation?</line>
<line form="verse">The king&#8217;s great name will temper thy misdeeds,</line>
<line form="verse">And give the bitter potion of reproach,</line>
<line form="verse">A sugared, sweet and most delicious taste.</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, it is no harm to do the thing</line>
<line form="verse">Which without shame could not be left undone.</line>
<line form="verse">Thus have I in his majesty&#8217;s behalf</line>
<line form="verse">Appareled sin in virtuous sentences,</line>
<line form="verse">And dwell upon thy answer in his suit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unnatural besiege! Woe me unhappy,</line>
<line form="verse">To have escaped the danger of my foes,</line>
<line form="verse">And to be ten times worse injured by friends!</line>
<line form="verse">Hath he no means to stain my honest blood,</line>
<line form="verse">But to corrupt the author of my blood</line>
<line form="verse">To be his scandalous and vile solicitor?</line>
<line form="verse">No marvel though the branches be then infected,</line>
<line form="verse">When poison hath encompassed the root:</line>
<line form="verse">No marvel though the leprous infant die,</line>
<line form="verse">When the stern dame invenometh the Dug.</line>
<line form="verse">Why then, give sin a passport to offend,</line>
<line form="verse">And youth the dangerous reign of liberty:</line>
<line form="verse">Blot out the strict forbidding of the law,</line>
<line form="verse">And cancel every cannon that prescribes</line>
<line form="verse">A shame for shame or penance for offence.</line>
<line form="verse">No, let me die, if his too boistrous will</line>
<line form="verse">Will have it so, before I will consent</line>
<line form="verse">To be an actor in his graceless lust.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WARWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, now thou speakst as I would have thee speak:</line>
<line form="verse">And mark how I unsay my words again.</line>
<line form="verse">An honorable grave is more esteemed</line>
<line form="verse">Than the polluted closet of a king:</line>
<line form="verse">The greater man, the greater is the thing,</line>
<line form="verse">Be it good or bad, that he shall undertake:</line>
<line form="verse">An unreputed mote, flying in the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">Presents a greater substance than it is:</line>
<line form="verse">The freshest summer&#8217;s day doth soonest taint</line>
<line form="verse">The loathed carrion that it seems to kiss:</line>
<line form="verse">Deep are the blows made with a mighty axe:</line>
<line form="verse">That sin doth ten times aggravate itself,</line>
<line form="verse">That is committed in a holy place:</line>
<line form="verse">An evil deed, done by authority,</line>
<line form="verse">Is sin and subornation: deck an ape</line>
<line form="verse">In tissue, and the beauty of the robe</line>
<line form="verse">Adds but the greater scorn unto the beast.</line>
<line form="verse">A spatious field of reasons could I urge</line>
<line form="verse">Between his glory, daughter, and thy shame:</line>
<line form="verse">That poison shews worst in a golden cup;</line>
<line form="verse">Dark night seems darker by the lightning flash;</line>
<line form="verse">Lilies that fester smell far worse than weeds;</line>
<line form="verse">And every glory that inclines to sin,</line>
<line form="verse">The shame is treble by the opposite.</line>
<line form="verse">So leave I with my blessing in thy bosom,</line>
<line form="verse">Which then convert to a most heavy curse,</line>
<line form="verse">When thou convertest from honor&#8217;s golden name</line>
<line form="verse">To the black faction of bed blotting shame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll follow thee; and when my mind turns so,</line>
<line form="verse">My body sink my soul in endless woe!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Roxborough. Another part of the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Derby, Audley, King, Lodowick, Prince Edward, Countess of Salisbury)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Earl of Derby and Audley meet up, having respectively mustered men and gained support from the Emperor for the expedition to France. The King, however, is so busy mooning over the Countess that he cannot keep his mind on military matters. In fact, he is losing all interest in war. Luckily, his son Prince Edward arrives with the troops he has raised, prepared to go to France. The King notes the resemblance between the Prince and his mother, and begins to realize how out-of-control his behavior is. This does not prevent him from joyously greeting the Countess when he believes she has arrived to yield to him, and at her request promising to execute both her husband and his wife. As a last resort, she pulls out a dagger and threatens to kill herself if he persists in his suit. Realizing that the case is hopeless, he swears to leave her alone, and goes off to conquer France instead.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter at one door Derby from France, At an other door Audley with a Drum.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thrice noble Audley, well encount&#8217;red here!</line>
<line form="verse">How is it with our sovereign and his peers?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis full a fortnight, since I saw his highness</line>
<line form="verse">What time he sent me forth to muster men;</line>
<line form="verse">Which I accordingly have done, and bring them hither</line>
<line form="verse">In fair array before his majesty.</line>
<line form="verse">What news, my Lord of Derby, from the Emperor?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As good as we desire: the Emperor</line>
<line form="verse">Hath yielded to his highness friendly aid,</line>
<line form="verse">And makes our king lieutenant general</line>
<line form="verse">In all his lands and large dominions;</line>
<line form="verse">Then <italian xml:lang="it">via</italian>! For the spatious bounds of France!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, doth his highness leap to hear these news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have not yet found time to open them;</line>
<line form="verse">The king is in his closet, malcontent;</line>
<line form="verse">For what, I know not, but he gave in charge,</line>
<line form="verse">Till after dinner none should interrupt him:</line>
<line form="verse">The Countess Salisbury and her father Warwick,</line>
<line form="verse">Artois and all look underneath the brows.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Undoubtedly, then, some thing is amiss.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Trumpet within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The trumpets sound, the king is now abroad.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the King.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here comes his highness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Befall my sovereign all my sovereign&#8217;s wish!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, that thou wert a witch to make it so!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Emperor greeteth you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Presenting Letters.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Would it were the Countess!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And hath accorded to your highness suite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Thou liest, she hath not; but I would she had.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All love and duty to my lord the King!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Well, all but one is none.&#8212;What news with you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have, my liege, levied those horse and foot</line>
<line form="verse">According to your charge, and brought them hither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then let those foot trudge hence upon those horse</line>
<line form="verse">According to our discharge, and be gone.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Darby, I&#8217;ll look upon the Countess&#8217; mind anon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Countess&#8217; mind, my liege?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I mean the Emperor. Leave me alone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is his mind?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Let&#8217;s leave him to his humor.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thus from the heart&#8217;s aboundance speaks the tongue;</line>
<line form="verse">Countess for Emperor: and, indeed, why not?</line>
<line form="verse">She is as imperator over me, and I to her</line>
<line form="verse">Am as a kneeling vassal, that observes</line>
<line form="verse">The pleasure or displeasure of her eye.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What says the more than Cleopatra&#8217;s match</line>
<line form="verse">To Caesar now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That yet, my liege, ere night</line>
<line form="verse">She will resolve your majesty.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Drum within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What drum is this that thunders forth this march,</line>
<line form="verse">To start the tender Cupid in my bosom?</line>
<line form="verse">Poor sheepskin, how it brawls with him that beateth it!</line>
<line form="verse">Go, break the thundring parchment bottom out,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will teach it to conduct sweet lines</line>
<line form="verse">Unto the bosom of a heavenly nymph;</line>
<line form="verse">For I will use it as my writing paper,</line>
<line form="verse">And so reduce him from a scolding drum</line>
<line form="verse">To be the herald and dear counsel bearer</line>
<line form="verse">Betwixt a goddess and a mighty king.</line>
<line form="verse">Go, bid the drummer learn to touch the Lute,</line>
<line form="verse">Or hang him in the braces of his drum,</line>
<line form="verse">For now we think it an uncivil thing,</line>
<line form="verse">To trouble heaven with such harsh resounds:</line>
<line form="verse">Away!</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The quarrel that I have requires no arms</line>
<line form="verse">But these of mine: and these shall meet my foe</line>
<line form="verse">In a deep march of penetrable groans;</line>
<line form="verse">My eyes shall be my arrows, and my sighs</line>
<line form="verse">Shall serve me as the vantage of the wind,</line>
<line form="verse">To whirl away my sweetest artillery.</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, but, alas, she wins the sun of me,</line>
<line form="verse">For that is she herself, and thence it comes</line>
<line form="verse">That poets term the wanton warrior blind;</line>
<line form="verse">But love hath eyes as judgement to his steps,</line>
<line form="verse">Till too much loved glory dazzles them.&#8212;</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My liege, the drum that stroke the lusty march,</line>
<line form="verse">Stands with Prince Edward, your thrice valiant son.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Prince Edward.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I see the boy; oh, how his mother&#8217;s face,</line>
<line form="verse">Modeled in his, corrects my strayed desire,</line>
<line form="verse">And rates my heart, and chides my thievish eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, being rich enough in seeing her,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet seeks elsewhere: and basest theft is that</line>
<line form="verse">Which cannot cloak itself on poverty.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Now, boy, what news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have assembled, my dear lord and father,</line>
<line form="verse">The choicest buds of all our English blood</line>
<line form="verse">For our affairs in France; and here we come</line>
<line form="verse">To take direction from your majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Still do I see in him delineate</line>
<line form="verse">His mother&#8217;s visage; those his eyes are hers,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, looking wistely on me, make me blush:</line>
<line form="verse">For faults against themselves give evidence;</line>
<line form="verse">Lust is fire, and men like lanthornes show</line>
<line form="verse">Light lust within themselves, even through themselves.</line>
<line form="verse">Away, loose silks of wavering vanity!</line>
<line form="verse">Shall the large limit of fair Britain</line>
<line form="verse">By me be overthrown, and shall I not</line>
<line form="verse">Master this little mansion of myself?</line>
<line form="verse">Give me an armor of eternal steel!</line>
<line form="verse">I go to conquer kings; and shall I not then</line>
<line form="verse">Subdue myself? And be my enemy&#8217;s friend?</line>
<line form="verse">It must not be.&#8212;Come, boy, forward, advance!</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s with our colours sweet the air of France.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lodowick.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LODOWICK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My liege, the Countess with a smiling cheer</line>
<line form="verse">Desires access unto your Majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, there it goes! That very smile of hers</line>
<line form="verse">Hath ransomed captive France, and set the King,</line>
<line form="verse">The Dauphin, and the peers at liberty.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Go, leave me, Ned, and revel with thy friends.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Prince Edward.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Thy mother is but black, and thou, like her,</line>
<line form="verse">Dost put it in my mind how foul she is.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Go, fetch the Countess hither in thy hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And let her chase away these winter clouds,</line>
<line form="verse">For she gives beauty both to heaven and earth.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The sin is more to hack and hew poor men,</line>
<line form="verse">Than to embrace in an unlawful bed</line>
<line form="verse">The register of all rarities</line>
<line form="verse">Since leatheren Adam till this youngest hour.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Countess escorted by Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Go, Lodowick, put thy hand into my purse,</line>
<line form="verse">Play, spend, give, riot, waste, do what thou wilt,</line>
<line form="verse">So thou wilt hence awhile and leave me here.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lodowick.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now, my soul&#8217;s playfellow, art thou come</line>
<line form="verse">To speak the more than heavenly word of &#8220;yea&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">To my objection in thy beauteous love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My father on his blessing hath commanded&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That thou shalt yield to me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, dear my liege, your due.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And that, my dearest love, can be no less</line>
<line form="verse">Than right for right and tender love for love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then wrong for wrong and endless hate for hate.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">But,&#8212;sith I see your majesty so bent,</line>
<line form="verse">That my unwillingness, my husband&#8217;s love,</line>
<line form="verse">Your high estate, nor no respect respected</line>
<line form="verse">Can be my help, but that your mightiness</line>
<line form="verse">Will overbear and awe these dear regards&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I bind my discontent to my content,</line>
<line form="verse">And what I would not I&#8217;ll compel I will,</line>
<line form="verse">Provided that yourself remove those lets</line>
<line form="verse">That stand between your highness&#8217; love and mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Name them, fair Countess, and, by heaven, I will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is their lives that stand between our love,</line>
<line form="verse">That I would have choked up, my sovereign.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whose lives, my Lady?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My thrice loving liege,</line>
<line form="verse">Your Queen and Salisbury, my wedded husband,</line>
<line form="verse">Who living have that title in our love,</line>
<line form="verse">That we cannot bestow but by their death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy opposition is beyond our Law.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So is your desire: if the law</line>
<line form="verse">Can hinder you to execute the one,</line>
<line form="verse">Let it forbid you to attempt the other.</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot think you love me as you say,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless you do make good what you have sworn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No more; thy husband and the Queen shall die.</line>
<line form="verse">Fairer thou art by far than Hero was,</line>
<line form="verse">Beardless Leander not so strong as I:</line>
<line form="verse">He swom an easy current for his love,</line>
<line form="verse">But I will through a Hellespont of blood,</line>
<line form="verse">To arrive at Sestos where my Hero lies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, You&#8217;ll do more; You&#8217;ll make the river to</line>
<line form="verse">With their heart bloods that keep our love asunder,</line>
<line form="verse">Of which my husband and your wife are twain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy beauty makes them guilty of their death</line>
<line form="verse">And gives in evidence that they shall die;</line>
<line form="verse">Upon which verdict I, their Judge, condemn them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O perjured beauty, more corrupted judge!</line>
<line form="verse">When to the great star-chamber o&#8217;er our heads</line>
<line form="verse">The universal sessions calls to count</line>
<line form="verse">This packing evil, we both shall tremble for it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What says my fair love? Is she resolute?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNTESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Resolute to be dissolute; and, therefore, this:</line>
<line form="verse">Keep but thy word, great king, and I am thine.</line>
<line form="verse">Stand where thou dost, I&#8217;ll part a little from thee,</line>
<line form="verse">And see how I will yield me to thy hands.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Turning suddenly upon him, and showing two daggers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here by my side doth hang my wedding knifes:</line>
<line form="verse">Take thou the one, and with it kill thy Queen,</line>
<line form="verse">And learn by me to find her where she lies;</line>
<line form="verse">And with this other I&#8217;ll dispatch my love,</line>
<line form="verse">Which now lies fast a sleep within my heart:</line>
<line form="verse">When they are gone, then I&#8217;ll consent to love.</line>
<line form="verse">Stir not, lascivious king, to hinder me;</line>
<line form="verse">My resolution is more nimbler far,</line>
<line form="verse">Than thy prevention can be in my rescue,</line>
<line form="verse">And if thou stir, I strike; therefore, stand still,</line>
<line form="verse">And hear the choice that I will put thee to:</line>
<line form="verse">Either swear to leave thy most unholy suit</line>
<line form="verse">And never hence forth to solicit me;</line>
<line form="verse">Or else, by heaven, this sharp-pointed knife</line>
<line form="verse">Shall stain thy earth with that which thou would stain,</line>
<line form="verse">My poor chaste blood. Swear, Edward, swear,</line>
<line form="verse">Or I will strike and die before thee here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Even by that power I swear, that gives me now</line>
<line form="verse">The power to be ashamed of myself,</line>
<line form="verse">I never mean to part my lips again</line>
<line form="verse">In any words that tends to such a suit.</line>
<line form="verse">Arise, true English lady, whom our isle</line>
<line form="verse">May better boast of than ever Roman might</line>
<line form="verse">Of her, whose ransacked treasury hath taskt</line>
<line form="verse">The vain endeavor of so many pens:</line>
<line form="verse">Arise, and be my fault thy honor&#8217;s fame,</line>
<line form="verse">Which after ages shall enrich thee with.</line>
<line form="verse">I am awakened from this idle dream.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Warwick, my son, Darby, Artois, and Audley!</line>
<line form="verse">Brave warriors all, where are you all this while?</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter all.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Warwick, I make thee Warden of the North:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou, Prince of Wales, and Audley, straight to sea;</line>
<line form="verse">Scour to Newhaven; some there stay for me:</line>
<line form="verse">Myself, Artois, and Darby will through Flanders,</line>
<line form="verse">To greet our friends there and to crave their aide.</line>
<line form="verse">This night will scarce suffice a faithful lover;</line>
<line form="verse">For, ere the sun shall gild the eastern sky,</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll wake him with our martial harmony.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Flanders. The French camp.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King John of France, Charles of Normandy, Phillip, Duke of Lorraine, King of Bohemia, Danes, Polish Captain, Soldiers, Mariner)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>King John of France and the Duke of Lorraine discuss their preparedness to deal with Edward. They are slightly worried by the reports of the forces and allies Edward has managed to assemble, but are fairly confident. The allies of the French arrive, led by the King of Bohemia, and are warmly welcomed. But this cannot last, as a French Mariner comes in to report that Edward&#8217;s fleet has arrived on the shores of France, and that the English King has already added the royal symbols of France to his flag. King John rapidly disposes his forces in expectation of a land assault, while waiting to hear how the battle at sea turns out. John and his son sit and eat as the battle rages; they soon find out that Edward has bested the French. John rushes to prepare his army for imminent fighting.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King John of France, his two sons, Charles of Normandy, and Phillip, and the Duke of Lorraine.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, till our navy of a thousand sail</line>
<line form="verse">Have made a breakfast to our foe by sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Let us encamp, to wait their happy speed.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Lorraine, what readiness is Edward in?</line>
<line form="verse">How hast thou heard that he provided is</line>
<line form="verse">Of martial furniture for this exploit?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAINE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To lay aside unnecessary soothing,</line>
<line form="verse">And not to spend the time in circumstance,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis bruited for a certainty, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">That he&#8217;s exceeding strongly fortified;</line>
<line form="verse">His subjects flock as willingly to war,</line>
<line form="verse">As if unto a triumph they were led.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">England was wont to harbour malcontents,</line>
<line form="verse">Blood thirsty and seditious Catelynes,</line>
<line form="verse">Spend thrifts, and such as gape for nothing else</line>
<line form="verse">But changing and alteration of the state;</line>
<line form="verse">And is it possible</line>
<line form="verse">That they are now so loyal in themselves?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAINE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All but the Scot, who solemnly protests,</line>
<line form="verse">As heretofore I have informed his grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Never to sheath his sword or take a truce.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, that&#8217;s the anchorage of some better hope!</line>
<line form="verse">But, on the other side, to think what friends</line>
<line form="verse">King Edward hath retained in Netherland,</line>
<line form="verse">Among those ever-bibbing Epicures,</line>
<line form="verse">Those frothy Dutch men, puff&#8217;d with double beer,</line>
<line form="verse">That drink and swill in every place they come,</line>
<line form="verse">Doth not a little aggravate mine ire;</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, we hear, the Emperor conjoins,</line>
<line form="verse">And stalls him in his own authority;</line>
<line form="verse">But, all the mightier that their number is,</line>
<line form="verse">The greater glory reaps the victory.</line>
<line form="verse">Some friends have we beside domestic power;</line>
<line form="verse">The stern Polonian, and the warlike Dane,</line>
<line form="verse">The King of Boheme and of Sicily,</line>
<line form="verse">Are all become confederates with us,</line>
<line form="verse">And, as I think, are marching hither apace.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Drum within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">But soft, I hear the music of their drums,</line>
<line form="verse">By which I guess that their approach is near.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the King of Bohemia, with Danes, and a Polish Captain, with other soldiers, another way.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING OF BOHEMIA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">King John of France, as league and neighborhood</line>
<line form="verse">Requires, when friends are any way distrest,</line>
<line form="verse">I come to aide thee with my country&#8217;s force.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POL. CAPTAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And from great Moscow, fearful to the Turk,</line>
<line form="verse">And lofty Poland, nurse of hardy men,</line>
<line form="verse">I bring these servitors to fight for thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Who willingly will venture in thy cause.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, Bohemian king, and welcome all:</line>
<line form="verse">This your great kindness I will not forget.</line>
<line form="verse">Besides your plentiful rewards in crowns,</line>
<line form="verse">That from our treasury ye shall receive,</line>
<line form="verse">There comes a hare brained nation, decked in pride,</line>
<line form="verse">The spoil of whom will be a treble gain.</line>
<line form="verse">And now my hope is full, my joy complete:</line>
<line form="verse">At sea, we are as puissant as the force</line>
<line form="verse">Of Agamemnon in the haven of Troy;</line>
<line form="verse">By land, with Zerxes we compare of strength,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose soldiers drank up rivers in their thirst;</line>
<line form="verse">Then Bayard-like, blind, overweaning Ned,</line>
<line form="verse">To reach at our imperial diadem</line>
<line form="verse">Is either to be swallowed of the waves,</line>
<line form="verse">Or hacked a pieces when thou comest ashore.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter French Mariner.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FR. MARINER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Near to the coast I have descried, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">As I was buy in my watchful charge,</line>
<line form="verse">The proud armado of King Edward&#8217;s ships:</line>
<line form="verse">Which, at the first, far off when I did ken,</line>
<line form="verse">Seemed as it were a grove of withered pines;</line>
<line form="verse">But, drawing near, their glorious bright aspect,</line>
<line form="verse">Their streaming ensigns, wrought of coloured silk,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a meadow full of sundry flowers,</line>
<line form="verse">Adorns the naked bosom of the earth:</line>
<line form="verse">Majestical the order of their course,</line>
<line form="verse">Figuring the horned circle of the moon:</line>
<line form="verse">And on the top gallant of the admiral</line>
<line form="verse">And likewise all the handmaids of his train</line>
<line form="verse">The arms of England and of France unite</line>
<line form="verse">Are quartered equally by heralds&#8217; art:</line>
<line form="verse">Thus, tightly carried with a merry gale,</line>
<line form="verse">They plough the ocean hitherward amain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dare he already crop the Fleur de Luce?</line>
<line form="verse">I hope, the honey being gathered thence,</line>
<line form="verse">He, with the spider, afterward approached,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall suck forth deadly venom from the leaves.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">But where&#8217;s our navy? How are they prepared</line>
<line form="verse">To wing themselves against this flight of ravens?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FR. MARINER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They, having knowledge, brought them by the scouts,</line>
<line form="verse">Did break from Anchor straight, and, puffed with rage,</line>
<line form="verse">No otherwise then were their sails with wind,</line>
<line form="verse">Made forth, as when the empty eagle flies,</line>
<line form="verse">To satisfy his hungry griping maw.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s for thy news. Return unto thy bark;</line>
<line form="verse">And if thou scape the bloody stroke of war</line>
<line form="verse">And do survive the conflict, come again,</line>
<line form="verse">And let us hear the manner of the fight.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit French Mariner.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Mean space, my lords, &#8217;tis best we be dispersed</line>
<line form="verse">To several places, least they chance to land:</line>
<line form="verse">First you, my lord, with your Bohemian troops,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall pitch your battailes on the lower hand;</line>
<line form="verse">My eldest son, the Duke of Normandy,</line>
<line form="verse">Together with the aide of Muscovites,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall climb the higher ground another way;</line>
<line form="verse">Here in the middle cost, betwixt you both,</line>
<line form="verse">Phillip, my youngest boy, and I will lodge.</line>
<line form="verse">So, lords, be gone, and look unto your charge:</line>
<line form="verse">You stand for France, an empire fair and large.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now tell me, Phillip, what is thy concept,</line>
<line form="verse">Touching the challenge that the English make?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I say, my lord, claim Edward what he can,</line>
<line form="verse">And bring he ne&#8217;er so plain a pedigree,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis you are in the possession of the crown,</line>
<line form="verse">And that&#8217;s the surest point of all the law:</line>
<line form="verse">But, were it not, yet ere he should prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll make a conduit of my dearest blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Or chase those straggling upstarts home again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well said, young Phillip! Call for bread and wine,</line>
<line form="verse">That we may cheer our stomachs with repast,</line>
<line form="verse">To look our foes more sternly in the face.</line>
<stagedir type="action">A table and provisions brought in. The battle hard a far off.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now is begun the heavy day at sea:</line>
<line form="verse">Fight, Frenchmen, fight! Be like the field of bears,</line>
<line form="verse">When they defend their younglings in the caves!</line>
<line form="verse">Stir, angry nemesis, the happy helm,</line>
<line form="verse">That, with the sulphur battles of your rage,</line>
<line form="verse">The English fleet may be dispersed and sunk.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Shot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O Father, how this echoing cannon shot,</line>
<line form="verse">Like sweet harmony, digests my eats!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, boy, thou hearest what thundering terror &#8217;tis</line>
<line form="verse">To buckle for a kingdom&#8217;s sovereignty:</line>
<line form="verse">The earth, with giddy trembling when it shakes,</line>
<line form="verse">Or when the exhalations of the air</line>
<line form="verse">Breaks in extremity of lightning flash,</line>
<line form="verse">Affrights not more than kings, when they dispose</line>
<line form="verse">To shew the rancor of their high swollen hearts.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Retreat.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Retreat is sounded; one side hath the worse;</line>
<line form="verse">O, if it be the French, sweet fortune, turn;</line>
<line form="verse">And, in thy turning, change the forward winds,</line>
<line form="verse">That, with advantage of a favoring sky,</line>
<line form="verse">Our men may vanquish, and the other fly!</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter French Mariner.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">My heart misgives:&#8212;say, mirror of pale death,</line>
<line form="verse">To whom belongs the honor of this day?</line>
<line form="verse">Relate, I pray thee, if thy breath will serve,</line>
<line form="verse">The sad discourse of this discomfiture.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FR. MARINER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my lord.</line>
<line form="verse">My gracious sovereign, Franch hath ta&#8217;en the foil,</line>
<line form="verse">And boasting Edward triumphs with success.</line>
<line form="verse">These iron-hearted navies,</line>
<line form="verse">When last I was reporter to your grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Both full of angry spleen, of hope, and fear,</line>
<line form="verse">Hasting to meet each other in the face,</line>
<line form="verse">At last conjoined; and by their admiral</line>
<line form="verse">Our admiral encountered many shot:</line>
<line form="verse">By this, the other, that beheld these twain</line>
<line form="verse">Give earnest penny of a further wrack,</line>
<line form="verse">Like fiery dragons took their haughty flight;</line>
<line form="verse">And, likewise meeting, from their smoky wombs</line>
<line form="verse">Sent many grim ambassadors of death.</line>
<line form="verse">Then &#8217;gan the day to turn to gloomy night,</line>
<line form="verse">And darkness did as well enclose the quick</line>
<line form="verse">As those that were but newly reft of life.</line>
<line form="verse">No leisure served for friends to bid farewell;</line>
<line form="verse">And, if it had, the hideous noise was such,</line>
<line form="verse">As each to other seemed deaf and dumb.</line>
<line form="verse">Purple the sea, whose channel filled as fast</line>
<line form="verse">With streaming gore, that from the maimed fell,</line>
<line form="verse">As did her gushing moisture break into</line>
<line form="verse">The crannied cleftures of the through shot planks.</line>
<line form="verse">Here flew a head, dissever&#8217;d from the trunk,</line>
<line form="verse">There mangled arms and legs were tossed aloft,</line>
<line form="verse">As when a whirl wind takes the summer dust</line>
<line form="verse">And scatters it in middle of the air.</line>
<line form="verse">Then might ye see the reeling vessels split,</line>
<line form="verse">And tottering sink into the ruthless flood,</line>
<line form="verse">Until their lofty tops were seen no more.</line>
<line form="verse">All shifts were tried, both for defence and hurt:</line>
<line form="verse">And now the effect of valor and of force,</line>
<line form="verse">Of resolution and of cowardice,</line>
<line form="verse">We lively pictures; how the one for fame,</line>
<line form="verse">The other by compulsion laid about;</line>
<line form="verse">Much did the Nonpareille, that brave ship;</line>
<line form="verse">So did the Black Snake of Bullen, then which</line>
<line form="verse">A bonnier vessel never yet spread sail.</line>
<line form="verse">But all in vain; both sun, the wind and tide,</line>
<line form="verse">Revolted all unto our foe men&#8217;s side,</line>
<line form="verse">That we perforce were fain to give them way,</line>
<line form="verse">And they are landed.&#8212;Thus my tale is done:</line>
<line form="verse">We have untimely lost, and they have won.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then rests there nothing, but with present speed</line>
<line form="verse">To join our several forces all in one,</line>
<line form="verse">And bid them battle, ere they range too far.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, gentle Phillip, let us hence depart;</line>
<line form="verse">This soldier&#8217;s words have pierced thy father&#8217;s heart.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The fields near Cressy.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Frenchmen, Frenchwoman, Children, Citizens)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Worried French citizens remove themselves to safety, just in case the armies pass nearby. They discuss the validity of Edward&#8217;s claim to the French throne. A newcomer rushes in to encourage them all to flee, as the entire countryside is being ravaged by three separate armies – Edward&#8217;s, King John&#8217;s, and the Prince of Wales&#8217;s – all converging on the same place.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter three Frenchmen; a Frenchwoman and two little children meet them, and other Citizens.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well met, my masters: how now? What&#8217;s the news?</line>
<line form="verse">And wherefore are ye laden thus with stuff?</line>
<line form="verse">What, is it quarter-day that you remove,</line>
<line form="verse">And carry bag and baggage too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Quarter-day? Aye, and quartering day, I fear:</line>
<line form="verse">Have ye not heard the news that flies abroad?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How the French navy is destroy&#8217;d at sea,</line>
<line form="verse">And that the English army is arrived.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What then?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What then, quoth you? Why, ist not time to fly,</line>
<line form="verse">When envy and destruction is so nigh?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content thee, man: they are far enough from hence,</line>
<line form="verse">And will be met, I warrant ye, to their cost,</line>
<line form="verse">Before they break so far into the realm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, so the grasshopper doth spend the time</line>
<line form="verse">In mirthful jollity, till winter come;</line>
<line form="verse">And then too late he would redeem his time,</line>
<line form="verse">When frozen cold hath nipped his careless head.</line>
<line form="verse">He, that no sooner will provide a cloak,</line>
<line form="verse">Then when he sees it doth begin to reign,</line>
<line form="verse">May, peradventure, for his negligence,</line>
<line form="verse">Be throughly washed, when he suspects it not.</line>
<line form="verse">We that have charge and such a train as this,</line>
<line form="verse">Must look in time to look for them and us,</line>
<line form="verse">Least, when we would, we cannot be relieved.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Belike, you then despair of all success,</line>
<line form="verse">And think your country will be subjugate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We cannot tell; &#8217;tis good to fear the worst.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yet rather fight, then, like unnatural sons,</line>
<line form="verse">Forsake your loving parents in distress.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tush, they that have already taken arms</line>
<line form="verse">Are many fearful millions in respect</line>
<line form="verse">Of that small handful of our enemies;</line>
<line form="verse">But &#8217;tis a rightful quarrel must prevail;</line>
<line form="verse">Edward is son unto our late king&#8217;s sister,</line>
<line form="verse">When John Valois is three degrees removed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FRENCHWOMAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Besides, there goes a prophecy abroad,</line>
<line form="verse">Published by one that was a friar once,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose oracles have many times proved true;</line>
<line form="verse">And now he says, the time will shortly come,</line>
<line form="verse">When as a lion, roused in the west,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall carry hence the fluerdeluce of France:</line>
<line form="verse">These, I can tell ye, and such like surmises</line>
<line form="verse">Strike many French men cold unto the heart.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Fourth Frenchman.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>4. FRENCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fly, country men and citizens of France!</line>
<line form="verse">Sweet flowering peace, the root of happy life,</line>
<line form="verse">Is quite abandoned and expulst the land;</line>
<line form="verse">Instead of whom ransacked constraining war</line>
<line form="verse">Sits like to ravens upon your houses&#8217; tops;</line>
<line form="verse">Slaughter and mischief walk within your streets,</line>
<line form="verse">And, unrestrained, make havoc as they pass;</line>
<line form="verse">The form whereof even now myself beheld</line>
<line form="verse">Upon this fair mountain whence I came.</line>
<line form="verse">For so far of as I directed mine eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">I might perceive five cities all on fire,</line>
<line form="verse">Corn fields and vineyards, burning like an oven;</line>
<line form="verse">And, as the reaking vapour in the wind</line>
<line form="verse">Turned but aside, I like wise might discern</line>
<line form="verse">The poor inhabitants, escaped the flame,</line>
<line form="verse">Fall numberless upon the soldiers&#8217; pikes.</line>
<line form="verse">Three ways these dreadful ministers of wrath</line>
<line form="verse">Do tread the measures of their tragic march:</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the right hand comes the conquering King,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the left his hot unbridled son,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the midst our nation&#8217;s glittering host,</line>
<line form="verse">All which, though distant yet, conspire in one,</line>
<line form="verse">To leave a desolation where they come.</line>
<line form="verse">Fly therefore, citizens, if you be wise,</line>
<line form="verse">Seek out some habitation further off:</line>
<line form="verse">Here is you stay, your wives will be abused,</line>
<line form="verse">Your treasure shared before your weeping eyes;</line>
<line form="verse">Shelter you yourselves, for now the storm doth rise.</line>
<line form="verse">Away, away; me thinks I hear their drums:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, wretched France, I greatly fear thy fall;</line>
<line form="verse">Thy glory shaketh like a tottering wall.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The fields near Cressy.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Edward, Earl of Darby, Soldiers, Gobin de Grey, Artois, Prince Edward, Lord Awdley, King John, Dukes of Normandy, Lorraine, King of Bohemia, Phillip, Four Heralds)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>King Edward rewards a French prisoner who led his army across the river Somme. Prince Edward arrives with his army, reporting his great successes in campaigning but also that the French, in general, would not submit. The Prince also tells his father that King John and his army are nearby. This is confirmed when John himself arrives to challenge Edward. The two kings exchanges insults, John refusing to give up his crown and Edward refusing to give up his claim. It becomes clear that battle is the only solution, and both kings rally their troops. John and his men leave to prepare for the fight. Edward knights his son. The English then prepare for battle.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward, and the Earl of Darby, with Soldiers, and Gobin de Grey.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where&#8217;s the Frenchman by whose cunning guide</line>
<line form="verse">We found the shallow of this river Somme,</line>
<line form="verse">And had directions how to pass the sea?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOBIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, my good lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How art thou called? Tell me thy name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOBIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gobin de Grey, if please your excellence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then, Gobin, for the service thou hast done,</line>
<line form="verse">We here enlarge and give thee liberty;</line>
<line form="verse">And, for recompense beside this good,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt receive five hundred marks in gold.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I know not how, we should have met our son,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom now in heart I wish I might behold.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Artois.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good news, my lord; the prince is hard at hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And with him comes Lord Audley and the rest,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom since our landing we could never meet.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Drums sound. Enter Prince Edward, Lord Audley, and Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, fair prince! How hast thou sped, my son,</line>
<line form="verse">Since thy arrival on the coast of France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Successfully, I thank the gracious heavens:</line>
<line form="verse">Some of their strongest cities we have won,</line>
<line form="verse">As Harflew, Lo, Crotay, and Carentigne,</line>
<line form="verse">And others wasted, leaving at our heels</line>
<line form="verse">A wide apparent field and beaten path</line>
<line form="verse">For solitariness to progress in:</line>
<line form="verse">Yet those that would submit we kindly pardoned,</line>
<line form="verse">But who in scorn refused our proffered peace,</line>
<line form="verse">Endured the penalty of sharp revenge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, France, why shouldest thou be thus obstinate</line>
<line form="verse">Against the kind embracement of thy friends?</line>
<line form="verse">How gently had we thought to touch thy breast</line>
<line form="verse">And set our foot upon thy tender mould,</line>
<line form="verse">But that, in froward and disdainful pride,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou, like a skittish and untamed colt,</line>
<line form="verse">Dost start aside and strike us with thy heels!</line>
<line form="verse">But tell me, Ned, in all thy warlike course,</line>
<line form="verse">Hast thou not seen the usurping King of France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, my good lord, and not two hours ago,</line>
<line form="verse">With full a hundred thousand fighting men&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the one side of the river&#8217;s bank</line>
<line form="verse">And on the other both, his multitudes.</line>
<line form="verse">I feared he would have cropped our smaller power:</line>
<line form="verse">But happily, perceiving your approach,</line>
<line form="verse">He hath with drawn himself to Cressy plains;</line>
<line form="verse">Where, as it seemeth by his good array,</line>
<line form="verse">He means to bid us battle presently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He shall be welcome; that&#8217;s the thing we crave.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Drums. Enter King John, the Dukes of Normandy and Lorraine, King of Bohemia, young Prince Phillip, and Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward, know that John, the true king of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Musing thou shouldst encroach upon his land,</line>
<line form="verse">And in thy tyranous proceeding slay</line>
<line form="verse">His faithful subjects and subvert his towns,</line>
<line form="verse">Spits in thy face; and in this manner following</line>
<line form="verse">Obraids thee with thine arrogant intrusion:</line>
<line form="verse">First, I condemn thee for a fugitive,</line>
<line form="verse">A thievish pirate, and a needy mate,</line>
<line form="verse">One that hath either no abiding place,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else, inhabiting some barren soil,</line>
<line form="verse">Where neither herb or fruitful grain is had,</line>
<line form="verse">Doest altogether live by pilfering:</line>
<line form="verse">Next, insomuch thou hast infringed thy faith,</line>
<line form="verse">Broke league and solemn covenant made with me,</line>
<line form="verse">I hold thee for a false pernicious wretch:</line>
<line form="verse">And, last of all, although I scorn to cope</line>
<line form="verse">With one so much inferior to myself,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet, in respect thy thirst is all for gold,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy labour rather to be feared than loved,</line>
<line form="verse">To satisfy thy lust in either part,</line>
<line form="verse">Here am I come, and with me have I brought</line>
<line form="verse">Exceeding store of treasure, pearl, and coin.</line>
<line form="verse">Leave, therefore, now to persecute the weak,</line>
<line form="verse">And armed entering conflict with the armed,</line>
<line form="verse">Let it be seen, &#8217;mongst other petty thefts,</line>
<line form="verse">How thou canst win this pillage manfully.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If gall or wormwood have a pleasant taste,</line>
<line form="verse">Then is thy salutation honey sweet;</line>
<line form="verse">But as the one hath no such property,</line>
<line form="verse">So is the other most satirical.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet wot how I regard thy worthless taunts:</line>
<line form="verse">If thou have uttered them to foil my fame</line>
<line form="verse">Or dim the reputation of my birth,</line>
<line form="verse">Know that thy wolvish barking cannot hurt;</line>
<line form="verse">If slyly to insinuate with the world,</line>
<line form="verse">And with a strumpet&#8217;s artificial line</line>
<line form="verse">To paint thy vicious and deformed cause,</line>
<line form="verse">Be well assured, the counterfeit will fade,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the end thy foul defects be seen;</line>
<line form="verse">But if thou didst it to provoke me on,</line>
<line form="verse">As who should say I were but timorous.</line>
<line form="verse">Or, coldly negligent, did need a spur,</line>
<line form="verse">Bethink thyself how slack I was at sea,</line>
<line form="verse">How since my landing I have won no towns,</line>
<line form="verse">Entered no further but upon the coast,</line>
<line form="verse">And there have ever since securely slept.</line>
<line form="verse">But if I have been other wise employed,</line>
<line form="verse">Imagine, Valois, whether I intend</line>
<line form="verse">To skirmish, not for pillage, but for the crown</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou dost wear; and that I vow to have,</line>
<line form="verse">Or one of us shall fall into his grave.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Look not for cross invectives at our hands,</line>
<line form="verse">Or railing execrations of despite:</line>
<line form="verse">Let creeping serpents, hid in hollow banks,</line>
<line form="verse">Sting with their tongues; we have remorseless swords,</line>
<line form="verse">And they shall plead for us and our affairs.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet thus much, briefly, by my father&#8217;s leave:</line>
<line form="verse">As all the immodest poison of thy throat</line>
<line form="verse">Is scandalous and most notorious lies,</line>
<line form="verse">And our pretended quarrel is truly just,</line>
<line form="verse">So end the battle when we meet today:</line>
<line form="verse">May either of us prosper and prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">Or, luckless, curst, receive eternal shame!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That needs no further question; and I know,</line>
<line form="verse">His conscience witnesseth, it is my right.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, Valois, say, wilt thou yet resign,</line>
<line form="verse">Before the sickles thrust into the corn,</line>
<line form="verse">Or that inkindled fury turn to flame?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward, I know what right thou hast in France;</line>
<line form="verse">And ere I basely will resign my crown,</line>
<line form="verse">This champion field shall be a pool of blood,</line>
<line form="verse">And all our prospect as a slaughter house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, that approves thee, tyrant, what thou art:</line>
<line form="verse">No father, king, or shepherd of thy realm,</line>
<line form="verse">But one, that tears her entrails with thy hands,</line>
<line form="verse">And, like a thirsty tyger, suckst her blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You peers of France, why do you follow him</line>
<line form="verse">That is so prodigal to spend your lives?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whom should they follow, aged impotent,</line>
<line form="verse">But he that is their true borne sovereign?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Obraidst thou him, because within his face</line>
<line form="verse">Time hath ingraved deep characters of age?</line>
<line form="verse">Know, these grave scholars of experience,</line>
<line form="verse">Like stiff grown oaks, will stand immovable,</line>
<line form="verse">When whirl wind quickly turns up younger trees.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DARBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Was ever any of thy father&#8217;s house</line>
<line form="verse">King but thyself, before this present time?</line>
<line form="verse">Edward&#8217;s great linage, by the mother&#8217;s side,</line>
<line form="verse">Five hundred years hath held the scepter up:</line>
<line form="verse">Judge then, conspiratours, by this descent,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is the true borne sovereign, this or that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Father, range your battles, prate no more;</line>
<line form="verse">These English fain would spend the time in words,</line>
<line form="verse">That, night approaching, they might escape unfought.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lords and my loving subjects, now&#8217;s the time,</line>
<line form="verse">That your intended force must bide the touch.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, my friends, consider this in brief:</line>
<line form="verse">He that you fight for is your natural King;</line>
<line form="verse">He against whom you fight, a foreigner:</line>
<line form="verse">He that you fight for, rules in clemency,</line>
<line form="verse">And reins you with a mild and gentle bit;</line>
<line form="verse">He against whom you fight, if he prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">Will straight inthrone himself in tyranny,</line>
<line form="verse">Makes slaves of you, and with a heavy hand</line>
<line form="verse">Curtail and curb your sweetest liberty.</line>
<line form="verse">Then, to protect your country and your King,</line>
<line form="verse">Let but the haughty courage of your hearts</line>
<line form="verse">Answer the number of your able hands,</line>
<line form="verse">And we shall quickly chase these fugitives.</line>
<line form="verse">For what&#8217;s this Edward but a belly god,</line>
<line form="verse">A tender and lascivious wantoness,</line>
<line form="verse">That thother day was almost dead for love?</line>
<line form="verse">And what, I pray you, is his goodly guard?</line>
<line form="verse">Such as, but scant them of their chines of beef</line>
<line form="verse">And take away their downy featherbeds,</line>
<line form="verse">And presently they are as resty stiff,</line>
<line form="verse">As &#8217;twere a many over ridden jades.</line>
<line form="verse">Then, Frenchmen, scorn that such should be your lords,</line>
<line form="verse">And rather bind ye them in captive bands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL FRENCHMEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse"><french xml:lang="fr">Vive le Roy!</french> God save King John of France!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now on this plain of Cressy spread yourselves,&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And, Edward, when thou darest, begin the fight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt King John, Charles, Philip, Lorraine, Boheme, and forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We presently will meet thee, John of France:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And, English lords, let us resolve this day,</line>
<line form="verse">Either to clear us of that scandalous crime,</line>
<line form="verse">Or be intombed in our innocence.</line>
<line form="verse">And, Ned, because this battle is the first</line>
<line form="verse">That ever yet thou foughtest in pitched field,</line>
<line form="verse">As ancient custom is of martialists,</line>
<line form="verse">To dub thee with the tip of chivalry,</line>
<line form="verse">In solemn manner we will give thee arms.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, therefore, heralds, orderly bring forth</line>
<line form="verse">A strong attirement for the prince my son.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter four Heralds, bringing in a coat-armor, a helmet, a lance, and a shield. The first Herald delivers the armor to King Edward, who puts it on his son.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward Plantagenet, in the name of God,</line>
<line form="verse">As with this armor I impale thy breast,</line>
<line form="verse">So be thy noble unrelenting heart</line>
<line form="verse">Walled in with flint of matchless fortitude,</line>
<line form="verse">That never base affections enter there:</line>
<line form="verse">Fight and be valiant, conquer where thou comest!</line>
<line form="verse">Now follow, lords, and do him honor to.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DARBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward Plantagenet, prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">As I do set this helmet on thy head,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherewith the chamber of thy brain is fenc&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">So may thy temples, with Bellona&#8217;s hand,</line>
<line form="verse">Be still adorned with laurel victory:</line>
<line form="verse">Fight and be valiant, conquer where thou comest!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward Plantagenet, prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">Receive this lance into thy manly hand;</line>
<line form="verse">Use it in fashion of a brazen pen,</line>
<line form="verse">To draw forth bloody stratagems in France,</line>
<line form="verse">And print thy valiant deeds in honor&#8217;s book:</line>
<line form="verse">Fight and be valiant, vanquish where thou comest!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward Plantagenet, prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">Hold, take this target, wear it on thy arm;</line>
<line form="verse">And may the view thereof, like Perseus&#8217; shield,</line>
<line form="verse">Astonish and transform thy gazing foes</line>
<line form="verse">To senseless images of meager death:</line>
<line form="verse">Fight and be valiant, conquer where thou comest!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now wants there nought but knighthood, which deferred</line>
<line form="verse">We leave, till thou hast won it in the field.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious father and ye forward peers,</line>
<line form="verse">This honor you have done me, animates</line>
<line form="verse">And cheers my green, yet scarce appearing strength</line>
<line form="verse">With comfortable good presaging signs,</line>
<line form="verse">No other wise than did old Jacob&#8217;s words,</line>
<line form="verse">When as he breathed his blessings on his sons.</line>
<line form="verse">These hallowed gifts of yours when I profane,</line>
<line form="verse">Or use them not to glory of my God,</line>
<line form="verse">To patronage the fatherless and poor,</line>
<line form="verse">Or for the benefit of England&#8217;s peace,</line>
<line form="verse">Be numb my joints, wax feeble both mine arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Wither my heart, that, like a sapless tree,</line>
<line form="verse">I may remain the map of infamy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then thus our steeled battles shall be ranged:</line>
<line form="verse">The leading of the vaward, Ned, is thine;</line>
<line form="verse">To dignify whose lusty spirit the more,</line>
<line form="verse">We temper it with Audley&#8217;s gravity,</line>
<line form="verse">That, courage and experience joined in one,</line>
<line form="verse">Your manage may be second unto none:</line>
<line form="verse">For the main battles, I will guide myself;</line>
<line form="verse">And, Darby, in the rearward march behind,</line>
<line form="verse">That orderly disposed and set in ray,</line>
<line form="verse">Let us to horse; and God grant us the day!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The fields near Cressy.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Frenchmen, Prince Edward, King John, Duke of Lorraine)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Prince Edward beats a large group of Frenchmen, who flee. Lorraine reports that the Genoese are to blame for the French rout; King John decides to try to convince some of the fleeing soldiers to return to the battle.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Enter a many Frenchmen flying. After them Prince Edward, running. Then enter King John and Duke of Lorraine.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Oh, Lorraine, say, what mean our men to fly?</line>
<line form="verse">Our number is far greater than our foes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORRAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The garrison of Genoaes, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">That came from Paris weary with their march,</line>
<line form="verse">Grudging to be so suddenly employ&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">No sooner in the forefront took their place,</line>
<line form="verse">But, straight retiring, so dismayed the rest,</line>
<line form="verse">As likewise they betook themselves to flight,</line>
<line form="verse">In which, for haste to make a safe escape,</line>
<line form="verse">More in the clustering throng are pressed to death,</line>
<line form="verse">Than by the enemy, a thousand fold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O hapless fortune! Let us yet assay,</line>
<line form="verse">If we can counsel some of them to stay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The fields near Cressy.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Edward, Audley, Artois, Derby, Audley, Prince Edward, King of Boheme)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Seeing that Prince Edward is doing good work, the King takes a break from the fight. He hears a French retreat sounded and believes the day is won. However, Artois comes in to beg the King to rescue the Prince, who is surrounded and will almost certainly be captured or killed. Edward refuses. Darby comes in with the same plea, and then Audley, but Edward insists that the Prince must win on his own, and cannot be led to believe that his father will always rescue him. The three lords are aghast at this lack of fatherly feeling, but Prince Edward soon arrives victorious, having not only escaped but also killed the King of Bohemia. He announces the massive scale of the English victory. Edward sends his son and Audley to chase King John while he himself goes to besiege Calais.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward and Audley.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Audley, whiles our son is in the chase,</line>
<line form="verse">With draw our powers unto this little hill,</line>
<line form="verse">And here a season let us breath ourselves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit. Sound Retreat.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Just dooming heaven, whose secret providence</line>
<line form="verse">To our gross judgement is inscrutable,</line>
<line form="verse">How are we bound to praise thy wondrous works,</line>
<line form="verse">That hast this day given way unto the right,</line>
<line form="verse">And made the wicked stumble at themselves!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Artois.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Rescue, king Edward! Rescue for thy son!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Rescue, Artois? What, is he prisoner,</line>
<line form="verse">Or by violence fell beside his horse?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Neither, my lord: but narrowly beset</line>
<line form="verse">With turning Frenchmen, whom he did pursue,</line>
<line form="verse">As &#8217;tis impossible that he should scape,</line>
<line form="verse">Except your highness presently descend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tut, let him fight; we gave him arms today,</line>
<line form="verse">And he is laboring for a knighthood, man.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Derby.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DARBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Prince, my lord, the Prince! Oh, succour him!</line>
<line form="verse">He&#8217;s close incompast with a world of odds!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then will he win a world of honor too,</line>
<line form="verse">If he by valour can redeem him thence;</line>
<line form="verse">If not, what remedy? We have more sons</line>
<line form="verse">Than one, to comfort our declining age.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Audley.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Renowned Edward, give me leave, I pray,</line>
<line form="verse">To lead my soldiers where I may relieve</line>
<line form="verse">Your Grace&#8217;s son, in danger to be slain.</line>
<line form="verse">The snares of French, like emmets on a bank,</line>
<line form="verse">Muster about him; whilest he, lion-like,</line>
<line form="verse">Intangled in the net of their assaults,</line>
<line form="verse">Franticly wrends, and bites the woven toil;</line>
<line form="verse">But all in vain, he cannot free himself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Audley, content; I will not have a man,</line>
<line form="verse">On pain of death, sent forth to succour him:</line>
<line form="verse">This is the day, ordained by destiny,</line>
<line form="verse">To season his courage with those grievous thoughts,</line>
<line form="verse">That, if he breaketh out, Nestor&#8217;s years on earth</line>
<line form="verse">Will make him savor still of this exploit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DARBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, but he shall not live to see those days.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, then his epitaph is lasting praise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yet, good my lord, &#8217;tis too much willfulness,</line>
<line form="verse">To let his blood be spilt, that may be saved.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Exclaim no more; for none of you can tell</line>
<line form="verse">Whether a borrowed aid will serve, or no;</line>
<line form="verse">Perhaps he is already slain or ta&#8217;en.</line>
<line form="verse">And dare a falcon when she&#8217;s in her flight,</line>
<line form="verse">And ever after she&#8217;ll be haggard like:</line>
<line form="verse">Let Edward be delivered by our hands,</line>
<line form="verse">And still, in danger, he&#8217;ll expect the like;</line>
<line form="verse">But if himself himself redeem from thence,</line>
<line form="verse">He will have vanquished cheerful death and fear,</line>
<line form="verse">And ever after dread their force no more</line>
<line form="verse">Than if they were but babes or captive slaves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O cruel Father! Farewell, Edward, then!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DARBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, sweet Prince, the hope of chivalry!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, would my life might ransom him from death!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Retreat sounded.</stagedir>
<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But soft, me thinks I hear</line>
<line form="verse">The dismal charge of trumpets&#8217; loud retreat.</line>
<line form="verse">All are not slain, I hope, that went with him;</line>
<line form="verse">Some will return with tidings, good or bad.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Prince Edward in triumph, bearing in his hands his chivered lance, and the King of Bohemia, borne before, wrapped in the colours. They run and embrace him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O joyful sight! Victorious Edward lives!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, brave Prince!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, Plantagenet!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Kneels and kisses his father&#8217;s hand.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">First having done my duty as beseemed,</line>
<line form="verse">Lords, I regreet you all with hearty thanks.</line>
<line form="verse">And now, behold, after my winter&#8217;s toil,</line>
<line form="verse">My painful voyage on the boisterous sea</line>
<line form="verse">Of wars devouring gulfs and steely rocks,</line>
<line form="verse">I bring my fraught unto the wished port,</line>
<line form="verse">My summer&#8217;s hope, my travels&#8217; sweet reward:</line>
<line form="verse">And here, with humble duty, I present</line>
<line form="verse">This sacrifice, this first fruit of my sword,</line>
<line form="verse">Cropped and cut down even at the gate of death,</line>
<line form="verse">The king of Boheme, father, whom I slew;</line>
<line form="verse">Whose thousands had entrenched me round about,</line>
<line form="verse">And lay as thick upon my battered crest,</line>
<line form="verse">As on an anvil, with their ponderous glaves:</line>
<line form="verse">Yet marble courage still did underprop</line>
<line form="verse">And when my weary arms, with often blows,</line>
<line form="verse">Like the continual laboring wood-man&#8217;s Axe</line>
<line form="verse">That is enjoined to fell a load of oaks,</line>
<line form="verse">Began to faulter, straight I would record</line>
<line form="verse">My gifts you gave me, and my zealous vow,</line>
<line form="verse">And then new courage made me fresh again,</line>
<line form="verse">That, in despite, I carved my passage forth,</line>
<line form="verse">And put the multitude to speedy flight.</line>
<line form="verse">Lo, thus hath Edward&#8217;s hand filled your request,</line>
<line form="verse">And done, I hope, the duty of a knight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, well thou hast deserved a knighthood, Ned!</line>
<line form="verse">And, therefore, with thy sword, yet reaking warm</line>
<stagedir type="action">His sword borne by a soldier.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">With blood of those that fought to be thy bane.</line>
<line form="verse">Arise, Prince Edward, trusty knight at arms:</line>
<line form="verse">This day thou hast confounded me with joy,</line>
<line form="verse">And proud thyself fit heir unto a king.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here is a note, my gracious lord, of those</line>
<line form="verse">That in this conflict of our foes were slain:</line>
<line form="verse">Eleven princes of esteem, four score barons,</line>
<line form="verse">A hundred and twenty knights, and thirty thousand</line>
<line form="verse">Common soldiers; and, of our men, a thousand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Our God be praised! Now, John of France, I hope,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou knowest King Edward for no wantoness,</line>
<line form="verse">No love sick cockney, nor his soldiers jades.</line>
<line form="verse">But which way is the fearful king escaped?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Towards Poitiers, noble father, and his sons.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ned, thou and Audley shall pursue them still;</line>
<line form="verse">Myself and Derby will to Calice straight,</line>
<line form="verse">And there be begirt that haven town with siege.</line>
<line form="verse">Now lies it on an upshot; therefore strike,</line>
<line form="verse">And wistly follow, whiles the game&#8217;s on foot.</line>
<line form="verse">What picture&#8217;s this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">A pelican, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Wounding her bosom with her crooked beak,</line>
<line form="verse">That so her nest of young ones may be fed</line>
<line form="verse">With drops of blood that issue from her heart;</line>
<line form="verse">The motto, <latin xml:lang="la">Sic et vos</latin>: &#8220;And so should you&#8221;.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Bretagne. The camp of the English.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lord Mountford, Earl of Salisbury, Villiers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Earl of Mountford, now Duke of Bretagne since Charles of Blois has been killed, offers his allegiance to Salisbury as Edward&#8217;s representative. He hands over his ducal coronet and asks that it be sent to Edward. Salisbury accepts, but as his army is separated from his King&#8217;s by the French, he is uncertain of how to make his way to Calais. He offers his prisoner Villiers freedom if in return he will obtain a safe-conduct from the Duke of Normandy to allow Salisbury and his army to pass. Villiers accepts, swearing to return and continue as Salisbury&#8217;s prisoner if he cannot get the Duke to agree.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lord Mountford with a Coronet in his hand; with him the Earl of Salisbury.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MOUNTFORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord of Salisbury, since by your aide</line>
<line form="verse">Mine enemy Sir Charles of Blois is slain,</line>
<line form="verse">And I again am quietly possessed</line>
<line form="verse">In Britain&#8217;s dukedom, know that I resolve,</line>
<line form="verse">For this kind furtherance of your king and you,</line>
<line form="verse">To swear allegiance to his majesty:</line>
<line form="verse">In sign whereof receive this coronet,</line>
<line form="verse">Bear it unto him, and, withal, mine oath,</line>
<line form="verse">Never to be but Edward&#8217;s faithful friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I take it, Mountford. Thus, I hope, ere long</line>
<line form="verse">The whole dominions of the realm of France</line>
<line form="verse">Will be surrendered to his conquering hand.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Mountford.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now, if I knew but safely how to pass,</line>
<line form="verse">I would at Callice gladly meet his Grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Whether I am by letters certified</line>
<line form="verse">That he intends to have his host removed.</line>
<line form="verse">It shall be so, this policy will serve:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Ho, who&#8217;s within? Bring Villiers to me.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Villiers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Villiers, thou knowest, thou art my prisoner,</line>
<line form="verse">And that I might for ransom, if I would,</line>
<line form="verse">Require of thee a hundred thousand francs,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else retain and keep thee captive still:</line>
<line form="verse">But so it is, that for a smaller charge</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mayst be quit, and if thou wilt thyself.</line>
<line form="verse">And this it is: procure me but a passport</line>
<line form="verse">Of Charles, the Duke of Normandy, that I</line>
<line form="verse">Without restraint may have recourse to Callice</line>
<line form="verse">Through all the Countries where he hath to do;</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou mayst easily obtain, I think,</line>
<line form="verse">By reason I have often heard thee say,</line>
<line form="verse">He and thou were students once together:</line>
<line form="verse">And then thou shalt be set at liberty.</line>
<line form="verse">How saiest thou? Wilt thou undertake to do it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my lord; but I must speak with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, so thou shalt; take horse, and post from hence:</line>
<line form="verse">Only before thou goest, swear by thy faith,</line>
<line form="verse">That, if thou canst not compass my desire,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wilt return my prisoner back again;</line>
<line form="verse">And that shall be sufficient warrant for me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To that condition I agree, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">And will unfainedly perform the same.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, Villiers.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Thus once i mean to try a Frenchman&#8217;s faith.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The English camp before Calais.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Edward, Derby, Soldiers, Frenchmen, Lord Percy, French Captain, Poor Inhabitant of Calais)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>In response to Calais&#8217;s refusal to surrender, King Edward has his men completely surround the city and swears to starve them out. He chooses to feed rather than kill six famished Frenchmen who have been ejected from the city due to their inability to fight. Lord Percy arrives to tell Edward that his Queen has defeated the Scots in battle, but that the esquire who captured the Scottish King is refusing to hand him over. Edward sends an official command to the man to surrender the King, and is apprised of the Queen&#8217;s imminent arrival. A French Captain arrives to tell the King that the burghers of Calais have agreed to surrender if Edward will promise to spare their lives and good. Wrathful, Edward points out that he made much the same offer before, and it was rejected; he refuses to pardon the city unless the six richest men come to him in rags and accept to suffer any fate he chooses. The Captain considers that they would have surrendered earlier if they had not been promised that King John was going to relieve them.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward and Derby, with Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Since they refuse our proffered league, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">And will not ope their gates, and let us in,</line>
<line form="verse">We will entrench ourselves on every side,</line>
<line form="verse">That neither victuals nor supply of men</line>
<line form="verse">May come to succour this accursed town:</line>
<line form="verse">Famine shall combat where our swords are stopped.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter six poor Frenchmen, including a Poor Inhabitant of Calais.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The promised aid, that made them stand aloof,</line>
<line form="verse">Is now retired and gone an other way:</line>
<line form="verse">It will repent them of their stubborn will.</line>
<line form="verse">But what are these poor ragged slaves, my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ask what they are; it seems, they come from Callice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You wretched patterns of despair and woe,</line>
<line form="verse">What are you, living men or gliding ghosts,</line>
<line form="verse">Crept from your graves to walk upon the earth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No ghosts, my lord, but men that breath a life</line>
<line form="verse">Far worse than is the quiet sleep of death:</line>
<line form="verse">We are distressed poor inhabitants,</line>
<line form="verse">That long have been diseased, sick, and lame;</line>
<line form="verse">And now, because we are not fit to serve,</line>
<line form="verse">The captain of the town hath thrust us forth,</line>
<line form="verse">That so expense of victuals may be saved.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A charitable deed, no doubt, and worthy praise!</line>
<line form="verse">But how do you imagine then to speed?</line>
<line form="verse">We are your enemies; in such a case</line>
<line form="verse">We can no less but put ye to the sword,</line>
<line form="verse">Since, when we proffered truce, it was refused.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And if your grace no otherwise vouchsafe,</line>
<line form="verse">As welcome death is unto us as life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Poor silly men, much wronged and more distressed!</line>
<line form="verse">Go, Derby, go, and see they be relieved;</line>
<line form="verse">Command that victuals be appointed them,</line>
<line form="verse">And give to every one five crowns a piece.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Derby and Frenchmen.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The lion scorns to touch the yielding prey,</line>
<line form="verse">And Edward&#8217;s sword must flesh itself in such</line>
<line form="verse">As wilful stubbornness hath made perverse.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lord Percy.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Percy! Welcome: what&#8217;s the news in England?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PERCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Queen, my lord, comes here to your Grace,</line>
<line form="verse">And from her highness and the lord viceregent</line>
<line form="verse">I bring this happy tidings of success:</line>
<line form="verse">David of Scotland, lately up in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Thinking, belike, he soonest should prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">Your highness being absent from the realm,</line>
<line form="verse">Is, by the fruitful service of your peers</line>
<line form="verse">And painful travel of the Queen herself,</line>
<line form="verse">That, big with child, was every day in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Vanquished, subdued, and taken prisoner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, Percy, for thy news, with all my heart!</line>
<line form="verse">What was he took him prisoner in the field?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PERCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An esquire, my lord; John Copland is his name:</line>
<line form="verse">Who since, intreated by her Majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">Denies to make surrender of his prize</line>
<line form="verse">To any but unto your grace alone;</line>
<line form="verse">Whereat the Queen is grievously displeas&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, then we&#8217;ll have a Pursiuvant despatched,</line>
<line form="verse">To summon Copland hither out of hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And with him he shall bring his prisoner king.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PERCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Queen&#8217;s, my lord, herself by this at sea,</line>
<line form="verse">And purposeth, as soon as wind will serve,</line>
<line form="verse">To land at Callice, and to visit you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She shall be welcome; and, to wait her coming,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll pitch my tent near to the sandy shore.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter First French Captain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FR. CAPTAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Burgesses of Callice, mighty king,</line>
<line form="verse">Have by a counsel willingly decreed</line>
<line form="verse">To yield the town and castle to your hands,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon condition it will please your grace</line>
<line form="verse">To grant them benefit of life and goods.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They will so! Then, belike, they may command,</line>
<line form="verse">Dispose, elect, and govern as they list.</line>
<line form="verse">No, sirra, tell them, since they did refuse</line>
<line form="verse">Our princely clemency at first proclaimed,</line>
<line form="verse">They shall not have it now, although they would;</line>
<line form="verse">I will accept of nought but fire and sword,</line>
<line form="verse">Except, within these two days, six of them,</line>
<line form="verse">That are the wealthiest merchants in the town,</line>
<line form="verse">Come naked, all but for their linen shirts,</line>
<line form="verse">With each a halter hanged about his neck,</line>
<line form="verse">And prostrate yield themselves, upon their knees,</line>
<line form="verse">To be afflicted, hanged, or what I please;</line>
<line form="verse">And so you may inform their masterships.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Edward and Percy.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPTAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, this it is to trust a broken staff:</line>
<line form="verse">Had we not been persuaded, John our King</line>
<line form="verse">Would with his army have relieved the town,</line>
<line form="verse">We had not stood upon defiance so:</line>
<line form="verse">But now &#8217;tis past that no man can recall,</line>
<line form="verse">And better some do go to wrack them all.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. The French camp; tent of the Duke of Normandy.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Charles of Normandy, Villiers, King John)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Duke of Normandy is shocked at Villiers&#8217;s request for a safe-conduct for the English, and refuses it. He is even more shocked when Villiers then announces his intention of returning as a prisoner to Salisbury. They debate the nature of honor and of which oaths might supersede which other ones; in the end the Duke is so impressed by Villiers&#8217;s honor that he writes out the safe-conduct. Villiers goes off to deliver it, while King John comes in, prepared for battle. The Duke is more skeptical than the confident King of the wisdom of giving battle today, especially due to a prophecy he heard. But John reinterprets the prophecy to the advantage of the French. Certain that their numerical superiority will be sufficient, John plans to capture first Prince Edward and then his father.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles of Normandy and Villiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I wonder, Villiers, thou shouldest importune me</line>
<line form="verse">For one that is our deadly enemy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not for his sake, my gracious lord, so much</line>
<line form="verse">Am I become an earnest advocate,</line>
<line form="verse">As that thereby my ransom will be quit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy ransom, man? Why needest thou talk of that?</line>
<line form="verse">Art thou not free? And are not all occasions,</line>
<line form="verse">That happen for advantage of our foes,</line>
<line form="verse">To be accepted of, and stood upon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, good my lord, except the same be just;</line>
<line form="verse">For profit must with honor be comixt,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else our actions are but scandalous.</line>
<line form="verse">But, letting pass their intricate objections,</line>
<line form="verse">Wilt please your highness to subscribe, or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villiers, I will not, nor I cannot do it;</line>
<line form="verse">Salisbury shall not have his will so much,</line>
<line form="verse">To claim a passport how it pleaseth himself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, then I know the extremity, my lord;</line>
<line form="verse">I must return to prison whence I came.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Return? I hope thou wilt not;</line>
<line form="verse">What bird that hath escaped the fowler&#8217;s gin,</line>
<line form="verse">Will not beware how she&#8217;s ensnared again?</line>
<line form="verse">Or, what is he, so senseless and secure,</line>
<line form="verse">That, having hardly past a dangerous gul,</line>
<line form="verse">Will put himself in peril there again?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, but it is mine oath, my gracious lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Which I in conscience may not violate,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else a kingdom should not draw me hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thine oath? Why, tat doth bind thee to abide:</line>
<line form="verse">Hast thou not sworn obedience to thy Prince?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In all things that uprightly he commands:</line>
<line form="verse">But either to persuade or threaten me,</line>
<line form="verse">Not to perform the covenant of my word,</line>
<line form="verse">Is lawless, and I need not to obey.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, is it lawful for a man to kill,</line>
<line form="verse">And not, to break a promise with his foe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To kill, my lord, when war is once proclaimed,</line>
<line form="verse">So that our quarrel be for wrongs received,</line>
<line form="verse">No doubt, is lawfully permitted us;</line>
<line form="verse">But in an oath we must be well advised,</line>
<line form="verse">How we do swear, and, when we once have sworn,</line>
<line form="verse">Not to infringe it, though we die therefore:</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, my lord, as willing I return,</line>
<line form="verse">As if I were to fly to paradise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, my Villiers; thine honorable min</line>
<line form="verse">Deserves to be eternally admired.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy suit shall be no longer thus deferred:</line>
<line form="verse">Give me the paper, I&#8217;ll subscribe to it;</line>
<line form="verse">And, wheretofore I loved thee as Villiers,</line>
<line form="verse">Hereafter, I&#8217;ll embrace thee as myself.</line>
<line form="verse">Stay, and be still in favor with thy lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VILLIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I humbly thank you grace; I must dispatch,</line>
<line form="verse">And send this passport first unto the Earl,</line>
<line form="verse">And then I will attend your highness pleasure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do so, Villiers;&#8212;and Charles, when he hath need,</line>
<line form="verse">Be such his soldiers, howsoever he speed!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Villiers.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King John.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, Charles, and arm thee; Edward is entrapped,</line>
<line form="verse">The Prince of Wales is fallen into our hands,</line>
<line form="verse">And we have compassed him; he cannot escape.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But will your highness fight today?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What else, my son? He&#8217;s scarce eight thousand strong,</line>
<line form="verse">And we are threescore thousand at the least.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have a prophecy, my gracious lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein is written what success is like</line>
<line form="verse">To happen us in this outrageous war;</line>
<line form="verse">It was delivered me at Cressy&#8217;s field</line>
<line form="verse">By one that is an aged hermit there.</line>
<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;When feathered fowl shall make thine army tremble,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And flint stones rise and break the battle ray,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Then think on him that doth not now dissemble;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>For that shall be the hapless dreadful day:</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Yet, in the end, thy foot thou shalt advance</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>As far in England as thy foe in France.&#8221;</recite></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By this it seems we shall be fortunate:</line>
<line form="verse">For as it is impossible that stones</line>
<line form="verse">Should ever rise and break the battle ray,</line>
<line form="verse">Or airy foul make men in arms to quake,</line>
<line form="verse">So is it like, we shall not be subdued:</line>
<line form="verse">Or say this might be true, yet in the end,</line>
<line form="verse">Since he doth promise we shall drive him hence</line>
<line form="verse">And forage their country as they have done ours,</line>
<line form="verse">By this revenge that loss will seem the less.</line>
<line form="verse">But all are frivolous fancies, toys, and dreams:</line>
<line form="verse">Once we are sure we have ensnared the son,</line>
<line form="verse">Catch we the father after how we can.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. The English camp.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Prince Edward, Audley, French Heralds)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Prince Edward and Lord Audley are surrounded by the massive French army and can see no way out. A herald from King John comes to them, offering to spare the Englsih if the Prince and a hundred knights yield to John. The Prince rejects the offer, preferring to fight it out. A herald from the Duke of Normandy comes net, bringing a horse from the Duke and the suggestion that the Prince should fly or be killed; enraged at the suggestion of cowardice, Prince Edward sends him packing. A third herald, this one from King John&#8217;s second son, Philip, brings Prince Edward a prayer-book, telling him he is in great need of it. The Prince sends that herald back as well. He asks Audley&#8217;s advice on how they stand, and the old man replies by pointing out that the uselessness of fearing death.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Prince Edward, Audley, and others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Audley, the arms of death embrace us round,</line>
<line form="verse">And comfort have we none, save that to die</line>
<line form="verse">We pay sower earnest for a sweeter life.</line>
<line form="verse">At Cressy&#8217;s field out clouds of warlike smoke</line>
<line form="verse">Choked up those French mouths and dissevered them;</line>
<line form="verse">But now their multitudes of millions hide,</line>
<line form="verse">Masking as twere, the beauteous burning sun,</line>
<line form="verse">Leaving no hope to us, but sullen dark</line>
<line form="verse">And eyeless terror of all ending night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This sudden, mighty, and expedient head</line>
<line form="verse">That they have made, fair prince, is wonderful.</line>
<line form="verse">Before us in the valley lies the king,</line>
<line form="verse">Vantaged with all that heaven and earth can yield;</line>
<line form="verse">His party stronger battled than our whole:</line>
<line form="verse">His son, the braving Duke of Normandy,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath trimmed the mountain on our right hand up</line>
<line form="verse">In shining plate, that now the aspiring hill</line>
<line form="verse">Shews like a silver quarry or an orb,</line>
<line form="verse">Aloft the which the banners, bannarets,</line>
<line form="verse">And new replenished pendants cuff the air</line>
<line form="verse">And beat the winds, that for their gaudiness</line>
<line form="verse">Struggles to kiss them: on our left hand lies</line>
<line form="verse">Phillip, the younger issue of the king,</line>
<line form="verse">Coating the other hill in such array,</line>
<line form="verse">That all his guilded upright pikes do seem</line>
<line form="verse">Straight trees of gold, the pendants leaves;</line>
<line form="verse">And their device of antique heraldry,</line>
<line form="verse">Quartered in colours, seeming sundry fruits,</line>
<line form="verse">Makes it the orchard of the Hesperides:</line>
<line form="verse">Behind us too the hill doth bear his height,</line>
<line form="verse">For like a half-moon, opening but one way,</line>
<line form="verse">It rounds us in; there at our backs are lodged</line>
<line form="verse">The fatal crossbows, and the battle there</line>
<line form="verse">Is governed by the rough Chatillion.</line>
<line form="verse">Then thus it stands: the valley for our flight</line>
<line form="verse">The king binds in; the hills on either hand</line>
<line form="verse">Are proudly royalized by his sons;</line>
<line form="verse">And on the Hill behind stands certain death</line>
<line form="verse">In pay and service with Chatillion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Death&#8217;s name is much more mighty than his deeds;</line>
<line form="verse">Thy parcelling this power hath made it more.</line>
<line form="verse">As many sands as these my hands can hold,</line>
<line form="verse">Are but my handful of so many sands;</line>
<line form="verse">Then, all the world, and call it but a power,</line>
<line form="verse">Easily ta&#8217;en up, and quickly thrown away:</line>
<line form="verse">But if I stand to count them sand by sand,</line>
<line form="verse">The number would confound my memory,</line>
<line form="verse">And make a thousand millions of a task,</line>
<line form="verse">Which briefly is no more, indeed, than one.</line>
<line form="verse">These quarters, squadrons, and these regiments,</line>
<line form="verse">Before, behind us, and on either hand,</line>
<line form="verse">Are but a power. When we name a man,</line>
<line form="verse">His hand, his foot, his head hath several strengths;</line>
<line form="verse">And being all but one self instant strength,</line>
<line form="verse">Why, all this many, Audley, is but one,</line>
<line form="verse">And we can call it all but one man&#8217;s strength.</line>
<line form="verse">He that hath far to go, tells it by miles;</line>
<line form="verse">If he should tell the steps, it kills his heart:</line>
<line form="verse">The drops are infinite, that make a flood,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet, thou knowest, we call it but a Rain.</line>
<line form="verse">There is but one France, one King of France,</line>
<line form="verse">That France hath no more kings; and that same King</line>
<line form="verse">Hath but the puissant legion of one king,</line>
<line form="verse">And we have one: then apprehend no odds,</line>
<line form="verse">For one to one is fair equality.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter First French Herald from King John.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What tidings, messenger? Be plain and brief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FR. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The King of France, my sovereign lord and master,</line>
<line form="verse">Greets by me his foe, the Prince of Wales:</line>
<line form="verse">If thou call forth a hundred men of name,</line>
<line form="verse">Of lords, knights, squires, and English gentlemen,</line>
<line form="verse">And with thyself and those kneel at his feet,</line>
<line form="verse">He straight will fold his bloody colours up,</line>
<line form="verse">And ransom shall redeem lives forfeited;</line>
<line form="verse">If not, this day shall drink more English blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Than ere was buried in our British earth.</line>
<line form="verse">What is the answer to his proffered mercy?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This heaven, that covers France, contains the mercy</line>
<line form="verse">That draws from me submissive orizons;</line>
<line form="verse">That such base breath should vanish from my lips,</line>
<line form="verse">To urge the plea of mercy to a man,</line>
<line form="verse">The lord forbid! Return, and tell the king,</line>
<line form="verse">My tongue is made of steel, and it shall beg</line>
<line form="verse">My mercy on his coward burgonet;</line>
<line form="verse">Tell him, my colours are as red as his,</line>
<line form="verse">My men as bold, our English arms as strong:</line>
<line form="verse">Return him my defiance in his face.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FR. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Second French Herald.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What news with thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. FR. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Duke of Normandy, my lord and master,</line>
<line form="verse">Pitying thy youth is so ingirt with peril,</line>
<line form="verse">By me hath sent a nimble-jointed jennet,</line>
<line form="verse">As swift as ever yet thou didst bestride,</line>
<line form="verse">And therewithall he counsels thee to fly;</line>
<line form="verse">Else death himself hath sworn that thou shalt die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Back with the beast unto the beast that sent him!</line>
<line form="verse">Tell him I cannot sit a coward&#8217;s horse;</line>
<line form="verse">Bid him today bestride the jade himself,</line>
<line form="verse">For I will stain my horse quite o&#8217;er with blood,</line>
<line form="verse">And double gild my spurs, but I will catch him;</line>
<line form="verse">So tell the cap&#8217;ring boy, and get thee gone.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit French Herald.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Third French Herald.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FR. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward of Wales, Phillip, the second son</line>
<line form="verse">To the most mighty christian king of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Seeing thy body&#8217;s living date expired,</line>
<line form="verse">All full of charity and christian love,</line>
<line form="verse">Commends this book, full fraught with prayers,</line>
<line form="verse">To thy fair hand and for thy hour of life</line>
<line form="verse">Intreats thee that thou meditate therein,</line>
<line form="verse">And arm thy soul for her long journey towards&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Thus have I done his bidding, and return.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Herald of Phillip, greet thy lord from me:</line>
<line form="verse">All good that he can send, I can receive;</line>
<line form="verse">But thinkst thou not, the unadvised boy</line>
<line form="verse">Hath wronged himself in thus far tendering me?</line>
<line form="verse">Happily he cannot pray without the book&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I think him no divine extemporall&#8212;,</line>
<line form="verse">Then render back this common place of prayer,</line>
<line form="verse">To do himself good in adversity;</line>
<line form="verse">Beside he knows not my sins&#8217; quality,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore knows no prayers for my avail;</line>
<line form="verse">Ere night his prayer may be to pray to God,</line>
<line form="verse">To put it in my heart to hear his prayer.</line>
<line form="verse">So tell the courtly wanton, and be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. FR. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How confident their strength and number makes them!&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Now, Audley, sound those silver wings of thine,</line>
<line form="verse">And let those milk white messengers of time</line>
<line form="verse">Shew thy times learning in this dangerous time.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy self art bruis&#8217;d and bit with many broils,</line>
<line form="verse">And stratagems forepast with iron pens</line>
<line form="verse">Are texted in thine honorable face;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art a married man in this distress,</line>
<line form="verse">But danger woos me as a blushing maid:</line>
<line form="verse">Teach me an answer to this perilous time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To die is all as common as to live:</line>
<line form="verse">The one ince-wise, the other holds in chase;</line>
<line form="verse">For, from the instant we begin to live,</line>
<line form="verse">We do pursue and hunt the time to die:</line>
<line form="verse">First bud we, then we blow, and after seed,</line>
<line form="verse">Then, presently, we fall; and, as a shade</line>
<line form="verse">Follows the body, so we follow death.</line>
<line form="verse">If, then, we hunt for death, why do we fear it?</line>
<line form="verse">If we fear it, why do we follow it?</line>
<line form="verse">If we do fear, how can we shun it?</line>
<line form="verse">If we do fear, with fear we do but aide</line>
<line form="verse">The thing we fear to seize on us the sooner:</line>
<line form="verse">If we fear not, then no resolved proffer</line>
<line form="verse">Can overthrow the limit of our fate;</line>
<line form="verse">For, whether ripe or rotten, drop we shall,</line>
<line form="verse">As we do draw the lottery of our doom.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, good old man, a thousand thousand armors</line>
<line form="verse">These words of thine have buckled on my back:</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, what an idiot hast thou made of life,</line>
<line form="verse">To seek the thing it fears! And how disgraced</line>
<line form="verse">The imperial victory of murdering death,</line>
<line form="verse">Since all the lives his conquering arrows strike</line>
<line form="verse">Seek him, and he not them, to shame his glory!</line>
<line form="verse">I will not give a penny for a life,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor half a halfpenny to shun grim death,</line>
<line form="verse">Since for to live is but to seek to die,</line>
<line form="verse">And dying but beginning of new life.</line>
<line form="verse">Let come the hour when he that rules it will!</line>
<line form="verse">To live or die I hold indifferent.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. The French camp.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King John, Charles, Phillip, Salisbury, Second French Captain)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The sky grows dark and the French soldiers are struck with fear. Prince Philip reports that a huge flight of ravens has disquieted them even more. King John remembers the prophecy, but rejects fear, and again reinterprets the sign in favor of the French. A French captain brings in Salisbury, whom he has captured; John orders him hanged immediately, but the Duke of Normandy protests, knowing that Salisbury had his safe-conduct. The King and he argue, and in the end John angrily lets Salisbury go, telling him to inform Edward of his son&#8217;s impending death.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King John and Charles.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A sudden darkness hath defaced the sky,</line>
<line form="verse">The winds are crept into their caves for fear,</line>
<line form="verse">The leaves move not, the world is hushed and still,</line>
<line form="verse">The birds cease singing, and the wandering brooks</line>
<line form="verse">Murmur no wonted greeting to their shores;</line>
<line form="verse">Silence attends some wonder and expecteth</line>
<line form="verse">That heaven should pronounce some prophecy:</line>
<line form="verse">Where, or from whom, proceeds this silence, Charles?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Our men, with open mouths and staring eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">Look on each other, as they did attend</line>
<line form="verse">Each other&#8217;s words, and yet no creature speaks;</line>
<line form="verse">A tongue-tied fear hath made a midnight hour,</line>
<line form="verse">And speeches sleep through all the waking regions.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But now the pompous sun, in all his pride,</line>
<line form="verse">Looked through his golden coach upon the world,</line>
<line form="verse">And, on a sudden, hath he hid himself,</line>
<line form="verse">That now the under earth is as a grave,</line>
<line form="verse">Dark, deadly, silent, and uncomfortable.</line>
<stagedir type="action">A clamor of ravens.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hark, what a deadly outery do I hear?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here comes my brother Phillip.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">All dismayed:</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Phillip.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What fearful words are those thy looks presage?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A flight, a flight!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Coward, what flight? Thou liest, there needs no flight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A flight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Awake thy craven powers, and tell on</line>
<line form="verse">The substance of that very fear indeed,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is so ghastly printed in thy face:</line>
<line form="verse">What is the matter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A flight of ugly ravens</line>
<line form="verse">Do croak and hover o&#8217;er our soldiers&#8217; heads,</line>
<line form="verse">And keep in triangles and cornered squares,</line>
<line form="verse">Right as our forces are embattled;</line>
<line form="verse">With their approach there came this sudden fog,</line>
<line form="verse">Which now hath hid the airy floor of heaven</line>
<line form="verse">And made at noon a night unnatural</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the quaking and dismayed world:</line>
<line form="verse">In brief, our soldiers have let fall their arms,</line>
<line form="verse">And stand like metamorphosed images,</line>
<line form="verse">Bloodless and pale, one gazing on another.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, now I call to mind the prophecy,</line>
<line form="verse">But I must give no entrance to a fear.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Return, and hearten up these yielding souls:</line>
<line form="verse">Tell them, the ravens, seeing them in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">So many fair against a famished few,</line>
<line form="verse">Come but to dine upon their handy work</line>
<line form="verse">And prey upon the carrion that they kill:</line>
<line form="verse">For when we see a horse laid down to die,</line>
<line form="verse">Although he be not dead, the ravenous birds</line>
<line form="verse">Sit watching the departure of his life;</line>
<line form="verse">Even so these ravens for the carcasses</line>
<line form="verse">Of those poor English, that are marked to die,</line>
<line form="verse">Hover about, and, if they cry to us,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis but for meat that we must kill for them.</line>
<line form="verse">Away, and comfort up my soldiers,</line>
<line form="verse">And sound the trumpets, and at once dispatch</line>
<line form="verse">This little business of a silly fraud.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Phillip.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="action">Another noise. Salisbury brought in by the Second French Captain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. FR. CAPTAIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Behold, my liege, this knight and forty mo,</line>
<line form="verse">Of whom the better part are slain and fled,</line>
<line form="verse">With all endeavor sought to break our ranks,</line>
<line form="verse">And make their way to the encompassed prince:</line>
<line form="verse">Dispose of him as please your majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, and the next bough, soldier, that thou seest,</line>
<line form="verse">Disgrace it with his body presently;</line>
<line form="verse">For I do hold a tree in France too good</line>
<line form="verse">To be the gallows of an English thief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord of Normandy, I have your pass</line>
<line form="verse">And warrant for my safety through this land.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villiers procured it for thee, did he not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He did.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And it is current; thou shalt freely pass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Aye, freely to the gallows to be hanged,</line>
<line form="verse">Without denial or impediment.</line>
<line form="verse">Away with him!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hope your highness will not so disgrace me,</line>
<line form="verse">And dash the virtue of my seal at arms:</line>
<line form="verse">He hath my never broken name to shew,</line>
<line form="verse">Charactered with this princely hand of mine:</line>
<line form="verse">And rather let me leave to be a prince</line>
<line form="verse">Than break the stable verdict of a prince:</line>
<line form="verse">I do beseech you, let him pass in quiet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou and thy word lie both in my command:</line>
<line form="verse">What canst thou promise that I cannot break?</line>
<line form="verse">Which of these twain is greater infamy,</line>
<line form="verse">To disobey thy father or thyself?</line>
<line form="verse">Thy word, nor no mans, may exceed his power;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor that same man doth never break his word,</line>
<line form="verse">That keeps it to the utmost of his power.</line>
<line form="verse">The breach of faith dwells in the soul&#8217;s consent:</line>
<line form="verse">Which if thyself without consent do break,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art not charged with the breach of faith.</line>
<line form="verse">Go, hang him: for thy license lies in me,</line>
<line form="verse">And my constraint stands the excuse for thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, am I not a soldier in my word?</line>
<line form="verse">Then, arms, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>, and let them fight that list!</line>
<line form="verse">Shall I not give my girdle from my waste,</line>
<line form="verse">But with a gardion I shall be controlled,</line>
<line form="verse">To say I may not give my things away?</line>
<line form="verse">Upon my soul, had Edward, prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">Engaged his word, writ down his noble hand</line>
<line form="verse">For all your knights to pass his father&#8217;s land,</line>
<line form="verse">The royal king, to grace his warlike son,</line>
<line form="verse">Would not alone safe conduct give to them,</line>
<line form="verse">But with all bounty feasted them and theirs.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dwell&#8217;st thou on precedents? Then be it so!</line>
<line form="verse">Say, Englishman, of what degree thou art.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An Earl in England, though a prisoner here,</line>
<line form="verse">And those that know me, call me Salisbury.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then, Salisbury, say whether thou art bound.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To Callice, where my liege, King Edward, is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To Callice, Salisbury? Then, to Callice pack,</line>
<line form="verse">And bid the king prepare a noble grave,</line>
<line form="verse">To put his princely son, black Edward, in.</line>
<line form="verse">And as thou travelst westward from this place,</line>
<line form="verse">Some two leagues hence there is a lofty hill,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose top seems topless, for the embracing sky</line>
<line form="verse">Doth hide his high head in her azure bosom;</line>
<line form="verse">Upon whose tall top when thy foot attains,</line>
<line form="verse">Look back upon the humble vale beneath&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Humble of late, but now made proud with arms&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And thence behold the wretched prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">Hooped with a bond of iron round about.</line>
<line form="verse">After which sight, to Callice spur amain,</line>
<line form="verse">And say, the prince was smothered and not slain:</line>
<line form="verse">And tell the king this is not all his ill;</line>
<line form="verse">For I will greet him, ere he thinks I will.</line>
<line form="verse">Away, be gone; the smoke but of our shot</line>
<line form="verse">Will choke our foes, though bullets hit them not.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. A part of the field of battle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Edward, Artois)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Artois and Prince Edward meet up in the middle of battle. The English arrows have done great damage to the French, but the archers are running out. The Prince dismisses Artois wish for more, and encourages his men to throw aside their bows and fight the French with stones.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Enter prince Edward and Artois.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How fares your grace? Are you not shot, my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, dear Artois; but choked with dust and smoke,</line>
<line form="verse">And stepped aside for breath and fresher air.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ARTOIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Breath, then, and to it again: the amazed French</line>
<line form="verse">Are quite distract with gazing on the crows;</line>
<line form="verse">And, were our quivers full of shafts again,</line>
<line form="verse">Your grace should see a glorious day of this:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">O, for more arrows, lord; that&#8217;s our want.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Courage, Artois! A fig for feather&#8217;d shafts,</line>
<line form="verse">When feather&#8217;d fowls do bandy on our side.</line>
<line form="verse">What need we fight, and sweat, and keep a coil,</line>
<line form="verse">When railing crows outscold our adversaries?</line>
<line form="verse">Up, up, Artois! The ground itself is armed</line>
<line form="verse">With fire containing flint; command our bows</line>
<line form="verse">To hurl away their pretty colore&#8217;d yew,</line>
<line form="verse">And to it with stones: away, Artois, away!</line>
<line form="verse">My soul doth prophecy we win the day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="7">
<scenetitle>Scene 7</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. Another part of the field of battle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King John, Charles, Phillip)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Even King John finds himself fearful as he sees his panic-stricken army flee. The Duke of Normandy runs in to tell him that in the panic the French are starting to kill each other. Prince Philip is ashamed that so large an army is being beaten by so small a force. King John rallies his sons and his knights, and makes one last desperate charge.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Enter King John.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Our multitudes are in themselves confounded,</line>
<line form="verse">Dismayed, and distraught; swift starting fear</line>
<line form="verse">Hath buzzed a cold dismay through all our army,</line>
<line form="verse">And every petty disadvantage prompts</line>
<line form="verse">The fear possessed abject soul to fly.</line>
<line form="verse">Myself, whose spirit is steel to their dull lead,</line>
<line form="verse">What with recalling of the prophecy,</line>
<line form="verse">And that our native stones from English arms</line>
<line form="verse">Rebel against us, find myself attainted</line>
<line form="verse">With strong surprise of weak and yielding fear.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fly, father, fly! The French do kill the French,</line>
<line form="verse">Some that would stand let drive at some that fly;</line>
<line form="verse">Our drums strike nothing but discouragement,</line>
<line form="verse">Our trumpets sound dishonor and retire;</line>
<line form="verse">The spirit of fear, that feareth nought but death,</line>
<line form="verse">Cowardly works confusion on itself.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Phillip.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pluck out your eyes, and see not this day&#8217;s shame!</line>
<line form="verse">An arm hath beat an army; one poor David</line>
<line form="verse">Hath with a stone foiled twenty stout Goliaths;</line>
<line form="verse">Some twenty naked starvelings with small flints,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath driven back a puissant host of men,</line>
<line form="verse">Arrayed and fenced in all accomplements.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mordieu! They quoit at us and kill us up;</line>
<line form="verse">No less than forty thousand wicked elders</line>
<line form="verse">Have forty lean slaves this day stoned to death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, that I were some other countryman!</line>
<line form="verse">This day hath set derision on the French,</line>
<line form="verse">And all the world will blurt and scorn at us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, is there no hope left?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No hope, but death, to bury up our shame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Make up once more with me; the twentieth part</line>
<line form="verse">Of those that live, are men inow to quail</line>
<line form="verse">The feeble handful on the adverse part.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then charge again: if heaven be not opposed,</line>
<line form="verse">We cannot lose the day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">On, away!</line>
</speech>


<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="8">
<scenetitle>Scene 8</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. Another part of the field of battle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Audley, Two English Esquires)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Two squires rescue the wounded Audley.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Audley, wounded, and rescued by two English Esquires.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. ESQUIRE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How fares my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Even as a man may do,</line>
<line form="verse">That dines at such a bloody feast as this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. ESQUIRE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hope, my lord, that is no mortal scar.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No matter, if it be; the count is cast,</line>
<line form="verse">And, in the worst, ends but a mortal man.</line>
<line form="verse">Good friends, convey me to the princely Edward,</line>
<line form="verse">That in the crimson bravery of my blood</line>
<line form="verse">I may become him with saluting him.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll smile, and tell him, that this open scar</line>
<line form="verse">Doth end the harvest of his Audley&#8217;s war.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="9">
<scenetitle>Scene 9</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Poitou. Fields near Poitiers. The English camp.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Edward, King John, Charles, Artois, Phillip, Audley)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Both King John and the Duke of Normandy have been captured and are brought before Prince Edward. John insists that the English only won by luck, not by skill. Philip too is brought in a prisoner. So is the wounded Audley, who thinks himself near to death. The Prince refuses to let him die, offering him a great reward for his service that day, and calling for a litter to carry him with them as they march to Calais.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Prince Edward, King John, Charles, and all, with ensigns spread.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, John in France, and lately John of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy bloody ensigns are my captive colours;</line>
<line form="verse">And you, high vaunting Charles of Normandy,</line>
<line form="verse">That once today sent me a horse to fly,</line>
<line form="verse">Are now the subjects of my clemency.</line>
<line form="verse">Fie, lords! Is it not a shame that English boys,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose early days are yet not worth a beard,</line>
<line form="verse">Should in the bosom of your kingdom thus,</line>
<line form="verse">One against twenty, beat you up together?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy fortune, not thy force, hath conquered us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An argument that heaven aides the right.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Artois with Phillip.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">See, see! Artois doth bring with him along</line>
<line form="verse">The late good counsel giver to my soul.</line>
<line form="verse">Welcome, Artois; and welcome, Phillip, too:</line>
<line form="verse">Who now of you or I have need to pray?</line>
<line form="verse">Now is the proverb verified in you:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Too bright a morning breeds a low&#8217;ring day.&#8221;</line>
<stagedir type="action">Sound Trumpets. Enter Audley.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">But say, what grim discouragement comes here!</line>
<line form="verse">Alas, what thousand armed men of France</line>
<line form="verse">Have writ that note of death in Audley&#8217;s face?</line>
<line form="verse">Speak, thou that wooest death with thy careless smile,</line>
<line form="verse">And lookst so merrily upon thy grave,</line>
<line form="verse">As if thou were enamored on thine end:</line>
<line form="verse">What hungry sword hath so bereaved thy face,</line>
<line form="verse">And lopped a true friend from my loving soul?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O Prince, thy sweet bemoaning speech to me</line>
<line form="verse">Is as a mournful knell to one dead-sick.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dear Audley, if my tongue ring out thy end,</line>
<line form="verse">My arms shall be thy grave: what may I do</line>
<line form="verse">To win thy life, or to revenge thy death?</line>
<line form="verse">If thou wilt drink the blood of captive kings,</line>
<line form="verse">Or that it were restorative, command</line>
<line form="verse">A health of kings&#8217; blood, and I&#8217;ll drink to thee;</line>
<line form="verse">If honor may dispense for thee with death,</line>
<line form="verse">The never dying honor of this day</line>
<line form="verse">Share wholly, Audley, to thyself, and live.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Victorious Prince,&#8212;that thou art so, behold</line>
<line form="verse">A Caesar&#8217;s fame in king&#8217;s captivity&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">If I could hold him death but at a bay,</line>
<line form="verse">Till I did see my liege thy royal father,</line>
<line form="verse">My soul should yield this castle of my flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">This mangled tribute, with all willingness,</line>
<line form="verse">To darkness, consummation, dust, and worms.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cheerily, bold man, thy soul is all too proud</line>
<line form="verse">To yield her city for one little breach;</line>
<line form="verse">Should be divorced from her earthly spouse</line>
<line form="verse">By the soft temper of a Frenchman&#8217;s sword?</line>
<line form="verse">Lo, to repair thy life, I give to thee</line>
<line form="verse">Three thousand marks a year in English land.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AUDLEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I take thy gift, to pay the debts I owe:</line>
<line form="verse">These two poor esquires redeemed me from the French</line>
<line form="verse">With lusty and dear hazard of their lives:</line>
<line form="verse">What thou hast given me, I give to them;</line>
<line form="verse">And, as thou lovest me, prince, lay thy consent</line>
<line form="verse">To this bequeath in my last testament.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Renowned Audley, live, and have from me</line>
<line form="verse">This gift twice doubled to these esquires and thee:</line>
<line form="verse">But live or die, what thou hast given away</line>
<line form="verse">To these and theirs shall lasting freedom stay.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, gentlemen, I will see my friend bestowed</line>
<line form="verse">With in an easy litter; then we&#8217;ll march</line>
<line form="verse">Proudly toward Callice, with triumphant pace,</line>
<line form="verse">Unto my royal father, and there bring</line>
<line form="verse">The tribute of my wars, fair France his king.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Picardy. The English camp before Calais.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Edward, Queen Phillip, Derby, Soldiers, Six Citizens of Calais, Copland, King David, Salisbury, English Herald, Prince Edward, King John, Phillip, Audley, Artois)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>King Edward angrily orders an assault on the town when the six rich men of Calais finally arrive to offer their lives for the city. They beg him to remember his word, but they are so filthy and malnourished that he refuses to believe that they are in fact the richest men of Calais. They explain that it is the siege that has brought them to this, and Edward agrees to accept the capitulation, though he orders all is to be sent instantly to their deaths. Queen Philippa protests, arguing that he can only be called King of France if there are Frenchmen left alive. He yields to her and spares their lives. Copland, the esquire who captured the King of Scots, enters with his prisoner. He does not deny refusing to hand the King of Scots over, but excuses himself on the grounds of the need to think of his own repute, having decided to hand over his prisoner only to the King in person, which he now does. Edward bids his Queen to forgive him, and knights him. Salisbury arrives and gives Edward Mountford&#8217;s coronet, but also has to report his certainty that Prince Edward is dead. The Queen is distraught and the King little better, but a herald comes in to announce the arrival of the Prince, his army and his captives. Overjoyed, the King greets his son with great honor and King John with great sarcasm. The Prince asks his father to give him more opportunities to show his worth in battle. King Edward, however, announces a momentary end to the fighting and prepares to return to England with all the royal captives and his family.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King Edward, Queen Phillip, Derby, soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No more, Queen Phillip, pacify yourself;</line>
<line form="verse">Copland, except he can excuse his fault,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall find displeasure written in our looks.</line>
<line form="verse">And now unto this proud resisting town!</line>
<line form="verse">Soldiers, assault: I will no longer stay,</line>
<line form="verse">To be deluded by their false delays;</line>
<line form="verse">Put all to sword, and make the spoil your own.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter six Citizens of Calais in their shirts, barefoot, with halters about their necks.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. CIT. CAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mercy, king Edward, mercy, gracious lord!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Contemptuous villains, call ye now for truce?</line>
<line form="verse">Mine ears are stopped against your bootless cries:&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Sound, drums alarum; draw threatening swords!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. CIT. CAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, noble Prince, take pity on this town,</line>
<line form="verse">And hear us, mighty king:</line>
<line form="verse">We claim the promise that your highness made;</line>
<line form="verse">The two days&#8217; respite is not yet expired,</line>
<line form="verse">And we are come with willingness to bear</line>
<line form="verse">What torturing death or punishment you please,</line>
<line form="verse">So that the trembling multitude be saved.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My promise? Well, I do confess as much:</line>
<line form="verse">But I do require the chiefest citizens</line>
<line form="verse">And men of most account that should submit;</line>
<line form="verse">You, peradventure, are but servile grooms,</line>
<line form="verse">Or some felonious robbers on the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom, apprehended, law would execute,</line>
<line form="verse">Albeit severity lay dead in us:</line>
<line form="verse">No, no, ye cannot overreach us thus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. CIT. CAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The sun, dread lord, that in the western fall</line>
<line form="verse">Beholds us now low brought through misery,</line>
<line form="verse">Did in the Orient purple of the morn</line>
<line form="verse">Salute our coming forth, when we were known;</line>
<line form="verse">Or may our portion be with damned fiends.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If it be so, then let our covenant stand:</line>
<line form="verse">We take possession of the town in peace,</line>
<line form="verse">But, for yourselves, look you for no remorse;</line>
<line form="verse">But, as imperial justice hath decreed,</line>
<line form="verse">Your bodies shall be dragged about these walls,</line>
<line form="verse">And after feel the stroke of quartering steel:</line>
<line form="verse">This is your doom;&#8212;go, soldiers, see it done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUEEN PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, be more mild unto these yielding men!</line>
<line form="verse">It is a glorious thing to stablish peace,</line>
<line form="verse">And kings approach the nearest unto God</line>
<line form="verse">By giving life and safety unto men:</line>
<line form="verse">As thou intendest to be King of France,</line>
<line form="verse">So let her people live to call thee king;</line>
<line form="verse">For what the sword cuts down or fire hath spoiled,</line>
<line form="verse">Is held in reputation none of ours.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Although experience teach us this is true,</line>
<line form="verse">That peaceful quietness brings most delight,</line>
<line form="verse">When most of all abuses are controlled;</line>
<line form="verse">Yet, insomuch it shall be known that we</line>
<line form="verse">As well can master our affections</line>
<line form="verse">As conquer other by the dint of sword,</line>
<line form="verse">Phillip, prevail; we yield to thy request:</line>
<line form="verse">These men shall live to boast of clemency,</line>
<line form="verse">And, tyranny, strike terror to thyself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. CIT. CAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Long live your highness! Happy be your reign!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, get you hence, return unto the town,</line>
<line form="verse">And if this kindness hath deserved your love,</line>
<line form="verse">Learn then to reverence Edward as your king.&#8212;</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Citizens of Calais.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now, might we hear of our affairs abroad,</line>
<line form="verse">We would, till gloomy winter were o&#8217;er spent,</line>
<line form="verse">Dispose our men in garrison a while.</line>
<line form="verse">But who comes here?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Copland and King David.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DERBY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Copland, my lord, and David, King of Scots.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is this the proud presumptuous esquire of the north,</line>
<line form="verse">That would not yield his prisoner to my Queen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COPLAND.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am, my liege, a northern esquire indeed,</line>
<line form="verse">But neither proud nor insolent, I trust.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What moved thee, then, to be so obstinate</line>
<line form="verse">To contradict our royal Queen&#8217;s desire?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COPLAND.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No wilful disobedience, mighty lord,</line>
<line form="verse">But my desert and public law at arms:</line>
<line form="verse">I took the king myself in single fight,</line>
<line form="verse">And, like a soldiers, would be loath to lose</line>
<line form="verse">The least pre-eminence that I had won.</line>
<line form="verse">And Copland straight upon your highness&#8217; charge</line>
<line form="verse">Is come to France, and with a lowly mind</line>
<line form="verse">Doth vale the bonnet of his victory:</line>
<line form="verse">Receive, dread lord, the custom of my fraught,</line>
<line form="verse">The wealthy tribute of my laboring hands,</line>
<line form="verse">Which should long since have been surrendered up,</line>
<line form="verse">Had but your gracious self been there in place.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUEEN PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But, Copland, thou didst scorn the king&#8217;s command,</line>
<line form="verse">Neglecting our commission in his name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COPLAND.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His name I reverence, but his person more;</line>
<line form="verse">His name shall keep me in allegiance still,</line>
<line form="verse">But to his person I will bend my knee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray thee, Phillip, let displeasure pass;</line>
<line form="verse">This man doth please me, and I like his words:</line>
<line form="verse">For what is he that will attempt great deeds,</line>
<line form="verse">And lose the glory that ensues the same?</line>
<line form="verse">All rivers have recourse unto the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">And Copland&#8217;s faith relation to his king.</line>
<line form="verse">Kneel, therefore, down: now rise, king Edward&#8217;s knight;</line>
<line form="verse">And, to maintain thy state, I freely give</line>
<line form="verse">Five hundred marks a year to thee and thine.</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Salisbury.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Welcome, lord Salisbury: what news from Britain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This, mighty king: the country we have won,</line>
<line form="verse">And John de Mountford, regent of that place,</line>
<line form="verse">Presents your highness with this coronet,</line>
<line form="verse">Protesting true allegiance to your Grace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We thank thee for thy service, valiant Earl;</line>
<line form="verse">Challenge our favor, for we owe it thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But now, my lord, as this is joyful news,</line>
<line form="verse">So must my voice be tragical again,</line>
<line form="verse">And I must sing of doleful accidents.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, have our men the overthrow at Poictiers?</line>
<line form="verse">Or is our son beset with too much odds?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SALISBURY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He was, my lord: and as my worthless self</line>
<line form="verse">With forty other serviceable knights,</line>
<line form="verse">Under safe conduct of the Dauphin&#8217;s seal,</line>
<line form="verse">Did travail that way, finding him distressed,</line>
<line form="verse">A troop of lances met us on the way,</line>
<line form="verse">Surprised, and brought us prisoners to the king,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, proud of this, and eager of revenge,</line>
<line form="verse">Commanded straight to cut off all our heads:</line>
<line form="verse">And surely we had died, but that the Duke,</line>
<line form="verse">More full of honor than his angry sire,</line>
<line form="verse">Procured our quick deliverance from thence;</line>
<line form="verse">But, ere we went, &#8220;Salute your king,&#8221; quoth he,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Bid him provide a funeral for his son:</line>
<line form="verse">To day our sword shall cut his thread of life;</line>
<line form="verse">And, sooner than he thinks, we&#8217;ll be with him,</line>
<line form="verse">To quittance those displeasures he hath done.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">This said, we past, not daring to reply;</line>
<line form="verse">Our hearts were dead, our looks diffused and wan.</line>
<line form="verse">Wandering, at last we climed unto a hill,</line>
<line form="verse">From whence, although our grief were much before,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet now to see the occasion with our eyes</line>
<line form="verse">Did thrice so much increase our heaviness:</line>
<line form="verse">For there, my lord, oh, there we did descry</line>
<line form="verse">Down in a valley how both armies lay.</line>
<line form="verse">The French had cast their trenches like a ring,</line>
<line form="verse">And every barricado&#8217;s open front</line>
<line form="verse">Was thick embossed with brazen ordinance;</line>
<line form="verse">Here stood a battaile of ten thousand horse,</line>
<line form="verse">There twice as many pikes in quadrant wise,</line>
<line form="verse">Here crossbows, and deadly wounding darts:</line>
<line form="verse">And in the midst, like to a slender point</line>
<line form="verse">Within the compass of the horizon,</line>
<line form="verse">(As twere a rising bubble in the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">A hazle wand amidst a wood of pines,</line>
<line form="verse">Or as a bear fast chained unto a stake),</line>
<line form="verse">Stood famous Edward, still expecting when</line>
<line form="verse">Those dogs of France would fasten on his flesh.</line>
<line form="verse">Anon the death procuring knell begins:</line>
<line form="verse">Off go the cannons, that with trembling noise</line>
<line form="verse">Did shake the very mountain where they stood;</line>
<line form="verse">Then sound the trumpets&#8217; clangor in the air,</line>
<line form="verse">The battles join: and, when we could no more</line>
<line form="verse">Discern the difference twixt the friend and foe,</line>
<line form="verse">So intricate the dark confusion was,</line>
<line form="verse">Away we turned our watery eyes with sighs,</line>
<line form="verse">As black as powder fuming into smoke.</line>
<line form="verse">And thus, I fear, unhappy have I told</line>
<line form="verse">The most untimely tale of Edward&#8217;s fall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUEEN PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah me, is this my welcome into France?</line>
<line form="verse">Is this the comfort that I looked to have,</line>
<line form="verse">When I should meet with my beloved son?</line>
<line form="verse">Sweet Ned, I would thy mother in the sea</line>
<line form="verse">Had been prevented of this mortal grief!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content thee, Phillip; &#8217;tis not tears will serve</line>
<line form="verse">To call him back, if he be taken hence:</line>
<line form="verse">Comfort thyself, as I do, gentle Queen,</line>
<line form="verse">With hope of sharp, unheard of, dire revenge.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">He bids me to provide his funeral,</line>
<line form="verse">And so I will; but all the peers in France</line>
<line form="verse">Shall mourners be, and weep out bloody tears,</line>
<line form="verse">Until their empty veins be dry and sere:</line>
<line form="verse">The pillars of his hearse shall be his bones;</line>
<line form="verse">The mould that covers him, their city ashes;</line>
<line form="verse">His knell, the groaning cries of dying men;</line>
<line form="verse">And, in the stead of tapers on his tomb,</line>
<line form="verse">An hundred fifty towers shall burning blaze,</line>
<line form="verse">While we bewail our valiant son&#8217;s decease.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">After a flourish, sounded within, enter an English Herald.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ENG. HERALD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Rejoice, my lord; ascend the imperial throne!</line>
<line form="verse">The mighty and redoubted prince of Wales,</line>
<line form="verse">Great servitor to bloody Mars in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">The Frenchman&#8217;s terror, and his country&#8217;s fame,</line>
<line form="verse">Triumphant rideth like a Roman peer,</line>
<line form="verse">And, lowly at his stirrup, comes afoot</line>
<line form="verse">King John of France, together with his son,</line>
<line form="verse">In captive bonds; whose diadem he brings</line>
<line form="verse">To crown thee with, and to proclaim thee king.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Away with mourning, Phillip, wipe thine eyes;&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Sound, trumpets, welcome in Plantagenet!</line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Prince Edward, King John, Phillip, Audley, Artois.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">As things long lost, when they are found again,</line>
<line form="verse">So doth my son rejoice his father&#8217;s heart,</line>
<line form="verse">For whom even now my soul was much perplexed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUEEN PHILLIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be this a token to express my joy,</line>
<stagedir type="action">Kisses him.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">For inward passion will not let me speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious father, here receive the gift.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Presenting him with King John&#8217;s crown.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">This wreath of conquest and reward of war,</line>
<line form="verse">Got with as mickle peril of our lives,</line>
<line form="verse">As ere was thing of price before this day;</line>
<line form="verse">Install your highness in your proper right:</line>
<line form="verse">And, herewithall, I render to your hands</line>
<line form="verse">These prisoners, chief occasion of our strife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So, John of France, I see you keep your word:</line>
<line form="verse">You promised to be sooner with our self</line>
<line form="verse">Than we did think for, and &#8217;tis so indeed:</line>
<line form="verse">But, had you done at first as now you do,</line>
<line form="verse">How many civil towns had stood untouched,</line>
<line form="verse">That now are turned to ragged heaps of stones!</line>
<line form="verse">How many people&#8217;s lives mightst thou have saved,</line>
<line form="verse">That are untimely sunk into their graves!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Edward, recount not things irrevocable;</line>
<line form="verse">Tell me what ransom thou requirest to have.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy ransom, John, hereafter shall be known:</line>
<line form="verse">But first to England thou must cross the seas,</line>
<line form="verse">To see what entertainment it affords;</line>
<line form="verse">How ere it falls, it cannot be so bad,</line>
<line form="verse">As ours hath been since we arrived in France.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Accursed man! Of this I was foretold,</line>
<line form="verse">But did misconster what the prophet told.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PRINCE EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, father, this petition Edward makes</line>
<line form="verse">To thee, whose grace hath been his strongest shield,</line>
<line form="verse">That, as thy pleasure chose me for the man</line>
<line form="verse">To be the instrument to shew thy power,</line>
<line form="verse">So thou wilt grant that many princes more,</line>
<line form="verse">Bred and brought up within that little Isle,</line>
<line form="verse">May still be famous for like victories!</line>
<line form="verse">And, for my part, the bloody scars I bear,</line>
<line form="verse">And weary nights that I have watched in field,</line>
<line form="verse">The dangerous conflicts I have often had,</line>
<line form="verse">The fearful menaces were proffered me,</line>
<line form="verse">The heat and cold and what else might displease:</line>
<line form="verse">I wish were now redoubled twenty fold,</line>
<line form="verse">So that hereafter ages, when they read</line>
<line form="verse">The painful traffic of my tender youth,</line>
<line form="verse">Might thereby be inflamed with such resolve,</line>
<line form="verse">As not the territories of France alone,</line>
<line form="verse">But likewise Spain, Turkey, and what countries else</line>
<line form="verse">That justly would provoke fair England&#8217;s ire,</line>
<line form="verse">Might, at their presence, tremble and retire.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING EDWARD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, English lords, we do proclaim a rest,</line>
<line form="verse">An intercession of our painful arms:</line>
<line form="verse">Sheath up your swords, refresh your weary limbs,</line>
<line form="verse">Peruse your spoils; and, after we have breathed</line>
<line form="verse">A day or two within this haven town,</line>
<line form="verse">God willing, then for England we&#8217;ll be shipped;</line>
<line form="verse">Where, in a happy hour, I trust, we shall</line>
<line form="verse">Arrive, three kings, two princes, and a queen.</line>
</speech>

<finistitle>FINIS.</finistitle>

</scene>
</act>


<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>

