<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Henry VI, Pt. 1">The First Part of Henry the Sixth</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="Henry VI, Part 1">

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="PUC.">Joan de Pucelle</persname>
<persdescription>Joan de Pucelle is history&#8217;s Joan of Arc, though she is no saint in this play. An plain-spoken woman with no doubts whatsoever, she breezes through all difficulties, seeing at once that Reignier is not the Dolphin, convincing the French to follow her, vanquishing the English, talking her way out of blame, vanquishing again, and convincing the Duke of Burgundy to join the French cause. She is an excellent fighter, better at swordplay than Charles is. Other than all-out assault, she is also adept at tricking her way into advantageous situations and capturing cities that way. Though she claims to be a maid and helped by the Virgin Mary, it turns out that she actually talks with demons, and probably sleeps with the entirety of the French leadership. She has a sharp tongue, mocking the English well, and swearing with great effect when she is captured. She grows more and more full of herself as time goes on, and in the end refuses to recognize her father, insisting that she is in fact nobly born. Desperate to avoid death, she swears that she is a virgin and then that she is pregnant, but cannot decide on an identity for the father. She is burned alive at the stake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COUNT.">Countess of Auvergne</persname>
<persdescription>Countess of Auvergne is a patriotic Frenchwoman who thinks she will be able to deal a terrible blow to the English by capturing Talbot, and not incidentally become very famous. Unfortunately for her, he sees through her trick before he even meets her. She is bemused to find him a physically unimpressive man, and quite seduced by him once he tricks her &#8212; unless, of course, she is merely flattering out of fear for her life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MAR.">Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Margaret is Reignier of Anjou&#8217;s daughter, and sets stock by his empty claim to be a King. Captured by Suffolk, she is oblivious to the fact that he falls in love with her on sight, though she feels more than a twinge in the same direction herself. She attempts to immediately get down to business with him and to work out a ransom, and becomes impatient with his lack of attention to her. She is proud, though not unaware of the poverty of her position. She agrees to marry King Henry, though with no great passion. Where this leads may be discovered in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SHEP.">Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>A Shepherd is Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s father, who has been searching for her since she ran away. A simple man, he is desolated by the fact that she is going to die, and horrified when she denies him. His love turns to hate when she refuses to accept his blessing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PORT.">Porter</persname>
<persdescription>The Porter is charged by the Countess of Auvergne to lock the doors to her house once Talbot has entered in.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERG.">French Sergeant</persname>
<persdescription>The French Sergeant is in charge of setting sentinels to watch for the English.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GEN.">General of the French Force at Bordeaux</persname>
<persdescription>General of the French Force at Bordeaux detests Talbot, and rejoices to be able to inform him that he has fallen into a trap from which he cannot escape.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="M. GUN.">Master Gunner of Orléans</persname>
<persdescription>Master Gunner is in charge of the French artillery at Orl&#233;ans. He wishes to accomplish a great act that will bring him to the attention of the French leadership, and for that purpose has aimed a gun at a point where the English noblemen will come to look at the town. After three days of waiting for them, he is exhausted and sets his son to watch instead, which as far as his hopes of gaining recognition go is a mistake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GOV. PARIS.">Governor of Paris</persname>
<persdescription>The Governor of Paris attends Henry&#8217;s coronation as King of France and swears to accept no other King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BAST.">Bastard of Orléans</persname>
<persdescription>The Bastard of Orl&#233;ans is a French nobleman, the first to meet Joan de Pucelle and the one who brings her to Charles&#8217;s camp. He is greatly impressed by her and her intelligence. He is a vindictive man who wishes to have Talbot&#8217;s body torn to pieces and mocks the dead John Talbot.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ALAN.">Duke of Alanson</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Alanson is a French nobleman, one of Charles the Dolphin&#8217;s generals. He thinks little of the English and is therefore shocked when they succeed in beating him back. A rather brainless fellow, he becomes quite a worshipper of Joan. He counsels Charles to take the peace treaty that makes him King and ends the war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BUR.">Duke of Burgundy</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Burgundy is King Henry&#8217;s uncle, and a faithful supporter of the English until he is seduced to the French side by Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s arguments and accepts that he is himself a Frenchman. His defection marks the end of English hopes in France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="REIG.">Reignier, Duke of Anjou</persname>
<persdescription>Reignier, Duke of Anjou is an impoverished French nobleman who holds the purely cosmetic title of King of Naples. One of Charles&#8217;s main generals, he is as willing as his master to let Joan de Pucelle save their skins. When his daughter Margaret is captured by Suffolk, he is at first worried, but when the Englishman asks to have her married to King Henry, Reignier is quick to agree so long as the English stop attacking him. He is vainglorious and not particularly intelligent, though he does counsel Charles to take the peace treaty that makes him King and ends the war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CHAR.">Charles, Dauphin of France</persname>
<persdescription>Charles, Dauphin of France, and later King, is King Henry&#8217;s rival claimant to the throne of France. Following a string of victories, he has himself crowned King of France. He is greatly helped by the young lady Joan de Pucelle, who is a much better fighter than he is and with whom he is passionately in love. He is himself a bit of a coward, reneging on his word not to run away until he sees that he actually is in danger of death. He does not like taking responsibility and is quick to blame others. He is happily hypocritical when need be, swearing to a peace treaty he has no intention of keeping, and is a bit of a lightweight. Historically he is the same as the Dauphin of <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LAW.">Lawyer</persname>
<persdescription>A Lawyer, of the Yorkist party, is present at Somerset and Richard Plantagenet&#8217;s quarrel at the Temple (law school). On the basis of a point of law, he takes Richard&#8217;s side in their dispute.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BAS.">Basset</persname>
<persdescription>Basset, of the Lancastrian party, is a young Englishman who follows and supports the Duke of Somerset, insulting the Duke of York in Vernon&#8217;s presence. He is willing to fight for his master&#8217;s cause, to the point of asking the King to make an exception in the law against dueling so that he may fight Vernon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="VER.">Vernon</persname>
<persdescription>Vernon, of the Yorkist party, is a young Englishman who follows and supports Richard Plantagenet from the start, taking his side at the quarrel in the Temple Garden. He insults the Duke of Somerset in Basset&#8217;s presence, and is willing to fight for his master&#8217;s cause, to the point of asking the King to make an exception in the law against dueling so that he may fight Basset.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WOODV.">Woodvile</persname>
<persdescription>Woodvile is the Lieutenant of the Tower of London, charged with its defense. He refuses entry to the Duke of Gloucester on the Bishop of Winchester&#8217;s orders, precipitating a street brawl.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MAY.">Mayor of London</persname>
<persdescription>The Mayor of London is left shaking his head at the silliness of noblemen and their quarrels after he is forced to read the Riot Act to two of the highest magnates in the land and their men. When brawling breaks out yet again, he has no option but to beg the King for help. He is an ordinary civilian, more concerned with commerce than with the in-fighting of the nobility or the war in France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GAR.">Sir Thomas Gargrave</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Gargrave is an English knight who is part of the force besieging Orl&#233;ans and is an expert on artillery placement, though he disagrees with the other expert, Glansdale. He is killed outright by the volley of cannon fire that also kills the Earl of Salisbury.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GLAN.">Sir William Glansdale</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Glansdale is an English knight who is part of the force besieging Orl&#233;ans and is an expert on artillery placement, though he disagrees with the other expert, Gargrave.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUCY.">Sir William Lucy</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Lucy rushes to both Richard Duke of York and the Duke of Somerset to plead for reinforcements to help Talbot in his last battle, and is horrified at how they let their private quarrel intervene and use it as an excuse not to do so, and blame the other. Returning to the site of battle, he is distraught to find him dead. He can be pompous, and thinks little of the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FAL.">Sir John Falstaff</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Falstaff is a cowardly English knight who twice runs away from battle, leaving Talbot in grave difficulty, a fact that in one case leads to Talbot&#8217;s capture. He freely admits to valuing his own life more than anything, and is publically disgraced by Talbot in retaliation. He is not the same as the Falstaff of the <persnameref>Henry IV</persnameref> plays or <persnameref>The Merry Wives of Windsor</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOR.">Edmund Mortimer, Earl of March</persname>
<persdescription>Mortimer is an English lord who has been imprisoned for most of his life. Richard II&#8217;s chosen heir, he was displaced by King Henry&#8217;s grandfather, Henry IV, when the latter usurped the throne. He was part of a rebellion against the latter which failed, after which he was sent to jail (see <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>). Knowing himself to be dying, he calls his nephew Richard Plantagenet to his side to tell him of all this and let the young man know that he has more right to the throne than does the current King. He is very old, weak, and almost blind. Historically he is the same as the Mortimer of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JOHN.">John Talbot</persname>
<persdescription>John Talbot is the son of Lord Talbot, whom he loves and admires deeply. Imbued with the same ideals of knighthood, he refuses to leave the field of battle when his father asks him to, not being willing to risk being branded a coward. He is a courageous fighter, and bests Charles the Dolphin in combat, but his temper gets the best of him and he plunges into the fiercest part of the battle, where he is killed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TAL.">Lord Talbot</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Talbot, the Earl of Shrewsbury, is the greatest of the English generals in France, a man whose successes are so great that the mention of his name alone is enough to make the French run away. Though not a physically impressive man, he has great presence and commands intense loyalty from his men. He is a larger-than-life character, raging, proud, and with a great sense of humor and mockery. He is aware of how much he owes to his men, and regards them highly. He is distraught at being bested by Joan. He is not taken in by the Countess of Auvergne, suspecting a trap as soon as he receives her invitation. He is the ideal of English knighthood and knows it; he stands up for it and enforces its standards on those around him, punishing Falstaff for failing them. He loves his son and tries to make him leave their final battle, but fails. He holds as long as he can before falling in battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SUF.">Earl of Suffolk</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Suffolk (William de la Pole), of the Lancastrian party, is a young English nobleman, a friend of Somerset&#8217;s. He captures Margaret in the wars and is absolutely smitten by her, to the extent that he proposes to marry her to his King simply so he can have her close; being married already he cannot himself wed her. What this leads to is chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SAL.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury is an English nobleman and war commander who is besieging Orl&#233;ans, and a great friend of Talbot&#8217;s. Convinced that he is on the verge of capturing the city, he has half of his face torn away by a cannonball. He lingers for some minutes before dying. Historically he is the same as the Salisbury of <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WAR.">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>Earl of Warwick, of the Yorkist party, is a young English lord, a friend of Richard Plantagenet&#8217;s. Asked to mediate in the quarrel between Richard and the Duke of Somerset, he takes Richard&#8217;s side; he also presents the petition to the King that restores Richard to his inheritance. He acts as a restraint on Richard&#8217;s more violent instincts, holding him back from saying anything unforgivable. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PLAN.">Richard Plantagenet</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Plantagenet, head of the Yorkist party, is the son of the Earl of Cambridge, who attempted to assassinate the King&#8217;s father (see <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>). His father&#8217;s action left Richard deprived of all his wealth and titles until these are officially returned to him by the King, making him Duke of York. Richard feels the shame of this deeply, and is very touchy on the subject; his quarrel with Somerset on the matter leads to a breach that will turn into the War of the Roses. He is convinced that he has a better right to the throne than Henry VI does, and in law he does, as he is descended from an elder branch of the royal family. Named to a combined command of the army in France with Somerset, he lets his quarrel with the latter overbear the good of the country, and refuses to send aid to the beleaguered Talbot, thus causing the hero&#8217;s death; he refuses to accept any responsibility for this. He has the luck to capture Joan de Pucelle, and has her burnt alive, mocking her brutally beforehand. Richard can be pitiless, and is enraged when he hears of peace behind declared between England and France. He is ambitios and does not always manage to disguise this fact. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SOM.">John Beauford, Duke of Somerset</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Somerset, of the Lancastrian party, is a young and haughty lord, who despises Richard Plantagenet for being the son of a traitor, and is incensed when the latter is restored to his father&#8217;s lands and named Duke of York. His quarrel with Richard on this matter leads to a breach that will become the War of the Roses; he does not hold to his word to give in if more people side against him than with him. Named to an equal command with the new Duke of York in France, he refuses to collaborate with him, thereby leaving Talbot without help and causing his death. He refuses to accept any blame for Talbot&#8217;s demise. He cares only for his own good, nothing for the kingdom. He returns in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WIN.">Henry Beauford, Bishop of Winchester</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CAR.">Cardinal of Winchester</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Bishop of Winchester is the bastard son of the King&#8217;s great-grandfather. He is a crafty, hypocritical, sly man of high ambitions, who has a permanent feud with the Duke of Gloucester. He pretends to be highly pious but in fact acts only for his own material gain, and to become the most powerful man in the kingdom he plans to abduct the King from Gloucester&#8217;s care. Failing, he swears to be friends with the Duke, but doesn&#8217;t mean it. He bribes the Pope into naming him a cardinal, which gives him equal rank with Dukes, and is sent by the King to treat for peace with the French. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EXE.">Thomas Beauford, Duke of Exeter</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Exeter is King Henry&#8217;s great uncle; historically he is the same as the Exeter of <perstitleref>Henry V</perstitleref>. A fierce and warlike man, he is charged with the young King&#8217;s personal safety. He sees all too clearly what the quarrels between the various English aristocrats portend, and does not wish to live to see himself proved right. He is a member of the old guard, devoted to the memory of Henry V.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BED.">Duke of Bedford</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Bedford is Regent of France, in charge of continuing the war against the French and safeguarding Henry V&#8217;s conquests. An older man, he is impatient with the quarreling of the other English lords, being more concerned with the war than with their squabbling. He has a hard time believing that a woman could have any military ability. He falls ill as the fortune of battle shifts and shifts again, but forces himself to stay alive long enough to witness Roan being re-taken from the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GLOU.">Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Gloucester is King Henry&#8217;s uncle and Lord Protector, charged with the safety of the King in his youth and the government of the realm until he comes of age. Historically he is the same as the Gloucester of Henry V. He has an all-abiding hatred of the Bishop of Winchester and carries on an endless feud with him, no matter how much it may harm the kingdom. Due to this hatred, he has little regard for the Church. The King is greatly dependent on him, a fact that Gloucester is used to; he is appalled when the King disregards his advice on the matter of his marriage. He is willing to be convinced to calm down his quarreling with the Bishop, but still loses his temper every time he is in the prelate&#8217;s presence. Though loyal, he is more concerned with himself and his ward than for the realm itself. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING.">King Henry the Sixth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry VI is a very young, rather simple-minded monarch, of excessive piety and naivet&#233;, who relies almost entirely on his uncle the Duke of Gloucester. Becoming King while still a child, he is wide-eyed at the scuffles between his uncles, and cannot command as a King should; rather he begs, and occasionally cries. His greatest desire is for peace among his noblemen, though he believes entirely in his right to the French throne. He has absolutely no political sense, and agrees to Suffolk&#8217;s proposal that he should marry Margaret without considering any of the arguments against the match. He is generally a passive character, reacting to events rather than causing them. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>


<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PAP.">Papal Legate</persname>
<persdescription>Papal Legate comes from the Pope to crown the Bishop of Winchester as a Cardinal, and receives Winchester&#8217;s bribe money in return to bring back to the Pope. He also brings letters from the Pope requesting that Henry make peace with France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FIENDS.">Fiends</persname>
<persdescription>The Fiends [mute roles] are demons who have helped Joan de Pucelle achieve victory. They refuse to give her any more help despite all her offers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OFF.">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer reads out the Riot Act to Gloucester, Winchester and their followers as they riot, at the Mayor&#8217;s command.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WIN. SERV. ATT.">Winchester&#8217;s Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Winchester&#8217;s Serving Attendant follows his master and fights for him at the Tower of London, and continues to brawl with Gloucester&#8217;s men in the street. When forbidden to use weapons, he uses stones instead. He is not impressed by all the threats that Gloucester&#8217;s men make. He wears a tawny coat that marks him as Winchester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="M. GUN. BOY.">Master Gunner&#8217;s Boy</persname>
<persdescription>The Master Gunner&#8217;s Boy is the son of the Master Gunner of Orl&#233;ans, set to keep a lookout for the English nobility and to fetch his father so that the latter can shoot at them should they appear. However, preferring to get the glory himself, he shoots the gun off himself, killing Gargrave and Salisbury.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger brings news to the English court of how the French have taken back vast amounts of territory since Henry V dies. He lays the blame squarely at the feet of the quarreling English nobility, and has the courage and anger to tell them to shape up.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger brings to the English court the news that Charles has had himself crowned King, and that many great nobles of France have flocked to his side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger brings news to the English court of Talbot&#8217;s capture and Falstaff&#8217;s cowardice.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. MESS.">Fourth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Messenger comes to warn Talbot that the French have been joined by Joan de Pucelle and the Dolphin and are coming to raise the siege of Orl&#233;ans.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="5. MESS.">Fifth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fifth Messenger informs the Duke of York that the French armies have met and joined together, and that the full French force is attacking Talbot.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. WARDER">First Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The First Warder of the Tower refuses to open the gates to Gloucester, as he has his orders not to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. WARDER">Second Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Warder of the Tower insists that no-one can be let in, whoever they are.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. GLOU. SERV. ATT.">Gloucester&#8217;s First Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s First Serving Attendant follows his master and fights for him at the Tower of London, and continues to brawl with Winchester&#8217;s men in the street. When forbidden to use weapons, he uses stones instead. He is a very combative man. He wears a blue coat that marks him as Gloucester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. GLOU. SERV. ATT.">Gloucester&#8217;s Second Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s Second Serving Attendant insists that he and his friends and family will fight to the death for Gloucester&#8217;s honor. He seems slightly more intelligent than his fellows, as well as more resilient, going to a pub rather than to the doctor&#8217;s when wounded. He wears a blue coat that marks him as Gloucester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. SENT.">First Sentinel</persname>
<persdescription>The First Sentinel does not appreciate his job, as it is most uncomfortable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. SENT.">Second Sentinel</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Sentinel [mute role] keeps watch with the First Sentinel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ENG. SOLD.">English Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>An English Soldier knows perfectly well how much the French fears Talbot, and uses the fact to enrich himself by scaring them off with only the sound of Talbot&#8217;s name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS. COUNT.">Messenger of the Countess</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger of the Countess delivers the Countess of Auvergne&#8217;s invitation to Talbot. He knows how to flatter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. KEEPER.">First Keeper</persname>
<persdescription>The First Keeper is in charge of Mortimer&#8217;s prison. He is kind to his prisoner, and arranges a meeting with Richard Plantagenet when Mortimer asks him to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. KEEPER.">Second Keeper</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Keeper [mute role] is one of the guards of Mortimer&#8217;s prison. He helps carry the prisoner out to see Richard Plantagenet.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. SOLD.">First Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>The First Soldier is one of Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s disguised group that sneaks into Rouen, and enjoys a good pun.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAPT.">Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Captain is an English officer disgusted at Falstaff&#8217;s cowardice. When Talbot is surrounded by the Dolphin&#8217;s forces, he is sent to beg Somerset to send reinforcements. He is charged by Talbot with surrounding the Countess of Auvergne’s house and rescuing him at the sound of his horn.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SCOUT.">Scout</persname>
<persdescription>A Scout brings the French leadership the news that the two English armies have met and combined.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AMB. EMP.">Ambassador from the Emperor</persname>
<persdescription>Ambassador from the Emperor [mute role] has brought the Emperor&#8217;s request that England and France should make peace to King Henry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AMB. ARM.">Ambassador from the Earl of Armagnac</persname>
<persdescription>Ambassador from the Earl of Armagnac [mute role] has brought the Earl&#8217;s request that there should be peace between England and France to King Henry, and his offer of his daughter&#8217;s hand.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TAL. TRUMP.">Talbot&#8217;s Trumpeter</persname>
<persdescription>Talbot&#8217;s Trumpeter [mute role] follows his master and summons the French General to talk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. HER.">French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>French Herald [mute role] brings Lucy to the Dauphin&#8217;s tent under a safe-conduct.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SOLD. WATCH.">Soldier of the Watch</persname>
<persdescription>Soldier of the Watch is an English guard who lets Joan de Pucelle into Rouen, believing her story that she and her group are going to market.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TAL. SERV.">Talbot&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Talbot&#8217;s Servant accompanies his master to the battle and cares for him once he is injured.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Westminster Abbey.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Henry the Fifth, Duke of Bedford, Regent of France, Duke of Gloucester, Protector, Duke of Exeter, Earl of Warwick, Bishop of Winchester, Duke of Somerset, Heralds, Messengers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The nobility of England bear Henry V to his grave, lamenting the loss of the greatest soldier the kingdom has ever known. Winchester attributes the dead king&#8217;s successes to the church, but Gloucester angrily denies it. A messenger brings news of dreadful losses in France, accusing the nobles of squabbling amongst themselves and thereby leaving the soldiers in France unsupported. Bedford swears to go to France and reverse this, but a second messenger brings the news that Charles the Dolphin has had himself crowned King of France, and that many high nobles have joined his cause. A third messenger informs the nobility that their greatest general, Talbot, has been captured and imprisoned by the French. The English nobles leave to prepare for war, while Winchester, left with no official roles, plots to take control of the infant king and hence take power.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Dead march. Enter the Funeral of King Henry the Fifth, attended on by the Duke of Bedford, Regent of France, the Duke of Gloucester, Protector, the Duke of Exeter, the Earl of Warwick, the Bishop of Winchester, and the Duke of Somerset; Heralds, etc..</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hung be the heavens with black, yield day to night!</line>
<line form="verse">Comets, importing change of times and states,</line>
<line form="verse">Brandish your crystal tresses in the sky,</line>
<line form="verse">And with them scourge the bad revolting stars</line>
<line form="verse">That have consented unto Henry&#8217;s death:</line>
<line form="verse">King Henry the Fifth, too famous to live long!</line>
<line form="verse">England ne&#8217;er lost a king of so much worth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">England ne&#8217;er had a king until his time:</line>
<line form="verse">Virtue he had, deserving to command;</line>
<line form="verse">His brandish&#8217;d sword did blind men with his beams;</line>
<line form="verse">His arms spread wider than a dragon&#8217;s wings;</line>
<line form="verse">His sparkling eyes, replete with wrathful fire,</line>
<line form="verse">More dazzled and drove back his enemies</line>
<line form="verse">Than midday sun fierce bent against their faces.</line>
<line form="verse">What should I say? His deeds exceed all speech:</line>
<line form="verse">He ne&#8217;er lift up his hand but conquered.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We mourn in black, why mourn we not in blood?</line>
<line form="verse">Henry is dead, and never shall revive.</line>
<line form="verse">Upon a wooden coffin we attend,</line>
<line form="verse">And death&#8217;s dishonorable victory</line>
<line form="verse">We with our stately presence glorify,</line>
<line form="verse">Like captives bound to a triumphant car.</line>
<line form="verse">What? Shall we curse the planets of mishap</line>
<line form="verse">That plotted thus our glory&#8217;s overthrow?</line>
<line form="verse">Or shall we think the subtile-witted French</line>
<line form="verse">Conjurers and sorcerers, that, afraid of him,</line>
<line form="verse">By magic verses have contriv&#8217;d his end?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He was a king blest of the King of kings.</line>
<line form="verse">Unto the French the dreadful Judgment Day</line>
<line form="verse">So dreadful will not be as was his sight.</line>
<line form="verse">The battles of the Lord of hosts he fought;</line>
<line form="verse">The Church&#8217;s prayers made him so prosperous.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Church? Where is it? Had not churchmen pray&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">His thread of life had not so soon decay&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">None do you like but an effeminate prince,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom like a schoolboy you may overawe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gloucester, what e&#8217;er we like, thou art Protector,</line>
<line form="verse">And lookest to command the Prince and realm.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy wife is proud, she holdeth thee in awe,</line>
<line form="verse">More than God or religious churchmen may.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Name not religion, for thou lov&#8217;st the flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">And ne&#8217;er throughout the year to church thou go&#8217;st</line>
<line form="verse">Except it be to pray against thy foes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cease, cease these jars and rest your minds in peace.</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s to the altar. Heralds, wait on us.</line>
<line form="verse">In stead of gold, we&#8217;ll offer up our arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Since arms avail not now that Henry&#8217;s dead.</line>
<line form="verse">Posterity, await for wretched years,</line>
<line form="verse">When at their mothers&#8217; moist&#8217;ned eyes babes shall suck,</line>
<line form="verse">Our isle be made a nourish of salt tears,</line>
<line form="verse">And none but women left to wail the dead.</line>
<line form="verse">Henry the Fifth, thy ghost I invocate:</line>
<line form="verse">Prosper this realm, keep it from civil broils,</line>
<line form="verse">Combat with adverse planets in the heavens!</line>
<line form="verse">A far more glorious star thy soul will make</line>
<line form="verse">Than Julius Caesar or bright&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My honorable lords, health to you all!</line>
<line form="verse">Sad tidings bring I to you out of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Of loss, of slaughter, and discomfiture:</line>
<line form="verse">Guienne, Champaigne, Rheims, Orleance,</line>
<line form="verse">Paris, Guysors, Poictiers, are all quite lost.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What say&#8217;st thou, man, before dead Henry&#8217;s corse?</line>
<line form="verse">Speak softly, or the loss of those great towns</line>
<line form="verse">Will make him burst his lead and rise from death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is Paris lost? Is Roan yielded up?</line>
<line form="verse">If Henry were recall&#8217;d to life again,</line>
<line form="verse">These news would cause him once more yield the ghost.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How were they lost? What treachery was us&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No treachery, but want of men and money.</line>
<line form="verse">Amongst the soldiers this is muttered,</line>
<line form="verse">That here you maintain several factions;</line>
<line form="verse">And whilst a field should be dispatch&#8217;d and fought,</line>
<line form="verse">You are disputing of your generals.</line>
<line form="verse">One would have ling&#8217;ring wars with little cost;</line>
<line form="verse">Another would fly swift, but wanteth wings;</line>
<line form="verse">A third thinks, without expense at all,</line>
<line form="verse">By guileful fair words peace may be obtain&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Awake, awake, English nobility!</line>
<line form="verse">Let not sloth dim your honors new begot.</line>
<line form="verse">Cropp&#8217;d are the flower-de-luces in your arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Of England&#8217;s coat one half is cut away.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were our tears wanting to this funeral,</line>
<line form="verse">These tidings would call forth her flowing tides.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Me they concern, Regent I am of France.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me my steeled coat, I&#8217;ll fight for France.</line>
<line form="verse">Away with these disgraceful wailing robes!</line>
<line form="verse">Wounds will I lend the French in stead of eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">To weep their intermissive miseries.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter to them another Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lords, view these letters full of bad mischance.</line>
<line form="verse">France is revolted from the English quite,</line>
<line form="verse">Except some petty towns of no import.</line>
<line form="verse">The Dauphin Charles is crowned king in Rheims;</line>
<line form="verse">The Bastard of Orleance with him is join&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">Reignier, Duke of Anjou, doth take his part;</line>
<line form="verse">The Duke of Alanson flieth to his side.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Dauphin crowned king? All fly to him?</line>
<line form="verse">O, whither shall we fly from this reproach?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We will not fly but to our enemies&#8217; throats.</line>
<line form="verse">Bedford, if thou be slack, I&#8217;ll fight it out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gloucester, why doubt&#8217;st thou of my forwardness?</line>
<line form="verse">An army have I muster&#8217;d in my thoughts,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherewith already France is overrun.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter another Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious lords, to add to your laments,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherewith you now bedew King Henry&#8217;s hearse,</line>
<line form="verse">I must inform you of a dismal fight</line>
<line form="verse">Betwixt the stout Lord Talbot and the French.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Wherein Talbot overcame, is&#8217;t so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O no; wherein Lord Talbot was o&#8217;er-thrown.</line>
<line form="verse">The circumstance I&#8217;ll tell you more at large.</line>
<line form="verse">The tenth of August last this dreadful lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Retiring from the siege of Orleance,</line>
<line form="verse">Having full scarce six thousand in his troop,</line>
<line form="verse">By three and twenty thousand of the French</line>
<line form="verse">Was round encompassed, and set upon.</line>
<line form="verse">No leisure had he to enrank his men;</line>
<line form="verse">He wanted pikes to set before his archers;</line>
<line form="verse">In stead whereof sharp stakes pluck&#8217;d out of hedges</line>
<line form="verse">They pitched in the ground confusedly,</line>
<line form="verse">To keep the horsemen off from breaking in.</line>
<line form="verse">More than three hours the fight continued,</line>
<line form="verse">Where valiant Talbot above human thought</line>
<line form="verse">Enacted wonders with his sword and lance:</line>
<line form="verse">Hundreds he sent to hell, and none durst stand him;</line>
<line form="verse">Here, there, and every where, enrag&#8217;d he slew.</line>
<line form="verse">The French exclaim&#8217;d, the devil was in arms;</line>
<line form="verse">All the whole army stood agaz&#8217;d on him.</line>
<line form="verse">His soldiers, spying his undaunted spirit,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;A Talbot! A Talbot!&#8221; cried out amain,</line>
<line form="verse">And rush&#8217;d into the bowels of the battle.</line>
<line form="verse">Here had the conquest fully been seal&#8217;d up,</line>
<line form="verse">If Sir John Falstaff had not play&#8217;d the coward.</line>
<line form="verse">He, being in the vaward, plac&#8217;d behind</line>
<line form="verse">With purpose to relieve and follow them,</line>
<line form="verse">Cowardly fled, not having struck one stroke.</line>
<line form="verse">Hence grew the general wrack and massacre;</line>
<line form="verse">Enclosed were they with their enemies.</line>
<line form="verse">A base Wallon, to win the Dauphin&#8217;s grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Thrust Talbot with a spear into the back,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom all France with their chief assembled strength</line>
<line form="verse">Durst not presume to look once in the face.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is Talbot slain then? I will slay myself</line>
<line form="verse">For living idly here in pomp and ease,</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst such a worthy leader, wanting aid,</line>
<line form="verse">Unto his dastard foemen is betray&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O no, he lives, but is took prisoner,</line>
<line form="verse">And Lord Scales with him, and Lord Hungerford.</line>
<line form="verse">Most of the rest slaughter&#8217;d or took likewise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His ransom there is none but I shall pay:</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll hale the Dauphin headlong from his throne,</line>
<line form="verse">His crown shall be the ransom of my friend;</line>
<line form="verse">Four of their lords I&#8217;ll change for one of ours.</line>
<line form="verse">Farewell, my masters, to my task will I.</line>
<line form="verse">Bonfires in France forthwith I am to make,</line>
<line form="verse">To keep our great Saint George&#8217;s feast withal.</line>
<line form="verse">Ten thousand soldiers with me I will take,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose bloody deeds shall make all Europe quake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So you had need, for Orleance is besieg&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">The English army is grown weak and faint;</line>
<line form="verse">The Earl of Salisbury craveth supply,</line>
<line form="verse">And hardly keeps his men from mutiny,</line>
<line form="verse">Since they, so few, watch such a multitude.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Remember, lords, your oaths to Henry sworn:</line>
<line form="verse">Either to quell the Dauphin utterly,</line>
<line form="verse">Or bring him in obedience to your yoke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do remember it, and here take my leave,</line>
<line form="verse">To go about my preparation.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Bedford.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll to the Tower with all the haste I can,</line>
<line form="verse">To view th&#8217; artillery and munition,</line>
<line form="verse">And then I will proclaim young Henry king.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Gloucester.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To Eltam will I, where the young King is,</line>
<line form="verse">Being ordain&#8217;d his special governor,</line>
<line form="verse">And for his safety there I&#8217;ll best devise.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Each hath his place and function to attend:</line>
<line form="verse">I am left out; for me nothing remains.</line>
<line form="verse">But long I will not be Jack out of office.</line>
<line form="verse">The King from Eltam I intend to send,</line>
<line form="verse">And sit at chiefest stern of public weal.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Orleans.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Charles the Dauphin, Alanson, Reignier, Soldiers, Charles, Alanson, Reignier, Bastard of Orleance, Joan de Pucelle)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The French decide to raise the siege, but the English drive them back with a fury they cannot withstand, much to their amazement. The Bastard of Orleans brings in Joan la Pucelle, ordained deliverer of Orleans. She quickly picks out the Dauphin among the nobility, though she never saw him before, and tells him the vision promising her that she would be the savior of her country. Charles decides to test her fighting abilities, and she overcomes him in single combat. Charles falls for her, but she insists she must remain a virgin for her mission to succeed. She promises to raise the siege without delay.</scenedescription>


<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mars his true moving, even as in the heavens,</line>
<line form="verse">So in the earth, to this day is not known.</line>
<line form="verse">Late did he shine upon the English side;</line>
<line form="verse">Now we are victors, upon us he smiles.</line>
<line form="verse">What towns of any moment but we have?</line>
<line form="verse">At pleasure here we lie near Orleance;</line>
<line form="verse">Otherwhiles the famish&#8217;d English, like pale ghosts,</line>
<line form="verse">Faintly besiege us one hour in a month.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They want their porridge and their fat bull-beeves:</line>
<line form="verse">Either they must be dieted like mules</line>
<line form="verse">And have their provender tied to their mouths,</line>
<line form="verse">Or piteous they will look, like drowned mice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s raise the siege; why live we idly here?</line>
<line form="verse">Talbot is taken, whom we wont to fear;</line>
<line form="verse">Remaineth none but mad-brain&#8217;d Salisbury,</line>
<line form="verse">And he may well in fretting spend his gall&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor men nor money hath he to make war.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sound, sound alarum! We will rush on them.</line>
<line form="verse">Now for the honor of the forlorn French!</line>
<line form="verse">Him I forgive my death that killeth me,</line>
<line form="verse">When he sees me go back one foot or fly.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="fight">Here alarum; they are beaten back by the English with great loss.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Alanson, and Reignier.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who ever saw the like? What men have I!</line>
<line form="verse">Dogs! Cowards! Dastards! I would ne&#8217;er have fled,</line>
<line form="verse">But that they left me midst my enemies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Salisbury is a desperate homicide,</line>
<line form="verse">He fighteth as one weary of his life.</line>
<line form="verse">The other lords, like lions wanting food,</line>
<line form="verse">Do rush upon us as their hungry prey.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Froissard, a countryman of ours, records</line>
<line form="verse">England all Olivers and Rolands bred</line>
<line form="verse">During the time Edward the Third did reign.</line>
<line form="verse">More truly now may this be verified,</line>
<line form="verse">For none but Samsons and Goliases</line>
<line form="verse">It sendeth forth to skirmish. One to ten!</line>
<line form="verse">Lean raw-bon&#8217;d rascals! Who would e&#8217;er suppose</line>
<line form="verse">They had such courage and audacity?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s leave this town, for they are hare-brain&#8217;d slaves,</line>
<line form="verse">And hunger will enforce them to be more eager.</line>
<line form="verse">Of old I know them; rather with their teeth</line>
<line form="verse">The walls they&#8217;ll tear down than forsake the siege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think by some odd gimmors or device</line>
<line form="verse">Their arms are set, like clocks, still to strike on;</line>
<line form="verse">Else ne&#8217;er could they hold out so as they do.</line>
<line form="verse">By my consent, we&#8217;ll even let them alone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be it so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Bastard of Orleance.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where&#8217;s the Prince Dauphin? I have news for him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bastard of Orleance, thrice welcome to us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Methinks your looks are sad, your cheer appal&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Hath the late overthrow wrought this offense?</line>
<line form="verse">Be not dismay&#8217;d, for succor is at hand:</line>
<line form="verse">A holy maid hither with me I bring,</line>
<line form="verse">Which by a vision sent to her from heaven</line>
<line form="verse">Ordained is to raise this tedious siege,</line>
<line form="verse">And drive the English forth the bounds of France.</line>
<line form="verse">The spirit of deep prophecy she hath,</line>
<line form="verse">Exceeding the nine sibyls of old Rome:</line>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s past and what&#8217;s to come she can descry.</line>
<line form="verse">Speak, shall I call her in? Believe my words,</line>
<line form="verse">For they are certain and unfallible.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go call her in.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Bastard.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">But first, to try her skill,</line>
<line form="verse">Reignier, stand thou as Dauphin in my place;</line>
<line form="verse">Question her proudly, let thy looks be stern.</line>
<line form="verse">By this means shall we sound what skill she hath.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Joan de Pucelle and Bastard.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair maid, is&#8217;t thou wilt do these wondrous feats?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Reignier, is&#8217;t thou that thinkest to beguile me?</line>
<line form="verse">Where is the Dauphin? Come, come from behind,</line>
<line form="verse">I know thee well, though never seen before.</line>
<line form="verse">Be not amaz&#8217;d, there&#8217;s nothing hid from me;</line>
<line form="verse">In private will I talk with thee apart.</line>
<line form="verse">Stand back, you lords, and give us leave a while.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She takes upon her bravely at first dash.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dauphin, I am by birth a shepherd&#8217;s daughter,</line>
<line form="verse">My wit untrain&#8217;d in any kind of art.</line>
<line form="verse">Heaven and our Lady gracious hath it pleas&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To shine on my contemptible estate.</line>
<line form="verse">Lo, whilest I waited on my tender lambs,</line>
<line form="verse">And to sun&#8217;s parching heat display&#8217;d my cheeks,</line>
<line form="verse">God&#8217;s Mother deigned to appear to me,</line>
<line form="verse">And in a vision full of majesty</line>
<line form="verse">Will&#8217;d me to leave my base vocation</line>
<line form="verse">And free my country from calamity.</line>
<line form="verse">Her aid she promis&#8217;d, and assur&#8217;d success;</line>
<line form="verse">In complete glory she reveal&#8217;d herself;</line>
<line form="verse">And whereas I was black and swart before,</line>
<line form="verse">With those clear rays which she infus&#8217;d on me</line>
<line form="verse">That beauty am I blest with which you may see.</line>
<line form="verse">Ask me what question thou canst possible,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will answer unpremeditated;</line>
<line form="verse">My courage try by combat, if thou dar&#8217;st,</line>
<line form="verse">And thou shalt find that I exceed my sex.</line>
<line form="verse">Resolve on this: thou shalt be fortunate</line>
<line form="verse">If thou receive me for thy warlike mate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou hast astonish&#8217;d me with thy high terms.</line>
<line form="verse">Only this proof I&#8217;ll of thy valor make,</line>
<line form="verse">In single combat thou shalt buckle with me;</line>
<line form="verse">And if thou vanquishest, thy words are true,</line>
<line form="verse">Otherwise I renounce all confidence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am prepar&#8217;d; here is my keen-edg&#8217;d sword,</line>
<line form="verse">Deck&#8217;d with five flower-de-luces on each side,</line>
<line form="verse">The which at Touraine, in Saint Katherine&#8217;s church-yard,</line>
<line form="verse">Out of a great deal of old iron I chose forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then come a&#8217; God&#8217;s name, I fear no woman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And while I live, I&#8217;ll ne&#8217;er fly from a man.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Here they fight, and Joan de Pucelle overcomes.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, stay thy hands! Thou art an Amazon,</line>
<line form="verse">And fightest with the sword of Deborah.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Christ&#8217;s Mother helps me, else I were too weak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whoe&#8217;er helps thee, &#8217;tis thou that must help me:</line>
<line form="verse">Impatiently I burn with thy desire;</line>
<line form="verse">My heart and hands thou hast at once subdu&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Excellent Pucelle, if thy name be so,</line>
<line form="verse">Let me thy servant and not sovereign be.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis the French Dauphin sueth to thee thus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I must not yield to any rites of love,</line>
<line form="verse">For my profession&#8217;s sacred from above.</line>
<line form="verse">When I have chased all thy foes from hence,</line>
<line form="verse">Then will I think upon a recompense.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mean time look gracious on thy prostrate thrall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, methinks, is very long in talk.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Doubtless he shrives this woman to her smock,</line>
<line form="verse">Else ne&#8217;er could he so long protract his speech.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shall we disturb him, since he keeps no mean?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He may mean more than we poor men do know:</line>
<line form="verse">These women are shrewd tempters with their tongues.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, where are you? What devise you on?</line>
<line form="verse">Shall we give o&#8217;er Orleance, or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, no, I say. Distrustful recreants,</line>
<line form="verse">Fight till the last gasp; I&#8217;ll be your guard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What she says I&#8217;ll confirm. We&#8217;ll fight it out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Assign&#8217;d am I to be the English scourge.</line>
<line form="verse">This night the siege assuredly I&#8217;ll raise:</line>
<line form="verse">Expect Saint Martin&#8217;s summer, halcyons&#8217; days,</line>
<line form="verse">Since I have entered into these wars.</line>
<line form="verse">Glory is like a circle in the water,</line>
<line form="verse">Which never ceaseth to enlarge itself,</line>
<line form="verse">Till by broad spreading it disperse to nought.</line>
<line form="verse">With Henry&#8217;s death the English circle ends,</line>
<line form="verse">Dispersed are the glories it included.</line>
<line form="verse">Now am I like that proud insulting ship</line>
<line form="verse">Which Caesar and his fortune bare at once.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Was Mahomet inspired with a dove?</line>
<line form="verse">Thou with an eagle art inspired then.</line>
<line form="verse">Helen, the mother of great Constantine,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor yet Saint Philip&#8217;s daughters, were like thee.</line>
<line form="verse">Bright star of Venus, fall&#8217;n down on the earth,</line>
<line form="verse">How may I reverently worship thee enough?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Leave off delays, and let us raise the siege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Woman, do what thou canst to save our honors;</line>
<line form="verse">Drive them from Orleance and be immortaliz&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Presently we&#8217;ll try; come, let&#8217;s away about it.</line>
<line form="verse">No prophet will I trust, if she prove false.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. Before the Tower.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Gloucester, Gloucester&#8217;s First Serving Attendant, First Warder, Second Warder, Woodvile the Lieutenant, Winchester, Mayor of London, Officers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Duke of Gloucester is refused admittance to the Tower on Winchester&#8217;s orders. Winchester&#8217;s men come out and fight with Gloucester&#8217;s, who best them. The Mayor of London and his men arrive to restore peace, in the end having to read out the riot act to make the fighting cease. Winchester and Glocuester agree to obey the law, but leave swearing to continue the fight.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Gloucester with his Serving Attendants in blue coats.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am come to survey the Tower this day;</line>
<line form="verse">Since Henry&#8217;s death, I fear, there is conveyance.</line>
<line form="verse">Where be these warders, that they wait not here?</line>
<line form="verse">Open the gates, &#8217;tis Gloucester that calls.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WARDER</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Who&#8217;s there, that knocks so imperiously?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. GLOU. SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is the noble Duke of Gloucester.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WARDER</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Whoe&#8217;er he be, you may not be let in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. GLOU. SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villains, answer you so the Lord Protector?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WARDER</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The Lord protect him! So we answer him.</line>
<line form="verse">We do no otherwise than we are will&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who willed you? Or whose will stands but mine?</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s none Protector of the realm but I.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Break up the gates, I&#8217;ll be your warrantize.</line>
<line form="verse">Shall I be flouted thus by dunghill grooms?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Gloucester&#8217;s men rush at the Tower gates, and Woodvile the Lieutenant speaks within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WOODV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What noise is this? What traitors have we here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lieutenant, is it you whose voice I hear?</line>
<line form="verse">Open the gates, here&#8217;s Gloucester that would enter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WOODV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have patience, noble Duke, I may not open,</line>
<line form="verse">The Cardinal of Winchester forbids.</line>
<line form="verse">From him I have express commandement</line>
<line form="verse">That thou nor none of thine shall be let in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Faint-hearted Woodvile, prizest him &#8217;fore me?</line>
<line form="verse">Arrogant Winchester, that haughty prelate,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom Henry, our late sovereign, ne&#8217;er could brook?</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art no friend to God or to the King.</line>
<line form="verse">Open the gates, or I&#8217;ll shut thee out shortly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. GLOU. SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Open the gates unto the Lord Protector,</line>
<line form="verse">Or we&#8217;ll burst them open, if that you come not quickly.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter to the Protector at the Tower gates Winchester and his Men in tawny coats.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, ambitious Humphrey, what means this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peel&#8217;d priest, dost thou command me to be shut out?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do, thou most usurping proditor,</line>
<line form="verse">And not Protector, of the King or realm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stand back, thou manifest conspirator,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou that contrivedst to murder our dead lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou that giv&#8217;st whores indulgences to sin.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll canvass thee in thy broad cardinal&#8217;s hat,</line>
<line form="verse">If thou proceed in this thy insolence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, stand thou back, I will not budge a foot:</line>
<line form="verse">This be Damascus, be thou cursed Cain,</line>
<line form="verse">To slay thy brother Abel, if thou wilt.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not slay thee, but I&#8217;ll drive thee back.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy scarlet robes as a child&#8217;s bearing-cloth</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll use to carry thee out of this place.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do what thou dar&#8217;st, I beard thee to thy face.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Am I dar&#8217;d and bearded to my face?</line>
<line form="verse">Draw, men, for all this privileged place&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Blue coats to tawny coats! Priest, beware your beard,</line>
<line form="verse">I mean to tug it and to cuff you soundly.</line>
<line form="verse">Under my feet I stamp thy cardinal&#8217;s hat;</line>
<line form="verse">In spite of Pope or dignities of church,</line>
<line form="verse">Here by the cheeks I&#8217;ll drag thee up and down.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gloucester, thou wilt answer this before the Pope.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Winchester goose, I cry, &#8220;A rope! A rope!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Now beat them hence, why do you let them stay?</line>
<line form="verse">Thee I&#8217;ll chase hence, thou wolf in sheep&#8217;s array.</line>
<line form="verse">Out, tawny-coats! Out, scarlet hypocrite!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Here Gloucester&#8217;s men beat out the Cardinal&#8217;s men, and enter in the hurly-burly the Mayor of London and his Officers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, lords, that you, being supreme magistrates,</line>
<line form="verse">Thus contumeliously should break the peace!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peace, Mayor, thou know&#8217;st little of my wrongs.</line>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s Beauford, that regards nor God nor king,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath here distrain&#8217;d the Tower to his use.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s Gloucester, a foe to citizens,</line>
<line form="verse">One that still motions war and never peace,</line>
<line form="verse">O&#8217;ercharging your free purses with large fines;</line>
<line form="verse">That seeks to overthrow religion</line>
<line form="verse">Because he is Protector of the realm,</line>
<line form="verse">And would have armor here out of the Tower,</line>
<line form="verse">To crown himself king and suppress the Prince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not answer thee with words, but blows.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Here they skirmish again.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nought rests for me in this tumultuous strife</line>
<line form="verse">But to make open proclamation.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, officer, as loud as e&#8217;er thou canst,</line>
<line form="verse">Cry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OFF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All manner of men assembled here in arms this day against God&#8217;s peace and the King&#8217;s, we charge and command you, in his Highness&#8217; name, to repair to your several dwelling-places, and not to wear, handle, or use any sword, weapon, or dagger, henceforward, upon pain of death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cardinal, I&#8217;ll be no breaker of the law;</line>
<line form="verse">But we shall meet, and break our minds at large.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gloucester, we&#8217;ll meet to thy cost, be sure:</line>
<line form="verse">Thy heart-blood I will have for this day&#8217;s work.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll call for clubs, if you will not away.</line>
<line form="verse">This cardinal&#8217;s more haughty than the devil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mayor, farewell; thou dost but what thou mayst.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Abominable Gloucester, guard thy head,</line>
<line form="verse">For I intend to have it ere long.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt, several ways, Gloucester and Winchester with their Servingmen.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">See the coast clear&#8217;d, and then we will depart.</line>
<line form="verse">Good God, these nobles should such stomachs bear!</line>
<line form="verse">I myself fight not once in forty year.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Orleans.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Master Gunner of Orleance, Master Gunner&#8217;s Boy, Salisbury, Talbot, Sir William Glans-Dale, Sir Thomas Gargrave, Messenger)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The French master gunner has his boy keep a lookout for the English leaders on the tower from which they spy on the defenses, planning to blow them out of the air at the first opportunity. Talbot, recently freed from French captivity, joins the other English leaders, telling them of how poorly he was treated by the French, and swearing revenge on Falstolfe, whose cowardice led to his capture. The gunner&#8217;s boy fires his cannon, killing Salisbury and Gargrave. Talbot vows vengeance for their deaths; a messenger brings news that the dolphin and Joan la Pucelle have arrived to raise the siege.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Master Gunner of Orleance and his Boy.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>M. GUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sirrah, thou know&#8217;st how Orleance is besieg&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And how the English have the suburbs won.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>M. GUN. BOY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Father, I know, and oft have shot at them,</line>
<line form="verse">Howe&#8217;er unfortunate I miss&#8217;d my aim.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>M. GUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But now thou shalt not. Be thou rul&#8217;d by me.</line>
<line form="verse">Chief master gunner am I of this town,</line>
<line form="verse">Something I must do to procure me grace.</line>
<line form="verse">The Prince&#8217;s espials have informed me</line>
<line form="verse">How the English, in the suburbs close intrench&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Wont through a secret grate of iron bars</line>
<line form="verse">In yonder tower to overpeer the city,</line>
<line form="verse">And thence discover how with most advantage</line>
<line form="verse">They may vex us with shot or with assault.</line>
<line form="verse">To intercept this inconvenience,</line>
<line form="verse">A piece of ord&#8217;nance &#8217;gainst it I have plac&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And even these three days have I watch&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">If I could see them.</line>
<line form="verse">Now do thou watch, for I can stay no longer.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou spy&#8217;st any, run and bring me word,</line>
<line form="verse">And thou shalt find me at the Governor&#8217;s.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>M. GUN. BOY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Father, I warrant you, take you no care,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll never trouble you, if I may spy them.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Salisbury and Talbot, Sir William Glans-Dale, Sir Thomas Gargrave, on the turrets, with others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Talbot, my life, my joy, again return&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">How wert thou handled, being prisoner?</line>
<line form="verse">Or by what means gots thou to be releas&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">Discourse, I prithee, on this turret&#8217;s top.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Earl of Bedford had a prisoner</line>
<line form="verse">Call&#8217;d the brave Lord Ponton de Santrailles,</line>
<line form="verse">For him was I exchang&#8217;d and ransomed.</line>
<line form="verse">But with a baser man of arms by far</line>
<line form="verse">Once in contempt they would have barter&#8217;d me;</line>
<line form="verse">Which I, disdaining, scorn&#8217;d, and craved death</line>
<line form="verse">Rather than I would be so pill&#8217;d esteem&#8217;d:</line>
<line form="verse">In fine, redeem&#8217;d I was as I desir&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">But O, the treacherous Falstaff wounds my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom with my bare fists I would execute,</line>
<line form="verse">If I now had him brought into my power.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yet tell&#8217;st thou not how thou wert entertain&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With scoffs and scorns and contumelious taunts.</line>
<line form="verse">In open market-place produc&#8217;d they me</line>
<line form="verse">To be a public spectacle to all:</line>
<line form="verse">Here, said they, is the terror of the French,</line>
<line form="verse">The scarecrow that affrights our children so.</line>
<line form="verse">Then broke I from the officers that led me,</line>
<line form="verse">And with my nails digg&#8217;d stones out of the ground</line>
<line form="verse">To hurl at the beholders of my shame.</line>
<line form="verse">My grisly countenance made others fly,</line>
<line form="verse">None durst come near for fear of sudden death.</line>
<line form="verse">In iron walls they deem&#8217;d me not secure;</line>
<line form="verse">So great fear of my name &#8217;mongst them were spread</line>
<line form="verse">That they suppos&#8217;d I could rend bars of steel,</line>
<line form="verse">And spurn in pieces posts of adamant;</line>
<line form="verse">Wherefore a guard of chosen shot I had</line>
<line form="verse">That walk&#8217;d about me every minute while;</line>
<line form="verse">And if I did but stir out of my bed,</line>
<line form="verse">Ready they were to shoot me to the heart.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Boy with a linstock.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I grieve to hear what torments you endur&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">But we will be reveng&#8217;d sufficiently.</line>
<line form="verse">Now it is supper-time in Orleance:</line>
<line form="verse">Here, through this grate, I count each one,</line>
<line form="verse">And view the Frenchmen how they fortify.</line>
<line form="verse">Let us look in, the sight will much delight thee.</line>
<line form="verse">Sir Thomas Gargrave, and Sir William Glansdale,</line>
<line form="verse">Let me have your express opinions,</line>
<line form="verse">Where is best place to make our batt&#8217;ry next?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think at the North Gate, for there stands lords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I here, at the bulwark of the bridge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For aught I see, this city must be famish&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Or with light skirmishes enfeebled.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Here they shoot, and Salisbury falls down together with Gargrave.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O Lord, have mercy on us, wretched sinners!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O Lord, have mercy on me, woeful man!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What chance is this that suddenly hath cross&#8217;d us?</line>
<line form="verse">Speak, Salisbury; at least, if thou canst, speak.</line>
<line form="verse">How far&#8217;st thou, mirror of all martial men?</line>
<line form="verse">One of thy eyes and thy cheek&#8217;s side struck off!</line>
<line form="verse">Accursed tower! Accursed fatal hand</line>
<line form="verse">That hath contriv&#8217;d this woeful tragedy!</line>
<line form="verse">In thirteen battles Salisbury o&#8217;ercame;</line>
<line form="verse">Henry the Fifth he first train&#8217;d to the wars;</line>
<line form="verse">Whilst any trump did sound, or drum struck up,</line>
<line form="verse">His sword did ne&#8217;er leave striking in the field.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet liv&#8217;st thou, Salisbury? Though thy speech doth fail,</line>
<line form="verse">One eye thou hast to look to heaven for grace;</line>
<line form="verse">The sun with one eye vieweth all the world.</line>
<line form="verse">Heaven, be thou gracious to none alive,</line>
<line form="verse">If Salisbury wants mercy at thy hands!</line>
<line form="verse">Bear hence his body, I will help to bury it.</line>
<line form="verse">Sir Thomas Gargrave, hast thou any life?</line>
<line form="verse">Speak unto Talbot, nay, look up to him.</line>
<line form="verse">Salisbury, cheer thy spirit with this comfort,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt not die whiles&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">He beckons with his hand and smiles on me,</line>
<line form="verse">As who should say, &#8220;When I am dead and gone,</line>
<line form="verse">Remember to avenge me on the French.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Plantagenet, I will, and like thee, Nero,</line>
<line form="verse">Play on the lute, beholding the towns burn:</line>
<line form="verse">Wretched shall France be only in my name.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Here an alarum, and it thunders and lightens.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What stir is this? What tumult&#8217;s in the heavens?</line>
<line form="verse">Whence cometh this alarum, and the noise?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>4. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, my lord, the French have gather&#8217;d head.</line>
<line form="verse">The Dauphin, with one Joan de Pucelle join&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">A holy prophetess new risen up,</line>
<line form="verse">Is come with a great power to raise the siege.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Here Salisbury lifteth himself up and groans.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hear, hear how dying Salisbury doth groan!</line>
<line form="verse">It irks his heart he cannot be reveng&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Frenchmen, I&#8217;ll be a Salisbury to you.</line>
<line form="verse">Pucelle or puzzel, Dauphin or dogfish,</line>
<line form="verse">Your hearts I&#8217;ll stamp out with my horse&#8217;s heels,</line>
<line form="verse">And make a quagmire of your mingled brains.</line>
<line form="verse">Convey me Salisbury into his tent,</line>
<line form="verse">And then we&#8217;ll try what these dastard Frenchmen dare.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">>Alarum. Exeunt bearing out the bodies.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Orleans.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, Dauphin, Joan De Pucelle, Englishmen, Pucelle)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Joan la Pucelle drives back the English; she and Talbot fight each other, but though she beats him she does not kill him, as it is not yet his time to die. The incredulous Talbot is certain she is a witch. The shame of seeing th eenglish allow her to free Orleans is almost too much for him.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Here an alarum again, and Talbot pursueth the Dauphin, and driveth him.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="enter">Then enter Joan De Pucelle, driving Englishmen before her, and exit after them. Then enter Talbot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where is my strength, my valor, and my force?</line>
<line form="verse">Our English troops retire, I cannot stay them;</line>
<line form="verse">A woman clad in armor chaseth them.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Pucelle.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here, here she comes. I&#8217;ll have a bout with thee;</line>
<line form="verse">Devil or devil&#8217;s dam, I&#8217;ll conjure thee.</line>
<line form="verse">Blood will I draw on thee&#8212;thou art a witch&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And straightway give thy soul to him thou serv&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, come, &#8217;tis only I that must disgrace thee.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Here they fight.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Heavens, can you suffer hell so to prevail?</line>
<line form="verse">My breast I&#8217;ll burst with straining of my courage,</line>
<line form="verse">And from my shoulders crack my arms asunder,</line>
<line form="verse">But I will chastise this high-minded strumpet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Talbot, farewell, thy hour is not yet come.</line>
<line form="verse">I must go victual Orleance forthwith.</line>

<stagedir type="action">A short alarum: then enter the town with soldiers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O&#8217;ertake me if thou canst, I scorn thy strength.</line>
<line form="verse">Go, go, cheer up thy hungry-starved men;</line>
<line form="verse">Help Salisbury to make his testament.</line>
<line form="verse">This day is ours, as many more shall be.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My thoughts are whirled like a potter&#8217;s wheel,</line>
<line form="verse">I know not where I am, nor what I do.</line>
<line form="verse">A witch by fear, not force, like Hannibal,</line>
<line form="verse">Drives back our troops and conquers as she lists:</line>
<line form="verse">So bees with smoke and doves with noisome stench</line>
<line form="verse">Are from their hives and houses driven away.</line>
<line form="verse">They call&#8217;d us for our fierceness English dogs,</line>
<line form="verse">Now, like to whelps, we crying run away.</line>

<stagedir type="action">A short alarum.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hark, countrymen, either renew the fight,</line>
<line form="verse">Or tear the lions out of England&#8217;s coat;</line>
<line form="verse">Renounce your soil, give sheep in lions&#8217; stead:</line>
<line form="verse">Sheep run not half so treacherous from the wolf,</line>
<line form="verse">Or horse or oxen from the leopard,</line>
<line form="verse">As you fly from your oft-subdued slaves.</line>

<stagedir type="fight">Alarum. Here another skirmish.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">It will not be, retire into your trenches.</line>
<line form="verse">You all consented unto Salisbury&#8217;s death,</line>
<line form="verse">For none would strike a stroke in his revenge.</line>
<line form="verse">Pucelle is ent&#8217;red into Orleance</line>
<line form="verse">In spite of us, or aught that we could do.</line>
<line form="verse">O would I were to die with Salisbury!</line>
<line form="verse">The shame hereof will make me hide my head.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Talbot. Alarum; retreat.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Orleans.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Pucelle, Charles the Dauphin, Reignier, Alanson, Soldiers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>On the walls of Orleans, the victorious Charles praises Joan as the true winner of the day, and promises to give her half the kingdom. He predicts she will become France&#8217;s patron Saint.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Flourish. Enter on the walls Pucelle, Charles the Dauphin, Reignier, Alanson, and Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Advance our waving colors on the walls,</line>
<line form="verse">Rescu&#8217;d is Orleance from the English!</line>
<line form="verse">Thus Joan de Pucelle hath perform&#8217;d her word.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Divinest creature, Astraea&#8217;s daughter,</line>
<line form="verse">How shall I honor thee for this success?</line>
<line form="verse">Thy promises are like Adonis&#8217; garden,</line>
<line form="verse">That one day bloom&#8217;d and fruitful were the next.</line>
<line form="verse">France, triumph in thy glorious prophetess!</line>
<line form="verse">Recover&#8217;d is the town of Orleance.</line>
<line form="verse">More blessed hap did ne&#8217;er befall our state.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why ring not out the bells aloud throughout the town?</line>
<line form="verse">Dauphin, command the citizens make bonfires,</line>
<line form="verse">And feast and banquet in the open streets,</line>
<line form="verse">To celebrate the joy that God hath given us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All France will be replete with mirth and joy,</line>
<line form="verse">When they shall hear how we have play&#8217;d the men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis Joan, not we, by whom the day is won;</line>
<line form="verse">For which I will divide my crown with her,</line>
<line form="verse">And all the priests and friars in my realm</line>
<line form="verse">Shall in procession sing her endless praise.</line>
<line form="verse">A statelier pyramis to her I&#8217;ll rear</line>
<line form="verse">Than Rhodope&#8217;s of Memphis ever was.</line>
<line form="verse">In memory of her when she is dead,</line>
<line form="verse">Her ashes, in an urn more precious</line>
<line form="verse">Than the rich-jewell&#8217;d coffer of Darius,</line>
<line form="verse">Transported shall be at high festivals</line>
<line form="verse">Before the kings and queens of France.</line>
<line form="verse">No longer on Saint Denis will we cry,</line>
<line form="verse">But Joan de Pucelle shall be France&#8217;s saint.</line>
<line form="verse">Come in, and let us banquet royally,</line>
<line form="verse">After this golden day of victory.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Flourish. Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Orleans.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(French Sergeant, Sentinels, Talbot, Bedford, Burgundy, Bastard, Alanson, Reignier, Charles, Joan de Pucelle, English Soldier)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The English leaders scale the walls of Orleans in the dark, planning to take it back. They discuss Joan la Pucelle, snorting at the idea that she might be a virgin. The French, all asleep after their victory party, are taken completely by surprise, running around half-dressed and blaming each other for not taking proper care of the sentry duties. Charles accuses Joan of treachery and blames everybody but himself for what is happening. As they plan to regroup their soldiers, an English soldier runs in crying ‘A Talbot&#8217;, which terrifies them all so much that they run out, leaving their clothes behind. The English soldier picks up them, remarking that Talbot&#8217;s name is the only weapon he needs.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a French Sergeant of a band, with two Sentinels.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FR. SERG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sirs, take your places and be vigilant.</line>
<line form="verse">If any noise or soldier you perceive</line>
<line form="verse">Near to the walls, by some apparent sign</line>
<line form="verse">Let us have knowledge at the court of guard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sergeant, you shall.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Sergeant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Thus are poor servitors,</line>
<line form="verse">When others sleep upon their quiet beds,</line>
<line form="verse">Constrain&#8217;d to watch in darkness, rain, and cold.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Talbot, Bedford, and Burgundy, and forces with scaling-ladders.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Regent, and redoubted Burgundy,</line>
<line form="verse">By whose approach the regions of Artois,</line>
<line form="verse">Wallon, and Picardy are friends to us,</line>
<line form="verse">This happy night the Frenchmen are secure,</line>
<line form="verse">Having all day carous&#8217;d and banqueted:</line>
<line form="verse">Embrace we then this opportunity</line>
<line form="verse">As fitting best to quittance their deceit</line>
<line form="verse">Contriv&#8217;d by art and baleful sorcery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Coward of France, how much he wrongs his fame,</line>
<line form="verse">Despairing of his own arm&#8217;s fortitude,</line>
<line form="verse">To join with witches and the help of hell!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Traitors have never other company.</line>
<line form="verse">But what&#8217;s that Pucelle whom they term so pure?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A maid, they say.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">A maid? And be so martial?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pray God she prove not masculine ere long,</line>
<line form="verse">If underneath the standard of the French</line>
<line form="verse">She carry armor as she hath begun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, let them practice and converse with spirits.</line>
<line form="verse">God is our fortress, in whose conquering name</line>
<line form="verse">Let us resolve to scale their flinty bulwarks.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ascend, brave Talbot, we will follow thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not all together. Better far, I guess,</line>
<line form="verse">That we do make our entrance several ways;</line>
<line form="verse">That, if it chance the one of us do fail,</line>
<line form="verse">The other yet may rise against their force.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Agreed. I&#8217;ll to yond corner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">And I to this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And here will Talbot mount, or make his grave.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, Salisbury, for thee, and for the right</line>
<line form="verse">Of English Henry, shall this night appear</line>
<line form="verse">How much in duty I am bound to both.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Cry: &#8220;Saint George!&#8221; &#8220;A Talbot!&#8221; </stagedir>

<stagedir type="action">The English scale the walls.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Arm, arm! The enemy doth make assault!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">The French leap o&#8217;er the walls in their shirts. Enter, several ways, Bastard, Alanson, Reignier, half ready and half unready.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, my lords? What, all unready so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unready? Ay, and glad we scap&#8217;d so well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twas time, I trow, to wake and leave our beds,</line>
<line form="verse">Hearing alarums at our chamber-doors.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of all exploits since first I follow&#8217;d arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Ne&#8217;er heard I of a warlike enterprise</line>
<line form="verse">More venturous or desperate than this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think this Talbot be a fiend of hell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If not of hell, the heavens sure favor him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here cometh Charles, I marvel how he sped.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles and Joan de Pucelle.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tut, holy Joan was his defensive guard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is this thy cunning, thou deceitful dame?</line>
<line form="verse">Didst thou at first, to flatter us withal,</line>
<line form="verse">Make us partakers of a little gain,</line>
<line form="verse">That now our loss might be ten times so much?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wherefore is Charles impatient with his friend?</line>
<line form="verse">At all times will you have my power alike?</line>
<line form="verse">Sleeping or waking, must I still prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">Or will you blame and lay the fault on me?</line>
<line form="verse">Improvident soldiers, had your watch been good,</line>
<line form="verse">This sudden mischief never could have fall&#8217;n.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Duke of Alanson, this was your default,</line>
<line form="verse">That, being captain of the watch tonight,</line>
<line form="verse">Did look no better to that weighty charge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Had all your quarters been as safely kept</line>
<line form="verse">As that whereof I had the government,</line>
<line form="verse">We had not been thus shamefully surpris&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mine was secure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And so was mine, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And for myself, most part of all this night,</line>
<line form="verse">Within her quarter and mine own precinct</line>
<line form="verse">I was employ&#8217;d in passing to and fro,</line>
<line form="verse">About relieving of the sentinels.</line>
<line form="verse">Then how, or which way, should they first break in?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Question, my lords, no further of the case,</line>
<line form="verse">How or which way. &#8217;Tis sure they found some place</line>
<line form="verse">But weakly guarded, where the breach was made.</line>
<line form="verse">And now there rests no other shift but this,</line>
<line form="verse">To gather our soldiers, scatter&#8217;d and dispers&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And lay new platforms to endamage them.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Enter an English Soldier crying, &#8220;A Talbot! A Talbot!&#8221;</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="exit">They fly, leaving their clothes behind.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ENG. SOLD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll be so bold to take what they have left.</line>
<line form="verse">The cry of Talbot serves me for a sword,</line>
<line form="verse">For I have loaden me with many spoils,</line>
<line form="verse">Using no other weapon but his name.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Orleans. Within the town.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, Bedford, Burgundy, Captain, Messenger of the Countess)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The victorious English bury Salisbury, Talbot feeling that he has fulfilled his promise to avenge the dead man. The English wonder that Joan and Charles were not seen, but Burgundy reports how they fled when they were surprised together. A messenger brings Talbot an invitation from the Countess of Auvergne, who is anxious to meet the great man. Talbot whispers an order to his captain.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Talbot, Bedford, Burgundy, a Captain, and others, their Drums beating a dead march.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The day begins to break, and night is fled,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose pitchy mantle over-veil&#8217;d the earth.</line>
<line form="verse">Here sound retreat, and cease our hot pursuit.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Retreat.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bring forth the body of old Salisbury,</line>
<line form="verse">And here advance it in the market-place,</line>
<line form="verse">The middle centure of this cursed town.</line>
<line form="verse">Now have I paid my vow unto his soul;</line>
<line form="verse">For every drop of blood was drawn from him</line>
<line form="verse">There hath at least five Frenchmen died tonight.</line>
<line form="verse">And that hereafter ages may behold</line>
<line form="verse">What ruin happened in revenge of him,</line>
<line form="verse">Within their chiefest temple I&#8217;ll erect</line>
<line form="verse">A tomb, wherein his corpse shall be interr&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the which, that every one may read,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall be engrav&#8217;d the sack of Orleance,</line>
<line form="verse">The treacherous manner of his mournful death,</line>
<line form="verse">And what a terror he had been to France.</line>
<line form="verse">But, lords, in all our bloody massacre,</line>
<line form="verse">I muse we met not with the Dauphin&#8217;s grace,</line>
<line form="verse">His new-come champion, virtuous Joan of Aire,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor any of his false confederates.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis thought, Lord Talbot, when the fight began,</line>
<line form="verse">Rous&#8217;d on the sudden from their drowsy beds,</line>
<line form="verse">They did amongst the troops of armed men</line>
<line form="verse">Leap o&#8217;er the walls for refuge in the field.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Myself, as far as I could well discern</line>
<line form="verse">For smoke and dusky vapors of the night,</line>
<line form="verse">Am sure I scar&#8217;d the Dauphin and his trull,</line>
<line form="verse">When arm in arm they both came swiftly running,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a pair of loving turtle-doves</line>
<line form="verse">That could not live asunder day or night.</line>
<line form="verse">After that things are set in order here,</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll follow them with all the power we have.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Messenger of the Countess.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All hail, my lords! Which of this princely train</line>
<line form="verse">Call ye the warlike Talbot, for his acts</line>
<line form="verse">So much applauded through the realm of France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here is the Talbot, who would speak with him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The virtuous lady, Countess of Auvergne,</line>
<line form="verse">With modesty admiring thy renown,</line>
<line form="verse">By me entreats, great lord, thou wouldst vouchsafe</line>
<line form="verse">To visit her poor castle where she lies,</line>
<line form="verse">That she may boast she hath beheld the man</line>
<line form="verse">Whose glory fills the world with loud report.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is it even so? Nay, then I see our wars</line>
<line form="verse">Will turn unto a peaceful comic sport,</line>
<line form="verse">When ladies crave to be encount&#8217;red with.</line>
<line form="verse">You may not, my lord, despise her gentle suit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ne&#8217;er trust me then; for when a world of men</line>
<line form="verse">Could not prevail with all their oratory,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet hath a woman&#8217;s kindness overrul&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore tell her I return great thanks,</line>
<line form="verse">And in submission will attend on her.</line>
<line form="verse">Will not your honors bear me company?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, truly, &#8217;tis more than manners will;</line>
<line form="verse">And I have heard it said, unbidden guests</line>
<line form="verse">Are often welcomest when they are gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well then, alone (since there&#8217;s no remedy)</line>
<line form="verse">I mean to prove this lady&#8217;s courtesy.</line>
<line form="verse">Come hither, captain.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Whispers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">You perceive my mind?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do, my lord, and mean accordingly.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Auvergne. Court of the Countess&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Countess of Auvergne, Porter, Messenger of the Countess, Talbot, Porter, Soldiers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Countess of Auvergne makes sure that her porter has made the proper arrangements to execute her plan, and is excited at the prospect of how much fame she is about to gain. Talbot enters, and she is surprised to find that he is not really all that impressive in person. Talbot begins to leave, promising to prove that he is indeed Talbot, but she has locked the doors and crows that he is her prisoner. Talbot bursts out laughing. The Countess is confused as Talbot claims she has only captured his shadow, but understands when he blows his horn and his soldiers burst in and capture her. Talbot points out that however terrible his name is to the French, he is still nothing without his men. The lady is impressed and apologizes, and Talbot courteously tells her to think nothing of it, only asking for some refreshments for his men.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Countess of Auvergne and her Porter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Porter, remember what I gave in charge,</line>
<line form="verse">And when you have done so, bring the keys to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PORT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, I will.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The plot is laid. If all things fall out right,</line>
<line form="verse">I shall as famous be by this exploit</line>
<line form="verse">As Scythian Tomyris by Cyrus&#8217; death.</line>
<line form="verse">Great is the rumor of this dreadful knight,</line>
<line form="verse">And his achievements of no less account;</line>
<line form="verse">Fain would mine eyes be witness with mine ears</line>
<line form="verse">To give their censure of these rare reports.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Messenger of the Countess and Talbot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam,</line>
<line form="verse">According as your ladyship desir&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">By message crav&#8217;d, so is Lord Talbot come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And he is welcome. What? Is this the man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, it is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Is this the scourge of France?</line>
<line form="verse">Is this the Talbot, so much fear&#8217;d abroad</line>
<line form="verse">That with his name the mothers still their babes?</line>
<line form="verse">I see report is fabulous and false.</line>
<line form="verse">I thought I should have seen some Hercules,</line>
<line form="verse">A second Hector, for his grim aspect</line>
<line form="verse">And large proportion of his strong-knit limbs.</line>
<line form="verse">Alas, this is a child, a silly dwarf!</line>
<line form="verse">It cannot be this weak and writhled shrimp</line>
<line form="verse">Should strike such terror to his enemies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, I have been bold to trouble you;</line>
<line form="verse">But since your ladyship is not at leisure,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll sort some other time to visit you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Going.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What means he now? Go ask him whither he goes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, my Lord Talbot, for my lady craves</line>
<line form="verse">To know the cause of your abrupt departure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Marry, for that she&#8217;s in a wrong belief,</line>
<line form="verse">I go to certify her Talbot&#8217;s here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Porter with keys.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If thou be he, then art thou prisoner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Prisoner? To whom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">To me, blood-thirsty lord;</line>
<line form="verse">And for that cause I train&#8217;d thee to my house.</line>
<line form="verse">Long time thy shadow hath been thrall to me,</line>
<line form="verse">For in my gallery thy picture hangs;</line>
<line form="verse">But now the substance shall endure the like,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will chain these legs and arms of thine,</line>
<line form="verse">That hast by tyranny these many years</line>
<line form="verse">Wasted our country, slain our citizens,</line>
<line form="verse">And sent our sons and husbands captivate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ha, ha, ha!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Laughest thou, wretch? Thy mirth shall turn to moan.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I laugh to see your ladyship so fond</line>
<line form="verse">To think that you have aught but Talbot&#8217;s shadow</line>
<line form="verse">Whereon to practice your severity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why? Art not thou the man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I am indeed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then have I substance too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, no, I am but shadow of myself.</line>
<line form="verse">You are deceiv&#8217;d, my substance is not here;</line>
<line form="verse">For what you see is but the smallest part</line>
<line form="verse">And least proportion of humanity.</line>
<line form="verse">I tell you, madam, were the whole frame here,</line>
<line form="verse">It is of such a spacious lofty pitch,</line>
<line form="verse">Your roof were not sufficient to contain&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is a riddling merchant for the nonce:</line>
<line form="verse">He will be here, and yet he is not here.</line>
<line form="verse">How can these contrarieties agree?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That will I show you presently.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Winds his horn. Drums strike up; a peal of ordinance.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Soldiers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How say you, madam? Are you now persuaded</line>
<line form="verse">That Talbot is but shadow of himself?</line>
<line form="verse">These are his substance, sinews, arms, and strength,</line>
<line form="verse">With which he yoketh your rebellious necks,</line>
<line form="verse">Razeth your cities, and subverts your towns,</line>
<line form="verse">And in a moment makes them desolate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Victorious Talbot, pardon my abuse.</line>
<line form="verse">I find thou art no less than fame hath bruited,</line>
<line form="verse">And more than may be gathered by thy shape.</line>
<line form="verse">Let my presumption not provoke thy wrath,</line>
<line form="verse">For I am sorry that with reverence</line>
<line form="verse">I did not entertain thee as thou art.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be not dismay&#8217;d, fair lady, nor misconster</line>
<line form="verse">The mind of Talbot, as you did mistake</line>
<line form="verse">The outward composition of his body.</line>
<line form="verse">What you have done hath not offended me;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor other satisfaction do I crave,</line>
<line form="verse">But only, with your patience, that we may</line>
<line form="verse">Taste of your wine and see what cates you have,</line>
<line form="verse">For soldiers&#8217; stomachs always serve them well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COUNT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With all my heart, and think me honored</line>
<line form="verse">To feast so great a warrior in my house.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. The temple garden.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Richard Plantagenet, Warwick, Somerset, Pole the Earl of Suffolk, Vernon, Lawyer)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>In the gardens of the Temple law school, Richard Plantagenet and the Duke of Somerset continue to debate a difference of opinion they began over lunch, which soon grows to a quarrel. When their companions refuse to announce whose side they are on, Plantagenet picks a white rose and tells those who support him to do the same, while Somerset chooses a red rose. Somerset refuses to accept the verdict when more pick white roses than red, and the quarrel grows more abusive, until Somerset accuses Plantagenet of being a commoner and the son of a traitor. Plantagenet is needled by this, and both sides swear violence against each other. Warwick expresses his certainty that the blot of Plantagenet&#8217;s father&#8217;s treason will be wiped out in the coming parliament, and that Richard will be named Duke of York. Richard&#8217;s supporters pledge to keep wearing their roses, though they realize this is likely to lead to bloodshed.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Richard Plantagenet, Warwick, Somerset, Pole the Earl of Suffolk, and others; Vernon and a Lawyer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Great lords and gentlemen, what means this silence?</line>
<line form="verse">Dare no man answer in a case of truth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Within the Temple Hall we were too loud,</line>
<line form="verse">The garden here is more convenient.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then say at once if I maintain&#8217;d the truth;</line>
<line form="verse">Or else was wrangling Somerset in th&#8217; error?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Faith, I have been a truant in the law,</line>
<line form="verse">And never yet could frame my will to it,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore frame the law unto my will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Judge you, my Lord of Warwick, then between us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Between two hawks, which flies the higher pitch,</line>
<line form="verse">Between two dogs, which hath the deeper mouth,</line>
<line form="verse">Between two blades, which bears the better temper,</line>
<line form="verse">Between two horses, which doth bear him best,</line>
<line form="verse">Between two girls, which hath the merriest eye&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I have perhaps some shallow spirit of judgment;</line>
<line form="verse">But in these nice sharp quillets of the law,</line>
<line form="verse">Good faith, I am no wiser than a daw.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tut, tut, here is a mannerly forbearance.</line>
<line form="verse">The truth appears so naked on my side</line>
<line form="verse">That any purblind eye may find it out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And on my side it is so well apparell&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">So clear, so shining, and so evident,</line>
<line form="verse">That it will glimmer through a blindman&#8217;s eye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Since you are tongue-tied and so loath to speak,</line>
<line form="verse">In dumb significants proclaim your thoughts:</line>
<line form="verse">Let him that is a true-born gentleman</line>
<line form="verse">And stands upon the honor of his birth,</line>
<line form="verse">If he suppose that I have pleaded truth,</line>
<line form="verse">From off this brier pluck a white rose with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let him that is no coward nor no flatterer,</line>
<line form="verse">But dare maintain the party of the truth,</line>
<line form="verse">Pluck a red rose from off this thorn with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I love no colors; and without all color</line>
<line form="verse">Of base insinuating flattery,</line>
<line form="verse">I pluck this white rose with Plantagenet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pluck this red rose with young Somerset,</line>
<line form="verse">And say withal, I think he held the right.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, lords and gentlemen, and pluck no more,</line>
<line form="verse">Till you conclude that he upon whose side</line>
<line form="verse">The fewest roses are cropp&#8217;d from the tree</line>
<line form="verse">Shall yield the other in the right opinion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Master Vernon, it is well objected;</line>
<line form="verse">If I have fewest, I subscribe in silence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then for the truth and plainness of the case,</line>
<line form="verse">I pluck this pale and maiden blossom here,</line>
<line form="verse">Giving my verdict on the white rose side.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Prick not your finger as you pluck it off,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest, bleeding, you do paint the white rose red,</line>
<line form="verse">And fall on my side so against your will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If I, my lord, for my opinion bleed,</line>
<line form="verse">Opinion shall be surgeon to my hurt,</line>
<line form="verse">And keep me on the side where still I am.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, well, come on, who else?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unless my study and my books be false,</line>
<line form="verse">The argument you held was wrong in you;</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Somerset.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">In sign whereof I pluck a white rose too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, Somerset, where is your argument?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here in my scabbard, meditating that</line>
<line form="verse">Shall dye your white rose in a bloody red.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mean time your cheeks do counterfeit our roses;</line>
<line form="verse">For pale they look with fear, as witnessing</line>
<line form="verse">The truth on our side.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No, Plantagenet;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis not for fear, but anger, that thy cheeks</line>
<line form="verse">Blush for pure shame to counterfeit our roses,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet thy tongue will not confess thy error.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hath not thy rose a canker, Somerset?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hath not thy rose a thorn, Plantagenet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, sharp and piercing, to maintain his truth,</line>
<line form="verse">Whiles thy consuming canker eats his falsehood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, I&#8217;ll find friends to wear my bleeding roses,</line>
<line form="verse">That shall maintain what I have said is true,</line>
<line form="verse">Where false Plantagenet dare not be seen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, by this maiden blossom in my hand,</line>
<line form="verse">I scorn thee and thy fashion, peevish boy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Turn not thy scorns this way, Plantagenet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Proud Pole, I will, and scorn both him and thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll turn my part thereof into thy throat.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Away, away, good William de la Pole!</line>
<line form="verse">We grace the yeoman by conversing with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, by God&#8217;s will, thou wrong&#8217;st him, Somerset;</line>
<line form="verse">His grandfather was Lionel Duke of Clarence,</line>
<line form="verse">Third son to the third Edward, King of England.</line>
<line form="verse">Spring crestless yeomen from so deep a root?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He bears him on the place&#8217;s privilege,</line>
<line form="verse">Or durst not for his craven heart say thus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By Him that made me, I&#8217;ll maintain my words</line>
<line form="verse">On any plot of ground in Christendom.</line>
<line form="verse">Was not thy father, Richard Earl of Cambridge,</line>
<line form="verse">For treason executed in our late king&#8217;s days?</line>
<line form="verse">And by his treason, stand&#8217;st not thou attainted,</line>
<line form="verse">Corrupted, and exempt from ancient gentry?</line>
<line form="verse">His trespass yet lives guilty in thy blood,</line>
<line form="verse">And till thou be restor&#8217;d, thou art a yeoman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My father was attached, not attainted,</line>
<line form="verse">Condemn&#8217;d to die for treason, but no traitor;</line>
<line form="verse">And that I&#8217;ll prove on better men than Somerset,</line>
<line form="verse">Were growing time once ripened to my will.</line>
<line form="verse">For your partaker Pole, and you yourself,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll note you in my book of memory,</line>
<line form="verse">To scourge you for this apprehension.</line>
<line form="verse">Look to it well, and say you are well warn&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, thou shalt find us ready for thee still;</line>
<line form="verse">And know us by these colors for thy foes,</line>
<line form="verse">For these my friends in spite of thee shall wear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And, by my soul, this pale and angry rose,</line>
<line form="verse">As cognizance of my blood-drinking hate,</line>
<line form="verse">Will I forever and my faction wear,</line>
<line form="verse">Until it wither with me to my grave,</line>
<line form="verse">Or flourish to the height of my degree.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go forward, and be chok&#8217;d with thy ambition!</line>
<line form="verse">And so farewell until I meet thee next.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have with thee, Pole. Farewell, ambitious Richard.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How I am brav&#8217;d, and must perforce endure it!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This blot that they object against your house</line>
<line form="verse">Shall be wip&#8217;d out in the next parliament,</line>
<line form="verse">Call&#8217;d for the truce of Winchester and Gloucester;</line>
<line form="verse">And if thou be not then created York,</line>
<line form="verse">I will not live to be accounted Warwick.</line>
<line form="verse">Mean time, in signal of my love to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Against proud Somerset and William Pole,</line>
<line form="verse">Will I upon thy party wear this rose.</line>
<line form="verse">And here I prophesy: this brawl today,</line>
<line form="verse">Grown to this faction in the Temple Garden,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall send between the Red Rose and the White</line>
<line form="verse">A thousand souls to death and deadly night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Master Vernon, I am bound to you</line>
<line form="verse">That you on my behalf would pluck a flower.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In your behalf still will I wear the same.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so will I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Thanks, gentlemen.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, let us four to dinner. I dare say</line>
<line form="verse">This quarrel will drink blood another day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. A room in the Tower of London.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Mortimer, Richard Plantagenet, Keepers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The imprisoned Mortimer waits for his nephew, Richard Plantagenet, to visit him. Old and wearied, he is near death. When Plantagenet arrives, Mortimer tells him the story of how Henry IV usurped the crown from Richard II. Mortimer was Richard II&#8217;s legitimate heir, but the Lancastrian kings (Henry IV, Henry V, and now the infant Henry VI) took the throne and suppressed the Mortimer family, finally imprisoning Mortimer himself for life. As Richard Plantagenet is the son of Mortimer&#8217;s sister, Richard in fact has a better claim to the throne than does the King. Mortimer warns him to be careful about pressing this claim, as the Lancastrians are well-installed, and dies. Plantagenet mourns him, and leaves to the parliament, intent on being restored as Duke of York,</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Mortimer, brought in a chair, and Jailers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Kind keepers of my weak decaying age,</line>
<line form="verse">Let dying Mortimer here rest himself.</line>
<line form="verse">Even like a man new haled from the rack,</line>
<line form="verse">So fare my limbs with long imprisonment;</line>
<line form="verse">And these grey locks, the pursuivants of death,</line>
<line form="verse">Nestor-like aged, in an age of care,</line>
<line form="verse">Argue the end of Edmund Mortimer.</line>
<line form="verse">These eyes, like lamps whose wasting oil is spent,</line>
<line form="verse">Wax dim, as drawing to their exigent;</line>
<line form="verse">Weak shoulders, overborne with burdening grief,</line>
<line form="verse">And pithless arms, like to a withered vine</line>
<line form="verse">That droops his sapless branches to the ground.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet are these feet, whose strengthless stay is numb</line>
<line form="verse">(Unable to support this lump of clay),</line>
<line form="verse">Swift-winged with desire to get a grave,</line>
<line form="verse">As witting I no other comfort have.</line>
<line form="verse">But tell me, keeper, will my nephew come?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. KEEPER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Richard Plantagenet, my lord, will come.</line>
<line form="verse">We sent unto the Temple, unto his chamber,</line>
<line form="verse">And answer was return&#8217;d that he will come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Enough; my soul shall then be satisfied.</line>
<line form="verse">Poor gentleman, his wrong doth equal mine.</line>
<line form="verse">Since Henry Monmouth first began to reign,</line>
<line form="verse">Before whose glory I was great in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">This loathsome sequestration have I had;</line>
<line form="verse">And even since then hath Richard been obscur&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Depriv&#8217;d of honor and inheritance.</line>
<line form="verse">But now, the arbitrator of despairs,</line>
<line form="verse">Just Death, kind umpire of men&#8217;s miseries,</line>
<line form="verse">With sweet enlargement doth dismiss me hence.</line>
<line form="verse">I would his troubles likewise were expir&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">That so he might recover what was lost.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Richard Plantagenet.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. KEEPER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, your loving nephew now is come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Richard Plantagenet, my friend, is he come?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, noble uncle, thus ignobly us&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Your nephew, late-despised Richard, comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Direct mine arms I may embrace his neck,</line>
<line form="verse">And in his bosom spend my latter gasp.</line>
<line form="verse">O, tell me when my lips do touch his cheeks,</line>
<line form="verse">That I may kindly give one fainting kiss.</line>
<line form="verse">And now declare, sweet stem from York&#8217;s great stock,</line>
<line form="verse">Why didst thou say, of late thou wert despis&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">First, lean thine aged back against mine arm,</line>
<line form="verse">And in that ease, I&#8217;ll tell thee my disease.</line>
<line form="verse">This day, in argument upon a case,</line>
<line form="verse">Some words there grew &#8217;twixt Somerset and me;</line>
<line form="verse">Among which terms he us&#8217;d his lavish tongue</line>
<line form="verse">And did upbraid me with my father&#8217;s death;</line>
<line form="verse">Which obloquy set bars before my tongue,</line>
<line form="verse">Else with the like I had requited him.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, good uncle, for my father&#8217;s sake,</line>
<line form="verse">In honor of a true Plantagenet,</line>
<line form="verse">And for alliance sake, declare the cause</line>
<line form="verse">My father, Earl of Cambridge, lost his head.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That cause, fair nephew, that imprison&#8217;d me</line>
<line form="verse">And hath detain&#8217;d me all my flow&#8217;ring youth</line>
<line form="verse">Within a loathsome dungeon, there to pine,</line>
<line form="verse">Was cursed instrument of his decease.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Discover more at large what cause that was,</line>
<line form="verse">For I am ignorant and cannot guess.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, if that my fading breath permit</line>
<line form="verse">And death approach not ere my tale be done.</line>
<line form="verse">Henry the Fourth, grandfather to this king,</line>
<line form="verse">Depos&#8217;d his nephew Richard, Edward&#8217;s son,</line>
<line form="verse">The first begotten, and the lawful heir</line>
<line form="verse">Of Edward king, the third of that descent;</line>
<line form="verse">During whose reign the Percies of the north,</line>
<line form="verse">Finding his usurpation most unjust,</line>
<line form="verse">Endeavor&#8217;d my advancement to the throne.</line>
<line form="verse">The reason mov&#8217;d these warlike lords to this</line>
<line form="verse">Was, for that (young Richard thus remov&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Leaving no heir begotten of his body)</line>
<line form="verse">I was the next by birth and parentage;</line>
<line form="verse">For by my mother I derived am</line>
<line form="verse">From Lionel Duke of Clarence, third son</line>
<line form="verse">To King Edward the Third; whereas he</line>
<line form="verse">From John of Gaunt doth bring his pedigree,</line>
<line form="verse">Being but fourth of that heroic line.</line>
<line form="verse">But mark: as in this haughty great attempt</line>
<line form="verse">They labored to plant the rightful heir,</line>
<line form="verse">I lost my liberty, and they their lives.</line>
<line form="verse">Long after this, when Henry the Fifth</line>
<line form="verse">(Succeeding his father Bullingbrook) did reign,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy father, Earl of Cambridge then, deriv&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">From famous Edmund Langley, Duke of York,</line>
<line form="verse">Marrying my sister that thy mother was,</line>
<line form="verse">Again, in pity of my hard distress,</line>
<line form="verse">Levied an army, weening to redeem</line>
<line form="verse">And have install&#8217;d me in the diadem.</line>
<line form="verse">But as the rest, so fell that noble earl,</line>
<line form="verse">And was beheaded. Thus the Mortimers,</line>
<line form="verse">In whom the title rested, were suppress&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of which, my lord, your honor is the last.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">True; and thou seest that I no issue have,</line>
<line form="verse">And that my fainting words do warrant death.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art my heir; the rest I wish thee gather;</line>
<line form="verse">But yet be wary in thy studious care.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy grave admonishments prevail with me.</line>
<line form="verse">But yet methinks, my father&#8217;s execution</line>
<line form="verse">Was nothing less than bloody tyranny.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With silence, nephew, be thou politic.</line>
<line form="verse">Strong fixed is the house of Lancaster,</line>
<line form="verse">And like a mountain, not to be remov&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">But now thy uncle is removing hence,</line>
<line form="verse">As princes do their courts, when they are cloy&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With long continuance in a settled place.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O uncle, would some part of my young years</line>
<line form="verse">Might but redeem the passage of your age!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou dost then wrong me, as that slaughterer doth</line>
<line form="verse">Which giveth many wounds when one will kill.</line>
<line form="verse">Mourn not, except thou sorrow for my good,</line>
<line form="verse">Only give order for my funeral.</line>
<line form="verse">And so farewell, and fair be all thy hopes,</line>
<line form="verse">And prosperous be thy life in peace and war!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="MOR.">Dies.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And peace, no war, befall thy parting soul!</line>
<line form="verse">In prison hast thou spent a pilgrimage,</line>
<line form="verse">And like a hermit overpass&#8217;d thy days.</line>
<line form="verse">Well, I will lock his counsel in my breast,</line>
<line form="verse">And what I do imagine, let that rest.</line>
<line form="verse">Keepers, convey him hence, and I myself</line>
<line form="verse">Will see his burial better than his life.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Keepers, bearing out the body of Mortimer.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here dies the dusky torch of Mortimer,</line>
<line form="verse">Chok&#8217;d with ambition of the meaner sort;</line>
<line form="verse">And for those wrongs, those bitter injuries,</line>
<line form="verse">Which Somerset hath offer&#8217;d to my house,</line>
<line form="verse">I doubt not but with honor to redress.</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore haste I to the parliament,</line>
<line form="verse">Either to be restored to my blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Or make my will th&#8217; advantage of my good.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. The Parliament House.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King, Exeter, Gloucester, Winchester, Warwick, Somerset, Suffolk, Richard Plantagenet, Mayor of London, Serving Attendants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>At Parliament, Gloucester attempts to present a written list of complaints against Winchester, but the Bishop grabs it and rips it up, telling Gloucester to speak it all directly, charging that if the accusations are true there is no need to take the time to write them down. The two quarrel violently, despite the King&#8217;s attempts to pacify them. The Mayor enters, begging for help in keeping Gloucester and Winchester&#8217;s men from fighting, as they have started to throw stones at each other now that they are forbidden to carry actual weapons, and risk inflicting great damage on the citizens&#8217; property. The fighting spills into the parliament, where the servants refuse to be pacified. Warwick urges Gloucester and Winchester to reconcile, as the only way to prevent civil war. Gloucester yields, but Winchester must be coerced; he finally takes Gloucester&#8217;s hand, but does not intend to keep his word. Richard Plantagenet is restored to his place as Duke of York, and pledges his loyalty to the King; Somerset is disgusted. Gloucester proposes that the King be crowned a second time, as King of France, to reinvigorate the English cause in France. Henry agrees with his uncle. Exeter is worried, seeing that the dissention between the nobles does not bode well for the war in France; he recalls a prophecy that Henry of Monmouth (the dead Henry V) would win all, but Henry born at Windsor (Henry VI) would then lose it.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Flourish. Enter King, Exeter, Gloucester, Winchester, Warwick, Somerset, Suffolk, Richard Plantagenet, and others. Gloucester offers to put up a bill; Winchester snatches it, tears it.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Com&#8217;st thou with deep premeditated lines,</line>
<line form="verse">With written pamphlets studiously devis&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">Humphrey of Gloucester, if thou canst accuse,</line>
<line form="verse">Or aught intend&#8217;st to lay unto my charge,</line>
<line form="verse">Do it without invention, suddenly,</line>
<line form="verse">As I with sudden and extemporal speech</line>
<line form="verse">Purpose to answer what thou canst object.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Presumptuous priest, this place commands my patience,</line>
<line form="verse">Or thou shouldst find thou hast dishonor&#8217;d me.</line>
<line form="verse">Think not, although in writing I preferr&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The manner of thy vile outrageous crimes,</line>
<line form="verse">That therefore I have forg&#8217;d, or am not able</line>
<line form="verse">Verbatim to rehearse the method of my pen.</line>
<line form="verse">No, prelate, such is thy audacious wickedness,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy lewd, pestiferous, and dissentious pranks,</line>
<line form="verse">As very infants prattle of thy pride.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art a most pernicious usurer,</line>
<line form="verse">Froward by nature, enemy to peace,</line>
<line form="verse">Lascivious, wanton, more than well beseems</line>
<line form="verse">A man of thy profession and degree;</line>
<line form="verse">And for thy treachery, what&#8217;s more manifest?</line>
<line form="verse">In that thou laidst a trap to take my life,</line>
<line form="verse">As well at London Bridge as at the Tower.</line>
<line form="verse">Beside, I fear me, if thy thoughts were sifted,</line>
<line form="verse">The King, thy sovereign, is not quite exempt</line>
<line form="verse">From envious malice of thy swelling heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gloucester, I do defy thee. Lords, vouchsafe</line>
<line form="verse">To give me hearing what I shall reply.</line>
<line form="verse">If I were covetous, ambitious, or perverse,</line>
<line form="verse">As he will have me, how am I so poor?</line>
<line form="verse">Or how haps it I seek not to advance</line>
<line form="verse">Or raise myself, but keep my wonted calling?</line>
<line form="verse">And for dissension, who preferreth peace</line>
<line form="verse">More than I do, except I be provok&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">No, my good lords, it is not that offends,</line>
<line form="verse">It is not that that hath incens&#8217;d the Duke:</line>
<line form="verse">It is because no one should sway but he,</line>
<line form="verse">No one, but he, should be about the King;</line>
<line form="verse">And that engenders thunder in his breast,</line>
<line form="verse">And makes him roar these accusations forth.</line>
<line form="verse">But he shall know I am as good&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">As good?</line>
<line form="verse">Thou bastard of my grandfather!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, lordly sir; for what are you, I pray,</line>
<line form="verse">But one imperious in another&#8217;s throne?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Am I not Protector, saucy priest?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And am not I a prelate of the Church?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, as an outlaw in a castle keeps</line>
<line form="verse">And useth it to patronage his theft.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Unreverent Gloucester!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Thou art reverent</line>
<line form="verse">Touching thy spiritual function, not thy life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Rome shall remedy this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Roam thither then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To Winchester</stagedir>
<line form="verse">My lord, it were your duty to forbear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, so the Bishop be not overborne.</line>
<line form="verse">Methinks my lord should be religious,</line>
<line form="verse">And know the office that belongs to such.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Methinks his lordship should be humbler,</line>
<line form="verse">It fitteth not a prelate so to plead.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, when his holy state is touch&#8217;d so near.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">State holy or unhallow&#8217;d, what of that?</line>
<line form="verse">Is not his Grace Protector to the King?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Plantagenet, I see, must hold his tongue,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest it be said, &#8220;Speak, sirrah, when you should;</line>
<line form="verse">Must your bold verdict enter talk with lords?&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Else would I have a fling at Winchester.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Uncles of Gloucester and of Winchester,</line>
<line form="verse">The special watchmen of our English weal,</line>
<line form="verse">I would prevail, if prayers might prevail,</line>
<line form="verse">To join your hearts in love and amity.</line>
<line form="verse">O, what a scandal is it to our crown</line>
<line form="verse">That two such noble peers as ye should jar!</line>
<line form="verse">Believe me, lords, my tender years can tell,</line>
<line form="verse">Civil dissension is a viperous worm</line>
<line form="verse">That gnaws the bowels of the commonwealth.</line>

<stagedir type="action">A noise within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Down with the tawny-coats!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">What tumult&#8217;s this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">An uproar, I dare warrant,</line>
<line form="verse">Begun through malice of the Bishop&#8217;s men.</line>

<stagedir type="action">A noise again,</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="9">&#8220;Stones! Stones!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Mayor of London, attended.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O my good lords, and virtuous Henry,</line>
<line form="verse">Pity the city of London, pity us!</line>
<line form="verse">The Bishop and the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s men,</line>
<line form="verse">Forbidden late to carry any weapon,</line>
<line form="verse">Have fill&#8217;d their pockets full of pebble stones;</line>
<line form="verse">And, banding themselves in contrary parts,</line>
<line form="verse">Do pelt so fast at one another&#8217;s pate</line>
<line form="verse">That many have their giddy brains knock&#8217;d out;</line>
<line form="verse">Our windows are broke down in every street,</line>
<line form="verse">And we, for fear, compell&#8217;d to shut our shops.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servingmen of both parties, in skirmish, with bloody pates.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We charge you, on allegiance to ourself,</line>
<line form="verse">To hold your slaught&#8217;ring hands and keep the peace.</line>
<line form="verse">Pray, uncle Gloucester, mitigate this strife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, if we be forbidden stones, we&#8217;ll fall to it with our teeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. GLOU. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do what ye dare, we are as resolute.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Skirmish again.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You of my household, leave this peevish broil,</line>
<line form="verse">And set this unaccustom&#8217;d fight aside.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. GLOU. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, we know your Grace to be a man</line>
<line form="verse">Just and upright; and, for your royal birth,</line>
<line form="verse">Inferior to none but to his Majesty;</line>
<line form="verse">And ere that we will suffer such a prince,</line>
<line form="verse">So kind a father of the commonweal,</line>
<line form="verse">To be disgraced by an inkhorn mate,</line>
<line form="verse">We and our wives and children all will fight,</line>
<line form="verse">And have our bodies slaught&#8217;red by thy foes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and the very parings of our nails</line>
<line form="verse">Shall pitch a field when we are dead.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Begin again.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">Stay, stay, I say!</line>
<line form="verse">And if you love me, as you say you do,</line>
<line form="verse">Let me persuade you to forbear a while.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, how this discord doth afflict my soul!</line>
<line form="verse">Can you, my Lord of Winchester, behold</line>
<line form="verse">My sighs and tears, and will not once relent?</line>
<line form="verse">Who should be pitiful, if you be not?</line>
<line form="verse">Or who should study to prefer a peace,</line>
<line form="verse">If holy churchmen take delight in broils?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yield, my Lord Protector, yield, Winchester,</line>
<line form="verse">Except you mean with obstinate repulse</line>
<line form="verse">To slay your sovereign and destroy the realm.</line>
<line form="verse">You see what mischief, and what murder too,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath been enacted through your enmity.</line>
<line form="verse">Then be at peace, except ye thirst for blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He shall submit, or I will never yield.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Compassion on the King commands me stoop,</line>
<line form="verse">Or I would see his heart out ere the priest</line>
<line form="verse">Should ever get that privilege of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Behold, my Lord of Winchester, the Duke</line>
<line form="verse">Hath banish&#8217;d moody discontented fury,</line>
<line form="verse">As by his smoothed brows it doth appear.</line>
<line form="verse">Why look you still so stern and tragical?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, Winchester, I offer thee my hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, uncle Beauford, I have heard you preach</line>
<line form="verse">That malice was a great and grievous sin;</line>
<line form="verse">And will not you maintain the thing you teach,</line>
<line form="verse">But prove a chief offender in the same?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet King! The Bishop hath a kindly gird.</line>
<line form="verse">For shame, my Lord of Winchester, relent!</line>
<line form="verse">What, shall a child instruct you what to do?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, Duke of Gloucester, I will yield to thee;</line>
<line form="verse">Love for thy love and hand for hand I give.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Ay, but, I fear me, with a hollow heart.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">See here, my friends and loving countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">This token serveth for a flag of truce</line>
<line form="verse">Betwixt ourselves and all our followers.</line>
<line form="verse">So help me God, as I dissemble not!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">So help me God, as I intend it not!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O loving uncle, kind Duke of Gloucester,</line>
<line form="verse">How joyful am I made by this contract!</line>
<line form="verse">Away, my masters, trouble us no more,</line>
<line form="verse">But join in friendship, as your lords have done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content, I&#8217;ll to the surgeon&#8217;s.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. GLOU. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">And so will I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. GLOU. SERV. ATT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I will see what physic the tavern affords.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Servingmen, Mayor, etc.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Accept this scroll, most gracious sovereign,</line>
<line form="verse">Which in the right of Richard Plantagenet</line>
<line form="verse">We do exhibit to your Majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well urg&#8217;d, my Lord of Warwick; for, sweet prince,</line>
<line form="verse">And if your Grace mark every circumstance,</line>
<line form="verse">You have great reason to do Richard right,</line>
<line form="verse">Especially for those occasions</line>
<line form="verse">At Eltam Place I told your Majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And those occasions, uncle, were of force:</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, my loving lords, our pleasure is</line>
<line form="verse">That Richard be restored to his blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let Richard be restored to his blood,</line>
<line form="verse">So shall his father&#8217;s wrongs be recompens&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As will the rest, so willeth Winchester.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If Richard will be true, not that alone</line>
<line form="verse">But all the whole inheritance I give</line>
<line form="verse">That doth belong unto the house of York,</line>
<line form="verse">From whence you spring by lineal descent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy humble servant vows obedience</line>
<line form="verse">And humble service till the point of death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stoop then and set your knee against my foot,</line>
<line form="verse">And in reguerdon of that duty done,</line>
<line form="verse">I girt thee with the valiant sword of York:</line>
<line form="verse">Rise, Richard, like a true Plantagenet,</line>
<line form="verse">And rise created princely Duke of York.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PLAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so thrive Richard as thy foes may fall!</line>
<line form="verse">And as my duty springs, so perish they</line>
<line form="verse">That grudge one thought against your Majesty!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, high prince, the mighty Duke of York!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Perish, base prince, ignoble Duke of York!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now will it best avail your Majesty</line>
<line form="verse">To cross the seas and to be crown&#8217;d in France.</line>
<line form="verse">The presence of a king engenders love</line>
<line form="verse">Amongst his subjects and his loyal friends,</line>
<line form="verse">As it disanimates his enemies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When Gloucester says the word, King Henry goes,</line>
<line form="verse">For friendly counsel cuts off many foes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your ships already are in readiness.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Sennet. Flourish. Exeunt. Manet Exeter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, we may march in England, or in France,</line>
<line form="verse">Not seeing what is likely to ensue.</line>
<line form="verse">This late dissension grown betwixt the peers</line>
<line form="verse">Burns under feigned ashes of forg&#8217;d love,</line>
<line form="verse">And will at last break out into a flame:</line>
<line form="verse">As fest&#8217;red members rot but by degree,</line>
<line form="verse">Till bones and flesh and sinews fall away,</line>
<line form="verse">So will this base and envious discord breed.</line>
<line form="verse">And now I fear that fatal prophecy</line>
<line form="verse">Which in the time of Henry nam&#8217;d the Fifth</line>
<line form="verse">Was in the mouth of every sucking babe,</line>
<line form="verse">That Henry born at Monmouth should win all,</line>
<line form="verse">And Henry born at Windsor lose all:</line>
<line form="verse">Which is so plain that Exeter doth wish</line>
<line form="verse">His days may finish ere that hapless time.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>
 
</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Rouen.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Pucelle, Four Soldiers, Soldier of the Watch, Charles, Bastard, Alanson, Reignier, Talbot, Bedford, Talbot, Burgundy, Sir John Falstaff, Captain)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Joan la Pucelle and four men disguised as peasants sneak into Rouen and open the gates to Charles, who takes the town. Talbot and the English find themselves outside the walls. Talbot insults Joan and tries to convince the French soldiers to fight it out in the open field, but the French decline, as they would be giving up a great advantage in doing do. The ill Bedford is urged to retire to a safer place, but he refuses. Bedford watches as Talbot and the others take the town back from the French. Sir John Falstofe runs away from the battle in fear of his life. Having seen Rouen taken back, Bedford is content to die. Tablot and the others plan to go to King Henry in Paris once they have buried Bedford.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Pucelle, disguis&#8217;d, with four Soldiers with sacks upon their backs.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These are the city-gates, the gates of Roan,</line>
<line form="verse">Through which our policy must make a breach.</line>
<line form="verse">Take heed, be wary how you place your words,</line>
<line form="verse">Talk like the vulgar sort of market men</line>
<line form="verse">That come to gather money for their corn.</line>
<line form="verse">If we have entrance, as I hope we shall,</line>
<line form="verse">And that we find the slothful watch but weak,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll by a sign give notice to our friends,</line>
<line form="verse">That Charles the Dauphin may encounter them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SOLD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Our sacks shall be a mean to sack the city,</line>
<line form="verse">And we be lords and rulers over Roan,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore we&#8217;ll knock.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOLD. WATCH.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><french xml:lang="fr">Qui l&#224;?</french></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse"><french xml:lang="fr">Paysans, la pauvre gens de France,</french></line>
<line form="verse">Poor market folks that come to sell their corn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOLD. WATCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Enter, go in, the market bell is rung.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, Roan, I&#8217;ll shake thy bulwarks to the ground.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt to the town.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Bastard, Alanson, Reignier, and forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Saint Denis bless this happy stratagem!</line>
<line form="verse">And once again we&#8217;ll sleep secure in Roan.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here ent&#8217;red Pucelle and her practisants.</line>
<line form="verse">Now she is there, how will she specify</line>
<line form="verse">Here is the best and safest passage in?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By thrusting out a torch from yonder tower,</line>
<line form="verse">Which once discern&#8217;d, shows that her meaning is,</line>
<line form="verse">No way to that, for weakness, which she ent&#8217;red.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Pucelle on the top, thrusting out a torch burning.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Behold, this is the happy wedding torch</line>
<line form="verse">That joineth Roan unto her countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">But burning fatal to the Talbonites!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">See, noble Charles, the beacon of our friend,</line>
<line form="verse">The burning torch in yonder turret stands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now shine it like a comet of revenge,</line>
<line form="verse">A prophet to the fall of all our foes!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Defer no time, delays have dangerous ends,</line>
<line form="verse">Enter and cry &#8220;The Dauphin!&#8221; presently,</line>
<line form="verse">And then do execution on the watch.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter" actor="TAL.">An alarum. Enter Talbot in an excursion.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">France, thou shalt rue this treason with thy tears,</line>
<line form="verse">If Talbot but survive thy treachery.</line>
<line form="verse">Pucelle, that witch, that damned sorceress,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath wrought this hellish mischief unawares,</line>
<line form="verse">That hardly we escap&#8217;d the pride of France.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">An alarum. Excursions. Bedford brought in sick in a chair. Enter Talbot and Burgundy without; within, Pucelle, Charles, Bastard, Alanson, and Reignier, on the walls.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good morrow, gallants, want ye corn for bread?</line>
<line form="verse">I think the Duke of Burgundy will fast</line>
<line form="verse">Before he&#8217;ll buy again at such a rate.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twas full of darnel; do you like the taste?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Scoff on, vile fiend and shameless courtezan!</line>
<line form="verse">I trust ere long to choke thee with thine own,</line>
<line form="verse">And make thee curse the harvest of that corn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your Grace may starve, perhaps, before that time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, let no words, but deeds, revenge this treason!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What will you do, good greybeard? Break a lance,</line>
<line form="verse">And run a-tilt at Death within a chair?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Foul fiend of France, and hag of all despite,</line>
<line form="verse">Encompass&#8217;d with thy lustful paramours!</line>
<line form="verse">Becomes it thee to taunt his valiant age,</line>
<line form="verse">And twit with cowardice a man half dead?</line>
<line form="verse">Damsel, I&#8217;ll have a bout with you again,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else let Talbot perish with this shame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Are ye so hot, sir? Yet, Pucelle, hold thy peace,</line>
<line form="verse">If Talbot do but thunder, rain will follow.</line>

<stagedir type="action">They, the English, whisper together in council.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">God speed the parliament! Who shall be the speaker?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dare ye come forth and meet us in the field?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Belike your lordship takes us then for fools,</line>
<line form="verse">To try if that our own be ours or no.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I speak not to that railing Hecate,</line>
<line form="verse">But unto thee, Alanson, and the rest.</line>
<line form="verse">Will ye, like soldiers, come and fight it out?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Signior, no.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Signior, hang! Base muleters of France!</line>
<line form="verse">Like peasant footboys do they keep the walls,</line>
<line form="verse">And dare not take up arms like gentlemen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Away, captains, let&#8217;s get us from the walls,</line>
<line form="verse">For Talbot means no goodness by his looks.</line>
<line form="verse">God buy, my lord, we came but to tell you</line>
<line form="verse">That we are here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt from the walls.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And there will we be too, ere it be long,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else reproach be Talbot&#8217;s greatest fame!</line>
<line form="verse">Vow, Burgundy, by honor of thy house,</line>
<line form="verse">Prick&#8217;d on by public wrongs sustain&#8217;d in France,</line>
<line form="verse">Either to get the town again, or die:</line>
<line form="verse">And I, as sure as English Henry lives</line>
<line form="verse">And as his father here was conqueror,</line>
<line form="verse">As sure as in this late-betrayed town</line>
<line form="verse">Great Coeur de Lion&#8217;s heart was buried,</line>
<line form="verse">So sure I swear to get the town, or die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My vows are equal partners with thy vows.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But ere we go, regard this dying prince,</line>
<line form="verse">The valiant Duke of Bedford. Come, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">We will bestow you in some better place,</line>
<line form="verse">Fitter for sickness and for crazy age.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Talbot, do not so dishonor me:</line>
<line form="verse">Here will I sit before the walls of Roan</line>
<line form="verse">And will be partner of your weal or woe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Courageous Bedford, let us now persuade you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not to be gone from hence; for once I read</line>
<line form="verse">That stout Pendragon in his litter sick</line>
<line form="verse">Came to the field and vanquished his foes.</line>
<line form="verse">Methinks I should revive the soldiers&#8217; hearts,</line>
<line form="verse">Because I ever found them as myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Undaunted spirit in a dying breast!</line>
<line form="verse">Then be it so. Heavens keep old Bedford safe!</line>
<line form="verse">And now no more ado, brave Burgundy,</line>
<line form="verse">But gather we our forces out of hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And set upon our boasting enemy.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Burgundy and forces into the town.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">An alarum. Excursions. Enter Sir John Falstaff and a Captain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whither away, Sir John Falstaff, in such haste?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whither away? To save myself by flight.</line>
<line form="verse">We are like to have the overthrow again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Will you fly, and leave Lord Talbot?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="9">Ay,</line>
<line form="verse">All the Talbots in the world, to save my life.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cowardly knight, ill fortune follow thee!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit into the town.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="action">Retreat. Excursions. Pucelle, Alanson, and Charles enter from the town and fly.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BED.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, quiet soul, depart when heaven please,</line>
<line form="verse">For I have seen our enemies&#8217; overthrow.</line>
<line form="verse">What is the trust or strength of foolish man?</line>
<line form="verse">They that of late were daring with their scoffs</line>
<line form="verse">Are glad and fain by flight to save themselves.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="BED.">Bedford dies, and is carried in by two in his chair.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">An alarum. Enter Talbot, Burgundy, and the rest.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lost, and recovered in a day again!</line>
<line form="verse">This is a double honor, Burgundy;</line>
<line form="verse">Yet heavens have glory for this victory!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Warlike and martial Talbot, Burgundy</line>
<line form="verse">Enshrines thee in his heart, and there erects</line>
<line form="verse">Thy noble deeds as valor&#8217;s monuments.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, gentle Duke. But where is Pucelle now?</line>
<line form="verse">I think her old familiar is asleep.</line>
<line form="verse">Now where&#8217;s the Bastard&#8217;s braves, and Charles his glikes?</line>
<line form="verse">What, all amort? Roan hangs her head for grief</line>
<line form="verse">That such a valiant company are fled.</line>
<line form="verse">Now will we take some order in the town,</line>
<line form="verse">Placing therein some expert officers,</line>
<line form="verse">And then depart to Paris to the King,</line>
<line form="verse">For there young Henry with his nobles lie.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What wills Lord Talbot pleaseth Burgundy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But yet before we go, let&#8217;s not forget</line>
<line form="verse">The noble Duke of Bedford late deceas&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">But see his exequies fulfill&#8217;d in Roan.</line>
<line form="verse">A braver soldier never couched lance,</line>
<line form="verse">A gentler heart did never sway in court;</line>
<line form="verse">But kings and mightiest potentates must die,</line>
<line form="verse">For that&#8217;s the end of human misery.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. The plains near Rouen.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Charles, Bastard, Alanson, Pucelle, Duke of Burgundy)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Joan convinces the French lords to continue in their faith to her. They all agree, pledging to honor her forever. She plans to convinces the duke of Burgundy to abandon the English and join them, and calls him over to a parley as he passes on his way to Paris. She argues with him on the basis of his being French by birth, and he yields, uncertain whether he has been convinced by logic or bewitched.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Bastard, Alanson, Pucelle, and forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dismay not, princes, at this accident,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor grieve that Roan is so recovered:</line>
<line form="verse">Care is no cure, but rather corrosive,</line>
<line form="verse">For things that are not to be remedied.</line>
<line form="verse">Let frantic Talbot triumph for a while,</line>
<line form="verse">And like a peacock sweep along his tail;</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll pull his plumes and take away his train,</line>
<line form="verse">If Dauphin and the rest will be but rul&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We have been guided by thee hitherto,</line>
<line form="verse">And of thy cunning had no diffidence;</line>
<line form="verse">One sudden foil shall never breed distrust.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Search out thy wit for secret policies,</line>
<line form="verse">And we will make thee famous through the world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll set thy statue in some holy place,</line>
<line form="verse">And have thee reverenc&#8217;d like a blessed saint.</line>
<line form="verse">Employ thee then, sweet virgin, for our good.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then thus it must be, this doth Joan devise:</line>
<line form="verse">By fair persuasions, mix&#8217;d with sug&#8217;red words,</line>
<line form="verse">We will entice the Duke of Burgundy</line>
<line form="verse">To leave the Talbot and to follow us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, marry, sweeting, if we could do that,</line>
<line form="verse">France were no place for Henry&#8217;s warriors,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor should that nation boast it so with us,</line>
<line form="verse">But be extirped from our provinces.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Forever should they be expuls&#8217;d from France,</line>
<line form="verse">And not have title of an earldom here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your honors shall perceive how I will work</line>
<line form="verse">To bring this matter to the wished end.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Drum sounds afar off.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hark, by the sound of drum you may perceive</line>
<line form="verse">Their powers are marching unto Paris-ward.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Here sound an English march.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">There goes the Talbot, with his colors spread,</line>
<line form="verse">And all the troops of English after him.</line>

<stagedir type="action">French march.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now in the rearward comes the Duke and his.</line>
<line form="verse">Fortune in favor makes him lag behind.</line>
<line form="verse">Summon a parley, we will talk with him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Trumpets sound a parley.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Duke of Burgundy and forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A parley with the Duke of Burgundy!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who craves a parley with the Burgundy?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The princely Charles of France, thy countryman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What say&#8217;st thou, Charles? For I am marching hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak, Pucelle, and enchant him with thy words.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Brave Burgundy, undoubted hope of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Stay, let thy humble handmaid speak to thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak on, but be not over-tedious.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Look on thy country, look on fertile France,</line>
<line form="verse">And see the cities and the towns defac&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">By wasting ruin of the cruel foe.</line>
<line form="verse">As looks the mother on her lowly babe</line>
<line form="verse">When death doth close his tender-dying eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">See, see the pining malady of France!</line>
<line form="verse">Behold the wounds, the most unnatural wounds,</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou thyself hast given her woeful breast.</line>
<line form="verse">O, turn the edged sword another way,</line>
<line form="verse">Strike those that hurt, and hurt not those that help.</line>
<line form="verse">One drop of blood drawn from thy country&#8217;s bosom</line>
<line form="verse">Should grieve thee more than streams of foreign gore.</line>
<line form="verse">Return thee therefore with a flood of tears,</line>
<line form="verse">And wash away thy country&#8217;s stained spots.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Either she hath bewitch&#8217;d me with her words,</line>
<line form="verse">Or nature makes me suddenly relent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Besides, all French and France exclaims on thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Doubting thy birth and lawful progeny.</line>
<line form="verse">Who join&#8217;st thou with, but with a lordly nation</line>
<line form="verse">That will not trust thee but for profit&#8217;s sake?</line>
<line form="verse">When Talbot hath set footing once in France</line>
<line form="verse">And fashion&#8217;d thee that instrument of ill,</line>
<line form="verse">Who then but English Henry will be lord,</line>
<line form="verse">And thou be thrust out like a fugitive?</line>
<line form="verse">Call we to mind, and mark but this for proof:</line>
<line form="verse">Was not the Duke of Orleance thy foe?</line>
<line form="verse">And was he not in England prisoner?</line>
<line form="verse">But when they heard he was thine enemy,</line>
<line form="verse">They set him free without his ransom paid,</line>
<line form="verse">In spite of Burgundy and all his friends.</line>
<line form="verse">See then, thou fight&#8217;st against thy countrymen</line>
<line form="verse">And join&#8217;st with them will be thy slaughter-men.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, come, return; return, thou wandering lord!</line>
<line form="verse">Charles and the rest will take thee in their arms.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I am vanquished. These haughty words of hers</line>
<line form="verse">Have batt&#8217;red me like roaring cannon-shot,</line>
<line form="verse">And made me almost yield upon my knees.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Forgive me, country, and sweet countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">And, lords, accept this hearty kind embrace.</line>
<line form="verse">My forces and my power of men are yours.</line>
<line form="verse">So farewell, Talbot, I&#8217;ll no longer trust thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Done like a Frenchman&#8212;turn and turn again!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, brave Duke, thy friendship makes us fresh.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And doth beget new courage in our breasts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pucelle hath bravely play&#8217;d her part in this,</line>
<line form="verse">And doth deserve a coronet of gold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now let us on, my lords, and join our powers,</line>
<line form="verse">And seek how we may prejudice the foe.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Paris. A room in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King, Gloucester, Winchester, Richard Plantagenet/Duke of York, Suffolk, Somerset, Warwick, Exeter, Vernon, Basset, Soldiers, Talbot)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Talbot pays his duties to the King, who as a reward for his valor and successes creates him Earl of Shrewsbury. Vernon and Basset, wearing a white and a red rose respectively, quarrel over their difference in opinion.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the King, Gloucester, Winchester, Richard Plantagenet, now Duke of York, Suffolk, Somerset, Warwick, Exeter, Vernon, Basset, and others. To them, with his Soldiers, Talbot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious prince, and honorable peers,</line>
<line form="verse">Hearing of your arrival in this realm,</line>
<line form="verse">I have a while given truce unto my wars,</line>
<line form="verse">To do my duty to my sovereign;</line>
<line form="verse">In sign whereof, this arm, that hath reclaim&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To your obedience fifty fortresses,</line>
<line form="verse">Twelve cities, and seven walled towns of strength,</line>
<line form="verse">Beside five hundred prisoners of esteem,</line>
<line form="verse">Lets fall his sword before your Highness&#8217; feet,</line>
<line form="verse">And with submissive loyalty of heart</line>
<line form="verse">Ascribes the glory of his conquest got</line>
<line form="verse">First to my God and next unto your Grace.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Kneels.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is this the Lord Talbot, uncle Gloucester,</line>
<line form="verse">That hath so long been resident in France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, if it please your Majesty, my liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, brave captain and victorious lord!</line>
<line form="verse">When I was young (as yet I am not old),</line>
<line form="verse">I do remember how my father said</line>
<line form="verse">A stouter champion never handled sword.</line>
<line form="verse">Long since we were resolved of your truth,</line>
<line form="verse">Your faithful service, and your toil in war;</line>
<line form="verse">Yet never have you tasted our reward,</line>
<line form="verse">Or been reguerdon&#8217;d with so much as thanks,</line>
<line form="verse">Because till now we never saw your face.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore stand up, and for these good deserts</line>
<line form="verse">We here create you Earl of Shrewsbury,</line>
<line form="verse">And in our coronation take your place.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Sennet. Flourish. Exeunt. Manent Vernon and Basset.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, sir, to you, that were so hot at sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Disgracing of these colors that I wear</line>
<line form="verse">In honor of my noble Lord of York,</line>
<line form="verse">Dar&#8217;st thou maintain the former words thou spak&#8217;st?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, sir, as well as you dare patronage</line>
<line form="verse">The envious barking of your saucy tongue</line>
<line form="verse">Against my lord the Duke of Somerset.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sirrah, thy lord I honor as he is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, what is he? As good a man as York.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hark ye; not so; in witness, take ye that.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Strikes him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Villain, thou knowest the law of arms is such</line>
<line form="verse">That whoso draws a sword, &#8217;tis present death,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else this blow should broach thy dearest blood.</line>
<line form="verse">But I&#8217;ll unto his Majesty, and crave</line>
<line form="verse">I may have liberty to venge this wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">When thou shalt see I&#8217;ll meet thee to thy cost.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, miscreant, I&#8217;ll be there as soon as you,</line>
<line form="verse">And after meet you, sooner than you would.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Paris. A hall of state.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King, Gloucester, Winchester, York, Suffolk, Somerset, Warwick, Talbot, Governor of Paris, Exeter, Falstaff, Vernon, Basset)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Henry is crowned King of France, and the Mayor of Paris is bound on oath to elect no other king. Falstolfe, entering with a letter from the Duke of Burgundy, is stripped of his Order of the Garter by Talbot for his desertion, and is banished by the King. The letter from Burgundy informs the English that he has switched his allegiance, and Talbot is sent to deal with him. Vernon and Basset plead their quarrel before the King, supported by York and Somerset, each swearing that the other began the fight. The King begs for peace, but the quarrel grows until York challenges Somerset to fight. Incensed, Gloucester scolds them all for disturbing the royal council with such a little matter. King Henry comments on how foolish it would be to create dissention over a rose, and puts on a red one, insisting it does not mean he tends more towards Somerset than York. He orders the two of them to unite their forces in the fight in France. Richard is not pleased that the King took up a red rose, but keeps his mouth shut as he sees the King meant no malice. Exeter is worried at Richard&#8217;s temper and where it may lead.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King, Gloucester, Winchester, York, Suffolk, Somerset, Warwick, Talbot, and Governor of Paris, Exeter, and others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Bishop, set the crown upon his head.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God save King Henry, of that name the sixt!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, Governor of Paris, take your oath:</line>

<stagedir type="action">Governor kneels.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">That you elect no other king but him;</line>
<line form="verse">Esteem none friends but such as are his friends,</line>
<line form="verse">And none your foes but such as shall pretend</line>
<line form="verse">Malicious practices against his state.</line>
<line form="verse">This shall ye do, so help you righteous God!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Governor and Train.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Falstaff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My gracious sovereign, as I rode from Callice,</line>
<line form="verse">To haste unto your coronation,</line>
<line form="verse">A letter was deliver&#8217;d to my hands,</line>
<line form="verse">Writ to your Grace from th&#8217; Duke of Burgundy.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Presents it.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shame to the Duke of Burgundy and thee!</line>
<line form="verse">I vow&#8217;d, base knight, when I did meet thee next,</line>
<line form="verse">To tear the Garter from thy craven&#8217;s leg,</line>

<stagedir type="action">Plucking it off.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Which I have done, because (unworthily)</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wast installed in that high degree.</line>
<line form="verse">Pardon me, princely Henry, and the rest.</line>
<line form="verse">This dastard, at the battle of Poictiers,</line>
<line form="verse">When (but in all) I was six thousand strong</line>
<line form="verse">And that the French were almost ten to one,</line>
<line form="verse">Before we met, or that a stroke was given,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a trusty squire did run away;</line>
<line form="verse">In which assault we lost twelve hundred men;</line>
<line form="verse">Myself and divers gentlemen beside</line>
<line form="verse">Were there surpris&#8217;d and taken prisoners.</line>
<line form="verse">Then judge, great lords, if I have done amiss;</line>
<line form="verse">Or whether that such cowards ought to wear</line>
<line form="verse">This ornament of knighthood, yea or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To say the truth, this fact was infamous</line>
<line form="verse">And ill beseeming any common man,</line>
<line form="verse">Much more a knight, a captain, and a leader.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When first this order was ordain&#8217;d, my lords,</line>
<line form="verse">Knights of the Garter were of noble birth,</line>
<line form="verse">Valiant and virtuous, full of haughty courage,</line>
<line form="verse">Such as were grown to credit by the wars;</line>
<line form="verse">Not fearing death, nor shrinking for distress,</line>
<line form="verse">But always resolute in most extremes.</line>
<line form="verse">He then, that is not furnish&#8217;d in this sort,</line>
<line form="verse">Doth but usurp the sacred name of knight,</line>
<line form="verse">Profaning this most honorable order,</line>
<line form="verse">And should (if I were worthy to be judge)</line>
<line form="verse">Be quite degraded, like a hedge-born swain</line>
<line form="verse">That doth presume to boast of gentle blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stain to thy countrymen, thou hear&#8217;st thy doom!</line>
<line form="verse">Be packing therefore, thou that wast a knight;</line>
<line form="verse">Henceforth we banish thee, on pain of death.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Falstaff.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And now, Lord Protector, view the letter</line>
<line form="verse">Sent from our uncle Duke of Burgundy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What means his Grace, that he hath chang&#8217;d his style?</line>
<line form="verse">No more but plain and bluntly &#8220;To the King&#8221;?</line>
<line form="verse">Hath he forgot he is his sovereign?</line>
<line form="verse">Or doth this churlish superscription</line>
<line form="verse">Pretend some alteration in good will?</line>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s here?</line>

<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;I have, upon especial cause,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Mov&#8217;d with compassion of my country&#8217;s wrack,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Together with the pitiful complaints</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Of such as your oppression feeds upon,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Forsaken your pernicious faction</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And join&#8217;d with Charles, the rightful King of France.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">O monstrous treachery! Can this be so?</line>
<line form="verse">That in alliance, amity, and oaths,</line>
<line form="verse">There should be found such false dissembling guile?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Doth my uncle Burgundy revolt?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He doth, my lord, and is become your foe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is that the worst this letter doth contain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is the worst, and all, my lord, he writes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then Lord Talbot there shall talk with him,</line>
<line form="verse">And give him chastisement for this abuse.</line>
<line form="verse">How say you, my lord? Are you not content?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content, my liege? Yes. But that I am prevented,</line>
<line form="verse">I should have begg&#8217;d I might have been employ&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then gather strength and march unto him straight.</line>
<line form="verse">Let him perceive how ill we brook his treason,</line>
<line form="verse">And what offense it is to flout his friends.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I go, my lord, in heart desiring still</line>
<line form="verse">You may behold confusion of your foes.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Vernon and Basset.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Grant me the combat, gracious sovereign.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And me, my lord, grant me the combat too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is my servant, hear him, noble prince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And this is mine, sweet Henry, favor him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be patient, lords, and give them leave to speak.</line>
<line form="verse">Say, gentlemen, what makes you thus exclaim?</line>
<line form="verse">And wherefore crave you combat? Or with whom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With him, my lord, for he hath done me wrong.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I with him, for he hath done me wrong.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is that wrong whereof you both complain?</line>
<line form="verse">First let me know, and then I&#8217;ll answer you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Crossing the sea from England into France,</line>
<line form="verse">This fellow here, with envious carping tongue,</line>
<line form="verse">Upbraided me about the rose I wear,</line>
<line form="verse">Saying the sanguine color of the leaves</line>
<line form="verse">Did represent my master&#8217;s blushing cheeks,</line>
<line form="verse">When stubbornly he did repugn the truth</line>
<line form="verse">About a certain question in the law</line>
<line form="verse">Argu&#8217;d betwixt the Duke of York and him;</line>
<line form="verse">With other vile and ignominious terms:</line>
<line form="verse">In confutation of which rude reproach,</line>
<line form="verse">And in defense of my lord&#8217;s worthiness,</line>
<line form="verse">I crave the benefit of law of arms.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And that is my petition, noble lord.</line>
<line form="verse">For though he seem with forged quaint conceit</line>
<line form="verse">To set a gloss upon his bold intent,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet know, my lord, I was provok&#8217;d by him,</line>
<line form="verse">And he first took exceptions at this badge,</line>
<line form="verse">Pronouncing that the paleness of this flower</line>
<line form="verse">Bewray&#8217;d the faintness of my master&#8217;s heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Will not this malice, Somerset, be left?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your private grudge, my Lord of York, will out,</line>
<line form="verse">Though ne&#8217;er so cunningly you smother it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Lord, what madness rules in brain-sick men,</line>
<line form="verse">When for so slight and frivolous a cause</line>
<line form="verse">Such factious emulations shall arise!</line>
<line form="verse">Good cousins both, of York and Somerset,</line>
<line form="verse">Quiet yourselves, I pray, and be at peace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let this dissension first be tried by fight,</line>
<line form="verse">And then your Highness shall command a peace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The quarrel toucheth none but us alone,</line>
<line form="verse">Betwixt ourselves let us decide it then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is my pledge, accept it, Somerset.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, let it rest where it began at first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Confirm it so, mine honorable lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Confirm it so? Confounded be your strife,</line>
<line form="verse">And perish ye, with your audacious prate!</line>
<line form="verse">Presumptuous vassals, are you not asham&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With this immodest clamorous outrage</line>
<line form="verse">To trouble and disturb the King and us?</line>
<line form="verse">And you, my lords, methinks you do not well</line>
<line form="verse">To bear with their perverse objections;</line>
<line form="verse">Much less to take occasion from their mouths</line>
<line form="verse">To raise a mutiny betwixt yourselves.</line>
<line form="verse">Let me persuade you take a better course.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It grieves his Highness. Good my lords, be friends.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come hither, you that would be combatants:</line>
<line form="verse">Henceforth I charge you, as you love our favor,</line>
<line form="verse">Quite to forget this quarrel, and the cause.</line>
<line form="verse">And you, my lords: remember where we are&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">In France, amongst a fickle, wavering nation.</line>
<line form="verse">If they perceive dissension in our looks,</line>
<line form="verse">And that within ourselves we disagree,</line>
<line form="verse">How will their grudging stomachs be provok&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To willful disobedience, and rebel!</line>
<line form="verse">Beside, what infamy will there arise,</line>
<line form="verse">When foreign princes shall be certified</line>
<line form="verse">That for a toy, a thing of no regard,</line>
<line form="verse">King Henry&#8217;s peers and chief nobility</line>
<line form="verse">Destroy&#8217;d themselves, and lost the realm of France!</line>
<line form="verse">O, think upon the conquest of my father,</line>
<line form="verse">My tender years, and let us not forgo</line>
<line form="verse">That for a trifle that was bought with blood!</line>
<line form="verse">Let me be umpeer in this doubtful strife.</line>
<line form="verse">I see no reason, if I wear this rose,</line>

<stagedir type="action">Putting on a red rose.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">That any one should therefore be suspicious</line>
<line form="verse">I more incline to Somerset than York:</line>
<line form="verse">Both are my kinsmen, and I love them both.</line>
<line form="verse">As well they may upbraid me with my crown,</line>
<line form="verse">Because, forsooth, the King of Scots is crown&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">But your discretions better can persuade</line>
<line form="verse">Than I am able to instruct or teach;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore, as we hither came in peace,</line>
<line form="verse">So let us still continue peace, and love.</line>
<line form="verse">Cousin of York, we institute your Grace</line>
<line form="verse">To be our regent in these parts of France;</line>
<line form="verse">And, good my Lord of Somerset, unite</line>
<line form="verse">Your troops of horsemen with his bands of foot,</line>
<line form="verse">And like true subjects, sons of your progenitors,</line>
<line form="verse">Go cheerfully together and digest</line>
<line form="verse">Your angry choler on your enemies.</line>
<line form="verse">Ourself, my Lord Protector, and the rest,</line>
<line form="verse">After some respite, will return to Callice;</line>
<line form="verse">From thence to England, where I hope ere long</line>
<line form="verse">To be presented, by your victories,</line>
<line form="verse">With Charles, Alanson, and that traitorous rout.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Flourish. Exeunt. Manent York, Warwick, Exeter, Vernon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Lord of York, I promise you, the King</line>
<line form="verse">Prettily, methought, did play the orator.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so he did, but yet I like it not,</line>
<line form="verse">In that he wears the badge of Somerset.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tush, that was but his fancy, blame him not.</line>
<line form="verse">I dare presume, sweet prince, he thought no harm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And if I wist he did&#8212;but let it rest,</line>
<line form="verse">Other affairs must now be managed.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt. Manet Exeter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well didst thou, Richard, to suppress thy voice,</line>
<line form="verse">For had the passions of thy heart burst out,</line>
<line form="verse">I fear we should have seen decipher&#8217;d there</line>
<line form="verse">More rancorous spite, more furious raging broils,</line>
<line form="verse">Than yet can be imagin&#8217;d or suppos&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">But howsoe&#8217;er, no simple man that sees</line>
<line form="verse">This jarring discord of nobility,</line>
<line form="verse">This shouldering of each other in the court,</line>
<line form="verse">This factious bandying of their favorites,</line>
<line form="verse">But that it doth presage some ill event.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis much, when sceptres are in children&#8217;s hands;</line>
<line form="verse">But more, when envy breeds unkind division:</line>
<line form="verse">There comes the ruin, there begins confusion.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Bourdeaux.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, Talbot&#8217;s Trumpter, General)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Talbot calls on the commander of Bordeaux to surrender, but the latter refuses, informing the English commander that he has fallen into a trap and is doomed: Bordeaux is well-defended and the Charles is approaching with a strong army, and the Frenchmen have all pledged to kill Tablot. Talbot realizes the danger, but rallies his troops all the same, urging them to sell their lives dearly.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Talbot with Trump and Drum before Burdeaux.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go to the gates of Burdeaux, trumpeter,</line>
<line form="verse">Summon their general unto the wall.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Trumpet sounds. Enter General and others aloft.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">English John Talbot, captains, calls you forth,</line>
<line form="verse">Servant in arms to Harry King of England,</line>
<line form="verse">And thus he would: Open your city-gates,</line>
<line form="verse">Be humble to us, call my sovereign yours,</line>
<line form="verse">And do him homage as obedient subjects,</line>
<line form="verse">And I&#8217;ll withdraw me and my bloody power.</line>
<line form="verse">But if you frown upon this proffer&#8217;d peace,</line>
<line form="verse">You tempt the fury of my three attendants,</line>
<line form="verse">Lean famine, quartering steel, and climbing fire,</line>
<line form="verse">Who in a moment even with the earth</line>
<line form="verse">Shall lay your stately and air-braving towers,</line>
<line form="verse">If you forsake the offer of their love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou ominous and fearful owl of death,</line>
<line form="verse">Our nation&#8217;s terror and their bloody scourge!</line>
<line form="verse">The period of thy tyranny approacheth.</line>
<line form="verse">On us thou canst not enter but by death;</line>
<line form="verse">For I protest we are well fortified,</line>
<line form="verse">And strong enough to issue out and fight.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou retire, the Dauphin, well appointed,</line>
<line form="verse">Stands with the snares of war to tangle thee.</line>
<line form="verse">On either hand thee there are squadrons pitch&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">To wall thee from the liberty of flight;</line>
<line form="verse">And no way canst thou turn thee for redress,</line>
<line form="verse">But death doth front thee with apparent spoil,</line>
<line form="verse">And pale destruction meets thee in the face.</line>
<line form="verse">Ten thousand French have ta&#8217;en the sacrament</line>
<line form="verse">To rive their dangerous artillery</line>
<line form="verse">Upon no Christian soul but English Talbot.</line>
<line form="verse">Lo, there thou stand&#8217;st, a breathing valiant man,</line>
<line form="verse">Of an invincible unconquer&#8217;d spirit!</line>
<line form="verse">This is the latest glory of thy praise</line>
<line form="verse">That I thy enemy due thee withal;</line>
<line form="verse">For ere the glass, that now begins to run,</line>
<line form="verse">Finish the process of his sandy hour,</line>
<line form="verse">These eyes, that see thee now well colored,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall see thee withered, bloody, pale, and dead.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Drum afar off.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hark, hark, the Dauphin&#8217;s drum, a warning bell,</line>
<line form="verse">Sings heavy music to thy timorous soul,</line>
<line form="verse">And mine shall ring thy dire departure out.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with others above.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He fables not, I hear the enemy.</line>
<line form="verse">Out, some light horsemen, and peruse their wings.</line>
<line form="verse">O negligent and heedless discipline!</line>
<line form="verse">How are we park&#8217;d and bounded in a pale,</line>
<line form="verse">A little herd of England&#8217;s timorous deer,</line>
<line form="verse">Maz&#8217;d with a yelping kennel of French curs!</line>
<line form="verse">If we be English deer, be then in blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Not rascal-like, to fall down with a pinch,</line>
<line form="verse">But rather, moody-mad; and, desperate stags,</line>
<line form="verse">Turn on the bloody hounds with heads of steel,</line>
<line form="verse">And make the cowards stand aloof at bay.</line>
<line form="verse">Sell every man his life as dear as mine,</line>
<line form="verse">And they shall find dear deer of us, my friends.</line>
<line form="verse">God and Saint George, Talbot and England&#8217;s right,</line>
<line form="verse">Prosper our colors in this dangerous fight!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Plains in Gascony.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Messenger, York, Soldiers, Sir William Lucy)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>York learns that all the French armies are converging on Bordeaux to fight Talbot, and curses that Somerset has not sent him the reinforcements required so that he could help. Sir William Lucy arrives from Talbot begging aid, but York insists that he cannot help, casting all the blame on Somerset. Lucy is disgusted at how private quarrels are ruining the war effort.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Messenger that meets York. Enter York with Trumpet and many Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Are not the speedy scouts return&#8217;d again</line>
<line form="verse">That dogg&#8217;d the mighty army of the Dauphin?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>5. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They are return&#8217;d, my lord, and give it out</line>
<line form="verse">That he is march&#8217;d to Burdeaux with his power</line>
<line form="verse">To fight with Talbot. As he march&#8217;d along,</line>
<line form="verse">By your espials were discovered</line>
<line form="verse">Two mightier troops than that the Dauphin led,</line>
<line form="verse">Which join&#8217;d with him and made their march for Burdeaux.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A plague upon that villain Somerset,</line>
<line form="verse">That thus delays my promised supply</line>
<line form="verse">Of horsemen, that were levied for this siege!</line>
<line form="verse">Renowned Talbot doth expect my aid,</line>
<line form="verse">And I am louted by a traitor villain</line>
<line form="verse">And cannot help the noble chevalier.</line>
<line form="verse">God comfort him in this necessity!</line>
<line form="verse">If he miscarry, farewell wars in France!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter another Messenger, Sir William Lucy.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou princely leader of our English strength,</line>
<line form="verse">Never so needful on the earth of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Spur to the rescue of the noble Talbot,</line>
<line form="verse">Who now is girdled with a waist of iron</line>
<line form="verse">And hemm&#8217;d about with grim destruction.</line>
<line form="verse">To Burdeaux, warlike Duke! To Burdeaux, York!</line>
<line form="verse">Else farewell Talbot, France, and England&#8217;s honor!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O God, that Somerset, who in proud heart</line>
<line form="verse">Doth stop my cornets, were in Talbot&#8217;s place!</line>
<line form="verse">So should we save a valiant gentleman</line>
<line form="verse">By forfeiting a traitor and a coward.</line>
<line form="verse">Mad ire and wrathful fury makes me weep,</line>
<line form="verse">That thus we die, while remiss traitors sleep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, send some succor to the distress&#8217;d lord!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He dies, we lose; I break my warlike word;</line>
<line form="verse">We mourn, France smiles; we lose, they daily get;</line>
<line form="verse">All long of this vile traitor Somerset.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then God take mercy on brave Talbot&#8217;s soul,</line>
<line form="verse">And on his son young John, who two hours since</line>
<line form="verse">I met in travel toward his warlike father!</line>
<line form="verse">This seven years did not Talbot see his son,</line>
<line form="verse">And now they meet where both their lives are done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alas, what joy shall noble Talbot have</line>
<line form="verse">To bid his young son welcome to his grave?</line>
<line form="verse">Away! Vexation almost stops my breath,</line>
<line form="verse">That sund&#8217;red friends greet in the hour of death.</line>
<line form="verse">Lucy, farewell, no more my fortune can,</line>
<line form="verse">But curse the cause I cannot aid the man.</line>
<line form="verse">Maine, Blois, Poictiers, and Tours, are won away,</line>
<line form="verse">Long all of Somerset and his delay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with his Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thus while the vulture of sedition</line>
<line form="verse">Feeds in the bosom of such great commanders,</line>
<line form="verse">Sleeping neglection doth betray to loss</line>
<line form="verse">The conquest of our scarce-cold conqueror,</line>
<line form="verse">That ever-living man of memory,</line>
<line form="verse">Henry the Fifth. Whiles they each other cross,</line>
<line form="verse">Lives, honors, lands, and all, hurry to loss.</line> 
</speech>

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Other plains in Gascony.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Somerset, Captain, Sir William Lucy)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Somerset argues that it is too late for him tosend help to Talbot, and that York and the general planned the expedition poorly. Lucy arrives to beg for help; when Somerset blames York, Lucy explodes and shames the Duke, who agrees to send some horsemen to help, but Lucy is convinced they will arrive too late, and that Talbot will die, betrayed by his own countrymen.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Somerset with his army, a Captain of Talbot&#8217;s with him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is too late, I cannot send them now.</line>
<line form="verse">This expedition was by York and Talbot</line>
<line form="verse">Too rashly plotted. All our general force</line>
<line form="verse">Might with a sally of the very town</line>
<line form="verse">Be buckled with. The over-daring Talbot</line>
<line form="verse">Hath sullied all his gloss of former honor</line>
<line form="verse">By this unheedful, desperate, wild adventure.</line>
<line form="verse">York set him on to fight and die in shame,</line>
<line form="verse">That, Talbot dead, great York might bear the name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here is Sir William Lucy, who with me</line>
<line form="verse">Set from our o&#8217;ermatch&#8217;d forces forth for aid.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, Sir William, whither were you sent?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whither, my lord? From bought and sold Lord Talbot,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, ring&#8217;d about with bold adversity,</line>
<line form="verse">Cries out for noble York and Somerset</line>
<line form="verse">To beat assailing death from his weak legions;</line>
<line form="verse">And whiles the honorable captain there</line>
<line form="verse">Drops bloody sweat from his war-wearied limbs,</line>
<line form="verse">And, in advantage ling&#8217;ring, looks for rescue,</line>
<line form="verse">You, his false hopes, the trust of England&#8217;s honor,</line>
<line form="verse">Keep off aloof with worthless emulation.</line>
<line form="verse">Let not your private discord keep away</line>
<line form="verse">The levied succors that should lend him aid,</line>
<line form="verse">While he, renowned noble gentleman,</line>
<line form="verse">Yield up his life unto a world of odds.</line>
<line form="verse">Orleance the Bastard, Charles, Burgundy,</line>
<line form="verse">Alanson, Reignier, compass him about,</line>
<line form="verse">And Talbot perisheth by your default.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">York set him on, York should have sent him aid.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And York as fast upon your Grace exclaims,</line>
<line form="verse">Swearing that you withhold his levied host,</line>
<line form="verse">Collected for this expedition.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">York lies; he might have sent, and had the horse.</line>
<line form="verse">I owe him little duty, and less love,</line>
<line form="verse">And take foul scorn to fawn on him by sending.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The fraud of England, not the force of France,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath now entrapp&#8217;d the noble-minded Talbot:</line>
<line form="verse">Never to England shall he bear his life,</line>
<line form="verse">But dies, betray&#8217;d to fortune by your strife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come go, I will dispatch the horsemen straight;</line>
<line form="verse">Within six hours they will be at his aid.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Too late comes rescue, he is ta&#8217;en or slain;</line>
<line form="verse">For fly he could not, if he would have fled;</line>
<line form="verse">And fly would Talbot never, though he might.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If he be dead, brave Talbot, then <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His fame lives in the world, his shame in you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>English camp near Bourdeaux.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, John)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>John Talbot, who has galloped to join his father when he heard of the danger the older man was in, refuses to flee, and instead insists that Talbot himself be the one to go. Both too proud to leave, though anxious to save the other, they in the end both remain.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Talbot and his son, John.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O young John Talbot, I did send for thee</line>
<line form="verse">To tutor thee in stratagems of war,</line>
<line form="verse">That Talbot&#8217;s name might be in thee reviv&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">When sapless age and weak unable limbs</line>
<line form="verse">Should bring thy father to his drooping chair.</line>
<line form="verse">But O malignant and ill-boding stars!</line>
<line form="verse">Now thou art come unto a feast of death,</line>
<line form="verse">A terrible and unavoided danger;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, dear boy, mount on my swiftest horse,</line>
<line form="verse">And I&#8217;ll direct thee how thou shalt escape</line>
<line form="verse">By sudden flight. Come, dally not, be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is my name Talbot? And am I your son?</line>
<line form="verse">And shall I fly? O, if you love my mother,</line>
<line form="verse">Dishonor not her honorable name</line>
<line form="verse">To make a bastard and a slave of me!</line>
<line form="verse">The world will say, he is not Talbot&#8217;s blood,</line>
<line form="verse">That basely fled when noble Talbot stood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fly, to revenge my death, if I be slain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He that flies so will ne&#8217;er return again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If we both stay, we both are sure to die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then let me stay, and, father, do you fly.</line>
<line form="verse">Your loss is great, so your regard should be;</line>
<line form="verse">My worth unknown, no loss is known in me.</line>
<line form="verse">Upon my death the French can little boast;</line>
<line form="verse">In yours they will, in you all hopes are lost.</line>
<line form="verse">Flight cannot stain the honor you have won,</line>
<line form="verse">But mine it will, that no exploit have done.</line>
<line form="verse">You fled for vantage, every one will swear;</line>
<line form="verse">But if I bow, they&#8217;ll say it was for fear.</line>
<line form="verse">There is no hope that ever I will stay,</line>
<line form="verse">If the first hour I shrink and run away.</line>
<line form="verse">Here on my knee I beg mortality,</line>
<line form="verse">Rather than life preserv&#8217;d with infamy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shall all thy mother&#8217;s hopes lie in one tomb?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, rather than I&#8217;ll shame my mother&#8217;s womb.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon my blessing I command thee go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To fight I will, but not to fly the foe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Part of thy father may be sav&#8217;d in thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No part of him but will be shame in me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou never hadst renown, nor canst not lose it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, your renowned name. Shall flight abuse it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thy father&#8217;s charge shall clear thee from that stain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You cannot witness for me, being slain.</line>
<line form="verse">If death be so apparent, then both fly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And leave my followers here to fight and die?</line>
<line form="verse">My age was never tainted with such shame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And shall my youth be guilty of such blame?</line>
<line form="verse">No more can I be severed from your side</line>
<line form="verse">Than can yourself yourself in twain divide.</line>
<line form="verse">Stay, go, do what you will, the like do I;</line>
<line form="verse">For live I will not if my father die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then here I take my leave of thee, fair son,</line>
<line form="verse">Born to eclipse thy life this afternoon.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, side by side, together live and die,</line>
<line form="verse">And soul with soul from France to heaven fly.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A field of battle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, John)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Talbot rescues his son from the French, and again urges him to flee, arguing he has proved his worth and can leave without dishonor, and that he must live to continue the family name. John refuses to risk being considered a coward, and Talbot allows to stay and fight by his side.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Alarum. Excursions, wherein Talbot&#8217;s son, John, is hemm&#8217;d about, and Talbot rescues him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Saint George and victory! Fight, soldiers, fight!</line>
<line form="verse">The Regent hath with Talbot broke his word,</line>
<line form="verse">And left us to the rage of France his sword.</line>
<line form="verse">Where is John Talbot? Pause, and take thy breath;</line>
<line form="verse">I gave thee life, and rescu&#8217;d thee from death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, twice my father, twice am I thy son!</line>
<line form="verse">The life thou gav&#8217;st me first was lost and done,</line>
<line form="verse">Till with thy warlike sword, despite of fate,</line>
<line form="verse">To my determin&#8217;d time thou gav&#8217;st new date.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When from the Dauphin&#8217;s crest thy sword struck fire,</line>
<line form="verse">It warm&#8217;d thy father&#8217;s heart with proud desire</line>
<line form="verse">Of bold-fac&#8217;d victory. Then leaden age,</line>
<line form="verse">Quicken&#8217;d with youthful spleen and warlike rage,</line>
<line form="verse">Beat down Alanson, Orleance, Burgundy,</line>
<line form="verse">And from the pride of Gallia rescued thee.</line>
<line form="verse">The ireful Bastard Orleance, that drew blood</line>
<line form="verse">From thee, my boy, and had the maidenhood</line>
<line form="verse">Of thy first fight, I soon encountered,</line>
<line form="verse">And interchanging blows I quickly shed</line>
<line form="verse">Some of his bastard blood, and in disgrace</line>
<line form="verse">Bespoke him thus: &#8220;Contaminated, base,</line>
<line form="verse">And misbegotten blood I spill of thine,</line>
<line form="verse">Mean and right poor, for that pure blood of mine</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou didst force from Talbot, my brave boy.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Here, purposing the Bastard to destroy,</line>
<line form="verse">Came in strong rescue. Speak, thy father&#8217;s care:</line>
<line form="verse">Art thou not weary, John? How dost thou fare?</line>
<line form="verse">Wilt thou yet leave the battle, boy, and fly,</line>
<line form="verse">Now thou art seal&#8217;d the son of chivalry?</line>
<line form="verse">Fly, to revenge my death when I am dead;</line>
<line form="verse">The help of one stands me in little stead.</line>
<line form="verse">O, too much folly is it, well I wot,</line>
<line form="verse">To hazard all our lives in one small boat!</line>
<line form="verse">If I today die not with Frenchmen&#8217;s rage,</line>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow I shall die with mickle age.</line>
<line form="verse">By me they nothing gain and if I stay,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis but the short&#8217;ning of my life one day.</line>
<line form="verse">In thee thy mother dies, our household&#8217;s name,</line>
<line form="verse">My death&#8217;s revenge, thy youth, and England&#8217;s fame:</line>
<line form="verse">All these, and more, we hazard by thy stay;</line>
<line form="verse">All these are sav&#8217;d if thou wilt fly away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JOHN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The sword of Orleance hath not made me smart;</line>
<line form="verse">These words of yours draw life-blood from my heart.</line>
<line form="verse">On that advantage, bought with such a shame,</line>
<line form="verse">To save a paltry life and slay bright fame,</line>
<line form="verse">Before young Talbot from old Talbot fly</line>
<line form="verse">The coward horse that bears me fall and die!</line>
<line form="verse">And like me to the peasant boys of France,</line>
<line form="verse">To be shame&#8217;s scorn and subject of mischance!</line>
<line form="verse">Surely, by all the glory you have won,</line>
<line form="verse">And if I fly, I am not Talbot&#8217;s son.</line>
<line form="verse">Then talk no more of flight, it is no boot;</line>
<line form="verse">If son to Talbot, die at Talbot&#8217;s foot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then follow thou thy desp&#8217;rate sire of Crete,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou Icarus; thy life to me is sweet.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou wilt fight, fight by thy father&#8217;s side,</line>
<line form="verse">And commendable prov&#8217;d, let&#8217;s die in pride.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="7">
<scenetitle>Scene 7</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Another part of the battlefield.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Talbot, Talbot&#8217;s Servant, Soldiers, John Talbot, Charles, Alanson, Burgundy, Bastard, Pucelle, Lucy, Herald of the French)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Wounded, Talbot searches for his son, who defended his life but then plunged into the thick of the French ranks. John&#8217;s body is carried in, and Talbot laments over it before dying himself. Charles and the French enter, commenting that if York and Somerset had come with their forces, they would have had a harder day. Lucy comes in a parley, hoping to ransom Talbot, only to be told that he is dead. He is told to take the body away. Charles is convinced that all of France is theirs now that Talbot is dead.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Excursions. Enter old Talbot led by his Servant.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where is my other life? Mine own is gone.</line>
<line form="verse">O, where&#8217;s young Talbot? Where is valiant John?</line>
<line form="verse">Triumphant Death, smear&#8217;d with captivity,</line>
<line form="verse">Young Talbot&#8217;s valor makes me smile at thee.</line>
<line form="verse">When he perceiv&#8217;d me shrink and on my knee,</line>
<line form="verse">His bloody sword he brandish&#8217;d over me,</line>
<line form="verse">And like a hungry lion did commence</line>
<line form="verse">Rough deeds of rage and stern impatience;</line>
<line form="verse">But when my angry guardant stood alone,</line>
<line form="verse">Tend&#8217;ring my ruin and assail&#8217;d of none,</line>
<line form="verse">Dizzy-ey&#8217;d fury and great rage of heart</line>
<line form="verse">Suddenly made him from my side to start</line>
<line form="verse">Into the clust&#8217;ring battle of the French;</line>
<line form="verse">And in that sea of blood my boy did drench</line>
<line form="verse">His overmounting spirit; and there died</line>
<line form="verse">My Icarus, my blossom, in his pride.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Soldiers with John Talbot borne.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL. SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O my dear lord, lo where your son is borne!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou antic Death, which laugh&#8217;st us here to scorn,</line>
<line form="verse">Anon, from thy insulting tyranny,</line>
<line form="verse">Coupled in bonds of perpetuity,</line>
<line form="verse">Two Talbots, winged through the lither sky,</line>
<line form="verse">In thy despite shall scape mortality.</line>
<line form="verse">O thou whose wounds become hard-favored Death,</line>
<line form="verse">Speak to thy father ere thou yield thy breath!</line>
<line form="verse">Brave Death by speaking, whether he will or no;</line>
<line form="verse">Imagine him a Frenchman, and thy foe.</line>
<line form="verse">Poor boy, he smiles, methinks, as who should say,</line>
<line form="verse">Had Death been French, then Death had died today.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, come, and lay him in his father&#8217;s arms,</line>
<line form="verse">My spirit can no longer bear these harms.</line>
<line form="verse">Soldiers, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>! I have what I would have,</line>
<line form="verse">Now my old arms are young John Talbot&#8217;s grave.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="TAL.">Dies.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Alanson, Burgundy, Bastard, and Pucelle with forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Had York and Somerset brought rescue in,</line>
<line form="verse">We should have found a bloody day of this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How the young whelp of Talbot&#8217;s, raging wood,</line>
<line form="verse">Did flesh his puny sword in Frenchmen&#8217;s blood!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Once I encount&#8217;red him, and thus I said:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Thou maiden youth, be vanquish&#8217;d by a maid!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">But with a proud majestical high scorn</line>
<line form="verse">He answer&#8217;d thus: &#8220;Young Talbot was not born</line>
<line form="verse">To be the pillage of a giglot wench.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">So rushing in the bowels of the French,</line>
<line form="verse">He left me proudly, as unworthy fight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Doubtless he would have made a noble knight.</line>
<line form="verse">See where he lies inhearsed in the arms</line>
<line form="verse">Of the most bloody nurser of his harms!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAST.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hew them to pieces, hack their bones asunder,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose life was England&#8217;s glory, Gallia&#8217;s wonder.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O no, forbear! For that which we have fled</line>
<line form="verse">During the life, let us not wrong it dead.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lucy attended, Herald of the French preceding.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Herald, conduct me to the Dauphin&#8217;s tent,</line>
<line form="verse">To know who hath obtain&#8217;d the glory of the day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">On what submissive message art thou sent?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Submission, Dauphin? &#8217;Tis a mere French word;</line>
<line form="verse">We English warriors wot not what it means.</line>
<line form="verse">I come to know what prisoners thou hast ta&#8217;en,</line>
<line form="verse">And to survey the bodies of the dead.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For prisoners ask&#8217;st thou? Hell our prison is.</line>
<line form="verse">But tell me whom thou seek&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But where&#8217;s the great Alcides of the field,</line>
<line form="verse">Valiant Lord Talbot, Earl of Shrewsbury,</line>
<line form="verse">Created, for his rare success in arms,</line>
<line form="verse">Great Earl of Washford, Waterford, and Valence,</line>
<line form="verse">Lord Talbot of Goodrig and Urchinfield,</line>
<line form="verse">Lord Strange of Blackmere, Lord Verdon of Alton,</line>
<line form="verse">Lord Cromwell of Wingfield, Lord Furnival of Sheffield,</line>
<line form="verse">The thrice-victorious Lord of Falconbridge,</line>
<line form="verse">Knight of the noble Order of Saint George,</line>
<line form="verse">Worthy Saint Michael, and the Golden Fleece,</line>
<line form="verse">Great marshal to Henry the Sixth</line>
<line form="verse">Of all his wars within the realm of France?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s a silly stately style indeed!</line>
<line form="verse">The Turk, that two and fifty kingdoms hath,</line>
<line form="verse">Writes not so tedious a style as this.</line>
<line form="verse">Him that thou magnifi&#8217;st with all these titles</line>
<line form="verse">Stinking and fly-blown lies here at our feet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is Talbot slain, the Frenchmen&#8217;s only scourge,</line>
<line form="verse">Your kingdom&#8217;s terror and black Nemesis?</line>
<line form="verse">O, were mine eyeballs into bullets turn&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">That I in rage might shoot them at your faces!</line>
<line form="verse">O, that I could but call these dead to life,</line>
<line form="verse">It were enough to fright the realm of France!</line>
<line form="verse">Were but his picture left amongst you here,</line>
<line form="verse">It would amaze the proudest of you all.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me their bodies, that I may bear them hence</line>
<line form="verse">And give them burial as beseems their worth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think this upstart is old Talbot&#8217;s ghost,</line>
<line form="verse">He speaks with such a proud commanding spirit.</line>
<line form="verse">For God&#8217;s sake let him have &#8217;em; to keep them here,</line>
<line form="verse">They would but stink, and putrefy the air.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go take their bodies hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll bear them hence; but from their ashes shall be rear&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">A phoenix that shall make all France afeard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So we be rid of them, do with &#8217;em what thou wilt.</line>
<line form="verse">And now to Paris in this conquering vein,</line>
<line form="verse">All will be ours, now bloody Talbot&#8217;s slain.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. A room in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King, Gloucester, Exeter, Winchester, Ambassadors, Papal Legate)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The King and Gloucester discuss arrangements for a peace treaty with France, by which Henry shall marry the daughter of the Earl of Arminack. Henry fears he is too young to marry, as he much prefers studying to wasting his time with women. Winchester, now a Cardinal, is sent to represent England at the peace negotiations. Winchester takes the Papal Legate aside to pay the bribe money for his new position, and swears that he will never be inferior to Gloucester again.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Sennet. Enter King, Gloucester, and Exeter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have you perus&#8217;d the letters from the Pope,</line>
<line form="verse">The Emperor, and the Earl of Armagnac?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have, my lord, and their intent is this:</line>
<line form="verse">They humbly sue unto your Excellence</line>
<line form="verse">To have a godly peace concluded of</line>
<line form="verse">Between the realms of England and of France.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How doth your Grace affect their motion?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, my good lord, and as the only means</line>
<line form="verse">To stop effusion of our Christian blood,</line>
<line form="verse">And stablish quietness on every side.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, marry, uncle, for I always thought</line>
<line form="verse">It was both impious and unnatural</line>
<line form="verse">That such immanity and bloody strife</line>
<line form="verse">Should reign among professors of one faith.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Beside, my lord, the sooner to effect</line>
<line form="verse">And surer bind this knot of amity,</line>
<line form="verse">The Earl of Armagnac, near knit to Charles,</line>
<line form="verse">A man of great authority in France,</line>
<line form="verse">Proffers his only daughter to your Grace</line>
<line form="verse">In marriage, with a large and sumptuous dowry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Marriage, uncle? Alas, my years are young;</line>
<line form="verse">And fitter is my study and my books</line>
<line form="verse">Than wanton dalliance with a paramour.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet call th&#8217; ambassadors, and as you please,</line>
<line form="verse">So let them have their answers every one.</line>
<line form="verse">I shall be well content with any choice</line>
<line form="verse">Tends to God&#8217;s glory and my country&#8217;s weal.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Winchester in cardinal&#8217;s habit and three Ambassadors, one of them a Papal Legate.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, is my Lord of Winchester install&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And call&#8217;d unto a cardinal&#8217;s degree?</line>
<line form="verse">Then I perceive that will be verified</line>
<line form="verse">Henry the Fifth did sometime prophesy:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;If once he come to be a cardinal,</line>
<line form="verse">He&#8217;ll make his cap co-equal with the crown.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lords ambassadors, your several suits</line>
<line form="verse">Have been consider&#8217;d and debated on.</line>
<line form="verse">Your purpose is both good and reasonable;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore are we certainly resolv&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To draw conditions of a friendly peace,</line>
<line form="verse">Which by my Lord of Winchester we mean</line>
<line form="verse">Shall be transported presently to France.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To the Ambassador from Armagnac.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And for the proffer of my lord your master,</line>
<line form="verse">I have inform&#8217;d his Highness so at large,</line>
<line form="verse">As liking of the lady&#8217;s virtuous gifts,</line>
<line form="verse">Her beauty, and the value of her dower,</line>
<line form="verse">He doth intend she shall be England&#8217;s queen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In argument and proof of which contract,</line>
<line form="verse">Bear her this jewel, pledge of my affection.</line>
<line form="verse">And so, my Lord Protector, see them guarded</line>
<line form="verse">And safely brought to Dover, wherein shipp&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Commit them to the fortune of the sea.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt all but Winchester and Legate.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, my lord legate, you shall first receive</line>
<line form="verse">The sum of money which I promised</line>
<line form="verse">Should be delivered to his Holiness</line>
<line form="verse">For clothing me in these grave ornaments.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will attend upon your lordship&#8217;s leisure.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>WIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now Winchester will not submit, I trow,</line>
<line form="verse">Or be inferior to the proudest peer.</line>
<line form="verse">Humphrey of Gloucester, thou shalt well perceive</line>
<line form="verse">That neither in birth, or for authority,</line>
<line form="verse">The Bishop will be overborne by thee.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll either make thee stoop and bend thy knee,</line>
<line form="verse">Or sack this country with a mutiny.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Plains in Anjou.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Charles, Burgundy, Alanson, Bastard, Reignier, Joan de Pucelle, Scout)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Charles, hearing that the Parisians are rebelling against the English, prepares to march to Paris. A scout informs him that the two English armies have combined and are moving on the French. Though unprepared, the French prepare to fight.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Burgundy, Alanson, Bastard, Reignier, and Joan de Pucelle, with forces.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These news, my lords, may cheer our drooping spirits:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis said the stout Parisians do revolt,</line>
<line form="verse">And turn again unto the warlike French.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then march to Paris, royal Charles of France,</line>
<line form="verse">And keep not back your powers in dalliance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peace be amongst them if they turn to us,</line>
<line form="verse">Else ruin combat with their palaces!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Scout.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SCOUT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Success unto our valiant general,</line>
<line form="verse">And happiness to his accomplices!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What tidings send our scouts? I prithee speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SCOUT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The English army, that divided was</line>
<line form="verse">Into two parties, is now conjoin&#8217;d in one,</line>
<line form="verse">And means to give you battle presently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Somewhat too sudden, sirs, the warning is,</line>
<line form="verse">But we will presently provide for them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I trust the ghost of Talbot is not there.</line>
<line form="verse">Now he is gone, my lord, you need not fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of all base passions, fear is most accurs&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Command the conquest, Charles, it shall be thine,</line>
<line form="verse">Let Henry fret, and all the world repine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then on, my lords, and France be fortunate!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>France. Before Angiers.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Joan de Pucelle, Fiends, Burgundy, York, Suffolk, Margaret, Reignier)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Joan la Pucelle, seeing the French fleeing before the English, invokes fiends to help her, but despite all her offers they refuse to speak to her, and she realizes that she is done for. York captures her and walks her off to the stake. Suffolk comes in, having captured Margaret, the daughter of the French leader Reignier. Besotted by his captive, he is at a loss what to do, as he is already married but cannot bring himself to give her up. He comes up instead with the plan of marrying her to the King, though he knows the other nobles will object as she has neither great political connections nor any money. She assents to this proposal, and he acquires the consent of her father on condition that he be allowed to rule over his counties of Anjou and Maine in peace. Suffolk steals a kiss from Margaret as he leaves, still wishing she could be for himself, but preparing to sing her praises to the King.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Excursions. Enter Joan de Pucelle.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Regent conquers, and the Frenchmen fly.</line>
<line form="verse">Now help, ye charming spells and periapts,</line>
<line form="verse">And ye choice spirits that admonish me</line>
<line form="verse">And give me signs of future accidents.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Thunder.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">You speedy helpers, that are substitutes</line>
<line form="verse">Under the lordly Monarch of the North,</line>
<line form="verse">Appear, and aid me in this enterprise.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Fiends.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">This speedy and quick appearance argues proof</line>
<line form="verse">Of your accustom&#8217;d diligence to me.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, ye familiar spirits, that are cull&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Out of the powerful regions under earth,</line>
<line form="verse">Help me this once, that France may get the field.</line>

<stagedir type="action">They walk, and speak not.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O, hold me not with silence over-long!</line>
<line form="verse">Where I was wont to feed you with my blood,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll lop a member off and give it you</line>
<line form="verse">In earnest of a further benefit,</line>
<line form="verse">So you do condescend to help me now.</line>

<stagedir type="action">They hang their heads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">No hope to have redress? My body shall</line>
<line form="verse">Pay recompense, if you will grant my suit.</line>

<stagedir type="action">They shake their heads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Cannot my body nor blood-sacrifice</line>
<line form="verse">Entreat you to your wonted furtherance?</line>
<line form="verse">Then take my soul&#8212;my body, soul, and all,</line>
<line form="verse">Before that England give the French the foil.</line>

<stagedir type="action">They depart.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">See, they forsake me! Now the time is come</line>
<line form="verse">That France must vail her lofty-plumed crest</line>
<line form="verse">And let her head fall into England&#8217;s lap.</line>
<line form="verse">My ancient incantations are too weak,</line>
<line form="verse">And hell too strong for me to buckle with:</line>
<line form="verse">Now, France, thy glory droopeth to the dust.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="fight">Excursions. Burgundy and York enter and fight hand to hand.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="action">French fly. Pucelle is brought in captive.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Damsel of France, I think I have you fast:</line>
<line form="verse">Unchain your spirits now with spelling charms,</line>
<line form="verse">And try if they can gain your liberty.</line>
<line form="verse">A goodly prize, fit for the devil&#8217;s grace!</line>
<line form="verse">See how the ugly witch doth bend her brows,</line>
<line form="verse">As if, with Circe, she would change my shape!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Chang&#8217;d to a worser shape thou canst not be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, Charles the Dauphin is a proper man,</line>
<line form="verse">No shape but his can please your dainty eye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A plaguing mischief light on Charles and thee!</line>
<line form="verse">And may ye both be suddenly surpris&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">By bloody hands, in sleeping on your beds!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fell banning hag, enchantress, hold thy tongue!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I prithee give me leave to curse a while.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Curse, miscreant, when thou com&#8217;st to the stake.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum. Enter Suffolk with Margaret in his hand.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be what thou wilt, thou art my prisoner.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Gazes on her.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O fairest beauty, do not fear nor fly,</line>
<line form="verse">For I will touch thee but with reverend hands.</line>
<line form="verse">I kiss these fingers for eternal peace,</line>
<line form="verse">And lay them gently on thy tender side.</line>
<line form="verse">Who art thou? Say, that I may honor thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Margaret my name, and daughter to a king,</line>
<line form="verse">The King of Naples, whosoe&#8217;er thou art.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An earl I am, and Suffolk am I call&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Be not offended, nature&#8217;s miracle,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art allotted to be ta&#8217;en by me;</line>
<line form="verse">So doth the swan her downy cygnets save,</line>
<line form="verse">Keeping them prisoner underneath her wings.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet, if this servile usage once offend,</line>
<line form="verse">Go, and be free again, as Suffolk&#8217;s friend.</line>

<stagedir type="action">She is going.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O, stay!</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="2">I have no power to let her pass,</line>
<line form="verse">My hand would free her, but my heart says no.</line>
<line form="verse">As plays the sun upon the glassy streams,</line>
<line form="verse">Twinkling another counterfeited beam,</line>
<line form="verse">So seems this gorgeous beauty to mine eyes.</line>
<line form="verse">Fain would I woo her, yet I dare not speak:</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll call for pen and ink, and write my mind.</line>
<line form="verse">Fie, De la Pole, disable not thyself.</line>
<line form="verse">Hast not a tongue? Is she not here?</line>
<line form="verse">Wilt thou be daunted at a woman&#8217;s sight?</line>
<line form="verse">Ay; beauty&#8217;s princely majesty is such,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Confounds the tongue and makes the senses rough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say, Earl of Suffolk&#8212;if thy name be so&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">What ransom must I pay before I pass?</line>
<line form="verse">For I perceive I am thy prisoner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How canst thou tell she will deny thy suit,</line>
<line form="verse">Before thou make a trial of her love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why speak&#8217;st thou not? What ransom must I pay?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">She&#8217;s beautiful; and therefore to be wooed:</line>
<line form="verse">She is a woman; therefore to be won.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wilt thou accept of ransom, yea or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Fond man, remember that thou hast a wife,</line>
<line form="verse">Then how can Margaret be thy paramour?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I were best to leave him, for he will not hear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">There all is marr&#8217;d; there lies a cooling card.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He talks at randon; sure the man is mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And yet a dispensation may be had.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And yet I would that you would answer me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll win this Lady Margaret. For whom?</line>
<line form="verse">Why, for my king. Tush, that&#8217;s a wooden thing!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He talks of wood; it is some carpenter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Yet so my fancy may be satisfied,</line>
<line form="verse">And peace established between these realms.</line>
<line form="verse">But there remains a scruple in that too;</line>
<line form="verse">For though her father be the King of Naples,</line>
<line form="verse">Duke of Anjou and Maine, yet is he poor,</line>
<line form="verse">And our nobility will scorn the match.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hear ye, captain? Are you not at leisure?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">It shall be so, disdain they ne&#8217;er so much.</line>
<line form="verse">Henry is youthful and will quickly yield.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Madam, I have a secret to reveal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What though I be enthrall&#8217;d, he seems a knight,</line>
<line form="verse">And will not any way dishonor me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lady, vouchsafe to listen what I say.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Perhaps I shall be rescu&#8217;d by the French,</line>
<line form="verse">And then I need not crave his courtesy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet madam, give me hearing in a cause.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Tush, women have been captivate ere now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lady, wherefore talk you so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I cry you mercy, &#8217;tis but quid for quo.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say, gentle Princess, would you not suppose</line>
<line form="verse">Your bondage happy, to be made a queen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To be a queen in bondage is more vile</line>
<line form="verse">Than is a slave in base servility;</line>
<line form="verse">For princes should be free.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">And so shall you,</line>
<line form="verse">If happy England&#8217;s royal king be free.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, what concerns his freedom unto me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll undertake to make thee Henry&#8217;s queen,</line>
<line form="verse">To put a golden sceptre in thy hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And set a precious crown upon thy head,</line>
<line form="verse">If thou wilt condescend to be my&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am unworthy to be Henry&#8217;s wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, gentle madam, I unworthy am</line>
<line form="verse">To woo so fair a dame to be his wife</line>
<line form="verse">And have no portion in the choice myself.</line>
<line form="verse">How say you, madam, are ye so content?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And if my father please, I am content.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then call our captains and our colors forth,</line>
<line form="verse">And, madam, at your father&#8217;s castle walls</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll crave a parley, to confer with him.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Sound a parley. Enter Reignier on the walls.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">See, Reignier, see, thy daughter prisoner!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To whom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">To me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Suffolk, what remedy?</line>
<line form="verse">I am a soldier, and unapt to weep,</line>
<line form="verse">Or to exclaim on fortune&#8217;s fickleness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, there is remedy enough, my lord.</line>
<line form="verse">Consent, and for thy honor give consent,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy daughter shall be wedded to my king,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom I with pain have wooed and won thereto;</line>
<line form="verse">And this her easy-held imprisonment</line>
<line form="verse">Hath gain&#8217;d thy daughter princely liberty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speaks Suffolk as he thinks?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Fair Margaret knows</line>
<line form="verse">That Suffolk doth not flatter, face, or feign.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon thy princely warrant, I descend</line>
<line form="verse">To give thee answer of thy just demand.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit from the walls.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And here I will expect thy coming.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Trumpets sound. Enter Reignier below.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Welcome, brave Earl, into our territories!</line>
<line form="verse">Command in Anjou what your honor pleases.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, Reignier, happy for so sweet a child,</line>
<line form="verse">Fit to be made companion with a king.</line>
<line form="verse">What answer makes your Grace unto my suit?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Since thou dost deign to woo her little worth</line>
<line form="verse">To be the princely bride of such a lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon condition I may quietly</line>
<line form="verse">Enjoy mine own, the country Maine and Anjou,</line>
<line form="verse">Free from oppression or the stroke of war,</line>
<line form="verse">My daughter shall be Henry&#8217;s, if he please.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That is her ransom; I deliver her,</line>
<line form="verse">And those two counties I will undertake</line>
<line form="verse">Your Grace shall well and quietly enjoy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I again, in Henry&#8217;s royal name,</line>
<line form="verse">As deputy unto that gracious king,</line>
<line form="verse">Give thee her hand, for sign of plighted faith.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Reignier of France, I give thee kingly thanks,</line>
<line form="verse">Because this is in traffic of a king.</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And yet methinks I could be well content</line>
<line form="verse">To be mine own attorney in this case.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll over then to England with this news,</line>
<line form="verse">And make this marriage to be solemniz&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">So farewell, Reignier! Set this diamond safe</line>
<line form="verse">In golden palaces, as it becomes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do embrace thee, as I would embrace</line>
<line form="verse">The Christian prince, King Henry, were he here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, my lord! Good wishes, praise, and prayers</line>
<line form="verse">Shall Suffolk ever have of Margaret.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">She is going.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, sweet madam! But hark you, Margaret,</line>
<line form="verse">No princely commendations to my king?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Such commendations as becomes a maid,</line>
<line form="verse">A virgin, and his servant, say to him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Words sweetly plac&#8217;d and modestly directed.</line>
<line form="verse">But, madam, I must trouble you again,</line>
<line form="verse">No loving token to his Majesty?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, my good lord, a pure unspotted heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Never yet taint with love, I send the King.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And this withal.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Kiss her.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That for thyself; I will not so presume</line>
<line form="verse">To send such peevish tokens to a king.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Reignier and Margaret.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, wert thou for myself! But, Suffolk, stay,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mayest not wander in that labyrinth,</line>
<line form="verse">There Minotaurs and ugly treasons lurk.</line>
<line form="verse">Solicit Henry with her wondrous praise;</line>
<line form="verse">Bethink thee on her virtues that surmount,</line>
<line form="verse">And natural graces that extinguish art;</line>
<line form="verse">Repeat their semblance often on the seas,</line>
<line form="verse">That, when thou com&#8217;st to kneel at Henry&#8217;s feet,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mayest bereave him of his wits with wonder.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Anjou. Camp of the Duke of York.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(York, Warwick, Shepherd, Pucelle, Cardinal Beauford, Charles, Alanson, Bastard, Reignier)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Joan&#8217;s father laments his daughter&#8217;s condemnation to death, but she refuses to recognize him as her father, insisting that she is of higher birth than a mere shepherd&#8217;s daughter. He curses her when she refuses to acknowledge him and urges the English to burn her. She claims to be a virgin, which only makes the English promise to burn her quickly, to alleviate her suffering; she then claims that she is pregnant, and claims that each of the French leaders in turn is the father, but each one merely makes the English ready to kill the child as well. Seeing that the English are inflexible, she curses them as she is led off to burn. The Cardinal (Winchester) enters on his peace mission, to the disgust of York, who sees all of the English losses as in vain if they simply give up fighting now. Charles and his party enter and negotiate; in the end, Charles accepts to become viceroy under Henry, being certain he&#8217;ll find opportunities to take over the rest of France and be full King at some point in the future.The French swear loyalty to the English.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter York, Warwick, Shepherd, Pucelle guarded.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bring forth that sorceress condemn&#8217;d to burn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHEP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ah, Joan, this kills thy father&#8217;s heart outright!</line>
<line form="verse">Have I sought every country far and near,</line>
<line form="verse">And now it is my chance to find thee out,</line>
<line form="verse">Must I behold thy timeless cruel death?</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, Joan, sweet daughter Joan, I&#8217;ll die with thee!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Decrepit miser! Base ignoble wretch!</line>
<line form="verse">I am descended of a gentler blood.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art no father nor no friend of mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHEP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Out, out! My lords, and please you, &#8217;tis not so,</line>
<line form="verse">I did beget her, all the parish knows.</line>
<line form="verse">Her mother liveth yet, can testify</line>
<line form="verse">She was the first fruit of my bach&#8217;lorship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Graceless, wilt thou deny thy parentage?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This argues what her kind of life hath been,</line>
<line form="verse">Wicked and vile, and so her death concludes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHEP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, Joan, that thou wilt be so obstacle!</line>
<line form="verse">God knows thou art a collop of my flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">And for thy sake have I shed many a tear.</line>
<line form="verse">Deny me not, I prithee, gentle Joan.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Peasant, avaunt!&#8212;You have suborn&#8217;d this man</line>
<line form="verse">Of purpose to obscure my noble birth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHEP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis true, I gave a noble to the priest</line>
<line form="verse">The morn that I was wedded to her mother.</line>
<line form="verse">Kneel down and take my blessing, good my girl.</line>
<line form="verse">Wilt thou not stoop? Now cursed be the time</line>
<line form="verse">Of thy nativity! I would the milk</line>
<line form="verse">Thy mother gave thee, when thou suck&#8217;st her breast,</line>
<line form="verse">Had been a little ratsbane for thy sake!</line>
<line form="verse">Or else, when thou didst keep my lambs a-field,</line>
<line form="verse">I wish some ravenous wolf had eaten thee!</line>
<line form="verse">Dost thou deny thy father, cursed drab?</line>
<line form="verse">O, burn her, burn her! Hanging is too good.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Take her away, for she hath liv&#8217;d too long,</line>
<line form="verse">To fill the world with vicious qualities.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">First let me tell you whom you have condemn&#8217;d:</line>
<line form="verse">Not me begotten of a shepherd swain,</line>
<line form="verse">But issued from the progeny of kings;</line>
<line form="verse">Virtuous and holy, chosen from above,</line>
<line form="verse">By inspiration of celestial grace,</line>
<line form="verse">To work exceeding miracles on earth.</line>
<line form="verse">I never had to do with wicked spirits.</line>
<line form="verse">But you, that are polluted with your lusts,</line>
<line form="verse">Stain&#8217;d with the guiltless blood of innocents,</line>
<line form="verse">Corrupt and tainted with a thousand vices,</line>
<line form="verse">Because you want the grace that others have,</line>
<line form="verse">You judge it straight a thing impossible</line>
<line form="verse">To compass wonders but by help of devils.</line>
<line form="verse">No, misconceived! Joan of Aire hath been</line>
<line form="verse">A virgin from her tender infancy,</line>
<line form="verse">Chaste, and immaculate in very thought,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose maiden blood, thus rigorously effus&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Will cry for vengeance at the gates of heaven.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, ay; away with her to execution!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And hark ye, sirs: because she is a maid,</line>
<line form="verse">Spare for no faggots, let there be enow.</line>
<line form="verse">Place barrels of pitch upon the fatal stake,</line>
<line form="verse">That so her torture may be shortened.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Will nothing turn your unrelenting hearts?</line>
<line form="verse">Then, Joan, discover thine infirmity,</line>
<line form="verse">That warranteth by law to be thy privilege.</line>
<line form="verse">I am with child, ye bloody homicides!</line>
<line form="verse">Murder not then the fruit within my womb,</line>
<line form="verse">Although ye hale me to a violent death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now heaven forfend, the holy maid with child?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The greatest miracle that e&#8217;er ye wrought!</line>
<line form="verse">Is all your strict preciseness come to this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She and the Dauphin have been juggling.</line>
<line form="verse">I did imagine what would be her refuge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, go to, we&#8217;ll have no bastards live,</line>
<line form="verse">Especially since Charles must father it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You are deceiv&#8217;d, my child is none of his,</line>
<line form="verse">It was Alanson that enjoy&#8217;d my love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alanson, that notorious Machevile?</line>
<line form="verse">It dies, and if it had a thousand lives.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, give me leave, I have deluded you,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twas neither Charles nor yet the duke I nam&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">But Reignier, King of Naples, that prevail&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A married man! That&#8217;s most intolerable.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, here&#8217;s a girl! I think she knows not well</line>
<line form="verse">(There were so many) whom she may accuse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It&#8217;s sign she hath been liberal and free.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And yet forsooth she is a virgin pure.</line>
<line form="verse">Strumpet, thy words condemn thy brat and thee.</line>
<line form="verse">Use no entreaty, for it is in vain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUC.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then lead me hence; with whom I leave my curse:</line>
<line form="verse">May never glorious sun reflex his beams</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the country where you make abode;</line>
<line form="verse">But darkness and the gloomy shade of death</line>
<line form="verse">Environ you, till mischief and despair</line>
<line form="verse">Drive you to break your necks or hang yourselves!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit guarded.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Break thou in pieces and consume to ashes,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou foul accursed minister of hell!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Winchester, now Cardinal Beauford, attended.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="WIN.">CAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lord Regent, I do greet your Excellence</line>
<line form="verse">With letters of commission from the King.</line>
<line form="verse">For know, my lords, the states of Christendom,</line>
<line form="verse">Mov&#8217;d with remorse of these outrageous broils,</line>
<line form="verse">Have earnestly implor&#8217;d a general peace</line>
<line form="verse">Betwixt our nation and the aspiring French;</line>
<line form="verse">And here at hand the Dauphin and his train</line>
<line form="verse">Approacheth, to confer about some matter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is all our travail turn&#8217;d to this effect?</line>
<line form="verse">After the slaughter of so many peers,</line>
<line form="verse">So many captains, gentlemen, and soldiers,</line>
<line form="verse">That in this quarrel have been overthrown</line>
<line form="verse">And sold their bodies for their country&#8217;s benefit,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall we at last conclude effeminate peace?</line>
<line form="verse">Have we not lost most part of all the towns,</line>
<line form="verse">By treason, falsehood, and by treachery,</line>
<line form="verse">Our great progenitors had conquered?</line>
<line form="verse">O Warwick, Warwick, I foresee with grief</line>
<line form="verse">The utter loss of all the realm of France.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be patient, York. If we conclude a peace,</line>
<line form="verse">It shall be with such strict and severe covenants,</line>
<line form="verse">As little shall the Frenchmen gain thereby.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Charles, Alanson, Bastard, Reignier, and others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Since, lords of England, it is thus agreed</line>
<line form="verse">That peaceful truce shall be proclaim&#8217;d in France,</line>
<line form="verse">We come to be informed by yourselves</line>
<line form="verse">What the conditions of that league must be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak, Winchester, for boiling choler chokes</line>
<line form="verse">The hollow passage of my poison&#8217;d voice,</line>
<line form="verse">By sight of these our baleful enemies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="WIN.">CAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Charles, and the rest, it is enacted thus:</line>
<line form="verse">That, in regard King Henry gives consent,</line>
<line form="verse">Of mere compassion and of lenity,</line>
<line form="verse">To ease your country of distressful war</line>
<line form="verse">And suffer you to breathe in fruitful peace,</line>
<line form="verse">You shall become true liegemen to his crown.</line>
<line form="verse">And, Charles, upon condition thou wilt swear</line>
<line form="verse">To pay him tribute and submit thyself,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt be plac&#8217;d as viceroy under him,</line>
<line form="verse">And still enjoy thy regal dignity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Must he be then as shadow of himself?</line>
<line form="verse">Adorn his temples with a coronet,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet, in substance and authority,</line>
<line form="verse">Retain but privilege of a private man?</line>
<line form="verse">This proffer is absurd and reasonless.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis known already that I am possess&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With more than half the Gallian territories,</line>
<line form="verse">And therein reverenc&#8217;d for their lawful king.</line>
<line form="verse">Shall I, for lucre of the rest unvanquish&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Detract so much from that prerogative</line>
<line form="verse">As to be call&#8217;d but viceroy of the whole?</line>
<line form="verse">No, lord ambassador, I&#8217;ll rather keep</line>
<line form="verse">That which I have than, coveting for more,</line>
<line form="verse">Be cast from possibility of all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Insulting Charles, hast thou by secret means</line>
<line form="verse">Us&#8217;d intercession to obtain a league,</line>
<line form="verse">And, now the matter grows to compromise,</line>
<line form="verse">Stand&#8217;st thou aloof upon comparison?</line>
<line form="verse">Either accept the title thou usurp&#8217;st,</line>
<line form="verse">Of benefit proceeding from our king,</line>
<line form="verse">And not of any challenge of desert,</line>
<line form="verse">Or we will plague thee with incessant wars.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>REIG.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Charles.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">My lord, you do not well in obstinacy</line>
<line form="verse">To cavil in the course of this contract.</line>
<line form="verse">If once it be neglected, ten to one</line>
<line form="verse">We shall not find like opportunity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALAN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Charles.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">To say the truth, it is your policy</line>
<line form="verse">To save your subjects from such massacre</line>
<line form="verse">And ruthless slaughters as are daily seen</line>
<line form="verse">By our proceeding in hostility,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore take this compact of a truce,</line>
<line form="verse">Although you break it when your pleasure serves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>WAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How say&#8217;st thou, Charles? Shall our condition stand?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHAR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It shall;</line>
<line form="verse">Only reserv&#8217;d, you claim no interest</line>
<line form="verse">In any of our towns of garrison.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>YORK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then swear allegiance to his Majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">As thou art knight, never to disobey</line>
<line form="verse">Nor be rebellious to the crown of England.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou, nor thy nobles, to the crown of England.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Charles and his party give tokens of fealty.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">So, now dismiss your army when ye please;</line>
<line form="verse">Hang up your ensigns, let your drums be still,</line>
<line form="verse">For here we entertain a solemn peace.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>London. A room in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Suffolk, King, Gloucester, Exeter)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Suffolk so praises Margaret that Henry is anxious to send for her. Gloucester reminds him of his engagement to the daughter of the Earl of Arminack, who is Charles&#8217;s kin and will bring a rich dowry with her. Suffolk and Gloucester argue the point, which is settled when the King sends Suffolk to France to marry Margaret by proxy for him and bring her back to England. Gloucester is concerned, while Suffolk looks forward to Margaret ruling the King, and he himself Margaret.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Suffolk in conference with the King, Gloucester, and Exeter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your wondrous rare description, noble Earl,</line>
<line form="verse">Of beauteous Margaret hath astonish&#8217;d me.</line>
<line form="verse">Her virtues, graced with external gifts,</line>
<line form="verse">Do breed love&#8217;s settled passions in my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">And like as rigor of tempestuous gusts</line>
<line form="verse">Provokes the mightiest hulk against the tide,</line>
<line form="verse">So am I driven by breath of her renown,</line>
<line form="verse">Either to suffer shipwrack, or arrive</line>
<line form="verse">Where I may have fruition of her love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tush, my good lord, this superficial tale</line>
<line form="verse">Is but a preface of her worthy praise.</line>
<line form="verse">The chief perfections of that lovely dame</line>
<line form="verse">(Had I sufficient skill to utter them)</line>
<line form="verse">Would make a volume of enticing lines,</line>
<line form="verse">Able to ravish any dull conceit;</line>
<line form="verse">And, which is more, she is not so divine,</line>
<line form="verse">So full replete with choice of all delights,</line>
<line form="verse">But with as humble lowliness of mind</line>
<line form="verse">She is content to be at your command&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Command, I mean, of virtuous chaste intents,</line>
<line form="verse">To love and honor Henry as her lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And otherwise will Henry ne&#8217;er presume.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, my Lord Protector, give consent</line>
<line form="verse">That Marg&#8217;ret may be England&#8217;s royal queen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So should I give consent to flatter sin.</line>
<line form="verse">You know, my lord, your Highness is betroth&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Unto another lady of esteem.</line>
<line form="verse">How shall we then dispense with that contract,</line>
<line form="verse">And not deface your honor with reproach?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As doth a ruler with unlawful oaths,</line>
<line form="verse">Or one that at a triumph, having vow&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To try his strength, forsaketh yet the lists</line>
<line form="verse">By reason of his adversary&#8217;s odds.</line>
<line form="verse">A poor earl&#8217;s daughter is unequal odds,</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore may be broke without offense.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, what, I pray, is Margaret more than that?</line>
<line form="verse">Her father is no better than an earl,</line>
<line form="verse">Although in glorious titles he excel.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, my lord, her father is a king,</line>
<line form="verse">The King of Naples and Jerusalem,</line>
<line form="verse">And of such great authority in France</line>
<line form="verse">As his alliance will confirm our peace,</line>
<line form="verse">And keep the Frenchmen in allegiance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so the Earl of Armagnac may do,</line>
<line form="verse">Because he is near kinsman unto Charles.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EXE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Beside, his wealth doth warrant a liberal dower,</line>
<line form="verse">Where Reignier sooner will receive than give.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A dow&#8217;r, my lords? Disgrace not so your king,</line>
<line form="verse">That he should be so abject, base, and poor,</line>
<line form="verse">To choose for wealth and not for perfect love.</line>
<line form="verse">Henry is able to enrich his queen,</line>
<line form="verse">And not to seek a queen to make him rich:</line>
<line form="verse">So worthless peasants bargain for their wives,</line>
<line form="verse">As market men for oxen, sheep, or horse.</line>
<line form="verse">Marriage is a matter of more worth</line>
<line form="verse">Than to be dealt in by attorneyship.</line>
<line form="verse">Not whom we will, but whom his Grace affects,</line>
<line form="verse">Must be companion of his nuptial bed.</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore, lords, since he affects her most,</line>
<line form="verse">Most of all these reasons bindeth us</line>
<line form="verse">In our opinions she should be preferr&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">For what is wedlock forced, but a hell,</line>
<line form="verse">An age of discord and continual strife?</line>
<line form="verse">Whereas the contrary bringeth bliss,</line>
<line form="verse">And is a pattern of celestial peace.</line>
<line form="verse">Whom should we match with Henry, being a king,</line>
<line form="verse">But Margaret, that is daughter to a king?</line>
<line form="verse">Her peerless feature, joined with her birth,</line>
<line form="verse">Approves her fit for none but for a king.</line>
<line form="verse">Her valiant courage and undaunted spirit</line>
<line form="verse">(More than in women commonly is seen)</line>
<line form="verse">Will answer our hope in issue of a king;</line>
<line form="verse">For Henry, son unto a conqueror,</line>
<line form="verse">Is likely to beget more conquerors,</line>
<line form="verse">If with a lady of so high resolve</line>
<line form="verse">(As is fair Margaret) he be link&#8217;d in love.</line>
<line form="verse">Then yield, my lords, and here conclude with me</line>
<line form="verse">That Margaret shall be Queen, and none but she.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>KING.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whether it be through force of your report,</line>
<line form="verse">My noble Lord of Suffolk, or for that</line>
<line form="verse">My tender youth was never yet attaint</line>
<line form="verse">With any passion of inflaming love,</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot tell; but this I am assur&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">I feel such sharp dissension in my breast,</line>
<line form="verse">Such fierce alarums both of hope and fear,</line>
<line form="verse">As I am sick with working of my thoughts.</line>
<line form="verse">Take therefore shipping, post, my lord, to France,</line>
<line form="verse">Agree to any covenants, and procure</line>
<line form="verse">That Lady Margaret do vouchsafe to come</line>
<line form="verse">To cross the seas to England and be crown&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">King Henry&#8217;s faithful and anointed queen.</line>
<line form="verse">For your expenses and sufficient charge,</line>
<line form="verse">Among the people gather up a tenth.</line>
<line form="verse">Be gone, I say, for till you do return,</line>
<line form="verse">I rest perplexed with a thousand cares.</line>
<line form="verse">And you, good uncle, banish all offense.</line>
<line form="verse">If you do censure me by what you were,</line>
<line form="verse">Not what you are, I know it will excuse</line>
<line form="verse">This sudden execution of my will.</line>
<line form="verse">And so conduct me where, from company,</line>
<line form="verse">I may revolve and ruminate my grief.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GLOU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, grief, I fear me, both at first and last.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Gloucester with Exeter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SUF.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thus Suffolk hath prevail&#8217;d, and thus he goes,</line>
<line form="verse">As did the youthful Paris once to Greece,</line>
<line form="verse">With hope to find the like event in love,</line>
<line form="verse">But prosper better than the Troyan did.</line>
<line form="verse">Margaret shall now be Queen, and rule the King;</line>
<line form="verse">But I will rule both her, the King, and realm.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>

