<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Macbeth">The Tragedy of Macbeth</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="Macbeth">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUN.">Duncan, King of Scotland</persname>
<persdescription>Duncan is the King of Scotland, an old, gracious, pious and gentle man, who resembles Lady Macbeth&#8217;s father in his sleep. He is somewhat too trusting, and will be betrayed twice by Thanes of Cawdor he trusted in the space of a very few days. He does not fight on the front line himself, but leaves this duty to others. He is nevertheless quite prepared to pronounce sentence of death on traitors. He promises to improve the fortunes of his victorious generals Banquo and Macbeth just before announcing Malcolm as his heir. He is stabbed to death in his sleep by Macbeth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MAL.">Malcolm</persname>
<persdescription>Malcolm is Duncan&#8217;s eldest son. Almost captured in the battle that rages at the beginning of the play, he is rescued by the captain. He is named Prince of Cumberland and heir to the throne by Duncan once all the fighting is done. On his father&#8217;s death, he flees to England, unwilling to trust the Scottish nobles. This allows Macbeth to frame him as the murderer. In time he becomes the rallying point of opposition to Macbeth, and with the English king&#8217;s help assembles a massive army to recover his throne. To test Macduff&#8217;s loyalty to Scotland, Malcolm pretends to be a thoroughly vile human being to him; he is reassured that Macduff works for his country and not simply out of hatred when Macduff turns from him. He conceives the idea of camouflaging his army&#8217;s advance with the trees of Birnam Forest. On his victory, he re-titles the thanes as earls, an English title rather than a Scottish one.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DON.">Donalbain</persname>
<persdescription>Donalbain is Duncan&#8217;s second son. After his father&#8217;s murder, he suggests to Malcolm that they quickly leave. He flees to Ireland, arguing that by going to separate places he and his brother will be safer. He is not returned to join in the battle against Macbeth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MACB.">Macbeth</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="MACB. AND LEN.">Macbeth and Lennox</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Macbeth is Thane of Glamis. A superb general, he is a physically powerful man, able in a fight to eviscerate a man with an upward stroke. The predictions of the witches make a great impression on him; though he insists on reasons for being called Thane of Cawdor, the moment it is confirmed the thought of becoming king lodges in his mind. Very close to his wife, he writes to her of the prediction as soon as he can. Though at first he seems willing to let Fortune take care of bringing him to the throne, the thought of murder cannot be hid, and his wife soon pushes him to it. He still over-thinks the matter, finding out all the moral objections to the act, but he cannot adequately answer his wife&#8217;s incitements to committing it. He is possessed of a powerful imagination that is able to conjure a dagger before his eyes. As he leaves after killing Duncan, he hears a voice predicting that he will never sleep again, a prediction that comes true. He is quick-witted enough to kill Duncan&#8217;s grooms as his supposed murderers before they can protest their innocence. Deeply insecure, he is a paranoid king, keeping spies in the household of every nobleman. He plans to have Banquo and Fleance killed in the hopes of undoing the witches&#8217; prophecy that Banquo&#8217;s descendants would take the throne. Once king, he becomes far more manipulative than he was, able to convince the murderers that their complaints against him are actually Banquo&#8217;s responsibility. He hides the murder plot from his Queen, signaling an end to the closeness of their relationship. Courageous though he may be in battle, he is not proof against the supernatural, as evidenced by the apparition of Banquo&#8217;s ghost. To explain his fit, he explains to his assembled noblemen that he is subject to an epileptic-type condition, but whether this is true or not is uncertain. By this stage an insomniac, he has lost all hope of redemption, and is determined to do anything that he must to keep himself safe. To this end he visits the witches. He is reassured by the three apparitions they conjure for him, but fails to note the warnings in their shapes which offer a hint of the loopholes in their promises. Hearing of Macduff&#8217;s flight, he resolves to now act on his first impulses, and he sends his men to sack Fife and murder all of Macduff&#8217;s family. The reassurances of the witches lead him to discount the desertions in his ranks, but he is nevertheless grown to a state of despair, thinking that his life has gone on long enough. Still, he arms himself, and swears that he will not simply give up. He cares about his wife in her illness, though his concern for her state of mind may apply as much to his own. By the time Malcolm&#8217;s army begins its approach, he has lost all touch of the fear that afflicted him in the lead-up to his killing Duncan. He alternates between wild rage and deep, nihilistic depression as his wife commits suicide and his enemies arrive at his gate. He is brought to doubt the witches&#8217; promises by the moving forest of Birnam, and in his last moments convinced of their falseness when Macduff reveals the circumstances of his birth. He still pulls up his courage, however, and dies fighting.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LADY M.">Lady Macbeth</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Macbeth is a ruthless woman. More openly ambitious than her husband, she does not shy from murder, and pushes Macbeth towards it. She is worried that his kinder side may keep him from going as far as he may. She calls on the powers of darkness to steel her against remorse or misgiving, and concocts he whole plan of how to kill Duncan. When Macbeth backs out of the thought, she brings him around by a combination of mockery, belittling of his manhood, and accusations of cowardice. She drugs the king&#8217;s attendants herself, and leaves their daggers when Macbeth will see them. She considers committing the murder herself, but she is troubled by Duncan&#8217;s resemblance to her father, and forbears. Though frightened while waiting for Macbeth to emerge from Duncan&#8217;s chamber, she is controlled enough to erase all the evidence afterwards. Once Queen, her closeness with her husband begins to fray as he draws away from her, now hiding his plots. She is at first able to stop the feast from disintegrating into chaos when Macbeth sees Banquo&#8217;s ghost, but in the end realizes that she must rid the room of witnesses. Consciously she does not suffer the remorse that affects Macbeth; but while he can no longer sleep, she begins to sleepwalk, admitting to her guilt and begging for some way to wash away her sins. In the end she is guilt-ridden enough that she commits suicide.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="L. MACD.">Lady Macduff</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Macduff is a realist. Horrified at her abandonment by her husband, she castigates him in his absence for a lack of wisdom and normal human feeling. She considers him to be dead after he has fled to England. She is aware that innocence is no guarantee of safety from harm. She is killed by the same Three Murderers who kill Banquo.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BAN.">Banquo</persname>
<persdescription>Banquo is a Scottish Thane, Macbeth&#8217;s co-general in the wars. He spots the witches before Macbeth does, and is not afraid to question them, wishing for a prediction as to his future as well. When the first prediction comes true, he is startled, and worried that it may make Macbeth covet the crown. He is wary of the dark powers&#8217; wiliness. The witches and their prophecies remain on his mind, but he reaffirms his loyalty to Duncan when Macbeth subtly tests it. He suspects Macbeth of Duncan&#8217;s murder, and his accession to king leaves Banquo in hope that his children may yet take the throne. On being attacked by three murderers, his thoughts are for his son Fleance&#8217;s safety. After his death, he reappears as a ghost and as an apparition.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MACD.">Macduff</persname>
<persdescription>Macduff is the Thane of Fife. Commanded by Duncan to visit him early in the morning at Macbeth&#8217;s castle, he discovers the King&#8217;s body. Though he accepts the explanation that Duncan&#8217;s attendants committed the murder at his sons&#8217; instigation, he refuses to attend Macbeth&#8217;s coronation. Having refused to attend a feast of Macbeth&#8217;s, he is cast into disgrace, and travels to England to beg King Edward to help Malcolm overthrow the usurper. His wife accuses him of lacking natural human feeling and of being a coward for having fled. A noble and ethical idealist, he is horrified by Malcolm&#8217;s listing of his own vices, and finally must conclude that the young man is no more worthy of the throne than Macbeth. The revelation that Malcolm was merely testing him leaves him a touch off-kilter. Though he left them in Scotland, he remains fond of his wife and children, and is devastated when he learns that they have been slaughtered on his account. This grief becomes his chief spur against Macbeth. He leads a part of Malcolm&#8217;s army, but at the battle of Dunsinane soon abandons them while on a single-minded quest to find and kill Macbeth himself. Finding him, he wastes little time in dialogue, preferring to trust to his sword. He tears Macbeth&#8217;s last hope from him by revealing that he was the issue of a Caesarean birth, and threatens him with abject humiliation. In the end, he succeeds in beheading him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LEN.">Lennox</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="MACB. AND LEN.">Macbeth and Lennox</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Lennox is a young Thane attending on Duncan. He accompanies Macduff the morning of Duncan&#8217;s murder, and notes that he cannot remember as stormy a night as the preceding one. He joins Macbeth&#8217;s court, but is soon convinced of the usurper&#8217;s guilt, which he cautiously exposes to similarly-minded lords in ironical phrases. He still stays with Macbeth, however, bringing him the news of Macduff&#8217;s flight. He is one of the Thanes who deserts Macbeth once Malcolm invades, bringing reinforcements to Malcolm&#8217;s army, and is well-informed of who is present with Malcolm.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ROSSE.">Rosse</persname>
<persdescription>Rosse is the Thane who brings Duncan news of the Norwegian invasion and of Cawdor&#8217;s complicity in it. He is sent to have Cawdor executed and to give his title to Macbeth. He is present the morning after Duncan&#8217;s murder, and predicts Macbeth&#8217;s accession. Unlike Macduff, he decides to attend the new king&#8217;s coronation. Present at Macbeth&#8217;s feast, he is the first to note that Macbeth is acting oddly. He attempts to comfort Macduff&#8217;s wife, insisting on the flown thane&#8217;s wisdom and nobility, but not daring to stay too long with her. Gone to England himself, he at first tells Macduff that his family is well; it is not until he has received assurances from Malcolm that an invasion is imminent that he reveals that they have been murdered. He is present at the final battle, and brings Siward news of his son&#8217;s death. A glib-tongued fellow, he has a knack of being on the winning side and at placing himself first.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MENT.">Menteth</persname>
<persdescription>Menteth one of the four Thanes who desert Macbeth when Malcolm invades, bringing reinforcements to Malcolm&#8217;s army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANG.">Angus</persname>
<persdescription>Angus is a Thane who accompanies Ross in bringing Duncan news of the victory over Norway, and later bringing Macbeth the announcement of his accession to the rank of Thane of Cawdor. He is one of the four Thanes who desert Macbeth when Malcolm invades, bringing reinforcements to Malcolm&#8217;s army. He is less talkative than Ross.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CATH.">Cathness</persname>
<persdescription>Cathness is one of the four Thanes who desert Macbeth when Malcolm invades, bringing reinforcements to Malcolm&#8217;s army. He has the latest news of Macbeth&#8217;s preparations.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FLE.">Fleance</persname>
<persdescription>Fleance is Banquo&#8217;s son. He accompanies his father to Macbeth&#8217;s castle, and joins him in riding the day he is murdered. When the torch he and Banquo have is struck out when the murderers attack them, Fleance is able to flee in the dark.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SIW.">Siward, Earl of Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>Siward, the Earl of Northumberland, is a veteran soldier&#8217;s of the English king&#8217;s and Malcolm&#8217;s uncle. He is the leader of the English troops lent to Malcolm to retrieve his throne. On hearing of his son&#8217;s death, his only fear is that the young man may have been killed from behind. When told that that all the wounds were to the front, and that he therefore died fighting, Siward is quite reconciled to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="Y. SIW.">Young Siward</persname>
<persdescription>Young Siward is Siward&#8217;s son. During the battle at Macbeth&#8217;s castle, he comes across Macbeth and fights with him, but is killed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SEY.">Seyton</persname>
<persdescription>Seyton is Macbeth&#8217;s chief servant when his thanes are abandoning him. The fact that his name rhymes with &#8216;Satan&#8217; may be coincidental. He helps to arm Macbeth, and reports the Queen&#8217;s death to him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SON.">Son to Macduff</persname>
<persdescription>Macduff&#8217;s son is able to trade witticisms with his mother, and even to best her at times. He is fierce enough to deny his father to be a traitor and to insult a murderer to his face. On doing so, he is promptly murdered.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DOCT.">English Doctor</persname>
<persdescription>An English Doctor is involved with gathering sufferers from the Evil to receive the English king&#8217;s touch. He informs Malcolm of the king&#8217;s presence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DOCT. PHYS.">Doctor of Physic</persname>
<persdescription>A Doctor of Physic is called in by Lady Macbeth&#8217;s waiting-gentlewoman to witness her mistress&#8217;s sleepwalking. He is appalled at what he understands her unconscious words to mean, and all too aware of the danger of knowing them. He realizes that this is not a disease that a doctor can heal, and tells Macbeth as much. He has no trust that Macbeth will win, and wishes himself well away from Dunsinane.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERG.">Sergeant</persname>
<persdescription>A Sergeant in Duncan&#8217;s army saved Malcolm from being captured. He was present at the battle against Macdonald, where he is wounded; on his way to seek help, he meets Duncan and is able to tell him of Macbeth and Banquo&#8217;s success against the rebel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PORT.">Porter</persname>
<persdescription>A Porter at Macbeth&#8217;s castle got extremely drunk during the feast for Duncan. He has a lively imagination and is willing to speak bawdily to those who are by far his social superiors.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OLD MAN.">Old Man</persname>
<persdescription>An Old Man whose memory stretches back seventy years is disturbed by the unnatural phenomena that accompany Duncan&#8217;s murder.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. MUR.">First Murderer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.">Both First and Second Murderers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Murderer has some grievances against Macbeth that the latter convinces him were in fact Banquo&#8217;s fault. He has had a hard enough life that he is willing to turn murderer if it gives him a chance at fortune, as he does not much mind dying at this stage. He welcomes the Third Murderer to their party. He strikes out the torch carried by Banquo and Fleance to make killing them easier, but allowing Fleance to escape. He slices Banquo&#8217;s throat to be certain of his death. He later takes part in the sack of Macduff&#8217;s castle, killing his wife and children.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. MUR.">Second Murderer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.">Both First and Second Murderers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Murderer has some grievances against Macbeth that the latter convinces him were in fact Banquo&#8217;s fault. He has had a hard enough life that he will do anything to strike a blow back at it. He is quick to agree to murder Banquo, though irritated when the Third Murderer arrives to join them, seeing it as a sign of mistrust on Macbeth&#8217;s part. He later takes part in the sack of Macduff&#8217;s castle, killing his wife and children.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. MUR.">Third Murderer</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Murderer joins the first two murderers at Macbeth&#8217;s command for the ambush to kill Banquo. He knows something of Banquo&#8217;s habits. He later takes part in the sack of Macduff&#8217;s castle, killing his wife and children.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERV.">Servant</persname>
<persdescription>A Servant of the Macbeths brings to Lady Macbeth the news of both Duncan and Macbeth&#8217;s approach. He (or she) attends both Macbeth and Lady Macbeth, bearing a torch for them, calling for the murderers, and passing messages between the spouses. He is pale with fear when he comes to announce the invasion and the size of the English army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SOLDIERS.">Soldiers</persname>
<persdescription>Soldiers of Malcolm&#8217;s army cut down Birnam Wood to camouflage themselves as they approach Dunsinane. They fight and win the day, hailing Malcolm as King of Scotland when Macbeth&#8217;s death is confirmed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LORD.">Lord</persname>
<persdescription>A Lord attends Macbeth&#8217;s feast, where he pledges the King. He is confused by Macbeth&#8217;s actions and the Queen&#8217;s breach of protocol. He is able to give Lennox news of Malcolm and of Macduff&#8217;s flight to England, and of how England&#8217;s King Edward is promising to support the Scottish exiles against the usurper. A pious man, he keenly feels Macbeth&#8217;s tyranny and the breaches in normal life the usurpation has caused.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="GENT.">Gentlewoman</persname>
<persdescription>A Waiting-Gentlewoman of Lady Macbeth&#8217;s witnesses her mistress&#8217; sleepwalking and calls in the Doctor to help her. She understands just what Lady Macbeth means in her sleeping speech, but refuses to repeat it to anyone.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HEC.">Hecat</persname>
<persdescription>Hecat is the queen of witches. She is enraged that the main trio of witches have interfered with Macbeth without consulting her, particularly as she thinks little of him, and insists on joining their later interaction with him. She arrives with reinforcements to improve their brew before Macbeth arrives. She is given to bursting into song and taking flight at little notice. Four spirits call for Hecat and induce her to leave the three witches. They are Stadlin, Puckle, Hoppo, and Hellwain. A spirit like a cat (Malkin) descends from the sky to fetch Hecat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="1. WITCH.">First Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Witch seems to be the leader of the trio of witches. She speaks mainly of things that are in the past, and asks questions. She is vengeful, can fly about in a sieve, and command the winds. Her familiar is a cat named Grimalkin.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="2. WITCH.">Second Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Witch speaks of present things, rather than past or future. Like her sisters, she can command winds. Her familiar is a toad named Paddock.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="3. WITCH.">Third Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Witch speaks of future things. Like her sisters, she can command winds.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="4. WITCH.">Fourth Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fourth Witch attends on Hecat and adds some ingredients to the witches&#8217; brew.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="5. WITCH.">Fifth Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fifth Witch attends on Hecat and adds some ingredients to the witches&#8217; brew.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="6. WITCH.">Sixth Witch</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. WITCHES">All Witches</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Sixth Witch attends on Hecat and adds some ingredients to the witches&#8217; brew.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. APP.">First Apparition</persname>
<persdescription>The First Apparition, in the warlike shape of a head wearing a helmet, warns Macbeth of Macduff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. APP.">Second Apparition</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Apparition tells Macbeth that he shall not die at the hand of a woman born. Its shape as a bloody child suggests the trickery of the prediction, resembling the outcome of a Caesarean birth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. APP.">Third Apparition</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Apparition tells Macbeth not to fear defeat until Birnam Wood comes to Dunsinane. Its shape, a child crowned holding a tree in its hand, reveals how this shall come about.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MACB. MESS.">Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger is one of his guards, charged with keeping a lookout. He is the first to notice Birnam Wood moving. He may be the same as the Macbeths&#8217; Servant.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Messenger warns Lady Macduff that she should flee, though he refuses to tell her exactly what he fears. He is too scared for his own life to stay with her.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A desert place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Three Witches)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Amid thunder and lightning, three witches agree to meet again when the battle is over, by the end of the day, and meet Macbeth.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder and lightning. Enter three Witches.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">When shall we three meet again?</line>
<line form="rhyme">In thunder, lightning, or in rain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">When the hurly-burly&#8217;s done,</line>
<line form="rhyme">When the battle&#8217;s lost and won.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">That will be ere the set of sun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where the place?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Upon the heath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There to meet with Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I come, Graymalkin.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Paddock calls.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Anon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Fair is foul, and foul is fair,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Hover through the fog and filthy air.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A camp near Forres.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Duncan, Malcolm, Donalbain, Lennox, Attendants, Sergeant, Rosse, Angus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>An injured captain tells Duncan, King of Scots, of how the thane of Glamis, Macbeth, defeated the rebel Macdonwald and killed him; the captain faints as he explains that at that moment, the King of Norway began a second attack. Ross arrives to inform the King that Macbeth proceeded to beat Norway, along with the traitor Thane of Cawdor who was helping him. The defeat is complete; in recognition of Macbeth&#8217;s valor, Duncan gives him Cawdor&#8217;s title as he sentences the traitor to death.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Alarum within. Enter King Duncan, Malcolm, Donalbain, Lennox, with Attendants, meeting a bleeding Sergeant.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What bloody man is that? He can report,</line>
<line form="verse">As seemeth by his plight, of the revolt</line>
<line form="verse">The newest state.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">This is the sergeant,</line>
<line form="verse">Who like a good and hardy soldier fought</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Gainst my captivity. Hail, brave friend!</line>
<line form="verse">Say to the King the knowledge of the broil</line>
<line form="verse">As thou didst leave it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Doubtful it stood,</line>
<line form="verse">As two spent swimmers that do cling together</line>
<line form="verse">And choke their art. The merciless Macdonwald</line>
<line form="verse">(Worthy to be a rebel, for to that</line>
<line form="verse">The multiplying villainies of nature</line>
<line form="verse">Do swarm upon him) from the Western Isles</line>
<line form="verse">Of kerns and gallowglasses is supplied,</line>
<line form="verse">And Fortune, on his damned quarrel smiling,</line>
<line form="verse">Show&#8217;d like a rebel&#8217;s whore. But all&#8217;s too weak;</line>
<line form="verse">For brave Macbeth (well he deserves that name),</line>
<line form="verse">Disdaining Fortune, with his brandish&#8217;d steel,</line>
<line form="verse">Which smok&#8217;d with bloody execution,</line>
<line form="verse">(Like Valor&#8217;s minion) carv&#8217;d out his passage</line>
<line form="verse">Till he fac&#8217;d the slave;</line>
<line form="verse">Which nev&#8217;r shook hands, nor bade farewell to him,</line>
<line form="verse">Till he unseam&#8217;d him from the nave to th&#8217; chops,</line>
<line form="verse">And fix&#8217;d his head upon our battlements.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O valiant cousin, worthy gentleman!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERG.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As whence the sun gins his reflection</line>
<line form="verse">Shipwracking storms and direful thunders break,</line>
<line form="verse">So from that spring whence comfort seem&#8217;d to come</line>
<line form="verse">Discomfort swells. Mark, King of Scotland, mark!</line>
<line form="verse">No sooner justice had, with valor arm&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Compell&#8217;d these skipping kerns to trust their heels,</line>
<line form="verse">But the Norweyan lord, surveying vantage,</line>
<line form="verse">With furbish&#8217;d arms and new supplies of men,</line>
<line form="verse">Began a fresh assault.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Dismay&#8217;d not this</line>
<line form="verse">Our captains, Macbeth and Banquo?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="9">Yes,</line>
<line form="verse">As sparrows eagles; or the hare the lion.</line>
<line form="verse">If I say sooth, I must report they were</line>
<line form="verse">As cannons overcharg&#8217;d with double cracks, so they</line>
<line form="verse">Doubly redoubled strokes upon the foe.</line>
<line form="verse">Except they meant to bathe in reeking wounds,</line>
<line form="verse">Or memorize another Golgotha,</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot tell&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">But I am faint, my gashes cry for help.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So well thy words become thee as thy wounds,</line>
<line form="verse">They smack of honor both. Go get him surgeons.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Sergeant, attended.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Rosse and Angus.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Who comes here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">The worthy Thane of Rosse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What a haste looks through his eyes! So should he look</line>
<line form="verse">That seems to speak things strange.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">God save the King!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whence cam&#8217;st thou, worthy thane?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">From Fife, great King,</line>
<line form="verse">Where the Norweyan banners flout the sky</line>
<line form="verse">And fan our people cold.</line>
<line form="verse">Norway himself, with terrible numbers,</line>
<line form="verse">Assisted by that most disloyal traitor,</line>
<line form="verse">The Thane of Cawdor, began a dismal conflict,</line>
<line form="verse">Till that Bellona&#8217;s bridegroom, lapp&#8217;d in proof,</line>
<line form="verse">Confronted him with self-comparisons,</line>
<line form="verse">Point against point, rebellious arm &#8217;gainst arm,</line>
<line form="verse">Curbing his lavish spirit; and to conclude,</line>
<line form="verse">The victory fell on us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Great happiness!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">That now</line>
<line form="verse">Sweno, the Norways&#8217; king, craves composition;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor would we deign him burial of his men</line>
<line form="verse">Till he disbursed at Saint Colme&#8217;s inch</line>
<line form="verse">Ten thousand dollars to our general use.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No more that Thane of Cawdor shall deceive</line>
<line form="verse">Our bosom interest. Go pronounce his present death,</line>
<line form="verse">And with his former title greet Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll see it done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What he hath lost, noble Macbeth hath won.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A heath near Forres.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Three Witches, Macbeth, Banquo, Rosse, Angus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The three witches trade tales of what evils they have been up to of late. On their way back from the battle, Macbeth and his fellow general Banquo are met by the three, who greet Macbeth as Thane of Glamis, Thane of Cawdor, and King to be. Macbeth is incredulous, as two of these titles are not his. Banquo asks the sisters to prophesy to him, too, and they tell him that though he shall never be King himself, his children will take the throne. As Macbeth seeks to know more, the witches vanish. Ross and Angus arrive to greet Macbeth with his new title; the general is amazed to be called Thane of Cawdor, but it is explained to him. The truth of the witches&#8217; words disturbs Macbeth, and Banquo cautions him not to aim at the throne despite the fulfillment of the prophecy, as it may merely be a bait of the devil. He and Banquo agree to discuss the matter further at a better time.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. Enter the three Witches.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where hast thou been, sister?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Killing swine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sister, where thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A sailor&#8217;s wife had chestnuts in her lap,</line>
<line form="verse">And mounch&#8217;d, and mounch&#8217;d, and mounch&#8217;d. &#8220;Give me!&#8221; quoth I.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Aroint thee, witch!&#8221; the rump-fed ronyon cries.</line>
<line form="verse">Her husband&#8217;s to Aleppo gone, master  o&#8217; th&#8217; Tiger;</line>
<line form="rhyme">But in a sieve I&#8217;ll thither sail,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And like a rat without a tail,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll do, I&#8217;ll do, and I&#8217;ll do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll give thee a wind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Th&#8217; art kind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">And I another.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">I myself have all the other,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And the very ports they blow,</line>
<line form="rhyme">All the quarters that they know</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217; th&#8217; shipman&#8217;s card.</line>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll drain him dry as hay:</line>
<line form="rhyme">Sleep shall neither night nor day</line>
<line form="rhyme">Hang upon his penthouse lid;</line>
<line form="rhyme">He shall live a man forbid;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Weary sev&#8217;nnights, nine times nine,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Shall he dwindle, peak, and pine;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Though his bark cannot be lost,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Yet it shall be tempest-toss&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Look what I have.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Show me, show me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here I have a pilot&#8217;s thumb,</line>
<line form="verse">Wrack&#8217;d as homeward he did come.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Drum within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">A drum, a drum!</line>
<line form="rhyme">Macbeth doth come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">The weird sisters, hand in hand,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Posters of the sea and land,</line>
<line form="verse">Thus do go, about, about,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Thrice to thine, and thrice to mine,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And thrice again, to make up nine.</line>
<line form="verse">Peace, the charm&#8217;s wound up.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth and Banquo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So foul and fair a day I have not seen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How far is&#8217;t call&#8217;d to Forres? What are these</line>
<line form="verse">So wither&#8217;d and so wild in their attire,</line>
<line form="verse">That look not like th&#8217; inhabitants  o&#8217; th&#8217; earth,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet are on&#8217;t? Live you? Or are you aught</line>
<line form="verse">That man may question? You seem to understand me,</line>
<line form="verse">By each at once her choppy finger laying</line>
<line form="verse">Upon her skinny lips. You should be women,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet your beards forbid me to interpret</line>
<line form="verse">That you are so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Speak, if you can: what are you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All hail, Macbeth, hail to thee, Thane of Glamis!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All hail, Macbeth, hail to thee. Thane of Cawdor!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All hail, Macbeth, that shalt be King hereafter!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good sir, why do you start, and seem to fear</line>
<line form="verse">Things that do sound so fair?&#8212;I&#8217; th&#8217; name of truth,</line>
<line form="verse">Are ye fantastical, or that indeed</line>
<line form="verse">Which outwardly ye show? My noble partner</line>
<line form="verse">You greet with present grace, and great prediction</line>
<line form="verse">Of noble having and of royal hope,</line>
<line form="verse">That he seems rapt withal; to me you speak not.</line>
<line form="verse">If you can look into the seeds of time,</line>
<line form="verse">And say which grain will grow, and which will not,</line>
<line form="verse">Speak then to me, who neither beg nor fear</line>
<line form="verse">Your favors nor your hate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lesser than Macbeth, and greater.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not so happy, yet much happier.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt get kings, though thou be none.</line>
<line form="verse">So all hail, Macbeth and Banquo!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Banquo and Macbeth, all hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, you imperfect speakers, tell me more:</line>
<line form="verse">By Sinel&#8217;s death I know I am Thane of Glamis,</line>
<line form="verse">But how of Cawdor? The Thane of Cawdor lives</line>
<line form="verse">A prosperous gentleman; and to be king</line>
<line form="verse">Stands not within the prospect of belief,</line>
<line form="verse">No more than to be Cawdor. Say from whence</line>
<line form="verse">You owe this strange intelligence, or why</line>
<line form="verse">Upon this blasted heath you stop our way</line>
<line form="verse">With such prophetic greeting? Speak, I charge you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Witches vanish.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The earth hath bubbles, as the water has,</line>
<line form="verse">And these are of them. Whither are they vanish&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Into the air; and what seem&#8217;d corporal melted,</line>
<line form="verse">As breath into the wind. Would they had stay&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were such things here as we do speak about?</line>
<line form="verse">Or have we eaten on the insane root</line>
<line form="verse">That takes the reason prisoner?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your children shall be kings.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">You shall be king.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And Thane of Cawdor too; went it not so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To th&#8217; self-same tune and words. Who&#8217;s here?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Rosse and Angus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The King hath happily receiv&#8217;d, Macbeth,</line>
<line form="verse">The news of thy success; and when he reads</line>
<line form="verse">Thy personal venture in the rebels&#8217; fight,</line>
<line form="verse">His wonders and his praises do contend</line>
<line form="verse">Which should be thine or his. Silenc&#8217;d with that,</line>
<line form="verse">In viewing  o&#8217;er the rest  o&#8217; th&#8217; self-same day,</line>
<line form="verse">He finds thee in the stout Norweyan ranks,</line>
<line form="verse">Nothing afeard of what thyself didst make,</line>
<line form="verse">Strange images of death. As thick as tale</line>
<line form="verse">Came post with post, and every one did bear</line>
<line form="verse">Thy praises in his kingdom&#8217;s great defense,</line>
<line form="verse">And pour&#8217;d them down before him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">We are sent</line>
<line form="verse">To give thee from our royal master thanks,</line>
<line form="verse">Only to herald thee into his sight,</line>
<line form="verse">Not pay thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And for an earnest of a greater honor,</line>
<line form="verse">He bade me, from him, call thee Thane of Cawdor;</line>
<line form="verse">In which addition, hail, most worthy thane,</line>
<line form="verse">For it is thine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">What, can the devil speak true?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Thane of Cawdor lives; why do you dress me</line>
<line form="verse">In borrowed robes?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Who was the thane lives yet,</line>
<line form="verse">But under heavy judgment bears that life</line>
<line form="verse">Which he deserves to lose. Whether he was combin&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With those of Norway, or did line the rebel</line>
<line form="verse">With hidden help and vantage, or that with both</line>
<line form="verse">He labor&#8217;d in his country&#8217;s wrack, I know not;</line>
<line form="verse">But treasons capital, confess&#8217;d and prov&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Have overthrown him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Glamis, and Thane of Cawdor!</line>
<line form="verse">The greatest is behind.</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To Rosse and Angus.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Thanks for your pains.</line>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Banquo.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Do you not hope your children shall be kings,</line>
<line form="verse">When those that gave the Thane of Cawdor to me</line>
<line form="verse">Promis&#8217;d no less to them?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Macbeth.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">That, trusted home,</line>
<line form="verse">Might yet enkindle you unto the crown,</line>
<line form="verse">Besides the Thane of Cawdor. But &#8217;tis strange;</line>
<line form="verse">And oftentimes, to win us to our harm,</line>
<line form="verse">The instruments of darkness tell us truths,</line>
<line form="verse">Win us with honest trifles, to betray &#8217;s</line>
<line form="verse">In deepest consequence.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Cousins, a word, I pray you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Two truths are told,</line>
<line form="verse">As happy prologues to the swelling act</line>
<line form="verse">Of the imperial theme.&#8212;I thank you, gentlemen.</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">This supernatural soliciting</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot be ill; cannot be good. If ill,</line>
<line form="verse">Why hath it given me earnest of success,</line>
<line form="verse">Commencing in a truth? I am Thane of Cawdor.</line>
<line form="verse">If good, why do I yield to that suggestion</line>
<line form="verse">Whose horrid image doth unfix my hair</line>
<line form="verse">And make my seated heart knock at my ribs,</line>
<line form="verse">Against the use of nature? Present fears</line>
<line form="verse">Are less than horrible imaginings:</line>
<line form="verse">My thought, whose murder yet is but fantastical,</line>
<line form="verse">Shakes so my single state of man that function</line>
<line form="verse">Is smother&#8217;d in surmise, and nothing is</line>
<line form="verse">But what is not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Look how our partner&#8217;s rapt.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">If chance will have me king, why, chance may crown me</line>
<line form="verse">Without my stir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">New honors come upon him,</line>
<line form="verse">Like our strange garments, cleave not to their mould</line>
<line form="verse">But with the aid of use.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Come what come may,</line>
<line form="verse">Time and the hour runs through the roughest day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Worthy Macbeth, we stay upon your leisure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Give me your favor; my dull brain was wrought</line>
<line form="verse">With things forgotten. Kind gentlemen, your pains</line>
<line form="verse">Are regist&#8217;red where every day I turn</line>
<line form="verse">The leaf to read them. Let us toward the King.</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Banquo.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Think upon what hath chanc&#8217;d; and at more time,</line>
<line form="verse">The interim having weigh&#8217;d it, let us speak</line>
<line form="verse">Our free hearts each to other.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Very gladly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Till then, enough.&#8212;Come, friends.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Forres. A room in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Duncan, Lennox, Malcolm, Donalbain, Attendants, Macbeth, Banquo, Rosse, and Angus)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Malcolm describes to his father Duncan how well the traitor Cawdor died; Duncan points out that people&#8217;s faces do not necessarily reveal their thoughts. Macbeth and Banquo arrive, and the King greets them heartily, promising to lavish rewards on them. Duncan then immediately names Malcolm heir to the throne. Macbeth realizes that this puts Malcolm in the way to the throne. Duncan invites himself to Macbeth&#8217;s castle for dinner, and Macbeth leaves to prepare his household for the King&#8217;s arrival.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Flourish. Enter King Duncan, Lennox, Malcolm, Donalbain, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is execution done on Cawdor? Are not</line>
<line form="verse">Those in commission yet return&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">My liege,</line>
<line form="verse">They are not yet come back. But I have spoke</line>
<line form="verse">With one that saw him die; who did report</line>
<line form="verse">That very frankly he confess&#8217;d his treasons,</line>
<line form="verse">Implor&#8217;d your Highness&#8217; pardon, and set forth</line>
<line form="verse">A deep repentance. Nothing in his life</line>
<line form="verse">Became him like the leaving it. He died</line>
<line form="verse">As one that had been studied in his death,</line>
<line form="verse">To throw away the dearest thing he ow&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">As &#8217;twere a careless trifle.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">There&#8217;s no art</line>
<line form="verse">To find the mind&#8217;s construction in the face:</line>
<line form="verse">He was a gentleman on whom I built</line>
<line form="verse">An absolute trust.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, Banquo, Rosse, and Angus.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">O worthiest cousin!</line>
<line form="verse">The sin of my ingratitude even now</line>
<line form="verse">Was heavy on me. Thou art so far before,</line>
<line form="verse">That swiftest wing of recompense is slow</line>
<line form="verse">To overtake thee. Would thou hadst less deserv&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">That the proportion both of thanks and payment</line>
<line form="verse">Might have been mine! Only I have left to say,</line>
<line form="verse">More is thy due than more than all can pay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The service and the loyalty I owe,</line>
<line form="verse">In doing it, pays itself. Your Highness&#8217; part</line>
<line form="verse">Is to receive our duties; and our duties</line>
<line form="verse">Are to your throne and state children and servants;</line>
<line form="verse">Which do but what they should, by doing every thing</line>
<line form="verse">Safe toward your love and honor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Welcome hither!</line>
<line form="verse">I have begun to plant thee, and will labor</line>
<line form="verse">To make thee full of growing. Noble Banquo,</line>
<line form="verse">That hast no less deserv&#8217;d, nor must be known</line>
<line form="verse">No less to have done so, let me infold thee</line>
<line form="verse">And hold thee to my heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">There if I grow,</line>
<line form="verse">The harvest is your own.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My plenteous joys,</line>
<line form="verse">Wanton in fullness, seek to hide themselves</line>
<line form="verse">In drops of sorrow. Sons, kinsmen, thanes,</line>
<line form="verse">And you whose places are the nearest, know</line>
<line form="verse">We will establish our estate upon</line>
<line form="verse">Our eldest, Malcolm, whom we name hereafter</line>
<line form="verse">The Prince of Cumberland; which honor must</line>
<line form="verse">Not unaccompanied invest him only,</line>
<line form="verse">But signs of nobleness, like stars, shall shine</line>
<line form="verse">On all deservers. From hence to Enverness,</line>
<line form="verse">And bind us further to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The rest is labor, which is not us&#8217;d for you.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll be myself the harbinger, and make joyful</line>
<line form="verse">The hearing of my wife with your approach;</line>
<line form="verse">So humbly take my leave.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My worthy Cawdor!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The Prince of Cumberland! That is a step</line>
<line form="verse">On which I must fall down, or else  o&#8217;erleap,</line>
<line form="verse">For in my way it lies. Stars, hide your fires,</line>
<line form="verse">Let not light see my black and deep desires;</line>
<line form="verse">The eye wink at the hand; yet let that be</line>
<line form="verse">Which the eye fears, when it is done, to see.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">True, worthy Banquo! He is full so valiant,</line>
<line form="verse">And in his commendations I am fed;</line>
<line form="verse">It is a banquet to me. Let&#8217;s after him,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose care is gone before to bid us welcome:</line>
<line form="verse">It is a peerless kinsman.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Flourish. Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Inverness. Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lady Macbeth, Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger, Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lady Macbeth reads the letter that Macbeth has sent her detailing his meeting with the witches. She immediately sees where the prophecy leads. She realizes, however, that Macbeth would rather simply become King by chance rather than play for the throne, and that he is not a natural hypocrite. She impatiently awaits his arrival so that she may convince him otherwise. Hearing that the King will be arriving that evening, she grasps the possibilities at once. She begs the spirits of the night to block all of her compassion so that she may be cruel enough to go through with her plan. Macbeth arrives, and she begins to work on him at once, offering to take care of everything; but he promises only that they shall discuss the matter further.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth&#8217;s Wife alone, with a letter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="prose"><recite>&#8220;They met me in the day of success; and I have learn&#8217;d by the perfect&#8217;st report, they have more in them than mortal knowledge. When I burnt in desire to question them further, they made themselves air, into which they vanish&#8217;d. Whiles I stood rapt in the wonder of it, came missives from the King, who all-hail&#8217;d me &#8220;Thane of Cawdor,&#8221; by which title, before, these we&#239;rd sisters saluted me, and referr&#8217;d me to the coming on of time with &#8220;Hail, King that shalt be!&#8221; This have I thought good to deliver thee, my dearest partner of greatness, that thou mightst not lose the dues of rejoicing by being ignorant of what greatness is promis&#8217;d thee. Lay it to thy heart, and farewell.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">Glamis thou art, and Cawdor, and shalt be</line>
<line form="verse">What thou art promis&#8217;d. Yet do I fear thy nature,</line>
<line form="verse">It is too full  o&#8217; th&#8217; milk of human kindness</line>
<line form="verse">To catch the nearest way. Thou wouldst be great,</line>
<line form="verse">Art not without ambition, but without</line>
<line form="verse">The illness should attend it. What thou wouldst highly,</line>
<line form="verse">That wouldst thou holily; wouldst not play false,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet wouldst wrongly win. Thou&#8217;ldst have, great Glamis,</line>
<line form="verse">That which cries, &#8220;Thus thou must do,&#8221; if thou have it;</line>
<line form="verse">And that which rather thou dost fear to do</line>
<line form="verse">Than wishest should be undone. Hie thee hither,</line>
<line form="verse">That I may pour my spirits in thine ear,</line>
<line form="verse">And chastise with the valor of my tongue</line>
<line form="verse">All that impedes thee from the golden round,</line>
<line form="verse">Which fate and metaphysical aid doth seem</line>
<line form="verse">To have thee crown&#8217;d withal.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What is your tidings?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The King comes here tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Thou&#8217;rt mad to say it!</line>
<line form="verse">Is not thy master with him? Who, were&#8217;t so,</line>
<line form="verse">Would have inform&#8217;d for preparation.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So please you, it is true; our thane is coming.</line>
<line form="verse">One of my fellows had the speed of him,</line>
<line form="verse">Who, almost dead for breath, had scarcely more</line>
<line form="verse">Than would make up his message.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Give him tending,</line>
<line form="verse">He brings great news.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">The raven himself is hoarse</line>
<line form="verse">That croaks the fatal entrance of Duncan</line>
<line form="verse">Under my battlements. Come, you spirits</line>
<line form="verse">That tend on mortal thoughts, unsex me here,</line>
<line form="verse">And fill me from the crown to the toe topful</line>
<line form="verse">Of direst cruelty! Make thick my blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Stop up th&#8217; access and passage to remorse,</line>
<line form="verse">That no compunctious visitings of nature</line>
<line form="verse">Shake my fell purpose, nor keep peace between</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; effect and it! Come to my woman&#8217;s breasts,</line>
<line form="verse">And take my milk for gall, you murd&#8217;ring ministers,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherever in your sightless substances</line>
<line form="verse">You wait on nature&#8217;s mischief! Come, thick night,</line>
<line form="verse">And pall thee in the dunnest smoke of hell,</line>
<line form="verse">That my keen knife see not the wound it makes,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor heaven peep through the blanket of the dark</line>
<line form="verse">To cry, &#8220;Hold, hold!&#8221;</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">Great Glamis! Worthy Cawdor!</line>
<line form="verse">Greater than both, by the all-hail hereafter!</line>
<line form="verse">Thy letters have transported me beyond</line>
<line form="verse">This ignorant present, and I feel now</line>
<line form="verse">The future in the instant.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My dearest love,</line>
<line form="verse">Duncan comes here tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">And when goes hence?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow, as he purposes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">O, never</line>
<line form="verse">Shall sun that morrow see!</line>
<line form="verse">Your face, my thane, is as a book, where men</line>
<line form="verse">May read strange matters. To beguile the time,</line>
<line form="verse">Look like the time; bear welcome in your eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Your hand, your tongue; look like th&#8217; innocent flower,</line>
<line form="verse">But be the serpent under&#8217;t. He that&#8217;s coming</line>
<line form="verse">Must be provided for; and you shall put</line>
<line form="verse">This night&#8217;s great business into my dispatch,</line>
<line form="verse">Which shall to all our nights and days to come</line>
<line form="verse">Give solely sovereign sway and masterdom.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We will speak further.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Only look up clear:</line>
<line form="verse">To alter favor ever is to fear.</line>
<line form="verse">Leave all the rest to me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Before Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(King Duncan, Malcolm, Donalbain, Banquo, Lennox, Macduff, Rosse, Angus, Attendants, Lady Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Duncan admires Macbeth&#8217;s castle. Lady Macbeth greets the King, his sons, generals, and attendants in courteous fashion, bland and obsequious, never giving a hint of her intentions as the kind old man promises to shower favors on Macbeth.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Hoboys and torches. Enter King Duncan, Malcolm, Donalbain, Banquo, Lennox, Macduff, Rosse, Angus, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This castle hath a pleasant seat, the air</line>
<line form="verse">Nimbly and sweetly recommends itself</line>
<line form="verse">Unto our gentle senses.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">This guest of summer,</line>
<line form="verse">The temple-haunting marlet, does approve,</line>
<line form="verse">By his lov&#8217;d mansionry, that the heaven&#8217;s breath</line>
<line form="verse">Smells wooingly here; no jutty, frieze,</line>
<line form="verse">Buttress, nor coign of vantage, but this bird</line>
<line form="verse">Hath made his pendant bed and procreant cradle.</line>
<line form="verse">Where they most breed and haunt, I have observ&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The air is delicate.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">See, see, our honor&#8217;d hostess!</line>
<line form="verse">The love that follows us sometime is our trouble,</line>
<line form="verse">Which still we thank as love. Herein I teach you</line>
<line form="verse">How you shall bid God &#8217;ield us for your pains,</line>
<line form="verse">And thank us for your trouble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">All our service</line>
<line form="verse">In every point twice done, and then done double,</line>
<line form="verse">Were poor and single business to contend</line>
<line form="verse">Against those honors deep and broad wherewith</line>
<line form="verse">Your Majesty loads our house. For those of old,</line>
<line form="verse">And the late dignities heap&#8217;d up to them,</line>
<line form="verse">We rest your ermites.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Where&#8217;s the Thane of Cawdor?</line>
<line form="verse">We cours&#8217;d him at the heels, and had a purpose</line>
<line form="verse">To be his purveyor; but he rides well,</line>
<line form="verse">And his great love, sharp as his spur, hath holp him</line>
<line form="verse">To his home before us. Fair and noble hostess,</line>
<line form="verse">We are your guest tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Your servants ever</line>
<line form="verse">Have theirs, themselves, and what is theirs, in compt,</line>
<line form="verse">To make their audit at your Highness&#8217; pleasure,</line>
<line form="verse">Still to return your own.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Give me your hand.</line>
<line form="verse">Conduct me to mine host, we love him highly,</line>
<line form="verse">And shall continue our graces towards him.</line>
<line form="verse">By your leave, hostess.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="7">
<scenetitle>Scene 7</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A room in Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Sewer, Servants, Macbeth, Lady Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth openly considers murdering the King, but the thought gnaws at his conscience, as the King is his kinsman and his guest, not to mention a good and mild King beloved by all. He realizes that he has no excuse or rationalization for the deed other than his own desire to be King. Lady Macbeth joins him and is shocked when he announces that he will not go through with the deed. She accuses him of cowardice, unmanliness, and oath-breaking, and he reveals his fear of failure. She points out how easy it will be to murder Duncan and frame his attendants. He reconciles himself to murder.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Hoboys, torches. Enter a Sewer and divers Servants with dishes and service over the stage. Then enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If it were done, when &#8217;tis done, then &#8217;twere well</line>
<line form="verse">It were done quickly. If th&#8217; assassination</line>
<line form="verse">Could trammel up the consequence, and catch</line>
<line form="verse">With his surcease, success; that but this blow</line>
<line form="verse">Might be the be-all and the end-all&#8212;here,</line>
<line form="verse">But here, upon this bank and shoal of time,</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ld jump the life to come. But in these cases</line>
<line form="verse">We still have judgment here, that we but teach</line>
<line form="verse">Bloody instructions, which, being taught, return</line>
<line form="verse">To plague th&#8217; inventor. This even-handed justice</line>
<line form="verse">Commends th&#8217; ingredience of our poison&#8217;d chalice</line>
<line form="verse">To our own lips. He&#8217;s here in double trust:</line>
<line form="verse">First, as I am his kinsman and his subject,</line>
<line form="verse">Strong both against the deed; then, as his host,</line>
<line form="verse">Who should against his murderer shut the door,</line>
<line form="verse">Not bear the knife myself. Besides, this Duncan</line>
<line form="verse">Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been</line>
<line form="verse">So clear in his great office, that his virtues</line>
<line form="verse">Will plead like angels, trumpet-tongu&#8217;d, against</line>
<line form="verse">The deep damnation of his taking-off;</line>
<line form="verse">And pity, like a naked new-born babe,</line>
<line form="verse">Striding the blast, or heaven&#8217;s cherubin, hors&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the sightless couriers of the air,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall blow the horrid deed in every eye,</line>
<line form="verse">That tears shall drown the wind. I have no spur</line>
<line form="verse">To prick the sides of my intent, but only</line>
<line form="verse">Vaulting ambition, which o&#8217;erleaps itself,</line>
<line form="verse">And falls on th&#8217; other&#8212;</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">How now? What news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He has almost supp&#8217;d. Why have you left the chamber?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hath he ask&#8217;d for me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Know you not he has?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We will proceed no further in this business:</line>
<line form="verse">He hath honor&#8217;d me of late, and I have bought</line>
<line form="verse">Golden opinions from all sorts of people,</line>
<line form="verse">Which would be worn now in their newest gloss,</line>
<line form="verse">Not cast aside so soon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Was the hope drunk</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein you dress&#8217;d yourself? Hath it slept since?</line>
<line form="verse">And wakes it now to look so green and pale</line>
<line form="verse">At what it did so freely? From this time</line>
<line form="verse">Such I account thy love. Art thou afeard</line>
<line form="verse">To be the same in thine own act and valor</line>
<line form="verse">As thou art in desire? Wouldst thou have that</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou esteem&#8217;st the ornament of life,</line>
<line form="verse">And live a coward in thine own esteem,</line>
<line form="verse">Letting &#8220;I dare not&#8221; wait upon &#8220;I would,&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Like the poor cat i&#8217; th&#8217; adage?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Prithee peace!</line>
<line form="verse">I dare do all that may become a man;</line>
<line form="verse">Who dares do more is none.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What beast was&#8217;t then</line>
<line form="verse">That made you break this enterprise to me?</line>
<line form="verse">When you durst do it, then you were a man;</line>
<line form="verse">And to be more than what you were, you would</line>
<line form="verse">Be so much more the man. Nor time, nor place,</line>
<line form="verse">Did then adhere, and yet you would make both:</line>
<line form="verse">They have made themselves, and that their fitness now</line>
<line form="verse">Does unmake you. I have given suck, and know</line>
<line form="verse">How tender &#8217;tis to love the babe that milks me;</line>
<line form="verse">I would, while it was smiling in my face,</line>
<line form="verse">Have pluck&#8217;d my nipple from his boneless gums,</line>
<line form="verse">And dash&#8217;d the brains out, had I so sworn as you</line>
<line form="verse">Have done to this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">If we should fail?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">We fail?</line>
<line form="verse">But screw your courage to the sticking place,</line>
<line form="verse">And we&#8217;ll not fail. When Duncan is asleep</line>
<line form="verse">(Whereto the rather shall his day&#8217;s hard journey</line>
<line form="verse">Soundly invite him), his two chamberlains</line>
<line form="verse">Will I with wine and wassail so convince,</line>
<line form="verse">That memory, the warder of the brain,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall be a fume, and the receipt of reason</line>
<line form="verse">A limbeck only. When in swinish sleep</line>
<line form="verse">Their drenched natures lies as in a death,</line>
<line form="verse">What cannot you and I perform upon</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; unguarded Duncan? What not put upon</line>
<line form="verse">His spungy officers, who shall bear the guilt</line>
<line form="verse">Of our great quell?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Bring forth men-children only!</line>
<line form="verse">For thy undaunted mettle should compose</line>
<line form="verse">Nothing but males. Will it not be receiv&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">When we have mark&#8217;d with blood those sleepy two</line>
<line form="verse">Of his own chamber, and us&#8217;d their very daggers,</line>
<line form="verse">That they have done&#8217;t?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Who dares receive it other,</line>
<line form="verse">As we shall make our griefs and clamor roar</line>
<line form="verse">Upon his death?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I am settled, and bend up</line>
<line form="verse">Each corporal agent to this terrible feat.</line>
<line form="verse">Away, and mock the time with fairest show:</line>
<line form="verse">False face must hide what the false heart doth know.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The court of Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Banquo, Fleance, Macbeth, Servant)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Banquo and his son Fleance are on their way to bed after the very late end of the night&#8217;s feasting. Banquo is uneasy. Met by Macbeth, Banquo hands over to him a diamond from Duncan. Banquo reveals that he has dreamt of the three weird sisters; Macbeth insists that he is not thinking of them, but asks that he and Banquo may have some further talk on the matter. Banquo agrees, while subtly making it clear that he will have no part in any action against Duncan. Left alone, preparing to go in to murder Duncan, Macbeth hallucinates a dagger in the air before him, on which he soon sees blood running. He summons up his courage, and hearing the bell toll goes in to end Duncan&#8217;s life.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Banquo, and Fleance with a torch before him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How goes the night, boy?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The moon is down; I have not heard the clock.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And she goes down at twelve.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I take&#8217;t, &#8217;tis later, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hold, take my sword. There&#8217;s husbandry in heaven,</line>
<line form="verse">Their candles are all out. Take thee that too.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Gives him his belt and dagger.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">A heavy summons lies like lead upon me,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet I would not sleep. Merciful powers,</line>
<line form="verse">Restrain in me the cursed thoughts that nature</line>
<line form="verse">Gives way to in repose!</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, and a Servant with a torch.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">Give me my sword.</line>
<line form="verse">Who&#8217;s there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, sir, not yet at rest? The King&#8217;s a-bed.</line>
<line form="verse">He hath been in unusual pleasure, and</line>
<line form="verse">Sent forth great largess to your offices.</line>
<line form="verse">This diamond he greets your wife withal,</line>
<line form="verse">By the name of most kind hostess, and shut up</line>
<line form="verse">In measureless content.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Being unprepar&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Our will became the servant to defect,</line>
<line form="verse">Which else should free have wrought.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">All&#8217;s well.</line>
<line form="verse">I dreamt last night of the three we&#239;rd sisters:</line>
<line form="verse">To you they have show&#8217;d some truth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">I think not of them;</line>
<line form="verse">Yet when we can entreat an hour to serve,</line>
<line form="verse">We would spend it in some words upon that business,</line>
<line form="verse">If you would grant the time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">At your kind&#8217;st leisure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If you shall cleave to my consent, when &#8217;tis,</line>
<line form="verse">It shall make honor for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">So I lose none</line>
<line form="verse">In seeking to augment it, but still keep</line>
<line form="verse">My bosom franchis&#8217;d and allegiance clear,</line>
<line form="verse">I shall be counsell&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Good repose the while!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, sir; the like to you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Banquo with Fleance.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go bid thy mistress, when my drink is ready,</line>
<line form="verse">She strike upon the bell. Get thee to bed.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Is this a dagger which I see before me,</line>
<line form="verse">The handle toward my hand? Come, let me clutch thee:</line>
<line form="verse">I have thee not, and yet I see thee still.</line>
<line form="verse">Art thou not, fatal vision, sensible</line>
<line form="verse">To feeling as to sight? Or art thou but</line>
<line form="verse">A dagger of the mind, a false creation,</line>
<line form="verse">Proceeding from the heat-oppressed brain?</line>
<line form="verse">I see thee yet, in form as palpable</line>
<line form="verse">As this which now I draw.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou marshal&#8217;st me the way that I was going,</line>
<line form="verse">And such an instrument I was to use.</line>
<line form="verse">Mine eyes are made the fools  o&#8217; th&#8217; other senses,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else worth all the rest. I see thee still;</line>
<line form="verse">And on thy blade and dudgeon gouts of blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Which was not so before. There&#8217;s no such thing:</line>
<line form="verse">It is the bloody business which informs</line>
<line form="verse">Thus to mine eyes. Now  o&#8217;er the one half world</line>
<line form="verse">Nature seems dead, and wicked dreams abuse</line>
<line form="verse">The curtain&#8217;d sleep; witchcraft celebrates</line>
<line form="verse">Pale Hecat&#8217;s off&#8217;rings; and wither&#8217;d Murder,</line>
<line form="verse">Alarum&#8217;d by his sentinel, the wolf,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose howl&#8217;s his watch, thus with his stealthy pace,</line>
<line form="verse">With Tarquin&#8217;s ravishing strides, towards his design</line>
<line form="verse">Moves like a ghost. Thou sure and firm-set earth,</line>
<line form="verse">Hear not my steps, which way they walk, for fear</line>
<line form="verse">The very stones prate of my whereabout,</line>
<line form="verse">And take the present horror from the time,</line>
<line form="verse">Which now suits with it. Whiles I threat, he lives:</line>
<line form="verse">Words to the heat of deeds too cold breath gives.</line>

<stagedir type="action">A bell rings.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">I go, and it is done; the bell invites me.</line>
<line form="verse">Hear it not, Duncan, for it is a knell,</line>
<line form="verse">That summons thee to heaven or to hell.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The court of Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lady Macbeth, Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lady Macbeth waits for Macbeth to return; she is nervous, realizing that success gives them everything, but failure will be the end of them. Macbeth comes out of Duncan&#8217;s room, his hands covered in blood, nerve-racked and terrified. Lady Macbeth tries to steel him as he talks of how he tried to say &#8220;Amen&#8221; to the prayer of one of the grooms, but could not, and how he thought he heard a voice announcing that since he had killed the sleeping King, he himself would never sleep again. His wife tries to snap him out of it, sending him to wash his hands, and discovering that he brought the murder weapons with him. Incensed, she takes the daggers back into the murder chamber after Macbeth refuses to go in there again. There is a knocking at the gate that startles Macbeth as Lady Macbeth returns, her hands now bloody as well. She insists that all they need do is wash their hands, and all will be well. They retire to their room to get undressed so that the new arrivals will not guess that they have been up all night.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That which hath made them drunk hath made me bold;</line>
<line form="verse">What hath quench&#8217;d them hath given me fire. Hark! Peace!</line>
<line form="verse">It was the owl that shriek&#8217;d, the fatal bellman,</line>
<line form="verse">Which gives the stern&#8217;st good-night. He is about it:</line>
<line form="verse">The doors are open; and the surfeited grooms</line>
<line form="verse">Do mock their charge with snores. I have drugg&#8217;d their possets,</line>
<line form="verse">That death and nature do contend about them,</line>
<line form="verse">Whether they live or die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Who&#8217;s there? What ho?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Alack, I am afraid they have awak&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And &#8217;tis not done; th&#8217; attempt, and not the deed,</line>
<line form="verse">Confounds us. Hark! I laid their daggers ready,</line>
<line form="verse">He could not miss &#8217;em. Had he not resembled</line>
<line form="verse">My father as he slept, I had done&#8217;t.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="7">My husband!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have done the deed. Didst thou not hear a noise?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I heard the owl scream and the crickets cry.</line>
<line form="verse">Did not you speak?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">When?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">As I descended?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hark! Who lies i&#8217; th&#8217; second chamber?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Donalbain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">This is a sorry sight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Looking on his hands.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A foolish thought, to say a sorry sight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s one did laugh in &#8217;s sleep, and one cried, &#8220;Murder!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">That they did wake each other. I stood and heard them;</line>
<line form="verse">But they did say their prayers, and address&#8217;d them</line>
<line form="verse">Again to sleep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">There are two lodg&#8217;d together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">One cried, &#8220;God bless us!&#8221; and &#8220;Amen!&#8221; the other,</line>
<line form="verse">As they had seen me with these hangman&#8217;s hands.</line>
<line form="verse">List&#8217;ning their fear, I could not say &#8220;Amen,&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">When they did say &#8220;God bless us!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Consider it not so deeply.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But wherefore could not I pronounce &#8220;Amen&#8221;?</line>
<line form="verse">I had most need of blessing, and &#8220;Amen&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Stuck in my throat.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">These deeds must not be thought</line>
<line form="verse">After these ways; so, it will make us mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Methought I heard a voice cry, &#8220;Sleep no more!</line>
<line form="verse">Macbeth does murder sleep&#8221;&#8212;the innocent sleep,</line>
<line form="verse">Sleep that knits up the ravell&#8217;d sleave of care,</line>
<line form="verse">The death of each day&#8217;s life, sore labor&#8217;s bath,</line>
<line form="verse">Balm of hurt minds, great nature&#8217;s second course,</line>
<line form="verse">Chief nourisher in life&#8217;s feast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What do you mean?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Still it cried, &#8220;Sleep no more!&#8221; to all the house;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Glamis hath murder&#8217;d sleep, and therefore Cawdor</line>
<line form="verse">Shall sleep no more&#8212;Macbeth shall sleep no more.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who was it that thus cried? Why, worthy thane,</line>
<line form="verse">You do unbend your noble strength, to think</line>
<line form="verse">So brain-sickly of things. Go get some water,</line>
<line form="verse">And wash this filthy witness from your hand.</line>
<line form="verse">Why did you bring these daggers from the place?</line>
<line form="verse">They must lie there. Go carry them, and smear</line>
<line form="verse">The sleepy grooms with blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I&#8217;ll go no more.</line>
<line form="verse">I am afraid to think what I have done;</line>
<line form="verse">Look on&#8217;t again I dare not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Infirm of purpose!</line>
<line form="verse">Give me the daggers. The sleeping and the dead</line>
<line form="verse">Are but as pictures; &#8217;tis the eye of childhood</line>
<line form="verse">That fears a painted devil. If he do bleed,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll gild the faces of the grooms withal,</line>
<line form="verse">For it must seem their guilt.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="action">Knock within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Whence is that knocking?</line>
<line form="verse">How is&#8217;t with me, when every noise appalls me?</line>
<line form="verse">What hands are here? Hah! They pluck out mine eyes.</line>
<line form="verse">Will all great Neptune&#8217;s ocean wash this blood</line>
<line form="verse">Clean from my hand? No; this my hand will rather</line>
<line form="verse">The multitudinous seas incarnadine,</line>
<line form="verse">Making the green one red.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My hands are of your color; but I shame</line>
<line form="verse">To wear a heart so white.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">I hear a knocking</line>
<line form="verse">At the south entry. Retire we to our chamber.</line>
<line form="verse">A little water clears us of this deed;</line>
<line form="verse">How easy is it then! Your constancy</line>
<line form="verse">Hath left you unattended.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">Hark, more knocking.</line>
<line form="verse">Get on your night-gown, lest occasion call us</line>
<line form="verse">And show us to be watchers. Be not lost</line>
<line form="verse">So poorly in your thoughts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To know my deed, &#8217;twere best not know myself.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Wake Duncan with thy knocking! I would thou couldst!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The court of Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Porter, Macduff, Lennox, Macbeth, Lady Macbeth, Banquo, Rosse, Malcolm, Donalbain)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Still drunk after last night&#8217;s reveling, the castle&#8217;s porter comes to open the gate to the new arrivals still pounding at the gate, imagining himself the porter of hell as he does so. The noblemen Macduff and Lennox come in, having orders to meet the King early. Macbeth joins them, and as Macduff goes to wake the King, Lennox talks to Macbeth about the wild storm the previous night, and odd portents that occurred. Having discovered the murder, Macduff reenters in shock, and wildly begins to rouse the house. Lady Macbeth comes in, pretending to wonder what all the commotion is about, and expresses horror at the King being murdered in her house. Slowly the other members of the court arrive. Macbeth, who had gone in with Lennox to witness the deed, returns. He has killed the grooms and begs pardon for having done so, saying that he lost his temper at their evident guilt and executed summary justice on them. Lady Macbeth faints, or pretends to faint, before he can be pressed too far on this point. The nobles agree to get properly dressed and discuss the matter in full. Left alone, Duncan&#8217;s sons Malcolm and Donalbain agree that they will not trust any of the nobles, and decide to flee the country, one to England and the other to Ireland, to escape the risk that they both be murdered as well.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Porter. Knocking within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PORT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here&#8217;s a knocking indeed! If a man were porter of Hell Gate, he should have old turning the key.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Knock, knock, knock! Who&#8217;s there, i&#8217; th&#8217; name of Belzebub? Here&#8217;s a farmer, that hang&#8217;d himself on th&#8217; expectation of plenty. Come in time! Have napkins enow about you, here You&#8217;ll sweat for&#8217;t.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Knock, knock! Who&#8217;s there, in th&#8217; other devil&#8217;s name? Faith, here&#8217;s an equivocator, that could swear in both the scales against either scale, who committed treason enough for God&#8217;s sake, yet could not equivocate to heaven. O, come in, equivocator.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Knock, knock, knock! Who&#8217;s there? Faith, here&#8217;s an English tailor come hither for stealing out of a French hose. Come in, tailor, here you may roast your goose.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Knock, knock! Never at quiet! What are you? But this place is too cold for hell. I&#8217;ll devil&#8212;porter it no further. I had thought to have let in some of all professions that go the primrose way to th&#8217; everlasting bonfire.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Anon, anon!</line>
<stagedir type="action">Opens the gate.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">I pray you remember the porter.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff and Lennox.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Was it so late, friend, ere you went to bed,</line>
<line form="verse">That you do lie so late?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PORT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Faith, sir, we were carousing till the second cock; and drink, sir, is a great provoker of three things.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What three things does drink especially provoke?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PORT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, nose-painting, sleep, and urine. Lechery, sir, it provokes, and unprovokes: it provokes the desire, but it takes away the performance. Therefore much drink may be said to be an equivocator with lechery: it makes him, and it mars him; it sets him on, and it takes him off; it persuades him, and disheartens him; makes him stand to, and not stand to; in conclusion, equivocates him in a sleep, and giving him the lie, leaves him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I believe drink gave thee the lie last night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PORT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That it did, sir, i&#8217; the very throat on me; but I requited him for his lie, and (I think) being too strong for him, though he took up my legs sometime, yet I made a shift to cast him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is thy master stirring?</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">Our knocking has awak&#8217;d him; here he comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good morrow, noble sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Good morrow, both.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is the King stirring, worthy thane?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Not yet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He did command me to call timely on him,</line>
<line form="verse">I have almost slipp&#8217;d the hour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I&#8217;ll bring you to him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know this is a joyful trouble to you;</line>
<line form="verse">But yet &#8217;tis one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The labor we delight in physics pain.</line>
<line form="verse">This is the door.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I&#8217;ll make so bold to call,</line>
<line form="verse">For &#8217;tis my limited service.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Macduff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Goes the King hence today?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">He does; he did appoint so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The night has been unruly. Where we lay,</line>
<line form="verse">Our chimneys were blown down, and (as they say)</line>
<line form="verse">Lamentings heard i&#8217; th&#8217; air; strange screams of death,</line>
<line form="verse">And prophesying, with accents terrible,</line>
<line form="verse">Of dire combustion and confus&#8217;d events</line>
<line form="verse">New hatch&#8217;d to th&#8217; woeful time. The obscure bird</line>
<line form="verse">Clamor&#8217;d the livelong night. Some say, the earth</line>
<line form="verse">Was feverous, and did shake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">&#8217;Twas a rough night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My young remembrance cannot parallel</line>
<line form="verse">A fellow to it.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O horror, horror, horror! Tongue nor heart</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot conceive nor name thee!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. AND LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What&#8217;s the matter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Confusion now hath made his masterpiece!</line>
<line form="verse">Most sacrilegious murder hath broke ope</line>
<line form="verse">The Lord&#8217;s anointed temple, and stole thence</line>
<line form="verse">The life  o&#8217; th&#8217; building!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What is&#8217;t you say&#8212;the life?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mean you his Majesty?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Approach the chamber, and destroy your sight</line>
<line form="verse">With a new Gorgon. Do not bid me speak;</line>
<line form="verse">See, and then speak yourselves.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Macbeth and Lennox.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="7">Awake, awake!</line>
<line form="verse">Ring the alarum-bell! Murder and treason!</line>
<line form="verse">Banquo and Donalbain! Malcolm, awake!</line>
<line form="verse">Shake off this downy sleep, death&#8217;s counterfeit,</line>
<line form="verse">And look on death itself! Up, up, and see</line>
<line form="verse">The great doom&#8217;s image! Malcolm! Banquo!</line>
<line form="verse">As from your graves rise up, and walk like sprites,</line>
<line form="verse">To countenance this horror! Ring the bell.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Bell rings.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s the business,</line>
<line form="verse">That such a hideous trumpet calls to parley</line>
<line form="verse">The sleepers of the house? Speak, speak!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">O gentle lady,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis not for you to hear what I can speak:</line>
<line form="verse">The repetition in a woman&#8217;s ear</line>
<line form="verse">Would murder as it fell.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Banquo.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="5">O Banquo, Banquo,</line>
<line form="verse">Our royal master&#8217;s murder&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Woe, alas!</line>
<line form="verse">What, in our house?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Too cruel any where.</line>
<line form="verse">Dear Duff, I prithee contradict thyself,</line>
<line form="verse">And say, it is not so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, Lennox, Rosse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Had I but died an hour before this chance,</line>
<line form="verse">I had liv&#8217;d a blessed time; for from this instant</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s nothing serious in mortality:</line>
<line form="verse">All is but toys: renown and grace is dead,</line>
<line form="verse">The wine of life is drawn, and the mere lees</line>
<line form="verse">Is left this vault to brag of.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Malcolm and Donalbain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is amiss?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">You are, and do not know&#8217;t.</line>
<line form="verse">The spring, the head, the fountain of your blood</line>
<line form="verse">Is stopp&#8217;d, the very source of it is stopp&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your royal father&#8217;s murder&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">O, by whom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Those of his chamber, as it seem&#8217;d, had done&#8217;t.</line>
<line form="verse">Their hands and faces were all badg&#8217;d with blood;</line>
<line form="verse">So were their daggers, which unwip&#8217;d we found</line>
<line form="verse">Upon their pillows. They star&#8217;d and were distracted;</line>
<line form="verse">No man&#8217;s life was to be trusted with them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, yet I do repent me of my fury,</line>
<line form="verse">That I did kill them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Wherefore did you so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who can be wise, amaz&#8217;d, temp&#8217;rate, and furious,</line>
<line form="verse">Loyal, and neutral, in a moment? No man.</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; expedition of my violent love</line>
<line form="verse">Outrun the pauser, reason. Here lay Duncan,</line>
<line form="verse">His silver skin lac&#8217;d with his golden blood,</line>
<line form="verse">And his gash&#8217;d stabs look&#8217;d like a breach in nature</line>
<line form="verse">For ruin&#8217;s wasteful entrance; there, the murderers,</line>
<line form="verse">Steep&#8217;d in the colors of their trade, their daggers</line>
<line form="verse">Unmannerly breech&#8217;d with gore. Who could refrain,</line>
<line form="verse">That had a heart to love, and in that heart</line>
<line form="verse">Courage to make &#8217;s love known?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Help me hence, ho!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Look to the lady.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Donalbain.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why do we hold our tongues,</line>
<line form="verse">That most may claim this argument for ours?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DON.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Malcolm.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What should be spoken here, where our fate,</line>
<line form="verse">Hid in an auger-hole, may rush and seize us?</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s away,</line>
<line form="verse">Our tears are not yet brew&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Donalbain.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Nor our strong sorrow</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the foot of motion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Look to the lady.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Lady Macbeth is carried out.</stagedir>

<line form="verse">And when we have our naked frailties hid,</line>
<line form="verse">That suffer in exposure, let us meet</line>
<line form="verse">And question this most bloody piece of work,</line>
<line form="verse">To know it further. Fears and scruples shake us.</line>
<line form="verse">In the great hand of God I stand, and thence</line>
<line form="verse">Against the undivulg&#8217;d pretense I fight</line>
<line form="verse">Of treasonous malice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And so do I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">So all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s briefly put on manly readiness,</line>
<line form="verse">And meet i&#8217; th&#8217; hall together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Well contented.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt all but Malcolm and Donalbain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What will you do? Let&#8217;s not consort with them;</line>
<line form="verse">To show an unfelt sorrow is an office</line>
<line form="verse">Which the false man does easy. I&#8217;ll to England.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To Ireland, I; our separated fortune</line>
<line form="verse">Shall keep us both the safer. Where we are,</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s daggers in men&#8217;s smiles; the near in blood,</line>
<line form="verse">The nearer bloody.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">This murderous shaft that&#8217;s shot</line>
<line form="verse">Hath not yet lighted, and our safest way</line>
<line form="verse">Is to avoid the aim. Therefore to horse,</line>
<line form="verse">And let us not be dainty of leave-taking,</line>
<line form="verse">But shift away. There&#8217;s warrant in that theft</line>
<line form="verse">Which steals itself, when there&#8217;s no mercy left.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Outside Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Rosse, Old Man, Macduff)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Ross and an old man discuss the terrible portents that have occurred, including the fact that Duncan&#8217;s horses have eaten one another, that the day is dark, and that a tiny owl killed a huge hunting hawk. Macduff greets Ross and tells him that Malcolm and Donalbain have fled and are therefore suspected of the murder. Ross realizes that Macbeth is the most likely heir, and decides to go to his coronation, though Macduff chooses to simply go home.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Rosse with an Old Man.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD MAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Threescore and ten I can remember well,</line>
<line form="verse">Within the volume of which time I have seen</line>
<line form="verse">Hours dreadful and things strange; but this sore night</line>
<line form="verse">Hath trifled former knowings.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Ha, good father,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou seest the heavens, as troubled with man&#8217;s act,</line>
<line form="verse">Threatens his bloody stage. By th&#8217; clock &#8217;tis day,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet dark night strangles the travelling lamp.</line>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t night&#8217;s predominance, or the day&#8217;s shame,</line>
<line form="verse">That darkness does the face of earth entomb,</line>
<line form="verse">When living light should kiss it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD MAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">&#8217;Tis unnatural,</line>
<line form="verse">Even like the deed that&#8217;s done. On Tuesday last,</line>
<line form="verse">A falcon, tow&#8217;ring in her pride of place,</line>
<line form="verse">Was by a mousing owl hawk&#8217;d at, and kill&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And Duncan&#8217;s horses (a thing most strange and certain),</line>
<line form="verse">Beauteous and swift, the minions of their race,</line>
<line form="verse">Turn&#8217;d wild in nature, broke their stalls, flung out,</line>
<line form="verse">Contending &#8217;gainst obedience, as they would make</line>
<line form="verse">War with mankind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD MAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">&#8217;Tis said, they eat each other.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They did so&#8212;to th&#8217; amazement of mine eyes</line>
<line form="verse">That look&#8217;d upon&#8217;t.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Here comes the good Macduff.</line>
<line form="verse">How goes the world, sir, now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Why, see you not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t known who did this more than bloody deed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Those that Macbeth hath slain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Alas the day,</line>
<line form="verse">What good could they pretend?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">They were suborned.</line>
<line form="verse">Malcolm and Donalbain, the King&#8217;s two sons,</line>
<line form="verse">Are stol&#8217;n away and fled, which puts upon them</line>
<line form="verse">Suspicion of the deed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">&#8217;Gainst nature still!</line>
<line form="verse">Thriftless ambition, that will ravin up</line>
<line form="verse">Thine own live&#8217;s means! Then &#8217;tis most like</line>
<line form="verse">The sovereignty will fall upon Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He is already nam&#8217;d, and gone to Scone</line>
<line form="verse">To be invested.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Where is Duncan&#8217;s body?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Carried to Colmekill,</line>
<line form="verse">The sacred store-house of his predecessors</line>
<line form="verse">And guardian of their bones.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Will you to Scone?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, cousin, I&#8217;ll to Fife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Well, I will thither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, may you see things well done there: <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest our old robes sit easier than our new!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD MAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God&#8217;s benison go with you, and with those</line>
<line form="verse">That would make good of bad, and friends of foes!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt omnes.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Forres. The palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Banquo, Macbeth, Lady Macbeth, Lennox, Rosse, Lords, Attendants, Servant, Two Murderers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Banquo sees that the witches&#8217; prophecy is fulfilled, and suspects that Macbeth helped it along a little. But he cannot forget the part about his own sons becoming kings rather than Macbeth&#8217;s. Macbeth enters with his train and invites Banquo to a feast that evening; Banquo says he will spend the time till then going for a ride with Fleance. Macbeth dismisses everyone, and calls for some men he spoke to the day before. As he waits for them, he ruminates on the same subject as Banquo, the insufferable idea that Banquo&#8217;s sons, not his, will succeed to the throne, and that therefore Macbeth has damned himself for Banquo&#8217;s good. The two men he has called for enter; they are sworn enemies of Banquo, and Macbeth brings them to agree to murder the man, explaining that he cannot do it openly himself. He lets them know where they can find them, insisting that they must kill Fleance as well.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Banquo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou hast it now: King, Cawdor, Glamis, all,</line>
<line form="verse">As the we&#239;rd women promis&#8217;d, and I fear</line>
<line form="verse">Thou play&#8217;dst most foully for&#8217;t; yet it was said</line>
<line form="verse">It should not stand in thy posterity,</line>
<line form="verse">But that myself should be the root and father</line>
<line form="verse">Of many kings. If there come truth from them&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">As upon thee, Macbeth, their speeches shine&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Why, by the verities on thee made good,</line>
<line form="verse">May they not be my oracles as well,</line>
<line form="verse">And set me up in hope? But hush, no more.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Sennet sounded. Enter Macbeth as King, Lady Macbeth as Queen, Lennox, Rosse, Lords, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s our chief guest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">If he had been forgotten,</line>
<line form="verse">It had been as a gap in our great feast,</line>
<line form="verse">And all-thing unbecoming.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tonight we hold a solemn supper, sir,</line>
<line form="verse">And I&#8217;ll request your presence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Let your Highness</line>
<line form="verse">Command upon me, to the which my duties</line>
<line form="verse">Are with a most indissoluble tie</line>
<line form="verse">Forever knit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ride you this afternoon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Ay, my good lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We should have else desir&#8217;d your good advice</line>
<line form="verse">(Which still hath been both grave and prosperous)</line>
<line form="verse">In this day&#8217;s council; but we&#8217;ll take tomorrow.</line>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t far you ride?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As far, my lord, as will fill up the time</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twixt this and supper. Go not my horse the better,</line>
<line form="verse">I must become a borrower of the night</line>
<line form="verse">For a dark hour or twain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Fail not our feast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, I will not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We hear our bloody cousins are bestow&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">In England and in Ireland, not confessing</line>
<line form="verse">Their cruel parricide, filling their hearers</line>
<line form="verse">With strange invention. But of that tomorrow,</line>
<line form="verse">When therewithal we shall have cause of state</line>
<line form="verse">Craving us jointly. Hie you to horse; <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>,</line>
<line form="verse">Till you return at night. Goes Fleance with you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, my good lord. Our time does call upon&#8217;s.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I wish your horses swift and sure of foot;</line>
<line form="verse">And so I do commend you to their backs.</line>
<line form="verse">Farewell.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Banquo.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Let every man be master of his time</line>
<line form="verse">Till seven at night. To make society</line>
<line form="verse">The sweeter welcome, we will keep ourself</line>
<line form="verse">Till supper-time alone; while then, God be with you!</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lords with Lady Macbeth and others. Manent Macbeth and a Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Sirrah, a word with you. Attend those men</line>
<line form="verse">Our pleasure?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They are, my lord, without the palace gate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bring them before us.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">To be thus is nothing,</line>
<line form="verse">But to be safely thus. Our fears in Banquo</line>
<line form="verse">Stick deep, and in his royalty of nature</line>
<line form="verse">Reigns that which would be fear&#8217;d. &#8217;Tis much he dares,</line>
<line form="verse">And to that dauntless temper of his mind,</line>
<line form="verse">He hath a wisdom that doth guide his valor</line>
<line form="verse">To act in safety. There is none but he</line>
<line form="verse">Whose being I do fear; and under him</line>
<line form="verse">My Genius is rebuk&#8217;d, as it is said</line>
<line form="verse">Mark Antony&#8217;s was by Caesar. He chid the sisters</line>
<line form="verse">When first they put the name of king upon me,</line>
<line form="verse">And bade them speak to him; then prophet-like</line>
<line form="verse">They hail&#8217;d him father to a line of kings.</line>
<line form="verse">Upon my head they plac&#8217;d a fruitless crown,</line>
<line form="verse">And put a barren sceptre in my gripe,</line>
<line form="verse">Thence to be wrench&#8217;d with an unlineal hand,</line>
<line form="verse">No son of mine succeeding. If&#8217;t be so,</line>
<line form="verse">For Banquo&#8217;s issue have I fil&#8217;d my mind,</line>
<line form="verse">For them the gracious Duncan have I murder&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Put rancors in the vessel of my peace</line>
<line form="verse">Only for them, and mine eternal jewel</line>
<line form="verse">Given to the common enemy of man,</line>
<line form="verse">To make them kings&#8212;the seeds of Banquo kings!</line>
<line form="verse">Rather than so, come fate into the list,</line>
<line form="verse">And champion me to th&#8217; utterance! Who&#8217;s there?</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servant and two Murderers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now go to the door, and stay there till we call.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Was it not yesterday we spoke together?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It was, so please your Highness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Well then, now</line>
<line form="verse">Have you consider&#8217;d of my speeches?&#8212;know</line>
<line form="verse">That it was he in the times past which held you</line>
<line form="verse">So under fortune, which you thought had been</line>
<line form="verse">Our innocent self? This I made good to you</line>
<line form="verse">In our last conference, pass&#8217;d in probation with you:</line>
<line form="verse">How you were borne in hand, how cross&#8217;d, the instruments,</line>
<line form="verse">Who wrought with them, and all things else that might</line>
<line form="verse">To half a soul and to a notion craz&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Say, &#8220;Thus did Banquo.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">You made it known to us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did so; and went further, which is now</line>
<line form="verse">Our point of second meeting. Do you find</line>
<line form="verse">Your patience so predominant in your nature</line>
<line form="verse">That you can let this go? Are you so gospell&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">To pray for this good man, and for his issue,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose heavy hand hath bow&#8217;d you to the grave,</line>
<line form="verse">And beggar&#8217;d yours forever?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">We are men, my liege.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, in the catalogue ye go for men,</line>
<line form="verse">As hounds and greyhounds, mungrels, spaniels, curs,</line>
<line form="verse">Shoughs, water-rugs, and demi-wolves are clipt</line>
<line form="verse">All by the name of dogs; the valued file</line>
<line form="verse">Distinguishes the swift, the slow, the subtle,</line>
<line form="verse">The house-keeper, the hunter, every one,</line>
<line form="verse">According to the gift which bounteous nature</line>
<line form="verse">Hath in him clos&#8217;d; whereby he does receive</line>
<line form="verse">Particular addition, from the bill</line>
<line form="verse">That writes them all alike: and so of men.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, if you have a station in the file,</line>
<line form="verse">Not i&#8217; th&#8217; worst rank of manhood, say&#8217;t,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will put that business in your bosoms,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose execution takes your enemy off,</line>
<line form="verse">Grapples you to the heart and love of us,</line>
<line form="verse">Who wear our health but sickly in his life,</line>
<line form="verse">Which in his death were perfect.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">I am one, my liege,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom the vile blows and buffets of the world</line>
<line form="verse">Hath so incens&#8217;d that I am reckless what</line>
<line form="verse">I do to spite the world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">And I another,</line>
<line form="verse">So weary with disasters, tugg&#8217;d with fortune,</line>
<line form="verse">That I would set my life on any chance,</line>
<line form="verse">To mend it, or be rid on&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Both of you</line>
<line form="verse">Know Banquo was your enemy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">True, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So is he mine; and in such bloody distance,</line>
<line form="verse">That every minute of his being thrusts</line>
<line form="verse">Against my near&#8217;st of life; and though I could</line>
<line form="verse">With barefac&#8217;d power sweep him from my sight,</line>
<line form="verse">And bid my will avouch it, yet I must not,</line>
<line form="verse">For certain friends that are both his and mine,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose loves I may not drop, but wail his fall</line>
<line form="verse">Who I myself struck down. And thence it is</line>
<line form="verse">That I to your assistance do make love,</line>
<line form="verse">Masking the business from the common eye</line>
<line form="verse">For sundry weighty reasons.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">We shall, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Perform what you command us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Though our lives&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your spirits shine through you. Within this hour, at most,</line>
<line form="verse">I will advise you where to plant yourselves,</line>
<line form="verse">Acquaint you with the perfect spy  o&#8217; th&#8217; time,</line>
<line form="verse">The moment on&#8217;t, for&#8217;t must be done tonight,</line>
<line form="verse">And something from the palace; always thought</line>
<line form="verse">That I require a clearness: and with him&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">To leave no rubs nor botches in the work&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Fleance his son, that keeps him company,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose absence is no less material to me</line>
<line form="verse">Than is his father&#8217;s, must embrace the fate</line>
<line form="verse">Of that dark hour. Resolve yourselves apart,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll come to you anon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">We are resolv&#8217;d, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll call upon you straight; abide within.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Murderers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">It is concluded: Banquo, thy soul&#8217;s flight,</line>
<line form="verse">If it find heaven, must find it out tonight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Forres. The palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lady Macbeth, Waiting Gentlewoman, Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lady Macbeth is concerned about her husband, who is dark-minded and cheerless. He tells her that she does not know what he is thinking, and refuses to let her in on it. Both of them have been suffering from bad dreams night after night. She realizes that he has planned something for Banquo and Fleance, but he does not tell her what.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth&#8217;s Lady and her Waiting Gentlewoman.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is Banquo gone from court?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, madam, but returns again tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say to the King, I would attend his leisure</line>
<line form="verse">For a few words.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Madam, I will.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Nought&#8217;s had, all&#8217;s spent,</line>
<line form="verse">Where our desire is got without content;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis safer to be that which we destroy</line>
<line form="verse">Than by destruction dwell in doubtful joy.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How now, my lord, why do you keep alone,</line>
<line form="verse">Of sorriest fancies your companions making,</line>
<line form="verse">Using those thoughts which should indeed have died</line>
<line form="verse">With them they think on? Things without all remedy</line>
<line form="verse">Should be without regard: what&#8217;s done, is done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We have scorch&#8217;d the snake, not kill&#8217;d it;</line>
<line form="verse">She&#8217;ll close and be herself, whilest our poor malice</line>
<line form="verse">Remains in danger of her former tooth.</line>
<line form="verse">But let the frame of things disjoint, both the worlds suffer,</line>
<line form="verse">Ere we will eat our meal in fear, and sleep</line>
<line form="verse">In the affliction of these terrible dreams</line>
<line form="verse">That shake us nightly. Better be with the dead,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom we, to gain our peace, have sent to peace,</line>
<line form="verse">Than on the torture of the mind to lie</line>
<line form="verse">In restless ecstasy. Duncan is in his grave;</line>
<line form="verse">After life&#8217;s fitful fever he sleeps well.</line>
<line form="verse">Treason has done his worst; nor steel, nor poison,</line>
<line form="verse">Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing,</line>
<line form="verse">Can touch him further.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Come on;</line>
<line form="verse">Gentle my lord, sleek  o&#8217;er your rugged looks,</line>
<line form="verse">Be bright and jovial among your guests tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So shall I, love, and so, I pray, be you.</line>
<line form="verse">Let your remembrance apply to Banquo,</line>
<line form="verse">Present him eminence both with eye and tongue:</line>
<line form="verse">Unsafe the while, that we</line>
<line form="verse">Must lave our honors in these flattering streams,</line>
<line form="verse">And make our faces vizards to our hearts,</line>
<line form="verse">Disguising what they are.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">You must leave this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, full of scorpions is my mind, dear wife!</line>
<line form="verse">Thou know&#8217;st that Banquo and his Fleance lives.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But in them nature&#8217;s copy&#8217;s not eterne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s comfort yet, they are assailable.</line>
<line form="verse">Then be thou jocund; ere the bat hath flown</line>
<line form="verse">His cloister&#8217;d flight, ere to black Hecat&#8217;s summons</line>
<line form="verse">The shard-borne beetle with his drowsy hums</line>
<line form="verse">Hath rung night&#8217;s yawning peal, there shall be done</line>
<line form="verse">A deed of dreadful note.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What&#8217;s to be done?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be innocent of the knowledge, dearest chuck,</line>
<line form="verse">Till thou applaud the deed. Come, seeling night,</line>
<line form="verse">Scarf up the tender eye of pitiful day,</line>
<line form="verse">And with thy bloody and invisible hand</line>
<line form="verse">Cancel and tear to pieces that great bond</line>
<line form="verse">Which keeps me pale! Light thickens, and the crow</line>
<line form="verse">Makes wing to th&#8217; rooky wood;</line>
<line form="verse">Good things of day begin to droop and drowse,</line>
<line form="verse">Whiles night&#8217;s black agents to their preys do rouse.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou marvel&#8217;st at my words, but hold thee still:</line>
<line form="verse">Things bad begun make strong themselves by ill.</line>
<line form="verse">So prithee go with me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Forres. A park near the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Three Murderers, Banquo, Fleance)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>A third murderer joins the first two, who are rather put out by what they see as a lack of trust on Macbeth&#8217;s part. Banquo and Fleance arrive, and the murderers set upon them, but Fleance, urged on by his father, escapes.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter three Murderers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But who did bid thee join with us?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He needs not our mistrust, since he delivers</line>
<line form="verse">Our offices, and what we have to do,</line>
<line form="verse">To the direction just.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Then stand with us.</line>
<line form="verse">The west yet glimmers with some streaks of day;</line>
<line form="verse">Now spurs the lated traveller apace</line>
<line form="verse">To gain the timely inn, and near approaches</line>
<line form="verse">The subject of our watch.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Hark, I hear horses.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Give us a light there, ho!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Then &#8217;tis he; the rest</line>
<line form="verse">That are within the note of expectation</line>
<line form="verse">Already are i&#8217; th&#8217; court.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">His horses go about.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Almost a mile; but he does usually,</line>
<line form="verse">So all men do, from hence to th&#8217; palace gate</line>
<line form="verse">Make it their walk.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Banquo, and Fleance with a torch.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">A light, a light!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">&#8217;Tis he.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stand to&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It will be rain tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Let it come down.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They assault Banquo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BAN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, treachery! Fly, good Fleance, fly, fly, fly!</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mayst revenge. O slave!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death">Dies.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="exit">Fleance escapes.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who did strike out the light?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Was&#8217;t not the way?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s but one down; the son is fled.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">We have lost</line>
<line form="verse">Best half of our affair.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, let&#8217;s away, and say how much is done.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A room of state in the palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Macbeth, Lady Macbeth, Rosse, Lennox, Lord, Attendants, First Murderer, Ghost of Banquo)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth cordially greets his guests to the banquet. One of the murderers arrives to let Macbeth know that the deed is done; Macbeth is full of praise until he hears that Fleance escaped. Lady Macbeth calls him back to the table to toast the guests; he does so, but as he attempts to take his place, he finds the seat reserved for him occupied by Banquo&#8217;s bleeding ghost, visible to him alone. As he raves at the apparently empty seat, Lady Macbeth attempts to reassure the noblemen, telling them that Macbeth occasionally suffers from fits and has done since his childhood. She drags her husband aside and urges him to stiffen his spine, insisting that it is only his overactive imagination at work. The ghost vanishes, and Macbeth regains control of himself, but then it appears again and he becomes even wilder. Seeing that he will not calm down and that his speech risks giving away their guilt, Lady Macbeth dismisses the lords in a hurry. Macbeth fears that Nature itself will give away their guilt. He asks why Macduff refused to come to the feast, revealing that he keeps a spy in all of the great households of the land, and decides that he will visit the weird sisters, in the hope of finding out the worst that is to come. He feels that he has gone so far in dark practices that he might as well continue now.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Banquet prepar&#8217;d.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, Lady Macbeth, Rosse, Lennox, Lords, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You know your own degrees, sit down. At first</line>
<line form="verse">And last, the hearty welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Thanks to your Majesty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ourself will mingle with society,</line>
<line form="verse">And play the humble host.</line>
<line form="verse">Our hostess keeps her state, but in best time</line>
<line form="verse">We will require her welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pronounce it for me, sir, to all our friends,</line>
<line form="verse">For my heart speaks they are welcome.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter First Murderer to the door.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">See, they encounter thee with their hearts&#8217; thanks.</line>
<line form="verse">Both sides are even; here I&#8217;ll sit i&#8217; th&#8217; midst.</line>
<line form="verse">Be large in mirth; anon we&#8217;ll drink a measure</line>
<line form="verse">The table round.&#8212;</line>
<stagedir type="action">Goes to the door.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s blood upon thy face.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">&#8217;Tis Banquo&#8217;s then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis better thee without than he within.</line>
<line form="verse">Is he dispatch&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">My lord, his throat is cut;</line>
<line form="verse">That I did for him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Thou art the best  o&#8217; th&#8217; cut-throats,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet he&#8217;s good that did the like for Fleance.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou didst it, thou art the nonpareil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most royal sir, Fleance is scap&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then comes my fit again. I had else been perfect,</line>
<line form="verse">Whole as the marble, founded as the rock,</line>
<line form="verse">As broad and general as the casing air;</line>
<line form="verse">But now I am cabin&#8217;d, cribb&#8217;d, confin&#8217;d, bound in</line>
<line form="verse">To saucy doubts and fears. But Banquo&#8217;s safe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, my good lord; safe in a ditch he bides,</line>
<line form="verse">With twenty trenched gashes on his head,</line>
<line form="verse">The least a death to nature.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Thanks for that:</line>
<line form="verse">There the grown serpent lies; the worm that&#8217;s fled</line>
<line form="verse">Hath nature that in time will venom breed,</line>
<line form="verse">No teeth for th&#8217; present. Get thee gone; tomorrow</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll hear ourselves again.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Murderer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">My royal lord,</line>
<line form="verse">You do not give the cheer. The feast is sold</line>
<line form="verse">That is not often vouch&#8217;d, while &#8217;tis a-making,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis given with welcome. To feed were best at home;</line>
<line form="verse">From thence, the sauce to meat is ceremony,</line>
<line form="verse">Meeting were bare without it.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Ghost of Banquo and sits in Macbeth&#8217;s place.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Sweet remembrancer!</line>
<line form="verse">Now good digestion wait on appetite,</line>
<line form="verse">And health on both!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">May&#8217;t please your Highness sit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here had we now our country&#8217;s honor roof&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Were the grac&#8217;d person of our Banquo present,</line>
<line form="verse">Who may I rather challenge for unkindness</line>
<line form="verse">Than pity for mischance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">His absence, sir,</line>
<line form="verse">Lays blame upon his promise. Please&#8217;t your Highness</line>
<line form="verse">To grace us with your royal company?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The table&#8217;s full.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Here is a place reserv&#8217;d, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, my good lord. What is&#8217;t that moves your Highness?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Which of you have done this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What, my good lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou canst not say I did it; never shake</line>
<line form="verse">Thy gory locks at me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gentlemen, rise, his Highness is not well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sit, worthy friends; my lord is often thus,</line>
<line form="verse">And hath been from his youth. Pray you keep seat.</line>
<line form="verse">The fit is momentary, upon a thought</line>
<line form="verse">He will again be well. If much you note him,</line>
<line form="verse">You shall offend him and extend his passion.</line>
<line form="verse">Feed, and regard him not.&#8212;Are you a man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and a bold one, that dare look on that</line>
<line form="verse">Which might appall the devil.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">O proper stuff!</line>
<line form="verse">This is the very painting of your fear;</line>
<line form="verse">This is the air-drawn dagger which you said</line>
<line form="verse">Led you to Duncan. O, these flaws and starts</line>
<line form="verse">(Impostors to true fear) would well become</line>
<line form="verse">A woman&#8217;s story at a winter&#8217;s fire,</line>
<line form="verse">Authoriz&#8217;d by her grandam. Shame itself,</line>
<line form="verse">Why do you make such faces? When all&#8217;s done,</line>
<line form="verse">You look but on a stool.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Prithee see there!</line>
<line form="verse">Behold! Look! Lo! How say you?</line>
<line form="verse">Why, what care I? If thou canst nod, speak too.</line>
<line form="verse">If charnel-houses and our graves must send</line>
<line form="verse">Those that we bury back, our monuments</line>
<line form="verse">Shall be the maws of kites.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Ghost.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What? Quite unmann&#8217;d in folly?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If I stand here, I saw him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Fie, for shame!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Blood hath been shed ere now, i&#8217; th&#8217; olden time,</line>
<line form="verse">Ere humane statute purg&#8217;d the gentle weal;</line>
<line form="verse">Ay, and since too, murders have been perform&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Too terrible for the ear. The time has been,</line>
<line form="verse">That when the brains were out, the man would die,</line>
<line form="verse">And there an end; but now they rise again</line>
<line form="verse">With twenty mortal murders on their crowns,</line>
<line form="verse">And push us from our stools. This is more strange</line>
<line form="verse">Than such a murder is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My worthy lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Your noble friends do lack you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">I do forget.</line>
<line form="verse">Do not muse at me, my most worthy friends,</line>
<line form="verse">I have a strange infirmity, which is nothing</line>
<line form="verse">To those that know me. Come, love and health to all,</line>
<line form="verse">Then I&#8217;ll sit down. Give me some wine, fill full.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Ghost.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I drink to th&#8217; general joy  o&#8217; th&#8217; whole table,</line>
<line form="verse">And to our dear friend Banquo, whom we miss;</line>
<line form="verse">Would he were here! To all, and him, we thirst,</line>
<line form="verse">And all to all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Our duties, and the pledge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Avaunt, and quit my sight! Let the earth hide thee!</line>
<line form="verse">Thy bones are marrowless, thy blood is cold;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast no speculation in those eyes</line>
<line form="verse">Which thou dost glare with!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Think of this, good peers,</line>
<line form="verse">But as a thing of custom. &#8217;Tis no other;</line>
<line form="verse">Only it spoils the pleasure of the time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What man dare, I dare.</line>
<line form="verse">Approach thou like the rugged Russian bear,</line>
<line form="verse">The arm&#8217;d rhinoceros, or th&#8217; Hyrcan tiger,</line>
<line form="verse">Take any shape but that, and my firm nerves</line>
<line form="verse">Shall never tremble. Or be alive again,</line>
<line form="verse">And dare me to the desert with thy sword;</line>
<line form="verse">If trembling I inhabit then, protest me</line>
<line form="verse">The baby of a girl. Hence, horrible shadow!</line>
<line form="verse">Unreal mock&#8217;ry, hence!</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Ghost.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Why, so; being gone,</line>
<line form="verse">I am a man again. Pray you sit still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You have displac&#8217;d the mirth, broke the good meeting,</line>
<line form="verse">With most admir&#8217;d disorder.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Can such things be,</line>
<line form="verse">And overcome us like a summer&#8217;s cloud,</line>
<line form="verse">Without our special wonder? You make me strange</line>
<line form="verse">Even to the disposition that I owe,</line>
<line form="verse">When now I think you can behold such sights,</line>
<line form="verse">And keep the natural ruby of your cheeks,</line>
<line form="verse">When mine is blanch&#8217;d with fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What sights, my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you speak not. He grows worse and worse,</line>
<line form="verse">Question enrages him. At once, good night.</line>
<line form="verse">Stand not upon the order of your going,</line>
<line form="verse">But go at once.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Good night, and better health</line>
<line form="verse">Attend his Majesty!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">A kind good night to all!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lords and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It will have blood, they say; blood will have blood.</line>
<line form="verse">Stones have been known to move and trees to speak;</line>
<line form="verse">Augures and understood relations have</line>
<line form="verse">By maggot-pies and choughs and rooks brought forth</line>
<line form="verse">The secret&#8217;st man of blood. What is the night?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Almost at odds with morning, which is which.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How say&#8217;st thou, that Macduff denies his person</line>
<line form="verse">At our great bidding?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Did you send to him, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hear it by the way; but I will send.</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s not a one of them but in his house</line>
<line form="verse">I keep a servant fee&#8217;d. I will tomorrow</line>
<line form="verse">(And betimes I will) to the we&#239;rd sisters.</line>
<line form="verse">More shall they speak; for now I am bent to know,</line>
<line form="verse">By the worst means, the worst. For mine own good</line>
<line form="verse">All causes shall give way. I am in blood</line>
<line form="verse">Stepp&#8217;d in so far that, should I wade no more,</line>
<line form="verse">Returning were as tedious as go  o&#8217;er.</line>
<line form="verse">Strange things I have in head, that will to hand,</line>
<line form="verse">Which must be acted ere they may be scann&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You lack the season of all natures, sleep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, we&#8217;ll to sleep. My strange and self-abuse</line>
<line form="verse">Is the initiate fear that wants hard use:</line>
<line form="verse">We are yet but young in deed.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A heath.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Three Witches, Hecat)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Hecate, the Queen of the witches, chides the three weird sisters for daring to traffic with Macbeth without involving her. She insists in joining in.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. Enter the three Witches, meeting Hecat.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, how now, Hecat? You look angerly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEC.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Have I not reason, beldams as you are?</line>
<line form="rhyme">Saucy and overbold, how did you dare</line>
<line form="rhyme">To trade and traffic with Macbeth</line>
<line form="rhyme">In riddles and affairs of death;</line>
<line form="rhyme">And I, the mistress of your charms,</line>
<line form="rhyme">The close contriver of all harms,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Was never call&#8217;d to bear my part,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Or show the glory of our art?</line>
<line form="rhyme">And which is worse, all you have done</line>
<line form="rhyme">Hath been but for a wayward son,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Spiteful and wrathful, who (as others do)</line>
<line form="rhyme">Loves for his own ends, not for you.</line>
<line form="rhyme">But make amends now. Get you gone,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And at the pit of Acheron</line>
<line form="rhyme">Meet me i&#8217; th&#8217; morning; thither he</line>
<line form="rhyme">Will come to know his destiny.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Your vessels and your spells provide,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Your charms and every thing beside.</line>
<line form="rhyme">I am for th&#8217; air; this night I&#8217;ll spend</line>
<line form="rhyme">Unto a dismal and a fatal end.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Great business must be wrought ere noon:</line>
<line form="rhyme">Upon the corner of the moon</line>
<line form="rhyme">There hangs a vap&#8217;rous drop profound,</line>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll catch it ere it come to ground;</line>
<line form="rhyme">And that, distill&#8217;d by magic sleights,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Shall raise such artificial sprites</line>
<line form="rhyme">As by the strength of their illusion</line>
<line form="rhyme">Shall draw him on to his confusion.</line>
<line form="rhyme">He shall spurn fate, scorn death, and bear</line>
<line form="rhyme">His hopes &#8217;bove wisdom, grace, and fear;</line>
<line form="rhyme">And you all know, security</line>
<line form="rhyme">Is mortals&#8217; chiefest enemy.</line>

<stagedir type="song">Music, and a song. Sing within:</stagedir>
<line type="lyric">&#8220;Come away, come away, etc.&#8221;</line>
<line type="lyric">Hark, I am call&#8217;d; my little spirit, see,</line>
<line type="lyric">Sits in a foggy cloud, and stays for me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, let&#8217;s make haste, she&#8217;ll soon be back again.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Forres. The palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lennox, Lord)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lennox and another lord sardonically list off Macbeth&#8217;s deed, leaving little doubt of their mutual conviction of his guilt. The Lord reveals that Macduff has fled to Malcolm&#8217;s side in England, where Duncan&#8217;s son is hoping for the help of the English King to raise an army and overthrow Macbeth. </scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lennox and another Lord.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My former speeches have but hit your thoughts,</line>
<line form="verse">Which can interpret farther; only I say</line>
<line form="verse">Things have been strangely borne. The gracious Duncan</line>
<line form="verse">Was pitied of Macbeth; marry, he was dead.</line>
<line form="verse">And the right valiant Banquo walk&#8217;d too late,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom you may say (if&#8217;t please you) Fleance kill&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">For Fleance fled. Men must not walk too late.</line>
<line form="verse">Who cannot want the thought, how monstrous</line>
<line form="verse">It was for Malcolm and for Donalbain</line>
<line form="verse">To kill their gracious father? Damned fact!</line>
<line form="verse">How it did grieve Macbeth! Did he not straight</line>
<line form="verse">In pious rage the two delinquents tear,</line>
<line form="verse">That were the slaves of drink and thralls of sleep?</line>
<line form="verse">Was not that nobly done? Ay, and wisely too;</line>
<line form="verse">For &#8217;twould have anger&#8217;d any heart alive</line>
<line form="verse">To hear the men deny&#8217;t. So that, I say,</line>
<line form="verse">He has borne all things well, and I do think</line>
<line form="verse">That had he Duncan&#8217;s sons under his key</line>
<line form="verse">(As, and&#8217;t please heaven, he shall not), they should find</line>
<line form="verse">What &#8217;twere to kill a father; so should Fleance.</line>
<line form="verse">But peace! For from broad words, and &#8217;cause he fail&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">His presence at the tyrant&#8217;s feast, I hear</line>
<line form="verse">Macduff lives in disgrace. Sir, can you tell</line>
<line form="verse">Where he bestows himself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">The son of Duncan</line>
<line form="verse">(From whom this tyrant holds the due of birth)</line>
<line form="verse">Lives in the English court, and is receiv&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Of the most pious Edward with such grace</line>
<line form="verse">That the malevolence of fortune nothing</line>
<line form="verse">Takes from his high respect. Thither Macduff</line>
<line form="verse">Is gone to pray the holy king, upon his aid</line>
<line form="verse">To wake Northumberland and warlike Siward,</line>
<line form="verse">That by the help of these (with Him above</line>
<line form="verse">To ratify the work) we may again</line>
<line form="verse">Give to our tables meat, sleep to our nights;</line>
<line form="verse">Free from our feasts and banquets bloody knives;</line>
<line form="verse">Do faithful homage and receive free honors;</line>
<line form="verse">All which we pine for now. And this report</line>
<line form="verse">Hath so exasperate the King that he</line>
<line form="verse">Prepares for some attempt of war.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Sent he to Macduff?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He did; and with an absolute &#8220;Sir, not I,&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">The cloudy messenger turns me his back,</line>
<line form="verse">And hums, as who should say, &#8220;You&#8217;ll rue the time</line>
<line form="verse">That clogs me with this answer.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">And that well might</line>
<line form="verse">Advise him to a caution, t&#8217; hold what distance</line>
<line form="verse">His wisdom can provide. Some holy angel</line>
<line form="verse">Fly to the court of England, and unfold</line>
<line form="verse">His message ere he come, that a swift blessing</line>
<line form="verse">May soon return to this our suffering country</line>
<line form="verse">Under a hand accurs&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LORD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I&#8217;ll send my prayers with him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A cavern.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Three Witches, Hecat, Macbeth, First Apparition, Second Apparition, Third Apparition, Kings, Banquo, Lennox)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>In a cavern, the three witches prepare a foul broth. Macbeth enters and demands from them that they answer the questions he will ask them, the consequences be damned. Given the choice between the witches and their spirit masters, he chooses the latter. A head in armor tells him to beware of Macduff. A blood child tells him that he will never be killed by anyone born of woman. Lastly, a child with a crown on its head, holding a tree, tells him that he will never be beaten until the forest of Birnam comes to Dunsinane castle. Reassured, Macbeth still wants to know whether Banquo&#8217;s descendants will take the throne, and despite warnings not to ask too much he insists on finding out. Eight kings appear, one after the other, the last showing him a mirror in which even more can be seen; Banquo&#8217;s ghost follows, proudly pointing to them as his own. The apparitions and the witches vanish. Macbeth calls for Lennox, who is waiting for him, but the man has seen nothing. Hearing that Macduff has fled, Macbeth resolves to slaughter the man&#8217;s family.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. Enter the three Witches.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thrice the brinded cat hath mew&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Thrice, and once the hedge-pig whin&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Harpier cries, &#8220;&#8217;Tis time, &#8217;tis time.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Round about the cauldron go;</line>
<line form="rhyme">In the poison&#8217;d entrails throw;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Toad, that under cold stone</line>
<line form="rhyme">Days and nights has thirty-one</line>
<line form="rhyme">Swelt&#8217;red venom sleeping got,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Boil thou first i&#8217; th&#8217; charmed pot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Double, double, toil and trouble;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Fire burn, and cauldron bubble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Fillet of a fenny snake,</line>
<line form="rhyme">In the cauldron boil and bake;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Eye of newt and toe of frog,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Wool of bat and tongue of dog,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Adder&#8217;s fork and blind-worm&#8217;s sting,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Lizard&#8217;s leg and howlet&#8217;s wing,</line>
<line form="rhyme">For a charm of pow&#8217;rful trouble,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Like a hell-broth boil and bubble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Double, double, toil and trouble;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Fire burn, and cauldron bubble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Scale of dragon, tooth of wolf,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Witch&#8217;s mummy, maw and gulf</line>
<line form="rhyme">Of the ravin&#8217;d salt-sea shark,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Root of hemlock digg&#8217;d i&#8217; th&#8217; dark,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Liver of blaspheming Jew,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Gall of goat, and slips of yew</line>
<line form="rhyme">Sliver&#8217;d in the moon&#8217;s eclipse,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Nose of Turk and Tartar&#8217;s lips,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Finger of birth-strangled babe</line>
<line form="rhyme">Ditch-deliver&#8217;d by a drab,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Make the gruel thick and slab.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Add thereto a tiger&#8217;s chawdron,</line>
<line form="rhyme">For th&#8217; ingredience of our cau&#8217;dron.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Double, double, toil and trouble;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Fire burn, and cauldron bubble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Cool it with a baboon&#8217;s blood,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Then the charm is firm and good.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Hecat and the other three Witches.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HEC.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">O, well done! I commend your pains,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And every one shall share i&#8217; th&#8217; gains.</line>
<line form="rhyme">And now about the cauldron sing,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Like elves and fairies in a ring,</line>
<line form="verse">Enchanting all that you put in.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music and a song: &#8220;Black spirits, etc.&#8221; </stagedir>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Hecat.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">By the pricking of my thumbs,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Something wicked this way comes.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Knocking.</stagedir>
<line form="rhyme" offset="2">Open, locks,</line>
<line form="rhyme" offset="2">Whoever knocks!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, you secret, black, and midnight hags?</line>
<line form="verse">What is&#8217;t you do?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">A deed without a name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I conjure you, by that which you profess</line>
<line form="verse">(How e&#8217;er you come to know it), answer me:</line>
<line form="verse">Though you untie the winds, and let them fight</line>
<line form="verse">Against the churches; though the yesty waves</line>
<line form="verse">Confound and swallow navigation up;</line>
<line form="verse">Though bladed corn be lodg&#8217;d, and trees blown down;</line>
<line form="verse">Though castles topple on their warders&#8217; heads;</line>
<line form="verse">Though palaces and pyramids do slope</line>
<line form="verse">Their heads to their foundations; though the treasure</line>
<line form="verse">Of nature&#8217;s germains tumble all together,</line>
<line form="verse">Even till destruction sicken; answer me</line>
<line form="verse">To what I ask you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Demand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">We&#8217;ll answer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say, if th&#8217; hadst rather hear it from our mouths,</line>
<line form="verse">Or from our masters&#8217;?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Call &#8217;em; let me see &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Pour in sow&#8217;s blood, that hath eaten</line>
<line form="rhyme">Her nine farrow; grease that&#8217;s sweaten</line>
<line form="verse">From the murderer&#8217;s gibbet throw</line>
<line form="verse">Into the flame.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" offset="3">Come high or low;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Thyself and office deftly show!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. First Apparition, an armed Head.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tell me, thou unknown power&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" offset="7">He knows thy thought:</line>
<line form="rhyme">Hear his speech, but say thou nought.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. APP.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Macbeth! Macbeth! Macbeth! Beware Macduff,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Beware the Thane of Fife. Dismiss me. Enough.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">He descends.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What e&#8217;er thou art, for thy good caution, thanks;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast harp&#8217;d my fear aright. But one word more&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He will not be commanded. Here&#8217;s another,</line>
<line form="verse">More potent than the first.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. Second Apparition, a bloody Child.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. APP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Macbeth! Macbeth! Macbeth!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Had I three ears, I&#8217;ld hear thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. APP.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Be bloody, bold, and resolute: laugh to scorn</line>
<line form="rhyme">The pow&#8217;r of man; for none of woman born</line>
<line form="verse">Shall harm Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Descends.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then live, Macduff; what need I fear of thee?</line>
<line form="verse">But yet I&#8217;ll make assurance double sure,</line>
<line form="verse">And take a bond of fate: thou shalt not live,</line>
<line form="verse">That I may tell pale-hearted fear it lies,</line>
<line form="verse">And sleep in spite of thunder.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Thunder. Third Apparition, a Child crowned, with a tree in his hand.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What is this</line>
<line form="verse">That rises like the issue of a king,</line>
<line form="verse">And wears upon his baby-brow the round</line>
<line form="verse">And top of sovereignty?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Listen, but speak not to&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. APP.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Be lion-mettled, proud, and take no care</line>
<line form="rhyme">Who chafes, who frets, or where conspirers are:</line>
<line form="rhyme">Macbeth shall never vanquish&#8217;d be until</line>
<line form="rhyme">Great Birnan wood to high Dunsinane hill</line>
<line form="verse">Shall come against him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Descend.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" offset="5">That will never be.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Who can impress the forest, bid the tree</line>
<line form="rhyme">Unfix his earth-bound root? Sweet bodements! Good!</line>
<line form="rhyme">Rebellious dead, rise never till the wood</line>
<line form="rhyme">Of Birnan rise, and our high-plac&#8217;d Macbeth</line>
<line form="rhyme">Shall live the lease of nature, pay his breath</line>
<line form="rhyme">To time and mortal custom. Yet my heart</line>
<line form="rhyme">Throbs to know one thing: tell me, if your art</line>
<line form="verse">Can tell so much, shall Banquo&#8217;s issue ever</line>
<line form="verse">Reign in this kingdom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Seek to know no more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will be satisfied. Deny me this,</line>
<line form="verse">And an eternal curse fall on you! Let me know.</line>
<line form="verse">Why sinks that cauldron? And what noise is this?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Hoboys.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Show!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Show!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Show!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. WITCHES</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Show his eyes, and grieve his heart;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Come like shadows, so depart.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">A show of eight Kings, the eighth with a glass in his hand, and Banquo last.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou art too like the spirit of Banquo; down!</line>
<line form="verse">Thy crown does sear mine eyeballs. And thy hair,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou other gold-bound brow, is like the first.</line>
<line form="verse">A third is like the former. Filthy hags,</line>
<line form="verse">Why do you show me this?&#8212;A fourth? Start, eyes!</line>
<line form="verse">What, will the line stretch out to th&#8217; crack of doom?</line>
<line form="verse">Another yet? A seventh? I&#8217;ll see no more.</line>
<line form="verse">And yet the eight appears, who bears a glass</line>
<line form="verse">Which shows me many more; and some I see</line>
<line form="verse">That twofold balls and treble sceptres carry.</line>
<line form="verse">Horrible sight! Now I see &#8217;tis true,</line>
<line form="verse">For the blood-bolter&#8217;d Banquo smiles upon me,</line>
<line form="verse">And points at them for his.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Apparitions vanish.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What? Is this so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. WITCH.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Ay, sir, all this is so. But why</line>
<line form="rhyme">Stands Macbeth thus amazedly?</line>
<line form="rhyme">Come, sisters, cheer we up his sprites,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And show the best of our delights.</line>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll charm the air to give a sound,</line>
<line form="rhyme">While you perform your antic round;</line>
<line form="rhyme">That this great king may kindly say</line>
<line form="rhyme">Our duties did his welcome pay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music. The Witches dance and vanish.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where are they? Gone? Let this pernicious hour</line>
<line form="verse">Stand aye accursed in the calendar!</line>
<line form="verse">Come in, without there!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lennox.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What&#8217;s your Grace&#8217;s will?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Saw you the we&#239;rd sisters?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Came they not by you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No indeed, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Infected be the air whereon they ride,</line>
<line form="verse">And damn&#8217;d all those that trust them! I did hear</line>
<line form="verse">The galloping of horse. Who was&#8217;t came by?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis two or three, my lord, that bring you word</line>
<line form="verse">Macduff is fled to England.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Fled to England!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, my good lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Time, thou anticipat&#8217;st my dread exploits:</line>
<line form="verse">The flighty purpose never is  o&#8217;ertook</line>
<line form="verse">Unless the deed go with it. From this moment</line>
<line form="verse">The very firstlings of my heart shall be</line>
<line form="verse">The firstlings of my hand. And even now,</line>
<line form="verse">To crown my thoughts with acts, be it thought and done:</line>
<line form="verse">The castle of Macduff I will surprise,</line>
<line form="verse">Seize upon Fife, give to th&#8217; edge  o&#8217; th&#8217; sword</line>
<line form="verse">His wife, his babes, and all unfortunate souls</line>
<line form="verse">That trace him in his line. No boasting like a fool;</line>
<line form="verse">This deed I&#8217;ll do before this purpose cool.</line>
<line form="verse">But no more sights!&#8212;Where are these gentlemen?</line>
<line form="verse">Come bring me where they are.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Fife. Macduff&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lady Macduff, Son, Rosse, Messenger, Murderers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lady Macduff complains bitterly to Ross about her husband&#8217;s desertion, though Ross insists Macduff&#8217;s flight cannot be seen as such. She is not mollified. Ross takes his leave, promising to return soon. Lady Macduff chats with her son, a highly intelligent and charming boy, but they are interrupted by the arrival of a messenger begging them to flee. Too late, however: Lady Macduff has nowhere to go. Macbeth&#8217;s underlings enter, referring to Macduff as a traitor, and when the son denies the charge kill him, before advancing on his mother.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff&#8217;s Wife, her Son, and Rosse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What had he done, to make him fly the land?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You must have patience, madam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">He had none;</line>
<line form="verse">His flight was madness. When our actions do not,</line>
<line form="verse">Our fears do make us traitors.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">You know not</line>
<line form="verse">Whether it was his wisdom or his fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wisdom? To leave his wife, to leave his babes,</line>
<line form="verse">His mansion and his titles, in a place</line>
<line form="verse">From whence himself does fly? He loves us not,</line>
<line form="verse">He wants the natural touch; for the poor wren,</line>
<line form="verse">The most diminutive of birds, will fight,</line>
<line form="verse">Her young ones in her nest, against the owl.</line>
<line form="verse">All is the fear, and nothing is the love;</line>
<line form="verse">As little is the wisdom, where the flight</line>
<line form="verse">So runs against all reason.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My dearest coz,</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you school yourself. But for your husband,</line>
<line form="verse">He is noble, wise, judicious, and best knows</line>
<line form="verse">The fits  o&#8217; th&#8217; season. I dare not speak much further,</line>
<line form="verse">But cruel are the times when we are traitors,</line>
<line form="verse">And do not know ourselves; when we hold rumor</line>
<line form="verse">From what we fear, yet know not what we fear,</line>
<line form="verse">But float upon a wild and violent sea</line>
<line form="verse">Each way, and move. I take my leave of you;</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Shall not be long but I&#8217;ll be here again.</line>
<line form="verse">Things at the worst will cease, or else climb upward</line>
<line form="verse">To what they were before. My pretty cousin,</line>
<line form="verse">Blessing upon you!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Father&#8217;d he is, and yet he&#8217;s fatherless.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am so much a fool, should I stay longer,</line>
<line form="verse">It would be my disgrace and your discomfort.</line>
<line form="verse">I take my leave at once.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Rosse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Sirrah, your father&#8217;s dead,</line>
<line form="verse">And what will you do now? How will you live?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As birds do, mother.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">What, with worms and flies?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With what I get, I mean, and so do they.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Poor bird, thou&#8217;dst never fear the net nor lime,</line>
<line form="verse">The pitfall nor the gin.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why should I, mother? Poor birds they are not set for.</line>
<line form="verse">My father is not dead, for all your saying.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, he is dead. How wilt thou do for a father?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, how will you do for a husband?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, I can buy me twenty at any market.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then You&#8217;ll buy &#8217;em to sell again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou speak&#8217;st with all thy wit, and yet, i&#8217; faith,</line>
<line form="verse">With wit enough for thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Was my father a traitor, mother?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, that he was.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What is a traitor?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, one that swears and lies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And be all traitors that do so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Every one that does so is a traitor, and must be hang&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And must they all be hang&#8217;d that swear and lie?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Every one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Who must hang them?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, the honest men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Then the liars and swearers are fools; for there are liars and swearers enow to beat the honest men and hang up them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Now God help thee, poor monkey! But how wilt thou do for a father?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If he were dead, you&#8217;ld weep for him; if you would not, it were a good sign that I should quickly have a new father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD. </speaker>
<line form="prose">Poor prattler, how thou talk&#8217;st!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bless you, fair dame! I am not to you known,</line>
<line form="verse">Though in your state of honor I am perfect.</line>
<line form="verse">I doubt some danger does approach you nearly.</line>
<line form="verse">If you will take a homely man&#8217;s advice,</line>
<line form="verse">Be not found here; hence with your little ones.</line>
<line form="verse">To fright you thus, methinks I am too savage;</line>
<line form="verse">To do worse to you were fell cruelty,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is too nigh your person. Heaven preserve you!</line>
<line form="verse">I dare abide no longer.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Whither should I fly?</line>
<line form="verse">I have done no harm. But I remember now</line>
<line form="verse">I am in this earthly world&#8212;where to do harm</line>
<line form="verse">Is often laudable, to do good sometime</line>
<line form="verse">Accounted dangerous folly. Why then, alas,</line>
<line form="verse">Do I put up that womanly defense,</line>
<line form="verse">To say I have done no harm?</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Murderers.</stagedir>

<line form="verse" offset="6">What are these faces?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where is your husband?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>L. MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hope, in no place so unsanctified</line>
<line form="verse">Where such as thou mayst find him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">He&#8217;s a traitor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou li&#8217;st, thou shag-ear&#8217;d villain!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. MUR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What, you egg!</line>
<stagedir type="fight">Stabbing him.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Young fry of treachery!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SON.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">He has kill&#8217;d me, mother:</line>
<line form="verse">Run away, I pray you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="SON.">Dies.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lady Macduff crying &#8220;Murder!&#8221; and pursued by the Murderers.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>England. Before the King&#8217;s palace.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Malcolm, Macduff, English Doctor, Rosse)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Maclcolm and Macduff discuss the sufferings of Scotland under Macbeth&#8217;s rule. Malcolm insists, however, that he would make a far worse king than Macbeth himself, detailing all of his various sins. Macduff brushes them all aside as irrelevant, until Malcolm convinces him that he is an appalling human being and Macduff weeps at the thought of Scotland suffering yet further. This is all Malcolm was waiting for, as he wanted to test Macduff&#8217;s good faith, since Macbeth has sent many spies to him. All he has said was lies. They are interrupted by an English doctor who informs them that the King, who has offered ten thousand men to help Malcolm overthrow Macbeth, is coming out of his palace to cure an evil plague by his touch. Ross arrives, and after temporizing, has to tell Macduff that his entire family has been killed. Macduff is broken by the news, laying all the blame on himself. Malcolm tries to console him by recommending that he use his grief as fodder for his anger as they attack Macbeth. Macduff reminds the others that Macbeth has no children himself, and cannot know what it is to lose them. He swears not to rest until he has killed Macbeth, and Malcolm urges that they go to the King of England and receive their forces.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Malcolm and Macduff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let us seek out some desolate shade, and there</line>
<line form="verse">Weep our sad bosoms empty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Let us rather</line>
<line form="verse">Hold fast the mortal sword, and like good men</line>
<line form="verse">Bestride our downfall birthdom. Each new morn</line>
<line form="verse">New widows howl, new orphans cry, new sorrows</line>
<line form="verse">Strike heaven on the face, that it resounds</line>
<line form="verse">As if it felt with Scotland, and yell&#8217;d out</line>
<line form="verse">Like syllable of dolor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What I believe, I&#8217;ll wail,</line>
<line form="verse">What know, believe; and what I can redress,</line>
<line form="verse">As I shall find the time to friend, I will.</line>
<line form="verse">What you have spoke, it may be so perchance.</line>
<line form="verse">This tyrant, whose sole name blisters our tongues,</line>
<line form="verse">Was once thought honest; you have lov&#8217;d him well;</line>
<line form="verse">He hath not touch&#8217;d you yet. I am young, but something</line>
<line form="verse">You may discern of him through me, and wisdom</line>
<line form="verse">To offer up a weak, poor, innocent lamb</line>
<line form="verse">T&#8217; appease an angry god.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am not treacherous.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">But Macbeth is.</line>
<line form="verse">A good and virtuous nature may recoil</line>
<line form="verse">In an imperial charge. But I shall crave your pardon;</line>
<line form="verse">That which you are, my thoughts cannot transpose:</line>
<line form="verse">Angels are bright still, though the brightest fell.</line>
<line form="verse">Though all things foul would wear the brows of grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet grace must still look so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I have lost my hopes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Perchance even there where I did find my doubts.</line>
<line form="verse">Why in that rawness left you wife and child,</line>
<line form="verse">Those precious motives, those strong knots of love,</line>
<line form="verse">Without leave-taking? I pray you,</line>
<line form="verse">Let not my jealousies be your dishonors,</line>
<line form="verse">But mine own safeties. You may be rightly just,</line>
<line form="verse">What ever I shall think.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Bleed, bleed, poor country!</line>
<line form="verse">Great tyranny, lay thou thy basis sure,</line>
<line form="verse">For goodness dare not check thee; wear thou thy wrongs,</line>
<line form="verse">The title is affeer&#8217;d! Fare thee well, lord,</line>
<line form="verse">I would not be the villain that thou think&#8217;st</line>
<line form="verse">For the whole space that&#8217;s in the tyrant&#8217;s grasp,</line>
<line form="verse">And the rich East to boot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Be not offended;</line>
<line form="verse">I speak not as in absolute fear of you.</line>
<line form="verse">I think our country sinks beneath the yoke:</line>
<line form="verse">It weeps, it bleeds, and each new day a gash</line>
<line form="verse">Is added to her wounds. I think withal</line>
<line form="verse">There would be hands uplifted in my right;</line>
<line form="verse">And here from gracious England have I offer</line>
<line form="verse">Of goodly thousands. But, for all this,</line>
<line form="verse">When I shall tread upon the tyrant&#8217;s head,</line>
<line form="verse">Or wear it on my sword, yet my poor country</line>
<line form="verse">Shall have more vices than it had before,</line>
<line form="verse">More suffer, and more sundry ways than ever,</line>
<line form="verse">By him that shall succeed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What should he be?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is myself I mean; in whom I know</line>
<line form="verse">All the particulars of vice so grafted</line>
<line form="verse">That, when they shall be open&#8217;d, black Macbeth</line>
<line form="verse">Will seem as pure as snow, and the poor state</line>
<line form="verse">Esteem him as a lamb, being compar&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With my confineless harms.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Not in the legions</line>
<line form="verse">Of horrid hell can come a devil more damn&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">In evils to top Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I grant him bloody,</line>
<line form="verse">Luxurious, avaricious, false, deceitful,</line>
<line form="verse">Sudden, malicious, smacking of every sin</line>
<line form="verse">That has a name; but there&#8217;s no bottom, none,</line>
<line form="verse">In my voluptuousness. Your wives, your daughters,</line>
<line form="verse">Your matrons, and your maids could not fill up</line>
<line form="verse">The cestern of my lust, and my desire</line>
<line form="verse">All continent impediments would  o&#8217;erbear</line>
<line form="verse">That did oppose my will. Better Macbeth</line>
<line form="verse">Than such an one to reign.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Boundless intemperance</line>
<line form="verse">In nature is a tyranny; it hath been</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; untimely emptying of the happy throne,</line>
<line form="verse">And fall of many kings. But fear not yet</line>
<line form="verse">To take upon you what is yours. You may</line>
<line form="verse">Convey your pleasures in a spacious plenty,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet seem cold, the time you may so hoodwink.</line>
<line form="verse">We have willing dames enough; there cannot be</line>
<line form="verse">That vulture in you to devour so many</line>
<line form="verse">As will to greatness dedicate themselves,</line>
<line form="verse">Finding it so inclin&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">With this, there grows</line>
<line form="verse">In my most ill-compos&#8217;d affection such</line>
<line form="verse">A stanchless avarice that, were I king,</line>
<line form="verse">I should cut off the nobles for their lands,</line>
<line form="verse">Desire his jewels, and this other&#8217;s house,</line>
<line form="verse">And my more-having would be as a sauce</line>
<line form="verse">To make me hunger more, that I should forge</line>
<line form="verse">Quarrels unjust against the good and loyal,</line>
<line form="verse">Destroying them for wealth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">This avarice</line>
<line form="verse">Sticks deeper, grows with more pernicious root</line>
<line form="verse">Than summer-seeming lust; and it hath been</line>
<line form="verse">The sword of our slain kings. Yet do not fear,</line>
<line form="verse">Scotland hath foisons to fill up your will</line>
<line form="verse">Of your mere own. All these are portable,</line>
<line form="verse">With other graces weigh&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But I have none. The king-becoming graces,</line>
<line form="verse">As justice, verity, temp&#8217;rance, stableness,</line>
<line form="verse">Bounty, perseverance, mercy, lowliness,</line>
<line form="verse">Devotion, patience, courage, fortitude,</line>
<line form="verse">I have no relish of them, but abound</line>
<line form="verse">In the division of each several crime,</line>
<line form="verse">Acting it many ways. Nay, had I pow&#8217;r, I should</line>
<line form="verse">Pour the sweet milk of concord into hell,</line>
<line form="verse">Uproar the universal peace, confound</line>
<line form="verse">All unity on earth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">O Scotland, Scotland!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If such a one be fit to govern, speak.</line>
<line form="verse">I am as I have spoken.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Fit to govern?</line>
<line form="verse">No, not to live. O nation miserable!</line>
<line form="verse">With an untitled tyrant bloody-sceptred,</line>
<line form="verse">When shalt thou see thy wholesome days again,</line>
<line form="verse">Since that the truest issue of thy throne</line>
<line form="verse">By his own interdiction stands accus&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And does blaspheme his breed? Thy royal father</line>
<line form="verse">Was a most sainted king; the queen that bore thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Oft&#8217;ner upon her knees than on her feet,</line>
<line form="verse">Died every day she liv&#8217;d. Fare thee well,</line>
<line form="verse">These evils thou repeat&#8217;st upon thyself</line>
<line form="verse">Hath banish&#8217;d me from Scotland. O my breast,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy hope ends here!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Macduff, this noble passion,</line>
<line form="verse">Child of integrity, hath from my soul</line>
<line form="verse">Wip&#8217;d the black scruples, reconcil&#8217;d my thoughts</line>
<line form="verse">To thy good truth and honor. Devilish Macbeth</line>
<line form="verse">By many of these trains hath sought to win me</line>
<line form="verse">Into his power, and modest wisdom plucks me</line>
<line form="verse">From over-credulous haste. But God above</line>
<line form="verse">Deal between thee and me! For even now</line>
<line form="verse">I put myself to thy direction, and</line>
<line form="verse">Unspeak mine own detraction; here abjure</line>
<line form="verse">The taints and blames I laid upon myself,</line>
<line form="verse">For strangers to my nature. I am yet</line>
<line form="verse">Unknown to woman, never was forsworn,</line>
<line form="verse">Scarcely have coveted what was mine own,</line>
<line form="verse">At no time broke my faith, would not betray</line>
<line form="verse">The devil to his fellow, and delight</line>
<line form="verse">No less in truth than life. My first false speaking</line>
<line form="verse">Was this upon myself. What I am truly</line>
<line form="verse">Is thine and my poor country&#8217;s to command:</line>
<line form="verse">Whither indeed, before thy here-approach,</line>
<line form="verse">Old Siward, with ten thousand warlike men</line>
<line form="verse">Already at a point, was setting forth.</line>
<line form="verse">Now we&#8217;ll together, and the chance of goodness</line>
<line form="verse">Be like our warranted quarrel! Why are you silent?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Such welcome and unwelcome things at once</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis hard to reconcile.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter English Doctor.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, more anon.&#8212;Comes the King forth, I pray you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, sir; there are a crew of wretched souls</line>
<line form="verse">That stay his cure. Their malady convinces</line>
<line form="verse">The great assay of art; but at his touch,</line>
<line form="verse">Such sanctity hath heaven given his hand,</line>
<line form="verse">They presently amend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I thank you, doctor.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit English Doctor.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s the disease he means?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">&#8217;Tis call&#8217;d the evil:</line>
<line form="verse">A most miraculous work in this good king,</line>
<line form="verse">Which often, since my here-remain in England,</line>
<line form="verse">I have seen him do. How he solicits heaven,</line>
<line form="verse">Himself best knows; but strangely-visited people,</line>
<line form="verse">All swoll&#8217;n and ulcerous, pitiful to the eye,</line>
<line form="verse">The mere despair of surgery, he cures,</line>
<line form="verse">Hanging a golden stamp about their necks,</line>
<line form="verse">Put on with holy prayers, and &#8217;tis spoken,</line>
<line form="verse">To the succeeding royalty he leaves</line>
<line form="verse">The healing benediction. With this strange virtue,</line>
<line form="verse">He hath a heavenly gift of prophecy,</line>
<line form="verse">And sundry blessings hang about his throne</line>
<line form="verse">That speak him full of grace.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Rosse.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">See who comes here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My countryman; but yet I know him not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My ever gentle cousin, welcome hither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know him now. Good God betimes remove</line>
<line form="verse">The means that makes us strangers!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Sir, amen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stands Scotland where it did?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Alas, poor country,</line>
<line form="verse">Almost afraid to know itself! It cannot</line>
<line form="verse">Be call&#8217;d our mother, but our grave; where nothing,</line>
<line form="verse">But who knows nothing, is once seen to smile;</line>
<line form="verse">Where sighs, and groans, and shrieks that rent the air</line>
<line form="verse">Are made, not mark&#8217;d; where violent sorrow seems</line>
<line form="verse">A modern ecstasy. The dead man&#8217;s knell</line>
<line form="verse">Is there scarce ask&#8217;d for who, and good men&#8217;s lives</line>
<line form="verse">Expire before the flowers in their caps,</line>
<line form="verse">Dying or ere they sicken.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">O relation!</line>
<line form="verse">Too nice, and yet too true.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What&#8217;s the newest grief?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That of an hour&#8217;s age doth hiss the speaker;</line>
<line form="verse">Each minute teems a new one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">How does my wife?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="2">And all my children?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Well too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The tyrant has not batter&#8217;d at their peace?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, they were well at peace when I did leave &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be not a niggard of your speech; how goes&#8217;t?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When I came hither to transport the tidings,</line>
<line form="verse">Which I have heavily borne, there ran a rumor</line>
<line form="verse">Of many worthy fellows that were out,</line>
<line form="verse">Which was to my belief witness&#8217;d the rather,</line>
<line form="verse">For that I saw the tyrant&#8217;s power afoot.</line>
<line form="verse">Now is the time of help; your eye in Scotland</line>
<line form="verse">Would create soldiers, make our women fight,</line>
<line form="verse">To doff their dire distresses.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Be&#8217;t their comfort</line>
<line form="verse">We are coming thither. Gracious England hath</line>
<line form="verse">Lent us good Siward, and ten thousand men;</line>
<line form="verse">An older and a better soldier none</line>
<line form="verse">That Christendom gives out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Would I could answer</line>
<line form="verse">This comfort with the like! But I have words</line>
<line form="verse">That would be howl&#8217;d out in the desert air,</line>
<line form="verse">Where hearing should not latch them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">What concern they?</line>
<line form="verse">The general cause? Or is it a fee-grief</line>
<line form="verse">Due to some single breast?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No mind that&#8217;s honest</line>
<line form="verse">But in it shares some woe, though the main part</line>
<line form="verse">Pertains to you alone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">If it be mine,</line>
<line form="verse">Keep it not from me, quickly let me have it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let not your ears despise my tongue forever,</line>
<line form="verse">Which shall possess them with the heaviest sound</line>
<line form="verse">That ever yet they heard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Humh! I guess at it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your castle is surpris&#8217;d; your wife, and babes,</line>
<line form="verse">Savagely slaughter&#8217;d. To relate the manner,</line>
<line form="verse">Were on the quarry of these murder&#8217;d deer</line>
<line form="verse">To add the death of you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Merciful heaven!</line>
<line form="verse">What, man, ne&#8217;er pull your hat upon your brows;</line>
<line form="verse">Give sorrow words. The grief that does not speak</line>
<line form="verse">Whispers the  o&#8217;er-fraught heart, and bids it break.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My children too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Wife, children, servants, all</line>
<line form="verse">That could be found.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And I must be from thence!</line>
<line form="verse">My wife kill&#8217;d too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I have said.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Be comforted.</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s make us med&#8217;cines of our great revenge</line>
<line form="verse">To cure this deadly grief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He has no children. All my pretty ones?</line>
<line form="verse">Did you say all? O hell-kite! All?</line>
<line form="verse">What, all my pretty chickens, and their dam,</line>
<line form="verse">At one fell swoop?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dispute it like a man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I shall do so;</line>
<line form="verse">But I must also feel it as a man:</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot but remember such things were,</line>
<line form="verse">That were most precious to me. Did heaven look on,</line>
<line form="verse">And would not take their part? Sinful Macduff,</line>
<line form="verse">They were all strook for thee! Naught that I am,</line>
<line form="verse">Not for their own demerits, but for mine,</line>
<line form="verse">Fell slaughter on their souls. Heaven rest them now!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be this the whetstone of your sword, let grief</line>
<line form="verse">Convert to anger; blunt not the heart, enrage it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, I could play the woman with mine eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">And braggart with my tongue! But, gentle heavens,</line>
<line form="verse">Cut short all intermission. Front to front</line>
<line form="verse">Bring thou this fiend of Scotland and myself;</line>
<line form="verse">Within my sword&#8217;s length set him; if he scape,</line>
<line form="verse">Heaven forgive him too!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">This tune goes manly.</line>
<line form="verse">Come go we to the King, our power is ready,</line>
<line form="verse">Our lack is nothing but our leave. Macbeth</line>
<line form="verse">Is ripe for shaking, and the pow&#8217;rs above</line>
<line form="verse">Put on their instruments. Receive what cheer you may,</line>
<line form="verse">The night is long that never finds the day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Dunsinane. An anteroom in the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Doctor of Physic, Waiting Gentlewoman, Lady Macbeth)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The doctor waits with Lady Macbeth&#8217;s Waiting-Gentlewoman for the third night in a row. She insists that what she has told him is true about Lady Macbeth sleepwalking, but refuses to repeat what she has heard the Queen say in her sleep. Lady Macbeth enters, endlessly wringing her hands as though to wash them. She begins to speak, wishing the spots on her hands away, as the Doctor notes down what she says. Her words clearly reveal her guilt over Duncan&#8217;s death, and those of Macduff&#8217;s family, not to mention Banquo. The doctor is horrified, and admits that he cannot cure her.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Doctor of Physic and a Waiting Gentlewoman.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I have two nights watch&#8217;d with you, but can perceive no truth in your report. When was it she last walk&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Since his Majesty went into the field, I have seen her rise from her bed, throw her night-gown upon her, unlock her closet, take forth paper, fold it, write upon&#8217;t, read it, afterwards seal it, and again return to bed; yet all this while in a most fast sleep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A great perturbation in nature, to receive at once the benefit of sleep and do the effects of watching! In this slumb&#8217;ry agitation, besides her walking and other actual performances, what, at any time, have you heard her say?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That, sir, which I will not report after her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You may to me, and &#8217;tis most meet you should.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Neither to you nor any one, having no witness to confirm my speech.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lady Macbeth with a taper.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Lo you, here she comes! This is her very guise, and upon my life, fast asleep. Observe her, stand close.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How came she by that light?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, it stood by her. She has light by her continually, &#8217;tis her command.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You see her eyes are open.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, but their sense are shut.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What is it she does now? Look how she rubs her hands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is an accustom&#8217;d action with her, to seem thus washing her hands. I have known her continue in this a quarter of an hour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yet here&#8217;s a spot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hark, she speaks. I will set down what comes from her, to satisfy my remembrance the more strongly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Out, damn&#8217;d spot! Out, I say! One&#8212;two&#8212;why then &#8217;tis time to do&#8217;t. Hell is murky. Fie, my lord, fie, a soldier, and afeard? What need we fear who knows it, when none can call our pow&#8217;r to accompt? Yet who would have thought the old man to have had so much blood in him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Do you mark that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The Thane of Fife had a wife; where is she now? What, will these hands ne&#8217;er be clean? No more  o&#8217; that, my lord, no more  o&#8217; that; you mar all with this starting.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Go to, go to; you have known what you should not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">She has spoke what she should not, I am sure of that; heaven knows what she has known.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here&#8217;s the smell of the blood still. All the perfumes of Arabia will not sweeten this little hand. O, O, O!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What a sigh is there! The heart is sorely charg&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I would not have such a heart in my bosom for the dignity of the whole body.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, well, well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Pray God it be, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This disease is beyond my practice; yet I have known those which have walk&#8217;d in their sleep who have died holily in their beds.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Wash your hands, put on your night-gown, look not so pale. I tell you yet again, Banquo&#8217;s buried; he cannot come out on &#8217;s grave.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Even so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LADY M.</speaker>
<line form="prose">To bed, to bed; there&#8217;s knocking at the gate. Come, come, come, come, give me your hand. What&#8217;s done cannot be undone. To bed, to bed, to bed.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lady.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Will she go now to bed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Directly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT. PHYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Foul whisp&#8217;rings are abroad. Unnatural deeds</line>
<line form="verse">Do breed unnatural troubles; infected minds</line>
<line form="verse">To their deaf pillows will discharge their secrets.</line>
<line form="verse">More needs she the divine than the physician.</line>
<line form="verse">God, God, forgive us all! Look after her,</line>
<line form="verse">Remove from her the means of all annoyance,</line>
<line form="verse">And still keep eyes upon her. So good night.</line>
<line form="verse">My mind she has mated, and amaz&#8217;d my sight.</line>
<line form="verse">I think, but dare not speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Good night, good doctor.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The country near Dunsinane.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Menteth, Cathness, Angus, Lennox, Soldiers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Scottish noblemen Mentieth, Angus, Lennox and Caithness all go with their soldiers to join Malcolm and Macduff. They discuss Macbeth, asserting that he rules only by ordering, not by love, and note that he has fortified Dunsinane against all comers.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Drum and Colors. Enter Menteth, Cathness, Angus, Lennox, Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The English pow&#8217;r is near, led on by Malcolm,</line>
<line form="verse">His uncle Siward, and the good Macduff.</line>
<line form="verse">Revenges burn in them; for their dear causes</line>
<line form="verse">Would to the bleeding and the grim alarm</line>
<line form="verse">Excite the mortified man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Near Birnan wood</line>
<line form="verse">Shall we well meet them; that way are they coming.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CATH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who knows if Donalbain be with his brother?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For certain, sir, he is not; I have a file</line>
<line form="verse">Of all the gentry. There is Siward&#8217;s son,</line>
<line form="verse">And many unrough youths that even now</line>
<line form="verse">Protest their first of manhood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What does the tyrant?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CATH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Great Dunsinane he strongly fortifies.</line>
<line form="verse">Some say he&#8217;s mad; others that lesser hate him</line>
<line form="verse">Do call it valiant fury; but for certain</line>
<line form="verse">He cannot buckle his distemper&#8217;d cause</line>
<line form="verse">Within the belt of rule.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANG.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Now does he feel</line>
<line form="verse">His secret murders sticking on his hands;</line>
<line form="verse">Now minutely revolts upbraid his faith-breach;</line>
<line form="verse">Those he commands move only in command,</line>
<line form="verse">Nothing in love. Now does he feel his title</line>
<line form="verse">Hang loose about him, like a giant&#8217;s robe</line>
<line form="verse">Upon a dwarfish thief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Who then shall blame</line>
<line form="verse">His pester&#8217;d senses to recoil and start,</line>
<line form="verse">When all that is within him does condemn</line>
<line form="verse">Itself for being there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CATH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Well, march we on</line>
<line form="verse">To give obedience where &#8217;tis truly ow&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Meet we the med&#8217;cine of the sickly weal,</line>
<line form="verse">And with him pour we, in our country&#8217;s purge,</line>
<line form="verse">Each drop of us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Or so much as it needs</line>
<line form="verse">To dew the sovereign flower and drown the weeds.</line>
<line form="verse">Make we our march towards Birnan.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt marching.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Dunsinane. A room in the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Macbeth, English Doctor, Attendants, Servant, Seyton)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth refuses to receive news of any more thanes fleeing, blustering about the safety that the prophecies have promised him. He bullies the servant who comes to warn him of the approach of the English army. But he is aware that he is not loved, and realizes that he is growing old without earning respect. He prepares himself for battle, insisting that he will put on his armor even though it is not needed yet, and sending out men to hang anyone heard speaking fearfully. Macbeth asks the doctor about Lady Macbeth, and queries whether it is possible for a physician to cure the afflictions of the mind the same way one can cure the body; but the doctor tells him that only the patient can do that. Macbeth denounces all medicine as useless and prepares to fight, as the doctor wishes he were well clear of the place.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, English Doctor, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bring me no more reports, let them fly all.</line>
<line form="verse">Till Birnan wood remove to Dunsinane</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot taint with fear. What&#8217;s the boy Malcolm?</line>
<line form="verse">Was he not born of woman? The spirits that know</line>
<line form="verse">All mortal consequences have pronounc&#8217;d me thus:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Fear not, Macbeth, no man that&#8217;s born of woman</line>
<line form="verse">Shall e&#8217;er have power upon thee.&#8221; Then fly, false thanes,</line>
<line form="verse">And mingle with the English epicures!</line>
<line form="verse">The mind I sway by, and the heart I bear,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall never sag with doubt, nor shake with fear.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The devil damn thee black, thou cream-fac&#8217;d loon!</line>
<line form="verse">Where got&#8217;st thou that goose-look?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is ten thousand&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Geese, villain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">Soldiers, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go prick thy face, and over-red thy fear,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou lily-liver&#8217;d boy. What soldiers, patch?</line>
<line form="verse">Death of thy soul! Those linen cheeks of thine</line>
<line form="verse">Are counsellors to fear. What soldiers, whey-face?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERV.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The English force, so please you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Take thy face hence.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Seyton!&#8212;I am sick at heart</line>
<line form="verse">When I behold&#8212;Seyton, I say!&#8212;This push</line>
<line form="verse">Will cheer me ever, or disseat me now.</line>
<line form="verse">I have liv&#8217;d long enough: my way of life</line>
<line form="verse">Is fall&#8217;n into the sear, the yellow leaf,</line>
<line form="verse">And that which should accompany old age,</line>
<line form="verse">As honor, love, obedience, troops of friends,</line>
<line form="verse">I must not look to have; but in their stead,</line>
<line form="verse">Curses, not loud but deep, mouth-honor, breath,</line>
<line form="verse">Which the poor heart would fain deny, and dare not.</line>
<line form="verse">Seyton!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Seyton.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s your gracious pleasure?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">What news more?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">All is confirm&#8217;d, my lord, which was reported.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll fight, till from my bones my flesh be hack&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me my armor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">&#8217;Tis not needed yet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll put it on.</line>
<line form="verse">Send out more horses, skirr the country round,</line>
<line form="verse">Hang those that talk of fear. Give me mine armor.</line>
<line form="verse">How does your patient, doctor?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Not so sick, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">As she is troubled with thick-coming fancies,</line>
<line form="verse">That keep her from her rest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Cure her of that.</line>
<line form="verse">Canst thou not minister to a mind diseas&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Pluck from the memory a rooted sorrow,</line>
<line form="verse">Raze out the written troubles of the brain,</line>
<line form="verse">And with some sweet oblivious antidote</line>
<line form="verse">Cleanse the stuff&#8217;d bosom of that perilous stuff</line>
<line form="verse">Which weighs upon the heart?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Therein the patient</line>
<line form="verse">Must minister to himself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Throw physic to the dogs, I&#8217;ll none of it.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, put mine armor on; give me my staff.</line>
<line form="verse">Seyton, send out. Doctor, the thanes fly from me.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Come, sir, dispatch.&#8212; If thou couldst, doctor, cast</line>
<line form="verse">The water of my land, find her disease,</line>
<line form="verse">And purge it to a sound and pristine health,</line>
<line form="verse">I would applaud thee to the very echo,</line>
<line form="verse">That should applaud again.&#8212;Pull&#8217;t off, I say.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">What rhubarb, cyme, or what purgative drug,</line>
<line form="verse">Would scour these English hence? Hear&#8217;st thou of them?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, my good lord; your royal preparation</line>
<line form="verse">Makes us hear something.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Bring it after me.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I will not be afraid of death and bane,</line>
<line form="verse">Till Birnan forest come to Dunsinane.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt all but the English Doctor.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DOCT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were I from Dunsinane away and clear,</line>
<line form="verse">Profit again should hardly draw me here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Country near Birnam wood.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Malcolm, Siward, Macduff, Siward&#8217;s Son, Menteth, Cathness, Angus, Lennox, Rosse, Soldiers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Arriving at Birnam forest, Malcolm orders that his soldiers cut down the trees and carry the branches in front of them to disguise their number and movements.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Drum and Colors. Enter Malcolm, Siward, Macduff, Siward&#8217;s Son, Menteth, Cathness, Angus, Lennox, Rosse, and Soldiers, marching.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Cousins, I hope the days are near at hand</line>
<line form="verse">That chambers will be safe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">We doubt it nothing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What wood is this before us?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MENT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">The wood of Birnan.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let every soldier hew him down a bough,</line>
<line form="verse">And bear&#8217;t before him, thereby shall we shadow</line>
<line form="verse">The numbers of our host, and make discovery</line>
<line form="verse">Err in report of us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOLDIERS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">It shall be done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We learn no other but the confident tyrant</line>
<line form="verse">Keeps still in Dunsinane, and will endure</line>
<line form="verse">Our setting down before&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">&#8217;Tis his main hope;</line>
<line form="verse">For where there is advantage to be given,</line>
<line form="verse">Both more and less have given him the revolt,</line>
<line form="verse">And none serve with him but constrained things,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose hearts are absent too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Let our just censures</line>
<line form="verse">Attend the true event, and put we on</line>
<line form="verse">Industrious soldiership.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">The time approaches</line>
<line form="verse">That will with due decision make us know</line>
<line form="verse">What we shall say we have, and what we owe.</line>
<line form="verse">Thoughts speculative their unsure hopes relate,</line>
<line form="verse">But certain issue strokes must arbitrate,</line>
<line form="verse">Towards which advance the war.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt marching.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Dunsinane. Within the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Macbeth, Seyton, Soldiers, Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth finalizes his preparations against a siege, certain that no enemy can get in, but his bluster is broken by women screaming, and the news that Lady Macbeth is dead. Already grown apathetic, Macbeth realizes to what an extent life is empty and meaningless. A sentry announces that he was looking towards Birnam forest and that he saw the wood begin to move. Shocked and enraged, Macbeth begins to doubt, wondering whether the prophecies leave him as safe as he thought; still, though beginning to be weary of life, he still insists that he and his men will die fighting.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth, Seyton, and Soldiers, with Drum and Colors.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hang out our banners on the outward walls,</line>
<line form="verse">The cry is still, &#8220;They come!&#8221; Our castle&#8217;s strength</line>
<line form="verse">Will laugh a siege to scorn; here let them lie</line>
<line form="verse">Till famine and the ague eat them up.</line>
<line form="verse">Were they not forc&#8217;d with those that should be ours,</line>
<line form="verse">We might have met them dareful, beard to beard,</line>
<line form="verse">And beat them backward home.</line>
<stagedir type="action">A cry within of women.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What is that noise?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is the cry of women, my good lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have almost forgot the taste of fears.</line>
<line form="verse">The time has been, my senses would have cool&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To hear a night-shriek, and my fell of hair</line>
<line form="verse">Would at a dismal treatise rouse and stir</line>
<line form="verse">As life were in&#8217;t. I have supp&#8217;d full with horrors;</line>
<line form="verse">Direness, familiar to my slaughterous thoughts,</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot once start me.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Seyton.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Wherefore was that cry?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Queen, my lord, is dead.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She should have died hereafter;</line>
<line form="verse">There would have been a time for such a word.</line>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow, and tomorrow, and tomorrow,</line>
<line form="verse">Creeps in this petty pace from day to day,</line>
<line form="verse">To the last syllable of recorded time;</line>
<line form="verse">And all our yesterdays have lighted fools</line>
<line form="verse">The way to dusty death. Out, out, brief candle!</line>
<line form="verse">Life&#8217;s but a walking shadow, a poor player,</line>
<line form="verse">That struts and frets his hour upon the stage,</line>
<line form="verse">And then is heard no more. It is a tale</line>
<line form="verse">Told by an idiot, full of sound and fury,</line>
<line form="verse">Signifying nothing.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth&#8217;s Messenger.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Thou com&#8217;st to use thy tongue;</line>
<line form="verse">Thy story quickly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Gracious my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">I should report that which I say I saw,</line>
<line form="verse">But know not how to do&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Well, say, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As I did stand my watch upon the hill,</line>
<line form="verse">I look&#8217;d toward Birnan, and anon methought</line>
<line form="verse">The wood began to move.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Liar and slave!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB. MESS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let me endure your wrath, if&#8217;t be not so.</line>
<line form="verse">Within this three mile may you see it coming;</line>
<line form="verse">I say, a moving grove.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">If thou speak&#8217;st false,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the next tree shall thou hang alive,</line>
<line form="verse">Till famine cling thee; if thy speech be sooth,</line>
<line form="verse">I care not if thou dost for me as much.</line>
<line form="verse">I pull in resolution, and begin</line>
<line form="verse">To doubt th&#8217; equivocation of the fiend</line>
<line form="verse">That lies like truth. &#8220;Fear not, till Birnan wood</line>
<line form="verse">Do come to Dunsinane,&#8221; and now a wood</line>
<line form="verse">Comes toward Dunsinane. Arm, arm, and out!</line>
<line form="verse">If this which he avouches does appear,</line>
<line form="verse">There is nor flying hence, nor tarrying here.</line>
<line form="verse">I gin to be a-weary of the sun,</line>
<line form="verse">And wish th&#8217; estate  o&#8217; th&#8217; world were now undone.</line>
<line form="verse">Ring the alarum-bell! Blow wind, come wrack,</line>
<line form="verse">At least we&#8217;ll die with harness on our back.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Dunsinane. Before the castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Malcolm, Siward, Macduff)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Considering that they have crept near enough to Dunsinane, Malcolm gives the order to toss away the branches and attack, sending Siward and his son to attack first, while he and Macduff will hang back to see where they will most be needed.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Drum and Colors. Enter Malcolm, Siward, Macduff, and their army, with boughs.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now near enough; your leavy screens throw down,</line>
<line form="verse">And show like those you are. You, worthy uncle,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall with my cousin, your right noble son,</line>
<line form="verse">Lead our first battle. Worthy Macduff and we</line>
<line form="verse">Shall take upon &#8217;s what else remains to do,</line>
<line form="verse">According to our order.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Fare you well.</line>
<line form="verse">Do we but find the tyrant&#8217;s power tonight,</line>
<line form="verse">Let us be beaten, if we cannot fight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Make all our trumpets speak, give them all breath,</line>
<line form="verse">Those clamorous harbingers of blood and death.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt. Alarums continued.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="7">
<scenetitle>Scene 7</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A part of the field.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Macbeth, Young Siward, Macduff, Malcolm, Siward)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth realizes that he is trapped, but still questions where the one not born of woman might be. Young Siward finds him and is killed by Macbeth, who sneers that the young man was born of woman. Macduff rushes in, having heard the noise, searching for Macbeth; he fears he will be haunted by his family forever if he is not the one to kill the tyrant. The battle is going so well for the English that Malcolm enters the castle.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They have tied me to a stake; I cannot fly,</line>
<line form="verse">But bear-like I must fight the course. What&#8217;s he</line>
<line form="verse">That was not born of woman? Such a one</line>
<line form="verse">Am I to fear, or none.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Young Siward.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Y. SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What is thy name?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Thou&#8217;lt be afraid to hear it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Y. SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No; though thou call&#8217;st thyself a hotter name</line>
<line form="verse">Than any is in hell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">My name&#8217;s Macbeth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Y. SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The devil himself could not pronounce a title</line>
<line form="verse">More hateful to mine ear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No; nor more fearful.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Y. SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou liest, abhorred tyrant, with my sword</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll prove the lie thou speak&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Fight, and Young Siward slain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Thou wast born of woman.</line>
<line form="verse">But swords I smile at, weapons laugh to scorn,</line>
<line form="verse">Brandish&#8217;d by man that&#8217;s of a woman born.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="enter">Alarums. Enter Macduff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That way the noise is. Tyrant, show thy face!</line>
<line form="verse">If thou beest slain and with no stroke of mine,</line>
<line form="verse">My wife and children&#8217;s ghosts will haunt me still.</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot strike at wretched kerns, whose arms</line>
<line form="verse">Are hir&#8217;d to bear their staves; either thou, Macbeth,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else my sword with an unbattered edge</line>
<line form="verse">I sheathe again undeeded. There thou shouldst be;</line>
<line form="verse">By this great clatter, one of greatest note</line>
<line form="verse">Seems bruited. Let me find him, Fortune!</line>
<line form="verse">And more I beg not.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit" actor="MACD.">Exit. Alarums.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Malcolm and Siward.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This way, my lord, the castle&#8217;s gently rend&#8217;red:</line>
<line form="verse">The tyrant&#8217;s people on both sides do fight,</line>
<line form="verse">The noble thanes do bravely in the war,</line>
<line form="verse">The day almost itself professes yours,</line>
<line form="verse">And little is to do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">We have met with foes</line>
<line form="verse">That strike beside us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Enter, sir, the castle.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt. Alarum.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="8">
<scenetitle>Scene 8</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Another part of the field.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Macbeth, Macduff)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Macbeth dismisses suicide as an option, just as Macduff finally finds him. Macbeth has no wish to fight him, and admits to having avoided Macduff so far, having killed too many of his family already. Macduf f has no patience for words, and they fight. When Macbeth taunts him with the prophecy about how he cannot be killed, Macduff strikes right back, revealing that he was not born of woman, but ripped from his mother in a Caesarian section. Macbeth is suddenly full of fear, and curses the witches; he tries to avoid fighting any more with Macduff, but the latter calls him a coward, offering him the chance to surrender and be paraded around the country in a cage. Macbeth regains his courage, and though all the prophecies that announce his time is up have been fulfilled, he chooses to try to escape all the same, and the two begin fighting again. Macduff kills Macbeth.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macbeth.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why should I play the Roman fool, and die</line>
<line form="verse">On mine own sword? Whiles I see lives, the gashes</line>
<line form="verse">Do better upon them.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Turn, hell-hound, turn!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of all men else I have avoided thee.</line>
<line form="verse">But get thee back, my soul is too much charg&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">With blood of thine already.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I have no words,</line>
<line form="verse">My voice is in my sword, thou bloodier villain</line>
<line form="verse">Than terms can give thee out!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="fight">Fight. Alarum.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Thou losest labor.</line>
<line form="verse">As easy mayst thou the intrenchant air</line>
<line form="verse">With thy keen sword impress as make me bleed.</line>
<line form="verse">Let fall thy blade on vulnerable crests,</line>
<line form="verse">I bear a charmed life, which must not yield</line>
<line form="verse">To one of woman born.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Despair thy charm,</line>
<line form="verse">And let the angel whom thou still hast serv&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Tell thee, Macduff was from his mother&#8217;s womb</line>
<line form="verse">Untimely ripp&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Accursed be that tongue that tells me so,</line>
<line form="verse">For it hath cow&#8217;d my better part of man!</line>
<line form="verse">And be these juggling fiends no more believ&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">That palter with us in a double sense,</line>
<line form="verse">That keep the word of promise to our ear,</line>
<line form="verse">And break it to our hope. I&#8217;ll not fight with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then yield thee, coward,</line>
<line form="verse">And live to be the show and gaze  o&#8217; th&#8217; time!</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll have thee, as our rarer monsters are,</line>
<line form="verse">Painted upon a pole, and underwrit,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Here may you see the tyrant.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MACB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I will not yield,</line>
<line form="verse">To kiss the ground before young Malcolm&#8217;s feet,</line>
<line form="verse">And to be baited with the rabble&#8217;s curse.</line>
<line form="verse">Though Birnan wood be come to Dunsinane,</line>
<line form="verse">And thou oppos&#8217;d, being of no woman born,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet I will try the last. Before my body</line>
<line form="verse">I throw my warlike shield. Lay on, Macduff,</line>
<line form="verse">And damn&#8217;d be him that first cries, &#8220;Hold, enough!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt fighting. Alarums.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter fighting, and Macbeth slain. Macduff carries off Macbeth&#8217;s body.</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene num="9">
<scenetitle>Scene 9</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Dunsinane. Within Macbeth&#8217;s castle.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Malcolm, Siward, Rosse, Thanes, Soldiers, Macduff)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The victors are assembling, the various commanders arriving and tallying up the dead. Ross informs Siward that Young Siward is dead, but the old man is not too fussed once he is reassured that the young man died fighting. Macduff, the only missing commander, enters, carrying Macbeth&#8217;s head, and salutes Malcolm as King of Scotland. Malcolm is pleased, and immediately re-titles all the Scottish nobles as Earls instead of Thanes, and plans to call back all the exiles. He mentions in passing that Lady Macbeth most likely killed herself. He invites everyone to join him at his coronation.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Retreat and flourish. Enter, with Drum and Colors, Malcolm, Siward, Rosse, Thanes, and Soldiers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would the friends we miss were safe arriv&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Some must go off; and yet, by these I see,</line>
<line form="verse">So great a day as this is cheaply bought.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Macduff is missing, and your noble son.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your son, my lord, has paid a soldier&#8217;s debt.</line>
<line form="verse">He only liv&#8217;d but till he was a man,</line>
<line form="verse">The which no sooner had his prowess confirm&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">In the unshrinking station where he fought,</line>
<line form="verse">But like a man he died.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Then he is dead?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and brought off the field. Your cause of sorrow</line>
<line form="verse">Must not be measur&#8217;d by his worth, for then</line>
<line form="verse">It hath no end.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Had he his hurts before?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ROSSE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, on the front.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Why then. God&#8217;s soldier be he!</line>
<line form="verse">Had I as many sons as I have hairs,</line>
<line form="verse">I would not wish them to a fairer death.</line>
<line form="verse">And so his knell is knoll&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">He&#8217;s worth more sorrow,</line>
<line form="verse">And that I&#8217;ll spend for him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SIW.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He&#8217;s worth no more;</line>
<line form="verse">They say he parted well, and paid his score,</line>
<line form="verse">And so God be with him! Here comes newer comfort.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Macduff with Macbeth&#8217;s head.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MACD.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hail, King! For so thou art. Behold where stands</line>
<line form="verse">Th&#8217; usurper&#8217;s cursed head: the time is free.</line>
<line form="verse">I see thee compass&#8217;d with thy kingdom&#8217;s pearl,</line>
<line form="verse">That speak my salutation in their minds;</line>
<line form="verse">Whose voices I desire aloud with mine:</line>
<line form="verse">Hail, King of Scotland!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Hail, King of Scotland!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Flourish.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We shall not spend a large expense of time</line>
<line form="verse">Before we reckon with your several loves,</line>
<line form="verse">And make us even with you. My thanes and kinsmen,</line>
<line form="verse">Henceforth be earls, the first that ever Scotland</line>
<line form="verse">In such an honor nam&#8217;d. What&#8217;s more to do,</line>
<line form="verse">Which would be planted newly with the time,</line>
<line form="verse">As calling home our exil&#8217;d friends abroad</line>
<line form="verse">That fled the snares of watchful tyranny,</line>
<line form="verse">Producing forth the cruel ministers</line>
<line form="verse">Of this dead butcher and his fiend-like queen,</line>
<line form="verse">Who (as &#8217;tis thought) by self and violent hands</line>
<line form="verse">Took off her life; this, and what needful else</line>
<line form="verse">That calls upon us, by the grace of Grace,</line>
<line form="verse">We will perform in measure, time, and place.</line>
<line form="verse">So thanks to all at once and to each one,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom we invite to see us crown&#8217;d at Scone.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Flourish. Exeunt omnes.</stagedir>

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>

