<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Merchant of Venice">The Merchant of Venice</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="The Merchant of Venice">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUKE.">The Duke of Venice</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Venice knows that he cannot risk Venice&#8217;s livelihood by denying Shylock&#8217;s suit, but is less than happy at the fact.When Shylock complains to him of his daughter&#8217;s abduction, he does his best to find her again, but to no avail. When it comes to Shylock&#8217;s suit against Antonio, the Duke hopes that the moneylender is merely playing for effect and that he will relent; even more optimistically, he hopes that Shylock will be kind to Antonio and halve the amount of the debt. Though knowing Shylock to be hard-hearted, he is still shocked by the moneylender&#8217;s intransigence. Though he knows he has the power to dismiss the court, he does not know enough law to find a loophole for Antonio. When Shylock is confounded and finds himself in danger of Venetian law, the Duke makes a point of pardoning him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANT.">Antonio</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio is a merchant of Venice who has invested deeply in overseas ventures, to the extent that he no longer has any ready money left. However, he is highly respected in the merchants&#8217; quarter, and his credit is strong with them, especially since he has dispersed his investments widely enough that it is unlikely they will all fail. He is a deeply melancholic man, strongly attached to Bassanio, and for love of him risks his credit to the tune of three thousand ducats to allow the younger man to woo his lady. He is also known for lending to friends and taking no interest, and he despises those who do otherwise, particularly Shylock &#8212; at times even paying the debt of people trapped by their borrowing from the moneylender. The level of detestation he has for that man has led him even to the indignity of spitting on him, and it is an uncomfortable moment when he is brought to have to borrow money from the man he has publically called a dog. When Shylock calls him out on his previous insulting behavior, he merely grows irate and insults him some more. Antonio is so certain of the return of his ships that he accepts Shylock&#8217;s bond of a pound of flesh should he default on repaying the loan in time. Over the next three months, however, his ships are wrecked one by one, and he is left owing the pound of flesh to Shylock. Finding the moneylender impossible to reason with, he resolves to cease trying, and readies himself to die, hoping only for Bassanio to come and see him one last time before then. On being saved by the unexpected advocacy of the young lawyer, he is merciful, merely making sure that Shylock&#8217;s daughter and her husband, Antonio&#8217;s young friend Lorenzo, will inherit his wealth, and that the Jewish moneylender&#8217;s soul will be saved by his becoming a Christian. In thanks, he gives his gloves to the young lawyer when so requested, and convinces Bassanio to give up the ring the lawyer wants. He goes with Bassanio to Belmont, where he discovers the lawyer&#8217;s identity, and that he is not ruined after all, as three of his ships have come to port.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BASS.">Bassanio</persname>
<persdescription>Bassanio is a young gentleman of Venice who has squandered all his fortune and is therefore in dire need of a rich wife. A great friend of Antonio&#8217;s, he convinces the latter to lend him the necessary money for him to properly woo Portia. He invites Shylock to dine with them over the matter of a loan for this, allowing Lorenzo to abduct Jessica. He agrees to let his friend Gratiano follow him to Belmont on condition that he keep himself under control. He is greatly liked by Portia and Nerissa, as well as Portia&#8217;s servants, but he insists on attempting the test of the caskets without waiting, despite Portia&#8217;s entreaties. Winning by choosing humbly, he is overjoyed to have gained the lady, though his joy is soon tempered by hearing of Antonio&#8217;s troubles, and he rushes from Portia to see what he can do to save him. He does not recognize his wife when she is dressed as a man, and refuses to give her (as lawyer) the ring he received from her (as herself) and had sworn to never part from until Antonio asks him to, at which point he immediately does. He half-hopes to hide the fact, but is unsuccessful. He is desperate to excuse himself, and greatly relieved when it turns out that the learned lawyer was actually his wife in disguise. Whether his greater love is to Antonio or Portia remains uncertain, however.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SOL.">Solanio</persname>
<persdescription>Solanio is a friend of Antonio&#8217;s, who once mercantile concerns are dismissed as a cause of the man&#8217;s melancholy leaps on love as the reason why. He hopes to cheer Antonio up, but is worried about him, particularly after witnessing Shylock&#8217;s mad ravings in the street about the loss of his money and daughter. He does not like the moneylender in the slightest, not least because he is thoroughly anti-Semitic. He follows Antonio when the latter is trying to reason with Shylock, and cannot believe that the bond will be followed through.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GRA.">Gratiano</persname>
<persdescription>Gratiano is a friend of Bassanio. A great talker, he is almost impossible to shut up, and can be unmannerly, to the extent that Bassanio only allows him to accompany his trip to Belmont on condition that he keep himself under control. He helps Lorenzo abduct Jessica, which almost makes him late for the departure to Belmont. He falls in love with Nerissa, Portia&#8217;s lady-in-waiting, who agrees to marry him on condition that Bassanio succeeds in the task of the caskets. He has no compunction about admitting to the mercenary nature of Bassanio&#8217;s choice of bride. He returns to Venice with Bassanio on his mission to rescue Antonio, and gives his tongue free rein during the trial, spitting out invective against Shylock, and then mercilessly mocking him once the carpet is pulled out from under him. Like Bassanio, he is willing to prefer Antonio&#8217;s life to his newly-acquired wife&#8217;s. The law-clerk manages to convince him to give his wedding ring as a gift of thanks in return, which leads to some problems on his return to Belmont, as he had sworn to Nerissa that he would never remove it. He gives away that Bassanio has done much the same. On it being revealed that Nerissa and the clerk were one and the same, he is much relieved to discover that he has not in fact been cuckolded, and closes the play on a bawdy pun.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SAL.">Salerio</persname>
<persdescription>Salerio is a well-connected merchant of Venice, and a friend of Antonio and Bassanio. Owning at least one ship, he is convinced that worry about merchandise is the root of Antonio&#8217;s melancholy. With Gratiano, he helps Lorenzo abduct Jessica, but does not know where the two runaways have gone. He is very worried about Antonio&#8217;s investments, as he is deeply fond of the man and scared of Shylock, though completely unapologetic about his role in Jessica&#8217;s flight. He is sent to Belmont by Antonio to let Bassanio know of his bankruptcy and of Shylock&#8217;s insistence on the payment of the pound of flesh, and begs Lorenzo and Jessica to accompany him in this task.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LOR.">Lorenzo</persname>
<persdescription>Lorenzo is a friend of Bassanio. In love with Shylock&#8217;s daughter Jessica, he helps her run away from her father&#8217;s, with the aid of Graziano and Salerio. He flees with her to Genoa, before moving on to Belmont at Salerio&#8217;s insistence, to help support Bassanio when the latter finds out about Antonio&#8217;s losses. Portia asks him to take charge of Belmont while she is gone on her retreat during Bassanio&#8217;s absence. He has a great appreciation of nighttime and a deep love of music, but is not quick-witted enough to keep up with Lancelot&#8217;s wordplay. He is delighted to discover himself to be Shylock&#8217;s heir.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SHY.">Shylock</persname>
<persdescription>Shylock is a Jewish moneylender in Venice, who detests and despises Christians. He makes his money by charging interest on his loans, and dislikes Antonio for not doing so and therefore ruining his business &#8212; particularly as Antonio sometimes pays the debts of those who cannot repay their loans in time, and therefore spoils Shylock&#8217;s enrichment by taking control of their forfeitures. When he calls Antonio out on the latter&#8217;s insults, he merely provokes more insults from the merchant. He decides to ask for a pound of flesh as his bond from Antonio, apparently as a jest. He is a miser and something of a puritan, having no taste for music or other reveling, starving his servant and letting him wear out his clothes rather than replacing them. Considering Launcelot a spendthrift, he is happy to let him leave to go serve Bassanio, as this will make the latter go through his money more swiftly. Even his daughter considers him cruel. He flies into a wild passion when she flees his house, taking with her massive amounts of his money, and has her chased after as much if not more for the money than for her own sake. Knowing that Antonio was aware of this abduction, and hearing that the latter is ruined, he is delighted at the possibility of cutting out the merchant&#8217;s heart. He is able to justify revenge on the basis of the bad behavior of Christians. His insistence on the letter of the law will be his undoing, leaving him not only unable to kill Antonio, but losing all the extra money offered him, the return of his principal, and soon forfeiting all of his wealth and his life. He accepts to turn Christian to save his life, but is left ill by the sudden reversal in his fortune. He is not a particularly nice man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TUB.">Tubal</persname>
<persdescription>Tubal is a wealthy Jew of Venice, who lends Shylock enough to make up the full three thousand ducats the latter lends to Antonio. Shylock sends him to track down Jessica, though he is unable to do so, only being able to make a list of all the bills she has run up over the course of her flight. He also brings Shylock news that Antonio is on the verge of bankruptcy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LAUN.">Launcelot Gobbo</persname>
<persdescription>Launcelot Gobbo is a quick-witted young fellow who is originally Shylock&#8217;s servant. Badly-fed in that household, he switches his allegiance to Bassanio. He is friendly with Jessica, whom he teases remorselessly about her Jewishness. A trickster, he also teases his blind father, pretending to be someone else, and not letting him complete his sentences when they are asking Bassanio to take him into his service. On his last day at Shylock&#8217;s, he serves as go-between for Jessica and Lorenzo. He follows Bassanio to Belmont, and remains there with Lorenzo and Jessica.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GOB.">Old Gobbo</persname>
<persdescription>Old Gobbo is an old man, blind or as well as, and not entirely comfortable with long words. He wishes the best for his son Launcelot, to the extent of bringing gifts to the young man&#8217;s master. He accepts to help Launcelot beg Bassanio to take him on as a servant so that he may leave Shylock&#8217;s.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LEON.">Leonardo</persname>
<persdescription>Leonardo is one of Bassanio&#8217;s servants. He is sent out to do some shopping for his master when the latter receives the money from Shylock.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BALTH.">Balthazar</persname>
<persdescription>Balthazar is one of Portia&#8217;s servants. She sends him to bring her letters to Bellario, and to meet her and Nerissa on the way to Venice with the law-clerk clothes Bellario will give him. Portia steals his name for her disguise as a boy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="STEPH.">Stephano</persname>
<persdescription>Stephano is a servant of Portia&#8217;s. He announces her return to Belmont, supposedly from her religious retreat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="POR.">Portia</persname>
<persdescription>Portia is an extraordinarily rich heiress of Belmont constrained by her father&#8217;s will to accept in marriage whichever suitor successfully passes the test of the three caskets. Luckily, as an unsuccessful suitor must swear to never marry, most of them refuse to go as far as the ordeal, but she is still not overly glad of her circumstances. She has no taste for dark-complexioned men, though she is tactful enough not to say so directly to the Prince of Morocco. She is highly hopeful that Bassanio will succeed, but worried enough that she begs him to wait a few days before attempting the task, as she does not want him to leave as he will have to if he fails. By this point she definitely knows which casket is the successful one, and she has a song sung during his meditations that contains many words rhyming with &#8220;lead.&#8221; On being won, she is somewhat uncertain as to what she is, now that all her wealth has passed to Bassanio. She is either wildly generous or has no actual sense of money, offering a massive fortune to Bassanio to help Antonio with Shylock. She is also highly intelligent and trained in law, and knows enough that she quickly conceives a plan to secretly save Antonio&#8217;s life disguised as a man. With the help of instructions from her father&#8217;s old friend Bellario, she is able to do so, though she drags it out unconscionably, giving Shylock multiple opportunities to stop, but letting him get to the point of killing Antonio before revealing that he cannot and stripping him of his wealth. As thanks for saving Antonio&#8217;s life, she receives the ring that she gave Bassanio that he had sworn never to part with. Not best pleased by this, especially as he has earlier sworn he&#8217;d give her up to save Antonio, she leads him a merry dance on his return to Belmont, refusing to listen to his protestations of good faith and swearing that she would sleep with the lawyer who had the ring should he come along. Having properly panicked Bassanio, she reveals the trick, to his evident relief. She is also able to let Antonio know that he is not ruined after all, one of his ships having made it to shore, though she refuses to say how she knows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="NER.">Nerissa</persname>
<persdescription>Nerissa is Portia&#8217;s lady-in-waiting, verbal sparring partner, and friend. She is a merry wench. Fully supportive of her mistress in all, she has high hopes that Bassanio will return to Belmont. She agrees to marry Gratiano on condition that Bassanio succeed in the task of the caskets. When this is accomplished, she is quite happy to do so. At his request, she takes care of Jessica when the latter arrives at Belmont. She joins Portia in dressing up as men to save Antonio&#8217;s life, playing the part of a law clerk. Hearing Gratiano swear that he&#8217;d prefer her dead if that might save Antonio&#8217;s life, she is not best pleased, and in return convinces Gratiano to give her (as the law clerk) the ring that she gave him (as herself) which he had sworn never to remove. On his return to Belmont, she rants at him upon hearing it, and manages to twist him around her little finger, swearing that she&#8217;s slept with the clerk before doing so with her husband.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="JES.">Jessica</persname>
<persdescription>Jessica is Shylock&#8217;s daughter. She does not have the happiest of home-lives with her father, finding it only relieved by Lancelot&#8217;s jesting. She feels wrong that she does not actually like her father, but she cannot agree with his ways. Falling in love with Lorenzo, she plots with him to run away together. She is practical-minded enough to let him know how much money she can bring with her. She disguises herself as a boy to facilitate her flight, though she is deeply embarrassed to do so. Fleeing to Genoa with him and hence escaping a fun-denying father, she spends a great deal of money in the flush of her freedom, even giving up an heirloom ring for a monkey. She follows Lorenzo to Belmont, and assures the others that her father will not relent in the matter of Antonio&#8217;s bond. Finding Launcelot again there, she takes his teasing well. She matches wits well with those she meets, swearing that she would be able to find more examples of nights and lovers than Lorenzo could. She does not speak on hearing what happened to her father, nor on learning that she and Lorenzo will inherit all his wealth on his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOR.">The Prince of Morocco</persname>
<persdescription>The Prince of Morocco is a suitor to Portia&#8217;s hand. Dark-skinned, he is a great and boastful warrior, whose grandiloquent language overbears all before it. He is aware that the color of his skin may not overly please Portia, but he is not ashamed of it. He is proud and convinced of his own worth, and dresses entirely in white.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AR.">The Prince of Arragon</persname>
<persdescription>The Prince of Arragon is a prince of Spain and a suitor to Portia&#8217;s hand. He is a pretentious, supercilious elitist, disdaining all that is common.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JAIL.">Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>The Jailer [mute role] is charged with keeping an eye on Antonio to prevent him from running away before having paid his debt to Shylock. Despite the moneylender&#8217;s scoldings, he allows Antonio to walk around wherever he pleases in the city, but never lets his prisoner out of his sight.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERV.">Portia&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Portia&#8217;s Servant announces to her that various of her suitors have decided not to risk having to swear never to marry if they choose wrongly in the casket trial, and are therefore leaving.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANT. SERV.">Antonio&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio&#8217;s Servant is sent to fetch Salerio and Solanio when Antonio learns of the extent of his losses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SING.">Singer</persname>
<persdescription>The Singer sings a song containing a remarkable number of words rhyming with &#8216;lead&#8217; while Bassanio is making his choice over the caskets.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Antonio, Salerio, Solanio, Bassanio, Lorenzo, Gratiano)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antonio cannot put a finger on why, exactly, he is so sad; none of his friends&#8217; suggestions quite hit the mark, and their attempts to cheer him up are unsuccessful. His good friend Bassiano joins him. Left alone, Bassiano explains to Antonio that to repair his squandered fortunes, he intends to win the hand of Portia, a wealthy heiress. To make a good show as he woos her, since she is being sought by many suitors from all over the world, he asks Antonio to lend him some money. Antonio agrees, but points out that he has no cash at present, as all his money has been invested in sea ventures that have not yet returned; but his credit is good enough that he believes he will be able to raise the sum.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antonio, Salerio, and Solanio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In sooth, I know not why I am so sad;</line>
<line form="verse">It wearies me, you say it wearies you;</line>
<line form="verse">But how I caught it, found it, or came by it,</line>
<line form="verse">What stuff &#8217;tis made of, whereof it is born,</line>
<line form="verse">I am to learn;</line>
<line form="verse">And such a want-wit sadness makes of me,</line>
<line form="verse">That I have much ado to know myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your mind is tossing on the ocean,</line>
<line form="verse">There where your argosies with portly sail</line>
<line form="verse">Like signiors and rich burghers on the flood,</line>
<line form="verse">Or as it were the pageants of the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Do overpeer the petty traffickers</line>
<line form="verse">That cur&#8217;sy to them, do them reverence,</line>
<line form="verse">As they fly by them with their woven wings.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Believe me, sir, had I such venture forth,</line>
<line form="verse">The better part of my affections would</line>
<line form="verse">Be with my hopes abroad. I should be still</line>
<line form="verse">Plucking the grass to know where sits the wind,</line>
<line form="verse">Piring in maps for ports and piers and roads;</line>
<line form="verse">And every object that might make me fear</line>
<line form="verse">Misfortune to my ventures, out of doubt</line>
<line form="verse">Would make me sad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">My wind cooling my broth</line>
<line form="verse">Would blow me to an ague when I thought</line>
<line form="verse">What harm a wind too great might do at sea.</line>
<line form="verse">I should not see the sandy hour-glass run</line>
<line form="verse">But I should think of shallows and of flats,</line>
<line form="verse">And see my wealthy Andrew dock&#8217;d in sand,</line>
<line form="verse">Vailing her high top lower than her ribs</line>
<line form="verse">To kiss her burial. Should I go to church</line>
<line form="verse">And see the holy edifice of stone,</line>
<line form="verse">And not bethink me straight of dangerous rocks,</line>
<line form="verse">Which touching but my gentle vessel&#8217;s side</line>
<line form="verse">Would scatter all her spices on the stream,</line>
<line form="verse">Enrobe the roaring waters with my silks,</line>
<line form="verse">And in a word, but even now worth this,</line>
<line form="verse">And now worth nothing? Shall I have the thought</line>
<line form="verse">To think on this, and shall I lack the thought</line>
<line form="verse">That such a thing bechanc&#8217;d would make me sad?</line>
<line form="verse">But tell not me; I know Antonio</line>
<line form="verse">Is sad to think upon his merchandise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Believe me, no. I thank my fortune for it,</line>
<line form="verse">My ventures are not in one bottom trusted,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor to one place; nor is my whole estate</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the fortune of this present year:</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore my merchandise makes me not sad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then you are in love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Fie, fie!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not in love neither? Then let us say you are sad</line>
<line form="verse">Because you are not merry; and &#8217;twere as easy</line>
<line form="verse">For you to laugh and leap, and say you are merry</line>
<line form="verse">Because you are not sad. Now by two-headed Janus,</line>
<line form="verse">Nature hath fram&#8217;d strange fellows in her time:</line>
<line form="verse">Some that will evermore peep through their eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">And laugh like parrots at a bagpiper;</line>
<line form="verse">And other of such vinegar aspect</line>
<line form="verse">That they&#8217;ll not show their teeth in way of smile</line>
<line form="verse">Though Nestor swear the jest be laughable.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bassanio, Lorenzo, and Gratiano.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here comes Bassanio, your most noble kinsman,</line>
<line form="verse">Gratiano, and Lorenzo. Fare ye well,</line>
<line form="verse">We leave you now with better company.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would have stay&#8217;d till I had made you merry,</line>
<line form="verse">If worthier friends had not prevented me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your worth is very dear in my regard.</line>
<line form="verse">I take it your own business calls on you,</line>
<line form="verse">And you embrace th&#8217; occasion to depart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good morrow, my good lords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good signiors both, when shall we laugh? Say, when?</line>
<line form="verse">You grow exceeding strange. Must it be so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll make our leisures to attend on yours.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Salerio and Solanio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Lord Bassanio, since you have found Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">We two will leave you, but at dinner-time</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you have in mind where we must meet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not fail you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You look not well, Signior Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">You have too much respect upon the world.</line>
<line form="verse">They lose it that do buy it with much care.</line>
<line form="verse">Believe me you are marvellously chang&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I hold the world but as the world, Gratiano,</line>
<line form="verse">A stage, where every man must play a part,</line>
<line form="verse">And mine a sad one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Let me play the fool,</line>
<line form="verse">With mirth and laughter let old wrinkles come,</line>
<line form="verse">And let my liver rather heat with wine</line>
<line form="verse">Than my heart cool with mortifying groans.</line>
<line form="verse">Why should a man, whose blood is warm within,</line>
<line form="verse">Sit like his grandsire cut in alablaster?</line>
<line form="verse">Sleep when he wakes? And creep into the jaundies</line>
<line form="verse">By being peevish? I tell thee what, Antonio&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I love thee, and &#8217;tis my love that speaks&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">There are a sort of men whose visages</line>
<line form="verse">Do cream and mantle like a standing pond,</line>
<line form="verse">And do a willful stillness entertain,</line>
<line form="verse">With purpose to be dress&#8217;d in an opinion</line>
<line form="verse">Of wisdom, gravity, profound conceit,</line>
<line form="verse">As who should say, &#8220;I am Sir Oracle,</line>
<line form="verse">And when I ope my lips let no dog bark!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">O my Antonio, I do know of these</line>
<line form="verse">That therefore only are reputed wise</line>
<line form="verse">For saying nothing; when I am very sure</line>
<line form="verse">If they should speak, would almost damn those ears</line>
<line form="verse">Which hearing them would call their brothers fools.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll tell thee more of this another time;</line>
<line form="verse">But fish not with this melancholy bait</line>
<line form="verse">For this fool gudgeon, this opinion.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, good Lorenzo. Fare ye well a while,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll end my exhortation after dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, we will leave you then till dinner-time.</line>
<line form="verse">I must be one of these same dumb wise men,</line>
<line form="verse">For Gratiano never lets me speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, keep me company but two years more,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt not know the sound of thine own tongue.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fare you well! I&#8217;ll grow a talker for this gear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, i&#8217; faith, for silence is only commendable</line>
<line form="verse">In a neat&#8217;s tongue dried and a maid not vendible.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Gratiano and Lorenzo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is that&#8212;any thing now!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Gratiano speaks an infinite deal of nothing, more than any man in all Venice. His reasons are as two grains of wheat hid in two bushels of chaff; you shall seek all day ere you find them, and when you have them, they are not worth the search.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, tell me now what lady is the same</line>
<line form="verse">To whom you swore a secret pilgrimage,</line>
<line form="verse">That you today promis&#8217;d to tell me of?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis not unknown to you, Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">How much I have disabled mine estate,</line>
<line form="verse">By something showing a more swelling port</line>
<line form="verse">Than my faint means would grant continuance.</line>
<line form="verse">Nor do I now make moan to be abridg&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">From such a noble rate, but my chief care</line>
<line form="verse">Is to come fairly off from the great debts</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein my time something too prodigal</line>
<line form="verse">Hath left me gag&#8217;d. To you, Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">I owe the most in money and in love,</line>
<line form="verse">And from your love I have a warranty</line>
<line form="verse">To unburden all my plots and purposes</line>
<line form="verse">How to get clear of all the debts I owe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you, good Bassanio, let me know it,</line>
<line form="verse">And if it stand, as you yourself still do,</line>
<line form="verse">Within the eye of honor, be assur&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">My purse, my person, my extremest means,</line>
<line form="verse">Lie all unlock&#8217;d to your occasions.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In my school-days, when I had lost one shaft,</line>
<line form="verse">I shot his fellow of the self-same flight</line>
<line form="verse">The self-same way with more advised watch</line>
<line form="verse">To find the other forth, and by adventuring both</line>
<line form="verse">I oft found both. I urge this childhood proof,</line>
<line form="verse">Because what follows is pure innocence.</line>
<line form="verse">I owe you much, and like a willful youth,</line>
<line form="verse">That which I owe is lost, but if you please</line>
<line form="verse">To shoot another arrow that self way</line>
<line form="verse">Which you did shoot the first, I do not doubt,</line>
<line form="verse">As I will watch the aim, or to find both</line>
<line form="verse">Or bring your latter hazard back again,</line>
<line form="verse">And thankfully rest debtor for the first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You know me well, and herein spend but time</line>
<line form="verse">To wind about my love with circumstance,</line>
<line form="verse">And out of doubt you do me now more wrong</line>
<line form="verse">In making question of my uttermost</line>
<line form="verse">Than if you had made waste of all I have.</line>
<line form="verse">Then do but say to me what I should do</line>
<line form="verse">That in your knowledge may by me be done,</line>
<line form="verse">And I am prest unto it; therefore speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In Belmont is a lady richly left,</line>
<line form="verse">And she is fair and, fairer than that word,</line>
<line form="verse">Of wondrous virtues. Sometimes from her eyes</line>
<line form="verse">I did receive fair speechless messages.</line>
<line form="verse">Her name is Portia, nothing undervalu&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To Cato&#8217;s daughter, Brutus&#8217; Portia.</line>
<line form="verse">Nor is the wide world ignorant of her worth,</line>
<line form="verse">For the four winds blow in from every coast</line>
<line form="verse">Renowned suitors, and her sunny locks</line>
<line form="verse">Hang on her temples like a golden fleece,</line>
<line form="verse">Which makes her seat of Belmont Colchis&#8217; strond,</line>
<line form="verse">And many Jasons come in quest of her.</line>
<line form="verse">O my Antonio, had I but the means</line>
<line form="verse">To hold a rival place with one of them,</line>
<line form="verse">I have a mind presages me such thrift</line>
<line form="verse">That I should questionless be fortunate!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou know&#8217;st that all my fortunes are at sea,</line>
<line form="verse">Neither have I money nor commodity</line>
<line form="verse">To raise a present sum; therefore go forth,</line>
<line form="verse">Try what my credit can in Venice do.</line>
<line form="verse">That shall be rack&#8217;d, even to the uttermost,</line>
<line form="verse">To furnish thee to Belmont, to fair Portia.</line>
<line form="verse">Go presently inquire, and so will I,</line>
<line form="verse">Where money is, and I no question make</line>
<line form="verse">To have it of my trust, or for my sake.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Portia, Nerissa, Servingman)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Portia laments how she cannot choose her husband for herself, but must accept whichever one chooses the correct casket that her father has left behind after his death. She and her lady-in-waiting Nerissa discuss the various suitors who have come to woo her, none of whom she particularly likes – though she has fond memories of Bassanio. Despite this lack of interest in the possibilities, Portia insists she will obey her father&#8217;s will. A servant informs her that four of her suitors have decided not to risk taking the casket test, since if they fail they are bound to never marry, and that the Prince of Morocco will be arriving that evening.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Portia with her waiting-woman, Nerissa.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">By my troth, Nerissa, my little body is a-weary of this great world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You would be, sweet madam, if your miseries were in the same abundance as your good fortunes are; and yet for aught I see, they are as sick that surfeit with too much as they that starve with nothing. It is no mean happiness therefore to be seated in the mean: superfluity comes sooner by white hairs, but competency lives longer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Good sentences, and well pronounc&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">They would be better if well follow&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If to do were as easy as to know what were good to do, chapels had been churches, and poor men&#8217;s cottages princes&#8217; palaces. 
It is a good divine that follows his own instructions; I can easier teach twenty what were good to be done, than to be one of the twenty to follow mine own teaching. 
The brain may devise laws for the blood, but a hot temper leaps o&#8217;er a cold decree&#8212;such a hare is madness the youth, to skip o&#8217;er the meshes of good counsel the cripple. 
But this reasoning is not in the fashion to choose me a husband. O me, the word choose! I may neither choose who I would, nor refuse who I dislike; 
so is the will of a living daughter curb&#8217;d by the will of a dead father. Is it not hard, Nerissa, that I cannot choose one, nor refuse none?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Your father was ever virtuous, and holy men at their death have good inspirations; therefore the lott&#8217;ry that he hath devis&#8217;d 
in these three chests of gold, silver, and lead, whereof who chooses his meaning chooses you, will no doubt never be chosen by any rightly but one who you shall rightly love. 
But what warmth is there in your affection towards any of these princely suitors that are already come?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I pray thee over-name them, and as thou namest them, I will describe them; and according to my description level at my affection.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">First, there is the Neapolitan prince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, that&#8217;s a colt indeed, for he doth nothing but talk of his horse, and he makes it a great appropriation to his own good parts 
that he can shoe him himself. I am much afeard my lady his mother play&#8217;d false with a smith.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Then is there the County Palentine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He doth nothing but frown, as who should say, &#8220;And you will not have me, choose.&#8221; He hears merry tales and smiles not. 
I fear he will prove the weeping philosopher when he grows old, being so full of unmannerly sadness in his youth. 
I had rather be married to a death&#8217;s-head with a bone in his mouth than to either of these. God defend me from these two!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How say you by the French lord, Monsieur Le Bon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">God made him, and therefore let him pass for a man. In truth, I know it is a sin to be a mocker, but he! Why, he hath a horse better than the Neapolitan&#8217;s, a better bad habit of frowning than the Count Palentine; he is every man in no man. If a throstle sing, he falls straight a-cap&#8217;ring. He will fence with his own shadow. If I should marry him, I should marry twenty husbands. If he would despise me, I would forgive him, for if he love me to madness, I shall never requite him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What say you then to Falconbridge, the young baron of England?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You know I say nothing to him, for he understands not me, nor I him. He hath neither Latin, French, nor Italian, and you will come into the court and swear that I have a poor pennyworth in the English. He is a proper man&#8217;s picture, but alas, who can converse with a dumb show? How oddly he is suited! I think he bought his doublet in Italy, his round hose in France, his bonnet in Germany, and his behavior every where.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What think you of the Scottish lord, his neighbor?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That he hath a neighborly charity in him, for he borrow&#8217;d a box of the ear of the Englishman, and swore he would pay him again when he was able. I think the Frenchman became his surety and seal&#8217;d under for another.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How like you the young German, the Duke of Saxony&#8217;s nephew?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Very vildly in the morning, when he is sober, and most vildly in the afternoon, when he is drunk. When he is best, he is a little worse than a man, and when he is worst, he is little better than a beast. And the worst fall that ever fell, I hope I shall make shift to go without him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If he should offer to choose, and choose the right casket, you should refuse to perform your father&#8217;s will, if you should refuse to accept him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Therefore for fear of the worst, I pray thee set a deep glass of Rhenish wine on the contrary casket, for if the devil be within, and that temptation without, I know he will choose it. I will do any thing, Nerissa, ere I will be married to a spunge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You need not fear, lady, the having any of these lords. They have acquainted me with their determinations, which is indeed to return to their home, and to trouble you with no more suit, unless you may be won by some other sort than your father&#8217;s imposition depending on the caskets.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If I live to be as old as Sibylla, I will die as chaste as Diana, unless I be obtain&#8217;d by the manner of my father&#8217;s will. 
I am glad this parcel of wooers are so reasonable, for there is not one among them but I dote on his very absence, and I pray God grant them a fair departure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Do you not remember, lady, in your father&#8217;s time, a Venetian, a scholar and a soldier, that came hither in company of the Marquis of Montferrat?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, yes, it was Bassanio&#8212;as I think, so was he call&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">True, madam; he, of all the men that ever my foolish eyes look&#8217;d upon, was the best deserving a fair lady.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I remember him well, and I remember him worthy of thy praise.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Servingman.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">How now, what news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SERV.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The four strangers seek for you, madam, to take their leave; and there is a forerunner come from a fift, the Prince of Morocco, who brings word the Prince his master will be here tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If I could bid the fift welcome with so good heart as I can bid the other four farewell, I should be glad of his approach. If he have the condition of a saint, and the complexion of a devil, I had rather he should shrive me than wive me.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Come, Nerissa. Sirrah, go before.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Whiles we shut the gate upon one wooer, another knocks at the door.</line>
</speech>


<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A public place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Bassanio, Shylock, Antonio)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Bassanio asks the Jewish money-lender Shylock to lend 3000 ducats on Antonio&#8217;s security. Shylock points out that all of Antonio&#8217;s wealth is in risky ventures at present. To himself he considers how much he hates Antonio, who ruins his trade by lending money without interest. Antonio enters, sneering at Shylock for lending at interest; the two loathe one another, Shylock remembering all the times Antonio has insulted him or even spat at him, Antonio showing no remorse. Shylock insists he wants to be friends with Antonio, however, and therefore agrees to make the loan and, as a joke, that they make the penalty for non-repayment a pound of Antonio&#8217;s flesh. Bassanio will not hear of it, but Antonio brushes off his fears, being utterly certain that his ships will return before the repayment due date.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bassanio with Shylock the Jew.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Three thousand ducats, well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, sir, for three months.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">For three months, well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">For the which, as I told you, Antonio shall be bound.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Antonio shall become bound, well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">May you stead me? Will you pleasure me? Shall I know your answer?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Three thousand ducats for three months, and Antonio bound.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Your answer to that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Antonio is a good man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Have you heard any imputation to the contrary?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ho, no, no, no, no! My meaning in saying he is a good man is to have you understand me that he is sufficient. Yet his means are in supposition: he hath an argosy bound to Tripolis, another to the Indies; I understand moreover upon the Rialto, he hath a third at Mexico, a fourth for England, and other ventures he hath, squand&#8217;red abroad. But ships are but boards, sailors but men; there be land-rats and water-rats, water-thieves and land-thieves, I mean pirates, and then there is the peril of waters, winds, and rocks. The man is notwithstanding sufficient. Three thousand ducats; I think I may take his bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Be assur&#8217;d you may.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I will be assur&#8217;d I may; and that I may be assur&#8217;d, I will bethink me. May I speak with Antonio?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If it please you to dine with us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, to smell pork, to eat of the habitation which your prophet the Nazarite conjur&#8217;d the devil into. I will buy with you, sell with you, talk with you, walk with you, and so following; but I will not eat with you, drink with you, nor pray with you. What news on the Rialto? Who is he comes here?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antonio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This is Signior Antonio.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How like a fawning publican he looks!</line>
<line form="verse">I hate him for he is a Christian;</line>
<line form="verse">But more, for that in low simplicity</line>
<line form="verse">He lends out money gratis, and brings down</line>
<line form="verse">The rate of usance here with us in Venice.</line>
<line form="verse">If I can catch him once upon the hip,</line>
<line form="verse">I will feed fat the ancient grudge I bear him.</line>
<line form="verse">He hates our sacred nation, and he rails</line>
<line form="verse">Even there where merchants most do congregate</line>
<line form="verse">On me, my bargains, and my well-won thrift,</line>
<line form="verse">Which he calls interest. Cursed be my tribe</line>
<line form="verse">If I forgive him!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Shylock, do you hear?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am debating of my present store,</line>
<line form="verse">And by the near guess of my memory,</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot instantly raise up the gross</line>
<line form="verse">Of full three thousand ducats. What of that?</line>
<line form="verse">Tubal, a wealthy Hebrew of my tribe,</line>
<line form="verse">Will furnish me. But soft, how many months</line>
<line form="verse">Do you desire?</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Antonio.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Rest you fair, good signior,</line>
<line form="verse">Your worship was the last man in our mouths.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shylock, albeit I neither lend nor borrow</line>
<line form="verse">By taking nor by giving of excess,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet to supply the ripe wants of my friend,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll break a custom.</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To Bassanio.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Is he yet possess&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">How much ye would?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Ay, ay, three thousand ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And for three months.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I had forgot&#8212;three months&#8212;</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To Bassanio.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="7">you told me so.</line>
<line form="verse">Well then, your bond; and let me see&#8212;but hear you,</line>
<line form="verse">Methoughts you said you neither lend nor borrow</line>
<line form="verse">Upon advantage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I do never use it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When Jacob graz&#8217;d his uncle Laban&#8217;s sheep&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">This Jacob from our holy Abram was</line>
<line form="verse">(As his wise mother wrought in his behalf)</line>
<line form="verse">The third possessor; ay, he was the third&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And what of him? Did he take interest?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, not take interest, not as you would say</line>
<line form="verse">Directly int&#8217;rest. Mark what Jacob did:</line>
<line form="verse">When Laban and himself were compremis&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">That all the eanlings which were streak&#8217;d and pied</line>
<line form="verse">Should fall as Jacob&#8217;s hire, the ewes being rank</line>
<line form="verse">In end of autumn turned to the rams,</line>
<line form="verse">And when the work of generation was</line>
<line form="verse">Between these woolly breeders in the act,</line>
<line form="verse">The skillful shepherd pill&#8217;d me certain wands,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the doing of the deed of kind,</line>
<line form="verse">He stuck them up before the fulsome ewes,</line>
<line form="verse">Who then conceiving did in eaning time</line>
<line form="verse">Fall parti-color&#8217;d lambs, and those were Jacob&#8217;s.</line>
<line form="verse">This was a way to thrive, and he was blest;</line>
<line form="verse">And thrift is blessing, if men steal it not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This was a venture, sir, that Jacob serv&#8217;d for,</line>
<line form="verse">A thing not in his power to bring to pass,</line>
<line form="verse">But sway&#8217;d and fashion&#8217;d by the hand of heaven.</line>
<line form="verse">Was this inserted to make interest good?</line>
<line form="verse">Or is your gold and silver ewes and rams?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I cannot tell, I make it breed as fast.</line>
<line form="verse">But note me, signior.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Mark you this, Bassanio,</line>
<line form="verse">The devil can cite Scripture for his purpose.</line>
<line form="verse">An evil soul producing holy witness</line>
<line form="verse">Is like a villain with a smiling cheek,</line>
<line form="verse">A goodly apple rotten at the heart.</line>
<line form="verse">O, what a goodly outside falsehood hath!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Three thousand ducats&#8212;&#8217;tis a good round sum.</line>
<line form="verse">Three months from twelve; then let me see, the rate&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, Shylock, shall we be beholding to you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Signior Antonio, many a time and oft</line>
<line form="verse">In the Rialto you have rated me</line>
<line form="verse">About my moneys and my usances.</line>
<line form="verse">Still have I borne it with a patient shrug</line>
<line form="verse">(For suff&#8217;rance is the badge of all our tribe).</line>
<line form="verse">You call me misbeliever, cut-throat dog,</line>
<line form="verse">And spet upon my Jewish gaberdine,</line>
<line form="verse">And all for use of that which is mine own.</line>
<line form="verse">Well then, it now appears you need my help.</line>
<line form="verse">Go to then, you come to me, and you say,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Shylock, we would have moneys,&#8221; you say so&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">You, that did void your rheum upon my beard,</line>
<line form="verse">And foot me as you spurn a stranger cur</line>
<line form="verse">Over your threshold; moneys is your suit.</line>
<line form="verse">What should I say to you? Should I not say,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Hath a dog money? Is it possible</line>
<line form="verse">A cur can lend three thousand ducats?&#8221; Or</line>
<line form="verse">Shall I bend low and in a bondman&#8217;s key,</line>
<line form="verse">With bated breath and whisp&#8217;ring humbleness,</line>
<line form="verse">Say this:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Fair sir, you spet on me on Wednesday last,</line>
<line form="verse">You spurn&#8217;d me such a day, another time</line>
<line form="verse">You call&#8217;d me dog; and for these courtesies</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll lend you thus much moneys&#8221;?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am as like to call thee so again,</line>
<line form="verse">To spet on thee again, to spurn thee too.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou wilt lend this money, lend it not</line>
<line form="verse">As to thy friends, for when did friendship take</line>
<line form="verse">A breed for barren metal of his friend?</line>
<line form="verse">But lend it rather to thine enemy,</line>
<line form="verse">Who if he break, thou mayst with better face</line>
<line form="verse">Exact the penalty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why, look you how you storm!</line>
<line form="verse">I would be friends with you, and have your love,</line>
<line form="verse">Forget the shames that you have stain&#8217;d me with,</line>
<line form="verse">Supply your present wants, and take no doit</line>
<line form="verse">Of usance for my moneys, and You&#8217;ll not hear me.</line>
<line form="verse">This is kind I offer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This were kindness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">This kindness will I show.</line>
<line form="verse">Go with me to a notary, seal me there</line>
<line form="verse">Your single bond; and in a merry sport</line>
<line form="verse">If you repay me not on such a day,</line>
<line form="verse">In such a place, such sum or sums as are</line>
<line form="verse">Express&#8217;d in the condition, let the forfeit</line>
<line form="verse">Be nominated for an equal pound</line>
<line form="verse">Of your fair flesh, to be cut off and taken</line>
<line form="verse">In what part of your body pleaseth me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content, in faith, I&#8217;ll seal to such a bond,</line>
<line form="verse">And say there is much kindness in the Jew.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You shall not seal to such a bond for me,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll rather dwell in my necessity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, fear not, man, I will not forfeit it.</line>
<line form="verse">Within these two months, that&#8217;s a month before</line>
<line form="verse">This bond expires, I do expect return</line>
<line form="verse">Of thrice three times the value of this bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O father Abram, what these Christians are,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose own hard dealings teaches them suspect</line>
<line form="verse">The thoughts of others! Pray you tell me this:</line>
<line form="verse">If he should break his day, what should I gain</line>
<line form="verse">By the exaction of the forfeiture?</line>
<line form="verse">A pound of man&#8217;s flesh taken from a man</line>
<line form="verse">Is not so estimable, profitable neither,</line>
<line form="verse">As flesh of muttons, beefs, or goats. I say,</line>
<line form="verse">To buy his favor, I extend this friendship.</line>
<line form="verse">If he will take it, so, if not, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>;</line>
<line form="verse">And for my love I pray you wrong me not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, Shylock, I will seal unto this bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then meet me forthwith at the notary&#8217;s;</line>
<line form="verse">Give him direction for this merry bond,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will go and purse the ducats straight,</line>
<line form="verse">See to my house, left in the fearful guard</line>
<line form="verse">Of an unthrifty knave, and presently</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll be with you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Hie thee, gentle Jew.</line>
<line form="verse">The Hebrew will turn Christian, he grows kind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I like not fair terms and a villain&#8217;s mind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come on, in this there can be no dismay,</line>
<line form="verse">My ships come home a month before the day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Prince of Morocco, Followers, Portia, Nerissa)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The bragging Prince of Morocco introduces himself to Portia, who flatters him. He declares his intention of undertaking the choice of caskets, though Portia reminds him that he must vow never to marry if he is unsuccessful. He is determined all the same.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Flourish cornets. Enter the Prince of Morocco, a tawny Moor, all in white, and three or four Followers accordingly, with Portia, Nerissa, and their Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Mislike me not for my complexion,</line>
<line form="verse">The shadowed livery of the burnish&#8217;d sun,</line>
<line form="verse">To whom I am a neighbor and near bred.</line>
<line form="verse">Bring me the fairest creature northward born,</line>
<line form="verse">Where Phoebus&#8217; fire scarce thaws the icicles,</line>
<line form="verse">And let us make incision for your love,</line>
<line form="verse">To prove whose blood is reddest, his or mine.</line>
<line form="verse">I tell thee, lady, this aspect of mine</line>
<line form="verse">Hath fear&#8217;d the valiant; by my love, I swear</line>
<line form="verse">The best-regarded virgins of our clime</line>
<line form="verse">Have lov&#8217;d it too. I would not change this hue,</line>
<line form="verse">Except to steal your thoughts, my gentle queen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In terms of choice I am not solely led</line>
<line form="verse">By nice direction of a maiden&#8217;s eyes;</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, the lott&#8217;ry of my destiny</line>
<line form="verse">Bars me the right of voluntary choosing.</line>
<line form="verse">But if my father had not scanted me,</line>
<line form="verse">And hedg&#8217;d me by his wit to yield myself</line>
<line form="verse">His wife who wins me by that means I told you,</line>
<line form="verse">Yourself, renowned Prince, then stood as fair</line>
<line form="verse">As any comer I have look&#8217;d on yet</line>
<line form="verse">For my affection.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Even for that I thank you;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore I pray you lead me to the caskets</line>
<line form="verse">To try my fortune. By this scimitar</line>
<line form="verse">That slew the Sophy and a Persian prince</line>
<line form="verse">That won three fields of Sultan Solyman,</line>
<line form="verse">I would o&#8217;erstare the sternest eyes that look,</line>
<line form="verse">Outbrave the heart most daring on the earth,</line>
<line form="verse">Pluck the young sucking cubs from the she-bear,</line>
<line form="verse">Yea, mock the lion when &#8217;a roars for prey,</line>
<line form="verse">To win thee, lady. But alas the while!</line>
<line form="verse">If Hercules and Lichas play at dice</line>
<line form="verse">Which is the better man, the greater throw</line>
<line form="verse">May turn by fortune from the weaker hand:</line>
<line form="verse">So is Alcides beaten by his rage,</line>
<line form="verse">And so may I, blind fortune leading me,</line>
<line form="verse">Miss that which one unworthier may attain,</line>
<line form="verse">And die with grieving.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">You must take your chance,</line>
<line form="verse">And either not attempt to choose at all,</line>
<line form="verse">Or swear before you choose, if you choose wrong</line>
<line form="verse">Never to speak to lady afterward</line>
<line form="verse">In way of marriage; therefore be advis&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nor will not. Come bring me unto my chance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">First, forward to the temple; after dinner</line>
<line form="verse">Your hazard shall be made.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Good fortune then!</line>
<line form="verse">To make me blest or cursed&#8217;st among men.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Cornets. Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Launcelot Gobbo, Old Gobbo, Bassanio, Followers, Leonardo, Gratiano)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Shylock&#8217;s servant Launcelot Gobbo wrestles with his conscience over whether to remain a servant to Shylock or not, and finally convinces himself to leave. His blind father comes looking for him, and he decides to play a trick on the old man, pretending to be someone else. In the end Launcelot admits to being himself, and explains that he intends to run away from Shylock, who starves him, and see if he can get service with Bassanio, who is hiring. Bassanio comes in, giving a flurry of instructions, and the two Gobbos interrupt him and plead for him to take Launcelot into his service, which in the end he does. Gratiano asks Bassanio to let him come along to Belmont with him, and Bassanio agrees on condition he keep a close watch on his sense of humor. </scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Clown Launcelot Gobbo alone.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Certainly my conscience will serve me to run from this Jew my master. 
The fiend is at mine elbow and tempts me, saying to me, &#8220;Gobbo, Launcelot Gobbo, good Launcelot,&#8221; or &#8220;good Gobbo,&#8221; 
or &#8220;good Launcelot Gobbo, use your legs, take the start, run away.&#8221; My conscience says, &#8220;No; take heed, honest Launcelot, take heed, honest Gobbo,&#8221; 
or as aforesaid, &#8220;honest Launcelot Gobbo, do not run, scorn running with thy heels.&#8221; 
Well, the most courageous fiend bids me pack. &#8220;Fia!&#8221; says the fiend; &#8220;away!&#8221; says the fiend; &#8220;for the heavens, rouse up a brave mind,&#8221; says the fiend, &#8220;and run.&#8221; Well, my conscience, hanging about the neck of my heart, says very wisely to me, &#8220;My honest friend Launcelot, being an honest man&#8217;s son&#8221;&#8212;or rather an honest woman&#8217;s son, for indeed my father did something smack, something grow to, he had a kind of taste&#8212;well, my conscience says, &#8220;Launcelot, bouge not.&#8221; &#8220;Bouge,&#8221; says the fiend. &#8220;Bouge not,&#8221; says my conscience. &#8220;Conscience,&#8221; say I, &#8220;you counsel well.&#8221; &#8220;Fiend,&#8221; say I, &#8220;you counsel well.&#8221; To be rul&#8217;d by my conscience, I should stay with the Jew my master, who (God bless the mark) is a kind of devil; and to run away from the Jew, I should be rul&#8217;d by the fiend, who, saving your reverence, is the devil himself. Certainly the Jew is the very devil incarnation, and in my conscience, my conscience is but a kind of hard conscience, to offer to counsel me to stay with the Jew. The fiend gives the more friendly counsel: I will run, fiend; my heels are at your commandment, I will run.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Old Gobbo with a basket.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Master young man, you, I pray you, which is the way to Master Jew&#8217;s?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir><line form="prose"> O heavens, this is my true-begotten father, who being more 
than sand-blind, high gravel-blind, knows me not. I will try confusions with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Master young gentleman, I pray you, which is the way to Master Jew&#8217;s?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Turn up on your right hand at the next turning, but at the next turning of all, on your left; marry, at the very next turning, turn of no hand, but turn down indirectly to the Jew&#8217;s house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Be God&#8217;s sonties, &#8217;twill be a hard way to hit. Can you tell me whether one Launcelot, that dwells with him, dwell with him or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Talk you of young Master Launcelot?</line>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Mark me now, now will I raise the waters.&#8212;Talk you of young Master Launcelot?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No master, sir, but a poor man&#8217;s son. His father, though I say&#8217;t, is an honest exceeding poor man and, God be thank&#8217;d, well to live.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, let his father be what &#8217;a will, we talk of young Master Launcelot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Your worship&#8217;s friend and Launcelot, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">But I pray you, ergo, old man, ergo, I beseech you, talk you of young Master Launcelot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Of Launcelot, an&#8217;t please your mastership.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ergo, Master Launcelot. Talk not of Master Launcelot, father, for the young gentleman, according to Fates and Destinies, and such odd sayings, the Sisters Three, and such branches of learning, is indeed deceas&#8217;d, or as you would say in plain terms, gone to heaven.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, God forbid, the boy was the very staff of my age, my very prop.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">Do I look like a cudgel or a hovel-post, a staff, or a prop?&#8212;Do you know me, father?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Alack the day, I know you not, young gentleman, but I pray you tell me, is my boy, God rest his soul, alive or dead?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Do you not know me, father?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Alack, sir, I am sand-blind, I know you not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, indeed if you had your eyes you might fail of the knowing me; it is a wise father that knows his own child. Well, old man, I will tell you news of your son. Give me your blessing; truth will come to light; murder cannot be hid long; a man&#8217;s son may, but in the end truth will out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Pray you, sir, stand up. I am sure you are not Launcelot, my boy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Pray you let&#8217;s have no more fooling about it, but give me your blessing. I am Launcelot, your boy that was, your son that is, your child that shall be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I cannot think you are my son.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I know not what I shall think of that; but I am Launcelot, the Jew&#8217;s man, and I am sure Margery your wife is my mother.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Her name is Margery indeed. I&#8217;ll be sworn, if thou be Launcelot, thou art mine own flesh and blood. 
Lord worshipp&#8217;d might he be, what a beard hast thou got! Thou hast got more hair on thy chin than Dobbin my fill-horse has on his tail.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It should seem then that Dobbin&#8217;s tail grows backward. I am sure he had more hair of his tail than I have of my face when I last saw him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Lord, how art thou chang&#8217;d! How dost thou and thy master agree? I have brought him a present. How &#8217;gree you now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, well; but for mine own part, as I have set up my rest to run away, so I will not rest till I have run some ground. My master&#8217;s a very Jew. Give him a present! Give him a halter. 
I am famish&#8217;d in his service; you may tell every finger I have with my ribs. Father, I am glad you are come; give me your present to one Master Bassanio, who indeed gives rare new liveries. If I serve not him, I will run as far as God has any ground. O rare fortune, here comes the man. To him, father, for I am a Jew if I serve the Jew any longer.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bassanio with a follower or two, one of them Leonardo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You may do so, but let it be so hasted that supper be ready at the farthest by five of the clock. See these letters deliver&#8217;d, put the liveries to making, and desire Gratiano to come anon to my lodging.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit one of his men.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">To him, father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">God bless your worship!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Gramercy, wouldst thou aught with me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here&#8217;s my son, sir, a poor boy&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not a poor boy, sir, but the rich Jew&#8217;s man, that would, sir, as my father shall specify&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He hath a great infection, sir, as one would say, to serve&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Indeed the short and the long is, I serve the Jew, and have a desire, as my father shall specify&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">His master and he (saving your worship&#8217;s reverence) are scarce cater-cousins&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">To be brief, the very truth is that the Jew, having done me wrong, doth cause me, as my father, being I hope an old man, shall frutify unto you&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I have here a dish of doves that I would bestow upon your worship, and my suit is&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">In very brief, the suit is impertinent to myself, as your worship shall know by this honest old man, and though I say it, though old man, yet poor man, my father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">One speak for both. What would you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Serve you, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GOB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That is the very defect of the matter, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know thee well, thou hast obtain&#8217;d thy suit.</line>
<line form="verse">Shylock thy master spoke with me this day,</line>
<line form="verse">And hath preferr&#8217;d thee, if it be preferment</line>
<line form="verse">To leave a rich Jew&#8217;s service, to become</line>
<line form="verse">The follower of so poor a gentleman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The old proverb is very well parted between my master Shylock and you, sir: you have the grace of God, sir, and he hath enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou speak&#8217;st it well. Go, father, with thy son.</line>
<line form="verse">Take leave of thy old master, and inquire</line>
<line form="verse">My lodging out.&#8212;Give him a livery</line>
<line form="verse">More guarded than his fellows&#8217;; see it done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Father, in. I cannot get a service, no, I have ne&#8217;er a tongue in my head, well!</line>
<stagedir type="action">Looking on his palm.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">If any man in Italy have a fairer table, which doth offer to swear upon a book, I shall have good fortune. Go to, here&#8217;s a simple line of life! Here&#8217;s a small trifle of wives! Alas, fifteen wives is nothing! Aleven widows and nine maids is a simple coming-in for one man. And then to scape drowning thrice, and to be in peril of my life with the edge of a feather-bed, here are simple scapes. Well, if Fortune be a woman, she&#8217;s a good wench for this gear. Father, come, I&#8217;ll take my leave of the Jew in the twinkling.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Clown with Old Gobbo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray thee, good Leonardo, think on this:</line>
<line form="verse">These things being bought and orderly bestowed,</line>
<line form="verse">Return in haste, for I do feast tonight</line>
<line form="verse">My best esteem&#8217;d acquaintance. Hie thee, go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My best endeavors shall be done herein.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Gratiano.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where&#8217;s your master?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LEON.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Yonder, sir, he walks.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Leonardo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Signior Bassanio!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Gratiano!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have suit to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">You have obtain&#8217;d it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You must not deny me; I must go with you to Belmont.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then you must. But hear thee, Gratiano:</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art too wild, too rude, and bold of voice&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Parts that become thee happily enough,</line>
<line form="verse">And in such eyes as ours appear not faults,</line>
<line form="verse">But where thou art not known, why, there they show</line>
<line form="verse">Something too liberal. Pray thee take pain</line>
<line form="verse">To allay with some cold drops of modesty</line>
<line form="verse">Thy skipping spirit, lest through thy wild behavior</line>
<line form="verse">I be misconst&#8217;red in the place I go to,</line>
<line form="verse">And lose my hopes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Signior Bassanio, hear me:</line>
<line form="verse">If I do not put on a sober habit,</line>
<line form="verse">Talk with respect, and swear but now and then,</line>
<line form="verse">Wear prayer-books in my pocket, look demurely,</line>
<line form="verse">Nay more, while grace is saying hood mine eyes</line>
<line form="verse">Thus with my hat, and sigh and say amen,</line>
<line form="verse">Use all the observance of civility,</line>
<line form="verse">Like one well studied in a sad ostent</line>
<line form="verse">To please his grandam, never trust me more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, we shall see your bearing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, but I bar tonight, you shall not gauge me</line>
<line form="verse">By what we do tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">No, that were pity.</line>
<line form="verse">I would entreat you rather to put on</line>
<line form="verse">Your boldest suit of mirth, for we have friends</line>
<line form="verse">That purpose merriment. But fare you well,</line>
<line form="verse">I have some business.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I must to Lorenzo and the rest,</line>
<line form="verse">But we will visit you at supper-time.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A room in Shylock&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Jessica, Launcelot)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Shylock&#8217;s daughter Jessica expresses her sorrow at Launcelot&#8217;s leaving, as he was the one distraction from the intense boredom of the household. She gives him a letter for Bassanio&#8217;s friend Lorenzo, whom she is planning to elope with.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Jessica and the Clown Launcelot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sorry thou wilt leave my father so.</line>
<line form="verse">Our house is hell, and thou, a merry devil,</line>
<line form="verse">Didst rob it of some taste of tediousness.</line>
<line form="verse">But fare thee well, there is a ducat for thee,</line>
<line form="verse">And, Launcelot, soon at supper shalt thou see</line>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo, who is thy new master&#8217;s guest.</line>
<line form="verse">Give him this letter, do it secretly,</line>
<line form="verse">And so farewell. I would not have my father</line>
<line form="verse">See me in talk with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose"><french xml:lang="fr">Adieu</french>, tears exhibit my tongue. Most beautiful pagan, most sweet Jew! If a Christian do not play the knave and get thee, I am much deceiv&#8217;d. 
But <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>, these foolish drops do something drown my manly spirit. <french xml:lang="fr">Adieu</french>!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Farewell, good Launcelot.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Launcelot.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Alack, what heinous sin is it in me</line>
<line form="verse">To be ashamed to be my father&#8217;s child!</line>
<line form="verse">But though I am a daughter to his blood,</line>
<line form="verse">I am not to his manners. O Lorenzo,</line>
<line form="verse">If thou keep promise, I shall end this strife,</line>
<line form="verse">Become a Christian and thy loving wife.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Gratiano, Lorenzo, Salerio, Solanio, Launcelot)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lorenzo, Gratiano, Solerio and Solanio discuss the details of the plan to help carry off Jessica. Launcelot delivers Jessica&#8217;s letter.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Gratiano, Lorenzo, Salerio, and Solanio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, we will slink away in supper-time,</line>
<line form="verse">Disguise us at my lodging, and return</line>
<line form="verse">All in an hour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We have not made good preparation.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We have not spoke us yet of torch-bearers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis vile, unless it may be quaintly ordered,</line>
<line form="verse">And better in my mind not undertook.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis now but four of clock, we have two hours</line>
<line form="verse">To furnish us.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Launcelot with a letter.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Friend Launcelot, what&#8217;s the news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And it shall please you to break up this, it shall seem to signify.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I know the hand; in faith, &#8217;tis a fair hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And whiter than the paper it writ on</line>
<line form="verse">Is the fair hand that writ.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Love-news, in faith.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By your leave, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Whither goest thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, sir, to bid my old master the Jew to sup tonight with my new master the Christian.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hold here, take this. Tell gentle Jessica</line>
<line form="verse">I will not fail her, speak it privately.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Clown.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Go, gentlemen,</line>
<line form="verse">Will you prepare you for this masque tonight?</line>
<line form="verse">I am provided of a torch-bearer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, marry, I&#8217;ll be gone about it straight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so will I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Meet me and Gratiano</line>
<line form="verse">At Gratiano&#8217;s lodging some hour hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis good we do so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Solanio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Was not that letter from fair Jessica?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I must needs tell thee all. She hath directed</line>
<line form="verse">How I shall take her from her father&#8217;s house,</line>
<line form="verse">What gold and jewels she is furnish&#8217;d with,</line>
<line form="verse">What page&#8217;s suit she hath in readiness.</line>
<line form="verse">If e&#8217;er the Jew her father come to heaven,</line>
<line form="verse">It will be for his gentle daughter&#8217;s sake,</line>
<line form="verse">And never dare misfortune cross her foot,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless she do it under this excuse,</line>
<line form="verse">That she is issue to a faithless Jew.</line>
<line form="verse">Come go with me, peruse this as thou goest.</line>
<line form="verse">Fair Jessica shall be my torch-bearer.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. Before Shylock&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Shylock, Launcelot, Jessica)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Shylock bids a grumpy farewell to Launcelot as he prepares to leave for dinner at Bassanio&#8217;s, predicting that the servant will not find life so easy with another master. He is uneasy and does not particularly wish to go to the meal. Still, he gives Jessica his keys and tells her to bar herself up against the possibility of seeing revelers pass by. He leaves.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Shylock the Jew and his man that was, the Clown Launcelot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, thou shalt see, thy eyes shall be thy judge,</line>
<line form="verse">The difference of old Shylock and Bassanio.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">What, Jessica!&#8212;Thou shalt not gurmandize,</line>
<line form="verse">As thou hast done with me&#8212;What, Jessica!&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And sleep and snore, and rend apparel out&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Why, Jessica, I say!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why, Jessica!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who bids thee call? I do not bid thee call.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your worship was wont to tell me I could do nothing without bidding.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Jessica.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Call you? What is your will?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am bid forth to supper, Jessica.</line>
<line form="verse">There are my keys. But wherefore should I go?</line>
<line form="verse">I am not bid for love, they flatter me,</line>
<line form="verse">But yet I&#8217;ll go in hate, to feed upon</line>
<line form="verse">The prodigal Christian. Jessica, my girl,</line>
<line form="verse">Look to my house. I am right loath to go;</line>
<line form="verse">There is some ill a-brewing towards my rest,</line>
<line form="verse">For I did dream of money-bags tonight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I beseech you, sir, go. My young master doth expect your reproach.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">So do I his.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And they have conspir&#8217;d together. I will not say you shall see a masque, but if you do, then it was not for nothing that my nose fell a-bleeding on 
Black Monday last at six a&#8217; clock i&#8217; th&#8217; morning, falling out that year on Ash We&#8217;n&#8217;sday was four year in th&#8217; afternoon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, are there masques? Hear you me, Jessica:</line>
<line form="verse">Lock up my doors, and when you hear the drum</line>
<line form="verse">And the vile squealing of the wry-neck&#8217;d fife,</line>
<line form="verse">Clamber not you up to the casements then,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor thrust your head into the public street</line>
<line form="verse">To gaze on Christian fools with varnish&#8217;d faces;</line>
<line form="verse">But stop my house&#8217;s ears, I mean my casements;</line>
<line form="verse">Let not the sound of shallow fopp&#8217;ry enter</line>
<line form="verse">My sober house. By Jacob&#8217;s staff I swear</line>
<line form="verse">I have no mind of feasting forth tonight;</line>
<line form="verse">But I will go. Go you before me, sirrah,</line>
<line form="verse">Say I will come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I will go before, sir. Mistress, look out at window for all this&#8212;</line>
<line form="rhyme" offset="2">There will come a Christian by,</line>
<line form="rhyme" offset="2">Will be worth a Jewess&#8217; eye.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What says that fool of Hagar&#8217;s offspring, ha?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His words were &#8220;Farewell, mistress!&#8221;&#8212;nothing else.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The patch is kind enough, but a huge feeder,</line>
<line form="verse">Snail-slow in profit, and he sleeps by day</line>
<line form="verse">More than the wild-cat. Drones hive not with me,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore I part with him, and part with him</line>
<line form="verse">To one that I would have him help to waste</line>
<line form="verse">His borrowed purse. Well, Jessica, go in,</line>
<line form="verse">Perhaps I will return immediately.</line>
<line form="verse">Do as I bid you, shut doors after you;</line>
<line form="verse">Fast bind, fast find&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">A proverb never stale in thrifty mind.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Farewell, and if my fortune be not cross&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">I have a father, you a daughter, lost.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. Before Shylock&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Gratiano, Salerio, Lorenzo, Jessica, Antonio)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lorenzo&#8217;s friends wait for him in front of Shylock&#8217;s house. He arrives and calls out. Jessica, dressed as a boy, throws him a casket of jewels and goes back to find more money, to the general approval of Lorenzo&#8217;s friends. As they leave, Antonio comes to find Gratiano and remind him that it is past time he were leaving with Bassanio.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter two of the masquers, Gratiano and Salerio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is the penthouse under which Lorenzo</line>
<line form="verse">Desir&#8217;d us to make stand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">His hour is almost past.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And it is marvel he out-dwells his hour,</line>
<line form="verse">For lovers ever run before the clock.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, ten times faster Venus&#8217; pigeons fly</line>
<line form="verse">To seal love&#8217;s bonds new made, than they are wont</line>
<line form="verse">To keep obliged faith unforfeited!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That ever holds. Who riseth from a feast</line>
<line form="verse">With that keen appetite that he sits down?</line>
<line form="verse">Where is the horse that doth untread again</line>
<line form="verse">His tedious measures with the unbated fire</line>
<line form="verse">That he did pace them first? All things that are,</line>
<line form="verse">Are with more spirit chased than enjoy&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">How like a younger or a prodigal</line>
<line form="verse">The scarfed bark puts from her native bay,</line>
<line form="verse">Hugg&#8217;d and embraced by the strumpet wind!</line>
<line form="verse">How like the prodigal doth she return,</line>
<line form="verse">With over-weather&#8217;d ribs and ragged sails,</line>
<line form="verse">Lean, rent, and beggar&#8217;d by the strumpet wind!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lorenzo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here comes Lorenzo, more of this hereafter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet friends, your patience for my long abode;</line>
<line form="verse">Not I but my affairs have made you wait.</line>
<line form="verse">When you shall please to play the thieves for wives,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll watch as long for you then. Approach,</line>
<line form="verse">Here dwells my father Jew. Ho! Who&#8217;s within?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Jessica above in boy&#8217;s clothes.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who are you? Tell me for more certainty,</line>
<line form="verse">Albeit I&#8217;ll swear that I do know your tongue.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo, and thy love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo, certain, and my love indeed,</line>
<line form="verse">For who love I so much? And now who knows</line>
<line form="verse">But you, Lorenzo, whether I am yours?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Heaven and thy thoughts are witness that thou art.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, catch this casket, it is worth the pains.</line>
<line form="verse">I am glad &#8217;tis night, you do not look on me,</line>
<line form="verse">For I am much asham&#8217;d of my exchange.</line>
<line form="verse">But love is blind, and lovers cannot see</line>
<line form="verse">The pretty follies that themselves commit,</line>
<line form="verse">For if they could, Cupid himself would blush</line>
<line form="verse">To see me thus transformed to a boy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Descend, for you must be my torch-bearer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, must I hold a candle to my shames?</line>
<line form="verse">They in themselves, good sooth, are too too light.</line>
<line form="verse">Why, &#8217;tis an office of discovery, love,</line>
<line form="verse">And I should be obscur&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">So are you, sweet,</line>
<line form="verse">Even in the lovely garnish of a boy.</line>
<line form="verse">But come at once,</line>
<line form="verse">For the close night doth play the runaway,</line>
<line form="verse">And we are stay&#8217;d for at Bassanio&#8217;s feast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will make fast the doors, and gild myself</line>
<line form="verse">With some more ducats, and be with you straight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit above.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now by my hood, a gentle, and no Jew.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Beshrow me but I love her heartily,</line>
<line form="verse">For she is wise, if I can judge of her,</line>
<line form="verse">And fair she is, if that mine eyes be true,</line>
<line form="verse">And true she is, as she hath prov&#8217;d herself;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore, like herself, wise, fair, and true,</line>
<line form="verse">Shall she be placed in my constant soul.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Jessica.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What, art thou come? On, gentlemen, away!</line>
<line form="verse">Our masquing mates by this time for us stay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Jessica and Salerio.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Antonio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who&#8217;s there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Signior Antonio!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, fie, Gratiano, where are all the rest?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis nine a&#8217; clock&#8212;our friends all stay for you.</line>
<line form="verse">No masque tonight, the wind is come about,</line>
<line form="verse">Bassanio presently will go aboard.</line>
<line form="verse">I have sent twenty out to seek for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am glad on&#8217;t. I desire no more delight</line>
<line form="verse">Than to be under sail, and gone tonight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="7">
<scenetitle>Scene 7</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Portia, Prince of Morocco)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Prince of Morocco considers the three caskets, and finally chooses the golden one, which promises he shall obtain what many men desire. Inside, however, is only a death&#8217;s head and a moralizing scroll warning him against being taken in by appearances. He leaves at once, to Portia&#8217;s relief.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Flourish cornets. Enter Portia with the Prince of Morocco and both their Trains.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, draw aside the curtains and discover</line>
<line form="verse">The several caskets to this noble prince.</line>
<line form="verse">Now make your choice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This first, of gold, who this inscription bears,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire&#8221;;</line>
<line form="verse">The second, silver, which this promise carries,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves&#8221;;</line>
<line form="verse">This third, dull lead, with warning all as blunt,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">How shall I know if I do choose the right?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The one of them contains my picture, Prince:</line>
<line form="verse">If you choose that, then I am yours withal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Some god direct my judgment! Let me see,</line>
<line form="verse">I will survey th&#8217; inscriptions back again.</line>
<line form="verse">What says this leaden casket?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Must give&#8212;for what? For lead, hazard for lead?</line>
<line form="verse">This casket threatens. Men that hazard all</line>
<line form="verse">Do it in hope of fair advantages;</line>
<line form="verse">A golden mind stoops not to shows of dross.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll then nor give nor hazard aught for lead.</line>
<line form="verse">What says the silver with her virgin hue?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">As much as he deserves! Pause there, Morocco,</line>
<line form="verse">And weigh thy value with an even hand.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou beest rated by thy estimation,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou dost deserve enough, and yet enough</line>
<line form="verse">May not extend so far as to the lady;</line>
<line form="verse">And yet to be afeard of my deserving</line>
<line form="verse">Were but a weak disabling of myself.</line>
<line form="verse">As much as I deserve! Why, that&#8217;s the lady.</line>
<line form="verse">I do in birth deserve her, and in fortunes,</line>
<line form="verse">In graces, and in qualities of breeding;</line>
<line form="verse">But more than these, in love I do deserve.</line>
<line form="verse">What if I stray&#8217;d no farther, but chose here?</line>
<line form="verse">Let&#8217;s see once more this saying grav&#8217;d in gold:</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">Why, that&#8217;s the lady, all the world desires her.</line>
<line form="verse">From the four corners of the earth they come</line>
<line form="verse">To kiss this shrine, this mortal breathing saint.</line>
<line form="verse">The Hyrcanian deserts and the vasty wilds</line>
<line form="verse">Of wide Arabia are as throughfares now</line>
<line form="verse">For princes to come view fair Portia.</line>
<line form="verse">The watery kingdom, whose ambitious head</line>
<line form="verse">Spets in the face of heaven, is no bar</line>
<line form="verse">To stop the foreign spirits, but they come</line>
<line form="verse">As o&#8217;er a brook to see fair Portia.</line>
<line form="verse">One of these three contains her heavenly picture.</line>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t like that lead contains her? &#8217;Twere damnation</line>
<line form="verse">To think so base a thought; it were too gross</line>
<line form="verse">To rib her cerecloth in the obscure grave.</line>
<line form="verse">Or shall I think in silver she&#8217;s immur&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Being ten times undervalued to tried gold?</line>
<line form="verse">O sinful thought! Never so rich a gem</line>
<line form="verse">Was set in worse than gold. They have in England</line>
<line form="verse">A coin that bears the figure of an angel</line>
<line form="verse">Stamp&#8217;d in gold, but that&#8217;s insculp&#8217;d upon;</line>
<line form="verse">But here an angel in a golden bed</line>
<line form="verse">Lies all within. Deliver me the key.</line>
<line form="verse">Here do I choose, and thrive I as I may!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There take it, Prince, and if my form lie there,</line>
<line form="verse">Then I am yours.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">He unlocks the golden casket.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">O hell! What have we here?</line>
<line form="verse">A carrion Death, within whose empty eye</line>
<line form="verse">There is a written scroll! I&#8217;ll read the writing.</line>

<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;All that glisters is not gold,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Often have you heard that told;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Many a man his life hath sold</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>But my outside to behold.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Gilded tombs do worms infold.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Had you been as wise as bold,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Young in limbs, in judgment old,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Your answer had not been inscroll&#8217;d.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Fare you well, your suit is cold.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Cold indeed, and labor lost:</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Then farewell heat, and welcome frost!</recite></line>
<line form="verse">Portia, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>. I have too griev&#8217;d a heart</line>
<line form="verse">To take a tedious leave; thus losers part.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with his Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A gentle riddance. Draw the curtains, go.</line>
<line form="verse">Let all of his complexion choose me so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="8">
<scenetitle>Scene 8</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Salerio, Solanio)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Salerio and Solanio discuss Shylock&#8217;s rage over the loss of his daughter and his money, and how he had the Duke search all over for both. His passion is such that he is being followed and mocked by all the children of Venice. The two realize that Antonio will be in danger from Shylock if he is unable to repay the loan, and Salerio is afraid, as he has heard of a shipwreck that may be of one of Antonio&#8217;s vessels. They leave to find Antonio and attempt to cheer him up a little.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Salerio and Solanio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, man, I saw Bassanio under sail,</line>
<line form="verse">With him is Gratiano gone along;</line>
<line form="verse">And in their ship I am sure Lorenzo is not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The villain Jew with outcries rais&#8217;d the Duke,</line>
<line form="verse">Who went with him to search Bassanio&#8217;s ship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He came too late, the ship was under sail,</line>
<line form="verse">But there the Duke was given to understand</line>
<line form="verse">That in a gondilo were seen together</line>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo and his amorous Jessica.</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, Antonio certified the Duke</line>
<line form="verse">They were not with Bassanio in his ship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never heard a passion so confus&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">So strange, outrageous, and so variable</line>
<line form="verse">As the dog Jew did utter in the streets.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;My daughter! O my ducats! O my daughter!</line>
<line form="verse">Fled with a Christian! O my Christian ducats!</line>
<line form="verse">Justice! The law! My ducats, and my daughter!</line>
<line form="verse">A sealed bag, two sealed bags of ducats,</line>
<line form="verse">Of double ducats, stol&#8217;n from me by my daughter!</line>
<line form="verse">And jewels, two stones, two rich and precious stones,</line>
<line form="verse">Stol&#8217;n by my daughter! Justice! Find the girl,</line>
<line form="verse">She hath the stones upon her, and the ducats.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, all the boys in Venice follow him,</line>
<line form="verse">Crying, his stones, his daughter, and his ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let good Antonio look he keep his day,</line>
<line form="verse">Or he shall pay for this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Marry, well rememb&#8217;red.</line>
<line form="verse">I reason&#8217;d with a Frenchman yesterday,</line>
<line form="verse">Who told me, in the Narrow Seas that part</line>
<line form="verse">The French and English, there miscarried</line>
<line form="verse">A vessel of our country richly fraught.</line>
<line form="verse">I thought upon Antonio when he told me,</line>
<line form="verse">And wish&#8217;d in silence that it were not his.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You were best to tell Antonio what you hear,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet do not suddenly, for it may grieve him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A kinder gentleman treads not the earth.</line>
<line form="verse">I saw Bassanio and Antonio part:</line>
<line form="verse">Bassanio told him he would make some speed</line>
<line form="verse">Of his return; he answered, &#8220;Do not so,</line>
<line form="verse">Slubber not business for my sake, Bassanio,</line>
<line form="verse">But stay the very riping of the time;</line>
<line form="verse">And for the Jew&#8217;s bond which he hath of me,</line>
<line form="verse">Let it not enter in your mind of love.</line>
<line form="verse">Be merry, and employ your chiefest thoughts</line>
<line form="verse">To courtship, and such fair ostents of love</line>
<line form="verse">As shall conveniently become you there.&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">And even there, his eye being big with tears,</line>
<line form="verse">Turning his face, he put his hand behind him,</line>
<line form="verse">And with affection wondrous sensible</line>
<line form="verse">He wrung Bassanio&#8217;s hand, and so they parted.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I think he only loves the world for him.</line>
<line form="verse">I pray thee let us go and find him out</line>
<line form="verse">And quicken his embraced heaviness</line>
<line form="verse">With some delight or other.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Do we so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="9">
<scenetitle>Scene 9</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Nerissa, Servitor, Prince of Arragon, Portia, Stephano)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The pretentious Prince of Aragon comes to make his choice of the caskets. He chooses the silver, who only contains a fool&#8217;s head and a scroll calling him an idiot. He leaves, and Portia&#8217;s servant Stephano announces the arrival of a contender from Venice, whom he praises to the skies. Portia is excited, and Nerissa hopes that it will prove to be Bassanio.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Nerissa and a Servitor.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Quick, quick, I pray thee, draw the curtain straight;</line>
<line form="verse">The Prince of Arragon hath ta&#8217;en his oath,</line>
<line form="verse">And comes to his election presently.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Flourish cornets. Enter the Prince of Arragon, his Train, and Portia.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Behold, there stand the caskets, noble Prince</line>
<line form="verse">If you choose that wherein I am contain&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Straight shall our nuptial rites be solemniz&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">But if you fail, without more speech, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">You must be gone from hence immediately.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am enjoin&#8217;d by oath to observe three things:</line>
<line form="verse">First, never to unfold to any one</line>
<line form="verse">Which casket &#8217;twas I chose; next, if I fail</line>
<line form="verse">Of the right casket, never in my life</line>
<line form="verse">To woo a maid in way of marriage;</line>
<line form="verse">Lastly,</line>
<line form="verse">If I do fail in fortune of my choice,</line>
<line form="verse">Immediately to leave you, and be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To these injunctions every one doth swear</line>
<line form="verse">That comes to hazard for my worthless self.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And so have I address&#8217;d me. Fortune now</line>
<line form="verse">To my heart&#8217;s hope! Gold, silver, and base lead.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">You shall look fairer ere I give or hazard.</line>
<line form="verse">What says the golden chest? Ha, let me see:</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">What many men desire! That many may be meant</line>
<line form="verse">By the fool multitude that choose by show,</line>
<line form="verse">Not learning more than the fond eye doth teach,</line>
<line form="verse">Which pries not to th&#8217; interior, but like the martlet</line>
<line form="verse">Builds in the weather on the outward wall,</line>
<line form="verse">Even in the force and road of casualty.</line>
<line form="verse">I will not choose what many men desire,</line>
<line form="verse">Because I will not jump with common spirits,</line>
<line form="verse">And rank me with the barbarous multitudes.</line>
<line form="verse">Why then to thee, thou silver treasure house,</line>
<line form="verse">Tell me once more what title thou dost bear:</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">And well said too; for who shall go about</line>
<line form="verse">To cozen fortune, and be honorable</line>
<line form="verse">Without the stamp of merit? Let none presume</line>
<line form="verse">To wear an undeserved dignity.</line>
<line form="verse">O that estates, degrees, and offices</line>
<line form="verse">Were not deriv&#8217;d corruptly, and that clear honor</line>
<line form="verse">Were purchas&#8217;d by the merit of the wearer!</line>
<line form="verse">How many then should cover that stand bare?</line>
<line form="verse">How many be commanded that command?</line>
<line form="verse">How much low peasantry would then be gleaned</line>
<line form="verse">From the true seed of honor? And how much honor</line>
<line form="verse">Pick&#8217;d from the chaff and ruin of the times</line>
<line form="verse">To be new varnish&#8217;d? Well, but to my choice:</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">I will assume desert. Give me a key for this,</line>
<line form="verse">And instantly unlock my fortunes here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">He unlocks the silver casket.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Too long a pause for that which you find there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s here? The portrait of a blinking idiot,</line>
<line form="verse">Presenting me a schedule! I will read it.</line>
<line form="verse">How much unlike art thou to Portia!</line>
<line form="verse">How much unlike my hopes and my deservings!</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Who chooseth me shall have as much as he deserves&#8221; !</line>
<line form="verse">Did I deserve no more than a fool&#8217;s head?</line>
<line form="verse">Is that my prize? Are my deserts no better?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To offend and judge are distinct offices,</line>
<line form="verse">And of opposed natures.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>AR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">What is here?</line>

<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;The fire seven times tried this:</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Seven times tried that judgment is,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>That did never choose amiss.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Some there be that shadows kiss,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Such have but a shadow&#8217;s bliss.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>There be fools alive, iwis,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Silver&#8217;d o&#8217;er, and so was this.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Take what wife you will to bed,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>I will ever be your head.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>So be gone, you are sped.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Still more fool I shall appear</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>By the time I linger here.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>With one fool&#8217;s head I came to woo,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>But I go away with two.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Sweet, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>. I&#8217;ll keep my oath,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Patiently to bear my wroth.</recite></line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with his Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thus hath the candle sing&#8217;d the moth.</line>
<line form="verse">O, these deliberate fools, when they do choose,</line>
<line form="verse">They have the wisdom by their wit to lose.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The ancient saying is no heresy,</line>
<line form="verse">Hanging and wiving goes by destiny.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come draw the curtain, Nerissa.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Stephano.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>STEPH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where is my lady?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Here; what would my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STEPH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, there is alighted at your gate</line>
<line form="verse">A young Venetian, one that comes before</line>
<line form="verse">To signify th&#8217; approaching of his lord,</line>
<line form="verse">From whom he bringeth sensible regreets:</line>
<line form="verse">To wit (besides commends and courteous breath),</line>
<line form="verse">Gifts of rich value. Yet I have not seen</line>
<line form="verse">So likely an embassador of love.</line>
<line form="verse">A day in April never came so sweet,</line>
<line form="verse">To show how costly summer was at hand,</line>
<line form="verse">As this fore-spurrer comes before his lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No more, I pray thee. I am half afeard</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wilt say anon he is some kin to thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou spend&#8217;st such high-day wit in praising him.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, come, Nerissa, for I long to see</line>
<line form="verse">Quick Cupid&#8217;s post that comes so mannerly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bassanio, Lord Love, if thy will it be!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Solanio, Salerio, Shylock, Antonio&#8217;s Servant, Tubal)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Salerio and Solanio discuss Antonio&#8217;s growing losses at sea. Shylock bitterly reproaches them for having known about his daughter&#8217;s flight, and they both admit to it and mock him on the subject. To their shock, the money-lender insists that he will have the pound of flesh he has been promised if Antonio cannot pay him back. Shylock&#8217;s acquaintance Tubal, who has been searching for Jessica, arrives to tell Shylock of how she has been seen all over Italy and has been extravagantly spending the stolen money, even giving away a ring her mother gave her father for the sake of a monkey. Tubal also tells Shylock that Antonio is almost certain to go bankrupt, and Shylock swears to cut out the merchant&#8217;s heart.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Solanio and Salerio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Now what news on the Rialto?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, yet it lives there uncheck&#8217;d that Antonio hath a ship of rich lading wrack&#8217;d on the Narrow Seas; the Goodwins I think they call the place, a very dangerous flat, and fatal, where the carcasses of many a tall ship lie buried, as they say, if my gossip Report be an honest woman of her word.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I would she were as lying a gossip in that as ever knapp&#8217;d ginger or made her neighbors believe she wept for the death of a third husband. But it is true, without any slips of prolixity, or crossing the plain highway of talk, that the good Antonio, the honest Antonio&#8212;O that I had a title good enough to keep his name company!&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Come, the full stop.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ha, what sayest thou? Why, the end is, he hath lost a ship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I would it might prove the end of his losses.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Let me say amen betimes, lest the devil cross my prayer, for here he comes in the likeness of a Jew.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Shylock.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">How now, Shylock, what news among the merchants?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You knew, none so well, none so well as you, of my daughter&#8217;s flight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That&#8217;s certain. I for my part knew the tailor that made the wings she flew withal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And Shylock for his own part knew the bird was fledge, and then it is the complexion of them all to leave the dam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">She is damn&#8217;d for it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That&#8217;s certain, if the devil may be her judge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">My own flesh and blood to rebel!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Out upon it, old carrion, rebels it at these years?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I say, my daughter is my flesh and my blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">There is more difference between thy flesh and hers than between jet and ivory, more between your 
bloods than there is between red wine and Rhenish. But tell us, do you hear whether Antonio have had any loss at sea or no?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">There I have another bad match. A bank-rout, a prodigal, who dare scarce show his head on the Rialto; a beggar, that was us&#8217;d to come so smug upon the mart: let him look to his bond. He was wont to call me usurer, let him look to his bond. He was wont to lend money for a Christian
 cur&#8217;sy, let him look to his bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, I am sure if he forfeit thou wilt not take his flesh. What&#8217;s that good for?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">To bait fish withal&#8212;if it will feed nothing else, it will feed my revenge. 
He hath disgrac&#8217;d me, and hind&#8217;red me half a million, laugh&#8217;d at my losses, mock&#8217;d at my gains, scorn&#8217;d my nation, thwarted my bargains, cool&#8217;d my friends, heated mine enemies; and what&#8217;s his reason? 
I am a Jew. Hath not a Jew eyes? Hath not a Jew hands, organs, dimensions, senses, affections, passions; fed with the same food, hurt with the same weapons, subject to the same diseases, heal&#8217;d by the same means, warm&#8217;d and cool&#8217;d by the same winter and summer, as a Christian is? If you prick us, do we not bleed? If you tickle us, do we not laugh? 
If you poison us, do we not die? And if you wrong us, shall we not revenge? If we are like you in the rest, we will resemble you in that. If a Jew wrong a Christian, what is his humility? Revenge. If a Christian wrong a Jew, what should his sufferance be by Christian example? 
Why, revenge. The villainy you teach me, I will execute, and it shall go hard but I will better the instruction.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Servingman from Antonio.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT. SERV.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Gentlemen, my master Antonio is at his house, and desires to speak with you both.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">We have been up and down to seek him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Tubal.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here comes another of the tribe; a third cannot be match&#8217;d, unless the devil himself turn Jew.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Gentlemen Solanio and Salerio, with Servingman.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How now, Tubal, what news from Genoa? Hast thou found my daughter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I often came where I did hear of her, but cannot find her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, there, there, there, there! A diamond gone, cost me two thousand ducats in Frankford! The curse never fell upon our nation till now, I never felt it till now. Two thousand ducats in that, and other precious, precious jewels. I would my daughter were dead at my foot, and the jewels in her ear! 
Would she were hears&#8217;d at my foot, and the ducats in her coffin! No news of them? Why, so&#8212;and I know not what&#8217;s spent in the search. Why, thou loss upon loss! 
The thief gone with so much, and so much to find the thief, and no satisfaction, no revenge, nor no ill luck stirring but what lights a&#8217; my shoulders, no sighs but a&#8217; my breathing, no tears but a&#8217; my shedding.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, other men have ill luck too. Antonio, as I heard in Genoa&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What, what, what? Ill luck, ill luck?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hath an argosy cast away, coming from Tripolis.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I thank God, I thank God. Is it true, is it true?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I spoke with some of the sailors that escap&#8217;d the wrack.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I thank thee, good Tubal, good news, good news! Ha, ha! Heard in Genoa?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Your daughter spent in Genoa, as I heard, one night fourscore ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Thou stick&#8217;st a dagger in me. I shall never see my gold again. Fourscore ducats at a sitting, fourscore ducats!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">There came divers of Antonio&#8217;s creditors in my company to Venice that swear he cannot choose but break.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I am very glad of it. I&#8217;ll plague him, I&#8217;ll torture him. I am glad of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">One of them show&#8217;d me a ring that he had of your daughter for a monkey.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Out upon her! Thou torturest me, Tubal. It was my turkis, I had it of Leah when I was a bachelor. 
I would not have given it for a wilderness of monkeys.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TUB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">But Antonio is certainly undone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, that&#8217;s true, that&#8217;s very true. Go, Tubal, fee me an officer; bespeak him a fortnight before. I will have the heart of him if he forfeit, for were he out of Venice I can make what merchandise I will. 
Go, Tubal, and meet me at our synagogue; go, good Tubal, at our synagogue, Tubal.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Bassanio, Portia, Gratiano, Nerissa, Lorenzo, Jessica, Salerio)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Portia, who is enjoying Bassanio&#8217;s company greatly and fears losing him should he make the wrong choice of casket, tries to convince him to wait a few days before making the test, but he insists on going through with it. After a long consideration, Bassanio chooses the lead casket, which contains a portrait of Portia. Both are overjoyed – as is Gratiano, who has been wooing Nerissa without their noticing, and now asks permission to marry her. Lorenzo, Jessica, and Salerio arrive and interrupt the joyfulness – Salerio bears a letter from Antonio informing Bassanio that he cannot repay to loan and will therefore be submitting to Shylock&#8217;s craving for a pound of his flesh. Salerio informs the horrified Bassanio that it seems Shylock would not take the money now even if Antonio had it, and Jessica confirms the likelihood of this. The supremely rich Portia offers to pay the debt many times over, and sends Bassanio on his way to save Antonio.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bassanio, Portia, Gratiano, Nerissa, and all their Trains.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you tarry, pause a day or two</line>
<line form="verse">Before you hazard, for in choosing wrong</line>
<line form="verse">I lose your company; therefore forbear a while.</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s something tells me (but it is not love)</line>
<line form="verse">I would not lose you, and you know yourself,</line>
<line form="verse">Hate counsels not in such a quality.</line>
<line form="verse">But lest you should not understand me well&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">And yet a maiden hath no tongue but thought&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I would detain you here some month or two</line>
<line form="verse">Before you venture for me. I could teach you</line>
<line form="verse">How to choose right, but then I am forsworn.</line>
<line form="verse">So will I never be, so may you miss me,</line>
<line form="verse">But if you do, You&#8217;ll make me wish a sin,</line>
<line form="verse">That I had been forsworn. Beshrow your eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">They have o&#8217;erlook&#8217;d me and divided me:</line>
<line form="verse">One half of me is yours, the other half yours&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Mine own, I would say; but if mine, then yours,</line>
<line form="verse">And so all yours. O, these naughty times</line>
<line form="verse">Puts bars between the owners and their rights!</line>
<line form="verse">And so though yours, not yours. Prove it so,</line>
<line form="verse">Let fortune go to hell for it, not I.</line>
<line form="verse">I speak too long, but &#8217;tis to peize the time,</line>
<line form="verse">To eche it, and to draw it out in length,</line>
<line form="verse">To stay you from election.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Let me choose,</line>
<line form="verse">For as I am, I live upon the rack.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon the rack, Bassanio! Then confess</line>
<line form="verse">What treason there is mingled with your love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">None but that ugly treason of mistrust,</line>
<line form="verse">Which makes me fear th&#8217; enjoying of my love;</line>
<line form="verse">There may as well be amity and life</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tween snow and fire, as treason and my love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, but I fear you speak upon the rack,</line>
<line form="verse">Where men enforced do speak any thing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Promise me life, and I&#8217;ll confess the truth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well then, confess and live.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Confess and love</line>
<line form="verse">Had been the very sum of my confession.</line>
<line form="verse">O happy torment, when my torturer</line>
<line form="verse">Doth teach me answers for deliverance!</line>
<line form="verse">But let me to my fortune and the caskets.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Away then! I am lock&#8217;d in one of them;</line>
<line form="verse">If you do love me, you will find me out.</line>
<line form="verse">Nerissa and the rest, stand all aloof.</line>
<line form="verse">Let music sound while he doth make his choice;</line>
<line form="verse">Then if he lose he makes a swan-like end,</line>
<line form="verse">Fading in music. That the comparison</line>
<line form="verse">May stand more proper, my eye shall be the stream</line>
<line form="verse">And wat&#8217;ry death-bed for him. He may win,</line>
<line form="verse">And what is music then? Then music is</line>
<line form="verse">Even as the flourish when true subjects bow</line>
<line form="verse">To a new-crowned monarch; such it is</line>
<line form="verse">As are those dulcet sounds in break of day</line>
<line form="verse">That creep into the dreaming bridegroom&#8217;s ear,</line>
<line form="verse">And summon him to marriage. Now he goes,</line>
<line form="verse">With no less presence, but with much more love,</line>
<line form="verse">Than young Alcides, when he did redeem</line>
<line form="verse">The virgin tribute paid by howling Troy</line>
<line form="verse">To the sea-monster. I stand for sacrifice;</line>
<line form="verse">The rest aloof are the Dardanian wives,</line>
<line form="verse">With bleared visages, come forth to view</line>
<line form="verse">The issue of th&#8217; exploit. Go, Hercules,</line>
<line form="verse">Live thou, I live; with much, much more dismay</line>
<line form="verse">I view the fight than thou that mak&#8217;st the fray.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Here music.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="song">A song, the whilst Bassanio comments on the caskets to himself.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SING.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Tell me where is fancy bred,</line>
<line type="lyric">Or in the heart or in the head?</line>
<line type="lyric">How begot, how nourished?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Reply, reply.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SING.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">It is engend&#8217;red in the eyes,</line>
<line type="lyric">With gazing fed, and fancy dies</line>
<line type="lyric">In the cradle where it lies.</line>
<line type="lyric">Let us all ring fancy&#8217;s knell.</line>
<line type="lyric">I&#8217;ll begin it.Ding, dong, bell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Ding, dong, bell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So may the outward shows be least themselves&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">The world is still deceiv&#8217;d with ornament.</line>
<line form="verse">In law, what plea so tainted and corrupt</line>
<line form="verse">But, being season&#8217;d with a gracious voice,</line>
<line form="verse">Obscures the show of evil? In religion,</line>
<line form="verse">What damned error but some sober brow</line>
<line form="verse">Will bless it, and approve it with a text,</line>
<line form="verse">Hiding the grossness with fair ornament?</line>
<line form="verse">There is no vice so simple but assumes</line>
<line form="verse">Some mark of virtue on his outward parts.</line>
<line form="verse">How many cowards, whose hearts are all as false</line>
<line form="verse">As stairs of sand, wear yet upon their chins</line>
<line form="verse">The beards of Hercules and frowning Mars,</line>
<line form="verse">Who inward search&#8217;d, have livers white as milk,</line>
<line form="verse">And these assume but valor&#8217;s excrement</line>
<line form="verse">To render them redoubted! Look on beauty,</line>
<line form="verse">And you shall see &#8217;tis purchas&#8217;d by the weight,</line>
<line form="verse">Which therein works a miracle in nature,</line>
<line form="verse">Making them lightest that wear most of it.</line>
<line form="verse">So are those crisped snaky golden locks,</line>
<line form="verse">Which make such wanton gambols with the wind</line>
<line form="verse">Upon supposed fairness, often known</line>
<line form="verse">To be the dowry of a second head,</line>
<line form="verse">The skull that bred them in the sepulchre.</line>
<line form="verse">Thus ornament is but the guiled shore</line>
<line form="verse">To a most dangerous sea; the beauteous scarf</line>
<line form="verse">Veiling an Indian beauty; in a word,</line>
<line form="verse">The seeming truth which cunning times put on</line>
<line form="verse">To entrap the wisest. Therefore then, thou gaudy gold,</line>
<line form="verse">Hard food for Midas, I will none of thee;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor none of thee, thou pale and common drudge</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tween man and man; but thou, thou meagre lead,</line>
<line form="verse">Which rather threaten&#8217;st than dost promise aught,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy paleness moves me more than eloquence,</line>
<line form="verse">And here choose I. Joy be the consequence!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How all the other passions fleet to air,</line>
<line form="verse">As doubtful thoughts, and rash-embrac&#8217;d despair,</line>
<line form="verse">And shudd&#8217;ring fear, and green-eyed jealousy!</line>
<line form="verse">O love, be moderate, allay thy ecstasy,</line>
<line form="verse">In measure rain thy joy, scant this excess!</line>
<line form="verse">I feel too much thy blessing; make it less,</line>
<line form="verse">For fear I surfeit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">What find I here?</line>

<stagedir type="action">Opening the leaden casket.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Fair Portia&#8217;s counterfeit! What demigod</line>
<line form="verse">Hath come so near creation? Move these eyes?</line>
<line form="verse">Or whether, riding on the balls of mine,</line>
<line form="verse">Seem they in motion? Here are sever&#8217;d lips,</line>
<line form="verse">Parted with sugar breath; so sweet a bar</line>
<line form="verse">Should sunder such sweet friends. Here in her hairs</line>
<line form="verse">The painter plays the spider, and hath woven</line>
<line form="verse">A golden mesh t&#8217; entrap the hearts of men</line>
<line form="verse">Faster than gnats in cobwebs. But her eyes&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">How could he see to do them? Having made one,</line>
<line form="verse">Methinks it should have power to steal both his</line>
<line form="verse">And leave itself unfurnish&#8217;d. Yet look how far</line>
<line form="verse">The substance of my praise doth wrong this shadow</line>
<line form="verse">In underprizing it, so far this shadow</line>
<line form="verse">Doth limp behind the substance. Here&#8217;s the scroll,</line>
<line form="verse">The continent and summary of my fortune.</line>

<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;You that choose not by the view,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Chance as fair, and choose as true:</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Since this fortune falls to you,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Be content, and seek no new.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>If you be well pleas&#8217;d with this,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And hold your fortune for your bliss,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Turn you where your lady is,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And claim her with a loving kiss.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">A gentle scroll. Fair lady, by your leave,</line>
<line form="verse">I come by note, to give and to receive.</line>
<line form="verse">Like one of two contending in a prize,</line>
<line form="verse">That thinks he hath done well in people&#8217;s eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">Hearing applause and universal shout,</line>
<line form="verse">Giddy in spirit, still gazing in a doubt</line>
<line form="verse">Whether those peals of praise be his or no,</line>
<line form="verse">So, thrice-fair lady, stand I, even so,</line>
<line form="verse">As doubtful whether what I see be true,</line>
<line form="verse">Until confirm&#8217;d, sign&#8217;d, ratified by you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You see me, Lord Bassanio, where I stand,</line>
<line form="verse">Such as I am. Though for myself alone</line>
<line form="verse">I would not be ambitious in my wish</line>
<line form="verse">To wish myself much better, yet for you,</line>
<line form="verse">I would be trebled twenty times myself,</line>
<line form="verse">A thousand times more fair, ten thousand times more rich,</line>
<line form="verse">That only to stand high in your account,</line>
<line form="verse">I might in virtues, beauties, livings, friends,</line>
<line form="verse">Exceed account. But the full sum of me</line>
<line form="verse">Is sum of something; which, to term in gross,</line>
<line form="verse">Is an unlesson&#8217;d girl, unschool&#8217;d, unpractic&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Happy in this, she is not yet so old</line>
<line form="verse">But she may learn; happier than this,</line>
<line form="verse">She is not bred so dull but she can learn;</line>
<line form="verse">Happiest of all, is that her gentle spirit</line>
<line form="verse">Commits itself to yours to be directed,</line>
<line form="verse">As from her lord, her governor, her king.</line>
<line form="verse">Myself, and what is mine, to you and yours</line>
<line form="verse">Is now converted. But now I was the lord</line>
<line form="verse">Of this fair mansion, master of my servants,</line>
<line form="verse">Queen o&#8217;er myself; and even now, but now,</line>
<line form="verse">This house, these servants, and this same myself</line>
<line form="verse">Are yours&#8212;my lord&#8217;s!&#8212;I give them with this ring,</line>
<line form="verse">Which when you part from, lose, or give away,</line>
<line form="verse">Let it presage the ruin of your love,</line>
<line form="verse">And be my vantage to exclaim on you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, you have bereft me of all words,</line>
<line form="verse">Only my blood speaks to you in my veins,</line>
<line form="verse">And there is such confusion in my powers,</line>
<line form="verse">As after some oration fairly spoke</line>
<line form="verse">By a beloved prince, there doth appear</line>
<line form="verse">Among the buzzing pleased multitude,</line>
<line form="verse">Where every something, being blent together,</line>
<line form="verse">Turns to a wild of nothing, save of joy</line>
<line form="verse">Express&#8217;d and not express&#8217;d. But when this ring</line>
<line form="verse">Parts from this finger, then parts life from hence;</line>
<line form="verse">O then be bold to say Bassanio&#8217;s dead!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord and lady, it is now our time,</line>
<line form="verse">That have stood by and seen our wishes prosper,</line>
<line form="verse">To cry good joy. Good joy, my lord and lady!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Lord Bassanio and my gentle lady,</line>
<line form="verse">I wish you all the joy that you can wish;</line>
<line form="verse">For I am sure you can wish none from me;</line>
<line form="verse">And when your honors mean to solemnize</line>
<line form="verse">The bargain of your faith, I do beseech you</line>
<line form="verse">Even at that time I may be married too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With all my heart, so thou canst get a wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I thank your lordship, you have got me one.</line>
<line form="verse">My eyes, my lord, can look as swift as yours:</line>
<line form="verse">You saw the mistress, I beheld the maid;</line>
<line form="verse">You lov&#8217;d, I lov&#8217;d; for intermission</line>
<line form="verse">No more pertains to me, my lord, than you;</line>
<line form="verse">Your fortune stood upon the caskets there,</line>
<line form="verse">And so did mine too as the matter falls;</line>
<line form="verse">For wooing here until I sweat again,</line>
<line form="verse">And swearing till my very roof was dry</line>
<line form="verse">With oaths of love, at last, if promise last,</line>
<line form="verse">I got a promise of this fair one here</line>
<line form="verse">To have her love&#8212;provided that your fortune</line>
<line form="verse">Achiev&#8217;d her mistress.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Is this true, Nerissa?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, it is, so you stand pleas&#8217;d withal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And do you, Gratiano, mean good faith?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, faith, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Our feast shall be much honored in your marriage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="prose">We&#8217;ll play with them the first boy for a thousand ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What, and stake down?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, we shall ne&#8217;er win at that sport, and stake down.</line>
<line form="verse">But who comes here? Lorenzo and his infidel?</line>
<line form="verse">What, and my old Venetian friend Salerio?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lorenzo, Jessica, and Salerio, a messenger from Venice.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo and Salerio, welcome hither,</line>
<line form="verse">If that the youth of my new int&#8217;rest here</line>
<line form="verse">Have power to bid you welcome. By your leave,</line>
<line form="verse">I bid my very friends and countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">Sweet Portia, welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">So do I, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">They are entirely welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I thank your honor. For my part, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">My purpose was not to have seen you here,</line>
<line form="verse">But meeting with Salerio by the way,</line>
<line form="verse">He did entreat me, past all saying nay,</line>
<line form="verse">To come with him along.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I did, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">And I have reason for it. Signior Antonio</line>
<line form="verse">Commends him to you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Gives Bassanio a letter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Ere I ope his letter,</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you tell me how my good friend doth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not sick, my lord, unless it be in mind,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor well, unless in mind. His letter there</line>
<line form="verse">Will show you his estate.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Bassanio opens the letter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nerissa, cheer yond stranger, bid her welcome.</line>
<line form="verse">Your hand, Salerio. What&#8217;s the news from Venice?</line>
<line form="verse">How doth that royal merchant, good Antonio?</line>
<line form="verse">I know he will be glad of our success;</line>
<line form="verse">We are the Jasons, we have won the fleece.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would you had won the fleece that he hath lost.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There are some shrowd contents in yond same paper</line>
<line form="verse">That steals the color from Bassanio&#8217;s cheek&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Some dear friend dead, else nothing in the world</line>
<line form="verse">Could turn so much the constitution</line>
<line form="verse">Of any constant man. What, worse and worse!</line>
<line form="verse">With leave, Bassanio, I am half yourself,</line>
<line form="verse">And I must freely have the half of any thing</line>
<line form="verse">That this same paper brings you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">O sweet Portia,</line>
<line form="verse">Here are a few of the unpleasant&#8217;st words</line>
<line form="verse">That ever blotted paper! Gentle lady,</line>
<line form="verse">When I did first impart my love to you,</line>
<line form="verse">I freely told you all the wealth I had</line>
<line form="verse">Ran in my veins: I was a gentleman;</line>
<line form="verse">And then I told you true. And yet, dear lady,</line>
<line form="verse">Rating myself at nothing, you shall see</line>
<line form="verse">How much I was a braggart: when I told you</line>
<line form="verse">My state was nothing, I should then have told you</line>
<line form="verse">That I was worse than nothing; for indeed</line>
<line form="verse">I have engag&#8217;d myself to a dear friend,</line>
<line form="verse">Engag&#8217;d my friend to his mere enemy,</line>
<line form="verse">To feed my means. Here is a letter, lady,</line>
<line form="verse">The paper as the body of my friend,</line>
<line form="verse">And every word in it a gaping wound</line>
<line form="verse">Issuing life-blood. But is it true, Salerio?</line>
<line form="verse">Hath all his ventures fail&#8217;d? What, not one hit?</line>
<line form="verse">From Tripolis, from Mexico, and England,</line>
<line form="verse">From Lisbon, Barbary, and India,</line>
<line form="verse">And not one vessel scape the dreadful touch</line>
<line form="verse">Of merchant-marring rocks?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Not one, my lord.</line>
<line form="verse">Besides, it should appear, that if he had</line>
<line form="verse">The present money to discharge the Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">He would not take it. Never did I know</line>
<line form="verse">A creature that did bear the shape of man</line>
<line form="verse">So keen and greedy to confound a man.</line>
<line form="verse">He plies the Duke at morning and at night,</line>
<line form="verse">And doth impeach the freedom of the state,</line>
<line form="verse">If they deny him justice. Twenty merchants,</line>
<line form="verse">The Duke himself, and the magnificoes</line>
<line form="verse">Of greatest port, have all persuaded with him,</line>
<line form="verse">But none can drive him from the envious plea</line>
<line form="verse">Of forfeiture, of justice, and his bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When I was with him I have heard him swear</line>
<line form="verse">To Tubal and to Chus, his countrymen,</line>
<line form="verse">That he would rather have Antonio&#8217;s flesh</line>
<line form="verse">Than twenty times the value of the sum</line>
<line form="verse">That he did owe him; and I know, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">If law, authority, and power deny not,</line>
<line form="verse">It will go hard with poor Antonio.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is it your dear friend that is thus in trouble?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The dearest friend to me, the kindest man,</line>
<line form="verse">The best-condition&#8217;d and unwearied spirit</line>
<line form="verse">In doing courtesies, and one in whom</line>
<line form="verse">The ancient Roman honor more appears</line>
<line form="verse">Than any that draws breath in Italy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What sum owes he the Jew?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For me, three thousand ducats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">What, no more?</line>
<line form="verse">Pay him six thousand, and deface the bond;</line>
<line form="verse">Double six thousand, and then treble that,</line>
<line form="verse">Before a friend of this description</line>
<line form="verse">Shall lose a hair through Bassanio&#8217;s fault.</line>
<line form="verse">First go with me to church and call me wife,</line>
<line form="verse">And then away to Venice to your friend;</line>
<line form="verse">For never shall you lie by Portia&#8217;s side</line>
<line form="verse">With an unquiet soul. You shall have gold</line>
<line form="verse">To pay the petty debt twenty times over.</line>
<line form="verse">When it is paid, bring your true friend along.</line>
<line form="verse">My maid Nerissa and myself mean time</line>
<line form="verse">Will live as maids and widows. Come away!</line>
<line form="verse">For you shall hence upon your wedding-day.</line>
<line form="verse">Bid your friends welcome, show a merry cheer&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Since you are dear bought, I will love you dear.</line>
<line form="verse">But let me hear the letter of your friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir> 
<line form="prose"><recite>&#8220;Sweet Bassanio, my ships have all miscarried, my creditors grow cruel, my estate is very low, my bond to the Jew is forfeit; and since in paying it, it is impossible I should live, all debts are clear&#8217;d between you and I, if I might but see you at my death. Notwithstanding, use your pleasure; if your love do not persuade you to come, let not my letter.&#8221;</recite></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O love! Dispatch all business and be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Since I have your good leave to go away,</line>
<line form="verse">I will make haste; but till I come again,</line>
<line form="verse">No bed shall e&#8217;er be guilty of my stay,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor rest be interposer &#8217;twixt us twain.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Shylock, Solanio, Antonio, Jailer)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Antonio, guarded by a jailer, attempts to speak to Shylock, but the latter refuses to hear him and insists that he will have the promised forfeit. To Solanio&#8217;s reassurance that the Duke will never let Shylock get away with it, Antonio points out that he will have no choice, as Venice&#8217;s whole economy would collapse if the Duke simply disregards a lawful bond simply because he doesn&#8217;t like it.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Shylock the Jew and Solanio and Antonio and the Jailer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Jailer, look to him, tell not me of mercy.</line>
<line form="verse">This is the fool that lent out money gratis.</line>
<line form="verse">Jailer, look to him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Hear me yet, good Shylock.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll have my bond, speak not against my bond,</line>
<line form="verse">I have sworn an oath that I will have my bond.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou call&#8217;dst me dog before thou hadst a cause,</line>
<line form="verse">But since I am a dog, beware my fangs.</line>
<line form="verse">The Duke shall grant me justice. I do wonder,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou naughty jailer, that thou art so fond</line>
<line form="verse">To come abroad with him at his request.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray thee hear me speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll have my bond; I will not hear thee speak.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll have my bond, and therefore speak no more.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll not be made a soft and dull-ey&#8217;d fool</line>
<line form="verse">To shake the head, relent, and sigh, and yield</line>
<line form="verse">To Christian intercessors. Follow not,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll have no speaking, I will have my bond.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Jew.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is the most impenetrable cur</line>
<line form="verse">That ever kept with men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Let him alone,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll follow him no more with bootless prayers.</line>
<line form="verse">He seeks my life; his reason well I know:</line>
<line form="verse">I oft deliver&#8217;d from his forfeitures</line>
<line form="verse">Many that have at times made moan to me;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore he hates me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I am sure the Duke</line>
<line form="verse">Will never grant this forfeiture to hold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The Duke cannot deny the course of law;</line>
<line form="verse">For the commodity that strangers have</line>
<line form="verse">With us in Venice, if it be denied,</line>
<line form="verse">Will much impeach the justice of the state,</line>
<line form="verse">Since that the trade and profit of the city</line>
<line form="verse">Consisteth of all nations. Therefore go.</line>
<line form="verse">These griefs and losses have so bated me</line>
<line form="verse">That I shall hardly spare a pound of flesh</line>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow to my bloody creditor.</line>
<line form="verse">Well, jailer, on. Pray God Bassanio come</line>
<line form="verse">To see me pay his debt, and then I care not!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A room in Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Portia, Nerissa, Lorenzo, Jessica, Balthazar)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>As Lorenzo praises Portia for offering to get Antonio out of trouble, the lady insists that it is nothing. She entrusts Belmont to Lorenzo and Jessica as she and Nerissa have decided to spend the time of their husbands&#8217; absence in a nearby monastery. Actually, Portia has a completely different plan in mind. She sends a letter to an old family friend, the noted lawyer Bellario, while she and Nerissa leave for Venice, planning to arrive there dressed as men.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Portia, Nerissa, Lorenzo, Jessica, and Balthazar, a man of Portia&#8217;s.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, although I speak it in your presence,</line>
<line form="verse">You have a noble and a true conceit</line>
<line form="verse">Of godlike amity, which appears most strongly</line>
<line form="verse">In bearing thus the absence of your lord.</line>
<line form="verse">But if you knew to whom you show this honor,</line>
<line form="verse">How true a gentleman you send relief,</line>
<line form="verse">How dear a lover of my lord your husband,</line>
<line form="verse">I know you would be prouder of the work</line>
<line form="verse">Than customary bounty can enforce you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I never did repent for doing good,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor shall not now: for in companions</line>
<line form="verse">That do converse and waste the time together,</line>
<line form="verse">Whose souls do bear an egall yoke of love,</line>
<line form="verse">There must be needs a like proportion</line>
<line form="verse">Of lineaments, of manners, and of spirit;</line>
<line form="verse">Which makes me think that this Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">Being the bosom lover of my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Must needs be like my lord. If it be so,</line>
<line form="verse">How little is the cost I have bestowed</line>
<line form="verse">In purchasing the semblance of my soul,</line>
<line form="verse">From out the state of hellish cruelty.</line>
<line form="verse">This comes too near the praising of myself,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore no more of it. Hear other things:</line>
<line form="verse">Lorenzo, I commit into your hands</line>
<line form="verse">The husbandry and manage of my house</line>
<line form="verse">Until my lord&#8217;s return. For mine own part,</line>
<line form="verse">I have toward heaven breath&#8217;d a secret vow</line>
<line form="verse">To live in prayer and contemplation,</line>
<line form="verse">Only attended by Nerissa here,</line>
<line form="verse">Until her husband and my lord&#8217;s return.</line>
<line form="verse">There is a monast&#8217;ry two miles off,</line>
<line form="verse">And there we will abide. I do desire you</line>
<line form="verse">Not to deny this imposition,</line>
<line form="verse">The which my love and some necessity</line>
<line form="verse">Now lays upon you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Madam, with all my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">I shall obey you in all fair commands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My people do already know my mind,</line>
<line form="verse">And will acknowledge you and Jessica</line>
<line form="verse">In place of Lord Bassanio and myself.</line>
<line form="verse">So fare you well till we shall meet again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair thoughts and happy hours attend on you!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I wish your ladyship all heart&#8217;s content.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I thank you for your wish, and am well pleas&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To wish it back on you. Fare you well, Jessica.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Jessica and Lorenzo.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Now, Balthazar,</line>
<line form="verse">As I have ever found thee honest-true,</line>
<line form="verse">So let me find thee still. Take this same letter,</line>
<line form="verse">And use thou all th&#8217; endeavor of a man</line>
<line form="verse">In speed to Padua. See thou render this</line>
<line form="verse">Into my cousin&#8217;s hands, Doctor Bellario,</line>
<line form="verse">And look what notes and garments he doth give thee,</line>
<line form="verse">Bring them, I pray thee, with imagin&#8217;d speed</line>
<line form="verse">Unto the traject, to the common ferry</line>
<line form="verse">Which trades to Venice. Waste no time in words,</line>
<line form="verse">But get thee gone. I shall be there before thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BALTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Madam, I go with all convenient speed.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come on, Nerissa, I have work in hand</line>
<line form="verse">That you yet know not of. We&#8217;ll see our husbands</line>
<line form="verse">Before they think of us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Shall they see us?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">They shall, Nerissa; but in such a habit</line>
<line form="verse">That they shall think we are accomplished</line>
<line form="verse">With that we lack. I&#8217;ll hold thee any wager,</line>
<line form="verse">When we are both accoutered like young men,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll prove the prettier fellow of the two,</line>
<line form="verse">And wear my dagger with the braver grace,</line>
<line form="verse">And speak between the change of man and boy</line>
<line form="verse">With a reed voice, and turn two mincing steps</line>
<line form="verse">Into a manly stride; and speak of frays</line>
<line form="verse">Like a fine bragging youth, and tell quaint lies,</line>
<line form="verse">How honorable ladies sought my love,</line>
<line form="verse">Which I denying, they fell sick and died.</line>
<line form="verse">I could not do withal. Then I&#8217;ll repent,</line>
<line form="verse">And wish, for all that, that I had not kill&#8217;d them;</line>
<line form="verse">And twenty of these puny lies I&#8217;ll tell,</line>
<line form="verse">That men shall swear I have discontinued school</line>
<line form="verse">Above a twelvemonth. I have within my mind</line>
<line form="verse">A thousand raw tricks of these bragging Jacks,</line>
<line form="verse">Which I will practice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why, shall we turn to men?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fie, what a question&#8217;s that,</line>
<line form="verse">If thou wert near a lewd interpreter!</line>
<line form="verse">But come, I&#8217;ll tell thee all my whole device</line>
<line form="verse">When I am in my coach, which stays for us</line>
<line form="verse">At the park-gate; and therefore haste away,</line>
<line form="verse">For we must measure twenty miles today.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. A garden at Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Launcelot, Jessica, Lorenzo)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Launcelot and Jessica meet again and trade barbs, the servant insisting that she is damned for not being a Christian. Lorenzo enters and joins in the fun, though in the end he dismisses Launcelot to his work. They are all in a merry mood. Jessica praises Portia, and Lorenzo assures her that he is as good a man as Portia is a good woman, a claim Jessica does not take overly seriously.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Clown Launcelot and Jessica.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes, truly, for look you, the sins of the father are to be laid upon the children; therefore, I promise you, I fear you. 
I was always plain with you, and so now I speak my agitation of the matter; therefore be a&#8217; good cheer, for truly I think you are damn&#8217;d. 
There is but one hope in it that can do you any good, and that is but a kind of bastard hope neither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And what hope is that, I pray thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, you may partly hope that your father got you not, that you are not the Jew&#8217;s daughter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That were a kind of bastard hope indeed; so the sins of my mother should be visited upon me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Truly then I fear you are damn&#8217;d both by father and mother; thus when I shun Scylla, your father, I fall into Charybdis, your mother. 
Well, you are gone both ways.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I shall be sav&#8217;d by my husband, he hath made me a Christian!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Truly, the more to blame he; we were Christians enow before, e&#8217;en as many as could well live one by another. 
This making of Christians will raise the price of hogs. If we grow all to be pork-eaters, we shall not shortly have a rasher on the coals for money.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lorenzo.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I&#8217;ll tell my husband, Launcelot, what you say. Here he comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I shall grow jealous of you shortly, Launcelot, if you thus get my wife into corners!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, you need not fear us, Lorenzo, Launcelot and I are out. He tells me flatly there&#8217;s no mercy for me in heaven because I am a Jew&#8217;s daughter; 
and he says you are no good member of the commonwealth, for in converting Jews to Christians, you raise the price of pork.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I shall answer that better to the commonwealth than you can the getting up of the Negro&#8217;s belly; the Moor is with child by you, Launcelot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is much that the Moor should be more than reason; but if she be less than an honest woman, she is indeed more than I took her for.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How every fool can play upon the word! I think the best grace of wit will shortly turn into silence, and discourse grow commendable in none only but parrots. Go in, sirrah, bid them prepare for dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That is done, sir, they have all stomachs!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Goodly Lord, what a wit-snapper are you! Then bid them prepare dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That is done too, sir, only &#8220;cover&#8221; is the word.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Will you cover then, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not so, sir, neither, I know my duty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yet more quarrelling with occasion! Wilt thou show the whole wealth of thy wit in an instant? I pray thee understand a plain man in his plain meaning: go to thy fellows, bid them cover the table, serve in the meat, and we will come in to dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">For the table, sir, it shall be serv&#8217;d in; for the meat, sir, it shall be cover&#8217;d; for your coming in to dinner, sir, why, let it be as humors and conceits shall govern.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Clown.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O dear discretion, how his words are suited!</line>
<line form="verse">The fool hath planted in his memory</line>
<line form="verse">An army of good words, and I do know</line>
<line form="verse">A many fools, that stand in better place,</line>
<line form="verse">Garnish&#8217;d like him, that for a tricksy word</line>
<line form="verse">Defy the matter. How cheer&#8217;st thou, Jessica?</line>
<line form="verse">And now, good sweet, say thy opinion,</line>
<line form="verse">How dost thou like the Lord Bassanio&#8217;s wife?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Past all expressing. It is very meet</line>
<line form="verse">The Lord Bassanio live an upright life,</line>
<line form="verse">For having such a blessing in his lady,</line>
<line form="verse">He finds the joys of heaven here on earth,</line>
<line form="verse">And if on earth he do not merit it,</line>
<line form="verse">In reason he should never come to heaven!</line>
<line form="verse">Why, if two gods should play some heavenly match,</line>
<line form="verse">And on the wager lay two earthly women,</line>
<line form="verse">And Portia one, there must be something else</line>
<line form="verse">Pawn&#8217;d with the other, for the poor rude world</line>
<line form="verse">Hath not her fellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Even such a husband</line>
<line form="verse">Hast thou of me as she is for a wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, but ask my opinion too of that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will anon, first let us go to dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, let me praise you while I have a stomach.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, pray thee, let it serve for table-talk;</line>
<line form="verse">Then howsome&#8217;er thou speak&#8217;st, &#8217;mong other things</line>
<line form="verse">I shall digest it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Well, I&#8217;ll set you forth.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A court of justice.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Duke, Magnificoes, Antonio, Bassanio, Salerio, Gratiano, Shylock, Nerissa, Portia)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The Duke of Venice tells Antonio how sorry he is about all this, but Antonio insists that he would rather suffer than see the law diminished. The Duke tells Shylock how he expects the money-lender to relent, but Shylock insists he will have his pound of flesh, predicting the downfall of all that sustains the state if he is refused. Bassanio offers him twice the amount of money he paid, but Shylock still refuses, while Antonio tells his friends that there is no point in trying to argue. The Duke threatens to dismiss the court unless the lawyer Bellario arrives, as Gratiano vomits insults on Shylock to no effect. In Bellario&#8217;s place come Portia and Nerissa, disguised as a lawyer and his clerk. After assessing the case, Portia concludes that nothing can stop Shylock other than his granting mercy, which she asks him to do, but he refuses. She reads the contract between Antonio and Shylock and insists that it must be followed to the letter. Antonio prepares to die. But just at the moment that Shylock is going to take his pound of flesh, Portia warns him that the contract does not allow him to take any of Antonio&#8217;s blood. Flummoxed, Shylock agrees to take the money he was offered, but now Portia is as inflexible as he was, insisting that he only take a pound of flesh, no more nor less, and without spilling any blood, on pain of being convicted of trying to murder a citizen of Venice. Bassanio is ready to pay Shylock back his money, but Portia rules that it is too late for that. Shylock gives up his claim, but now Portia tells him that for having attempted to kill a citizen, his goods are forfeited to Antonio and the state, and he himself is under sentence of death. To show off his mercy, the Duke immediately pardons the money-lender his life. Shylock protests that without his money, he is no longer anything. Antonio returns his goods to him, on condition that he swear to leave his money to Jessica and Lorenzo and that he become a Christian. Forced to agree, Shylock begs leave to return home, swearing he will sign all the promises there. He does not feel well. Antonio and Bassanio thank the lawyer, asking permission to pay &#8220;him&#8221;, but Portia insists she will accept nothing. To test her husband, she asks only for the ring he is wearing. He tries to refuse it, as he received it from his wife and swore to her he would not take it off, but in the end he sends Gratiano after the lawyer with the ring.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Duke, the Magnificoes, Antonio, Bassanio, Salerio, and Gratiano with others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What, is Antonio here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ready, so please your Grace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sorry for thee. Thou art come to answer</line>
<line form="verse">A stony adversary, an inhuman wretch,</line>
<line form="verse">Uncapable of pity, void and empty</line>
<line form="verse">From any dram of mercy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I have heard</line>
<line form="verse">Your Grace hath ta&#8217;en great pains to qualify</line>
<line form="verse">His rigorous course; but since he stands obdurate,</line>
<line form="verse">And that no lawful means can carry me</line>
<line form="verse">Out of his envy&#8217;s reach, I do oppose</line>
<line form="verse">My patience to his fury, and am arm&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To suffer, with a quietness of spirit,</line>
<line form="verse">The very tyranny and rage of his.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go one, and call the Jew into the court.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He is ready at the door; he comes, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Shylock.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Make room, and let him stand before our face.</line>
<line form="verse">Shylock, the world thinks, and I think so too,</line>
<line form="verse">That thou but leadest this fashion of thy malice</line>
<line form="verse">To the last hour of act, and then &#8217;tis thought</line>
<line form="verse">Thou&#8217;lt show thy mercy and remorse more strange</line>
<line form="verse">Than is thy strange apparent cruelty;</line>
<line form="verse">And where thou now exacts the penalty,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is a pound of this poor merchant&#8217;s flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wilt not only loose the forfeiture,</line>
<line form="verse">But touch&#8217;d with humane gentleness and love,</line>
<line form="verse">Forgive a moi&#8217;ty of the principal,</line>
<line form="verse">Glancing an eye of pity on his losses,</line>
<line form="verse">That have of late so huddled on his back,</line>
<line form="verse">Enow to press a royal merchant down,</line>
<line form="verse">And pluck commiseration of his state</line>
<line form="verse">From brassy bosoms and rough hearts of flints,</line>
<line form="verse">From stubborn Turks, and Tartars never train&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To offices of tender courtesy.</line>
<line form="verse">We all expect a gentle answer, Jew!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have possess&#8217;d your Grace of what I purpose,</line>
<line form="verse">And by our holy Sabaoth have I sworn</line>
<line form="verse">To have the due and forfeit of my bond.</line>
<line form="verse">If you deny it, let the danger light</line>
<line form="verse">Upon your charter and your city&#8217;s freedom!</line>
<line form="verse">You&#8217;ll ask me why I rather choose to have</line>
<line form="verse">A weight of carrion flesh than to receive</line>
<line form="verse">Three thousand ducats. I&#8217;ll not answer that;</line>
<line form="verse">But say it is my humor, is it answer&#8217;d?</line>
<line form="verse">What if my house be troubled with a rat,</line>
<line form="verse">And I be pleas&#8217;d to give ten thousand ducats</line>
<line form="verse">To have it ban&#8217;d? What, are you answer&#8217;d yet?</line>
<line form="verse">Some men there are love not a gaping pig;</line>
<line form="verse">Some that are mad if they behold a cat;</line>
<line form="verse">And others, when the bagpipe sings i&#8217; th&#8217; nose,</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot contain their urine: for affection,</line>
<line form="verse">Mistress of passion, sways it to the mood</line>
<line form="verse">Of what it likes or loathes. Now for your answer:</line>
<line form="verse">As there is no firm reason to be rend&#8217;red</line>
<line form="verse">Why he cannot abide a gaping pig;</line>
<line form="verse">Why he, a harmless necessary cat;</line>
<line form="verse">Why he, a woollen bagpipe, but of force</line>
<line form="verse">Must yield to such inevitable shame</line>
<line form="verse">As to offend, himself being offended;</line>
<line form="verse">So can I give no reason, nor I will not,</line>
<line form="verse">More than a lodg&#8217;d hate and a certain loathing</line>
<line form="verse">I bear Antonio, that I follow thus</line>
<line form="verse">A losing suit against him. Are you answered?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is no answer, thou unfeeling man,</line>
<line form="verse">To excuse the current of thy cruelty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am not bound to please thee with my answers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do all men kill the things they do not love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hates any man the thing he would not kill?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Every offense is not a hate at first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, wouldst thou have a serpent sting thee twice?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you think you question with the Jew:</line>
<line form="verse">You may as well go stand upon the beach</line>
<line form="verse">And bid the main flood bate his usual height;</line>
<line form="verse">You may as well use question with the wolf</line>
<line form="verse">Why he hath made the ewe bleak for the lamb;</line>
<line form="verse">You may as well forbid the mountain pines</line>
<line form="verse">To wag their high tops, and to make no noise</line>
<line form="verse">When they are fretten with the gusts of heaven;</line>
<line form="verse">You may as well do any thing most hard</line>
<line form="verse">As seek to soften that&#8212;than which what&#8217;s harder?&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">His Jewish heart! Therefore I do beseech you</line>
<line form="verse">Make no more offers, use no farther means,</line>
<line form="verse">But with all brief and plain conveniency</line>
<line form="verse">Let me have judgment and the Jew his will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For thy three thousand ducats here is six.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If every ducat in six thousand ducats</line>
<line form="verse">Were in six parts, and every part a ducat,</line>
<line form="verse">I would not draw them, I would have my bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How shalt thou hope for mercy, rend&#8217;ring none?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What judgment shall I dread, doing no wrong?</line>
<line form="verse">You have among you many a purchas&#8217;d slave,</line>
<line form="verse">Which like your asses, and your dogs and mules,</line>
<line form="verse">You use in abject and in slavish parts,</line>
<line form="verse">Because you bought them. Shall I say to you,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Let them be free! Marry them to your heirs!</line>
<line form="verse">Why sweat they under burdens? Let their beds</line>
<line form="verse">Be made as soft as yours, and let their palates</line>
<line form="verse">Be season&#8217;d with such viands?&#8221; You will answer,</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;The slaves are ours.&#8221; So do I answer you:</line>
<line form="verse">The pound of flesh which I demand of him</line>
<line form="verse">Is dearly bought as mine, and I will have it.</line>
<line form="verse">If you deny me, fie upon your law!</line>
<line form="verse">There is no force in the decrees of Venice.</line>
<line form="verse">I stand for judgment. Answer&#8212;shall I have it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Upon my power I may dismiss this court,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless Bellario, a learned doctor,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom I have sent for to determine this,</line>
<line form="verse">Come here today.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SAL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">My lord, here stays without</line>
<line form="verse">A messenger with letters from the doctor,</line>
<line form="verse">New come from Padua.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Bring us the letters; call the messenger.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good cheer, Antonio! What, man, courage yet!</line>
<line form="verse">The Jew shall have my flesh, blood, bones, and all,</line>
<line form="verse">Ere thou shalt lose for me one drop of blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am a tainted wether of the flock,</line>
<line form="verse">Meetest for death; the weakest kind of fruit</line>
<line form="verse">Drops earliest to the ground, and so let me.</line>
<line form="verse">You cannot better be employ&#8217;d, Bassanio,</line>
<line form="verse">Than to live still and write mine epitaph.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Nerissa dressed like a lawyer&#8217;s clerk.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Came you from Padua, from Bellario?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">From both, my lord. Bellario greets your Grace.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Presenting a letter.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why dost thou whet thy knife so earnestly?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">To cut the forfeiture from that bankrout there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not on thy sole, but on thy soul, harsh Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou mak&#8217;st thy knife keen; but no metal can,</line>
<line form="verse">No, not the hangman&#8217;s axe, bear half the keenness</line>
<line form="verse">Of thy sharp envy. Can no prayers pierce thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, none that thou hast wit enough to make.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, be thou damn&#8217;d, inexecrable dog!</line>
<line form="verse">And for thy life let justice be accus&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou almost mak&#8217;st me waver in my faith</line>
<line form="verse">To hold opinion with Pythagoras,</line>
<line form="verse">That souls of animals infuse themselves</line>
<line form="verse">Into the trunks of men. Thy currish spirit</line>
<line form="verse">Govern&#8217;d a wolf, who hang&#8217;d for human slaughter,</line>
<line form="verse">Even from the gallows did his fell soul fleet,</line>
<line form="verse">And whilst thou layest in thy unhallowed dam,</line>
<line form="verse">Infus&#8217;d itself in thee; for thy desires</line>
<line form="verse">Are wolvish, bloody, starv&#8217;d, and ravenous.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Till thou canst rail the seal from off my bond,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou but offend&#8217;st thy lungs to speak so loud.</line>
<line form="verse">Repair thy wit, good youth, or it will fall</line>
<line form="verse">To cureless ruin. I stand here for law.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This letter from Bellario doth commend</line>
<line form="verse">A young and learned doctor to our court.</line>
<line form="verse">Where is he?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">He attendeth here hard by</line>
<line form="verse">To know your answer, whether You&#8217;ll admit him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With all my heart. Some three or four of you</line>
<line form="verse">Go give him courteous conduct to this place.</line>
<line form="verse">Mean time the court shall hear Bellario&#8217;s letter.</line>
<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="prose"><recite>&#8220;Your Grace shall understand that at the receipt of your letter I am very sick, but in the instant that your messenger came, in loving visitation was with me a young doctor of Rome. His name is Balthazar. I acquainted him with the cause in controversy between the Jew and Antonio the merchant. We turn&#8217;d o&#8217;er many books together. He is furnish&#8217;d with my opinion, which better&#8217;d with his own learning, the greatness whereof I cannot enough commend, comes with him, at my importunity, to fill up your Grace&#8217;s request in my stead. 
I beseech you let his lack of years be no impediment to let him lack a reverend estimation, for I never knew so young a body with so old a head. I leave him to your gracious acceptance, whose trial shall better publish his commendation.&#8221;</recite></line>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Portia for Balthazar.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">You hear the learn&#8217;d Bellario, what he writes,</line>
<line form="verse">And here I take it is the doctor come.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me your hand. Come you from old Bellario?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I did, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">You are welcome, take your place.</line>
<line form="verse">Are you acquainted with the difference</line>
<line form="verse">That holds this present question in the court?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am informed throughly of the cause.</line>
<line form="verse">Which is the merchant here? And which the Jew?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Antonio and old Shylock, both stand forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is your name Shylock?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Shylock is my name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Of a strange nature is the suit you follow,</line>
<line form="verse">Yet in such rule that the Venetian law</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot impugn you as you do proceed.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">You stand within his danger, do you not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, so he says.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Do you confess the bond?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="2">Then must the Jew be merciful.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">On what compulsion must I? Tell me that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The quality of mercy is not strain&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">It droppeth as the gentle rain from heaven</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the place beneath. It is twice blest:</line>
<line form="verse">It blesseth him that gives and him that takes.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis mightiest in the mightiest, it becomes</line>
<line form="verse">The throned monarch better than his crown.</line>
<line form="verse">His sceptre shows the force of temporal power,</line>
<line form="verse">The attribute to awe and majesty,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein doth sit the dread and fear of kings;</line>
<line form="verse">But mercy is above this sceptred sway,</line>
<line form="verse">It is enthroned in the hearts of kings,</line>
<line form="verse">It is an attribute to God himself;</line>
<line form="verse">And earthly power doth then show likest God&#8217;s</line>
<line form="verse">When mercy seasons justice. Therefore, Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">Though justice be thy plea, consider this,</line>
<line form="verse">That in the course of justice, none of us</line>
<line form="verse">Should see salvation. We do pray for mercy,</line>
<line form="verse">And that same prayer doth teach us all to render</line>
<line form="verse">The deeds of mercy. I have spoke thus much</line>
<line form="verse">To mitigate the justice of thy plea,</line>
<line form="verse">Which if thou follow, this strict court of Venice</line>
<line form="verse">Must needs give sentence &#8217;gainst the merchant there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My deeds upon my head! I crave the law,</line>
<line form="verse">The penalty and forfeit of my bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is he not able to discharge the money?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yes, here I tender it for him in the court,</line>
<line form="verse">Yea, twice the sum. If that will not suffice,</line>
<line form="verse">I will be bound to pay it ten times o&#8217;er,</line>
<line form="verse">On forfeit of my hands, my head, my heart.</line>
<line form="verse">If this will not suffice, it must appear</line>
<line form="verse">That malice bears down truth.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To the Duke.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="7">And I beseech you</line>
<line form="verse">Wrest once the law to your authority:</line>
<line form="verse">To do a great right, do a little wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">And curb this cruel devil of his will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It must not be, there is no power in Venice</line>
<line form="verse">Can alter a decree established.</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twill be recorded for a precedent,</line>
<line form="verse">And many an error by the same example</line>
<line form="verse">Will rush into the state. It cannot be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A Daniel come to judgment! Yea, a Daniel!</line>
<line form="verse">O wise young judge, how I do honor thee!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you let me look upon the bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here &#8217;tis, most reverend doctor, here it is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shylock, there&#8217;s thrice thy money off&#8217;red thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">An oath, an oath, I have an oath in heaven!</line>
<line form="verse">Shall I lay perjury upon my soul?</line>
<line form="verse">No, not for Venice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why, this bond is forfeit,</line>
<line form="verse">And lawfully by this the Jew may claim</line>
<line form="verse">A pound of flesh, to be by him cut off</line>
<line form="verse">Nearest the merchant&#8217;s heart. Be merciful,</line>
<line form="verse">Take thrice thy money, bid me tear the bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When it is paid according to the tenure.</line>
<line form="verse">It doth appear you are a worthy judge;</line>
<line form="verse">You know the law, your exposition</line>
<line form="verse">Hath been most sound. I charge you by the law,</line>
<line form="verse">Whereof you are a well-deserving pillar,</line>
<line form="verse">Proceed to judgment. By my soul I swear</line>
<line form="verse">There is no power in the tongue of man</line>
<line form="verse">To alter me: I stay here on my bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most heartily I do beseech the court</line>
<line form="verse">To give the judgment.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Why then thus it is:</line>
<line form="verse">You must prepare your bosom for his knife&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O noble judge, O excellent young man!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">For the intent and purpose of the law</line>
<line form="verse">Hath full relation to the penalty,</line>
<line form="verse">Which here appeareth due upon the bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis very true. O wise and upright judge!</line>
<line form="verse">How much more elder art thou than thy looks!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Therefore lay bare your bosom.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Ay, his breast,</line>
<line form="verse">So says the bond, doth it not, noble judge?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Nearest his heart,&#8221; those are the very words.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is so. Are there balance here to weigh</line>
<line form="verse">The flesh?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">I have them ready.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have by some surgeon, Shylock, on your charge,</line>
<line form="verse">To stop his wounds, lest he do bleed to death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is it so nominated in the bond?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is not so express&#8217;d, but what of that?</line>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Twere good you do so much for charity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I cannot find it, &#8217;tis not in the bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You, merchant, have you any thing to say?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But little; I am arm&#8217;d and well prepar&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Give me your hand, Bassanio, fare you well.</line>
<line form="verse">Grieve not that I am fall&#8217;n to this for you;</line>
<line form="verse">For herein Fortune shows herself more kind</line>
<line form="verse">Than is her custom. It is still her use</line>
<line form="verse">To let the wretched man outlive his wealth,</line>
<line form="verse">To view with hollow eye and wrinkled brow</line>
<line form="verse">An age of poverty; from which ling&#8217;ring penance</line>
<line form="verse">Of such misery doth she cut me off.</line>
<line form="verse">Commend me to your honorable wife,</line>
<line form="verse">Tell her the process of Antonio&#8217;s end,</line>
<line form="verse">Say how I lov&#8217;d you, speak me fair in death;</line>
<line form="verse">And when the tale is told, bid her be judge</line>
<line form="verse">Whether Bassanio had not once a love.</line>
<line form="verse">Repent but you that you shall lose your friend,</line>
<line form="verse">And he repents not that he pays your debt;</line>
<line form="verse">For if the Jew do cut but deep enough,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll pay it instantly with all my heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Antonio, I am married to a wife</line>
<line form="verse">Which is as dear to me as life itself,</line>
<line form="verse">But life itself, my wife, and all the world,</line>
<line form="verse">Are not with me esteem&#8217;d above thy life.</line>
<line form="verse">I would lose all, ay, sacrifice them all</line>
<line form="verse">Here to this devil, to deliver you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your wife would give you little thanks for that</line>
<line form="verse">If she were by to hear you make the offer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have a wife who I protest I love;</line>
<line form="verse">I would she were in heaven, so she could</line>
<line form="verse">Entreat some power to change this currish Jew.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis well you offer it behind her back,</line>
<line form="verse">The wish would make else an unquiet house.</line>
</speech>



<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker><stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">These be the Christian husbands. I have a daughter&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Would any of the stock of Barrabas</line>
<line form="verse">Had been her husband rather than a Christian!</line>
<line form="verse">&#8212;We trifle time. I pray thee pursue sentence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A pound of that same merchant&#8217;s flesh is thine,</line>
<line form="verse">The court awards it, and the law doth give it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most rightful judge!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And you must cut this flesh from off his breast,</line>
<line form="verse">The law allows it, and the court awards it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most learned judge, a sentence! Come prepare!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tarry a little, there is something else.</line>
<line form="verse">This bond doth give thee here no jot of blood;</line>
<line form="verse">The words expressly are &#8216;a pound of flesh.&#8217;</line>
<line form="verse">Take then thy bond, take thou thy pound of flesh,</line>
<line form="verse">But in the cutting it, if thou dost shed</line>
<line form="verse">One drop of Christian blood, thy lands and goods</line>
<line form="verse">Are by the laws of Venice confiscate</line>
<line form="verse">Unto the state of Venice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O upright judge! Mark, Jew. O learned judge!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Is that the law?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Thyself shalt see the act;</line>
<line form="verse">For as thou urgest justice, be assur&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt have justice more than thou desir&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O learned judge! Mark, Jew, a learned judge!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I take this offer then; pay the bond thrice</line>
<line form="verse">And let the Christian go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Here is the money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Soft,</line>
<line form="verse">The Jew shall have all justice. Soft, no haste.</line>
<line form="verse">He shall have nothing but the penalty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O Jew! An upright judge, a learned judge!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Therefore prepare thee to cut off the flesh.</line>
<line form="verse">Shed thou no blood, nor cut thou less nor more</line>
<line form="verse">But just a pound of flesh. If thou tak&#8217;st more</line>
<line form="verse">Or less than a just pound, be it but so much</line>
<line form="verse">As makes it light or heavy in the substance</line>
<line form="verse">Or the division of the twentith part</line>
<line form="verse">Of one poor scruple, nay, if the scale do turn</line>
<line form="verse">But in the estimation of a hair,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou diest, and all thy goods are confiscate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A second Daniel! A Daniel, Jew!</line>
<line form="verse">Now, infidel, I have you on the hip.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why doth the Jew pause? Take thy forfeiture.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Give me my principal, and let me go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have it ready for thee, here it is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He hath refus&#8217;d it in the open court;</line>
<line form="verse">He shall have merely justice and his bond.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A Daniel, still say I, a second Daniel!</line>
<line form="verse">I thank thee, Jew, for teaching me that word.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Shall I not have barely my principal?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt have nothing but the forfeiture,</line>
<line form="verse">To be so taken at thy peril, Jew.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then the devil give him good of it!</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll stay no longer question.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Tarry, Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">The law hath yet another hold on you.</line>
<line form="verse">It is enacted in the laws of Venice,</line>
<line form="verse">If it be proved against an alien,</line>
<line form="verse">That by direct or indirect attempts</line>
<line form="verse">He seek the life of any citizen,</line>
<line form="verse">The party &#8217;gainst the which he doth contrive</line>
<line form="verse">Shall seize one half his goods; the other half</line>
<line form="verse">Comes to the privy coffer of the state,</line>
<line form="verse">And the offender&#8217;s life lies in the mercy</line>
<line form="verse">Of the Duke only, &#8217;gainst all other voice:</line>
<line form="verse">In which predicament I say thou stand&#8217;st;</line>
<line form="verse">For it appears, by manifest proceeding,</line>
<line form="verse">That indirectly, and directly too,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast contrived against the very life</line>
<line form="verse">Of the defendant; and thou hast incurr&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The danger formerly by me rehears&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Down therefore, and beg mercy of the Duke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Beg that thou mayst have leave to hang thyself,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet thy wealth being forfeit to the state,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast not left the value of a cord;</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore thou must be hang&#8217;d at the state&#8217;s charge.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That thou shalt see the difference of our spirit,</line>
<line form="verse">I pardon thee thy life before thou ask it.</line>
<line form="verse">For half thy wealth, it is Antonio&#8217;s;</line>
<line form="verse">The other half comes to the general state,</line>
<line form="verse">Which humbleness may drive unto a fine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, for the state, not for Antonio.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, take my life and all, pardon not that:</line>
<line form="verse">You take my house when you do take the prop</line>
<line form="verse">That doth sustain my house; you take my life</line>
<line form="verse">When you do take the means whereby I live.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What mercy can you render him, Antonio?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A halter gratis&#8212;nothing else, for God sake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So please my lord the Duke and all the court</line>
<line form="verse">To quit the fine for one half of his goods,</line>
<line form="verse">I am content; so he will let me have</line>
<line form="verse">The other half in use, to render it</line>
<line form="verse">Upon his death unto the gentleman</line>
<line form="verse">That lately stole his daughter.</line>
<line form="verse">Two things provided more, that for this favor</line>
<line form="verse">He presently become a Christian;</line>
<line form="verse">The other, that he do record a gift,</line>
<line form="verse">Here in the court, of all he dies possess&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">Unto his son Lorenzo and his daughter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He shall do this, or else I do recant</line>
<line form="verse">The pardon that I late pronounced here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Art thou contented, Jew? What dost thou say?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am content.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Clerk, draw a deed of gift.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SHY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you give me leave to go from hence,</line>
<line form="verse">I am not well. Send the deed after me,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will sign it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Get thee gone, but do it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In christ&#8217;ning shalt thou have two god-fathers:</line>
<line form="verse">Had I been judge, thou shouldst have had ten more,</line>
<line form="verse">To bring thee to the gallows, not to the font.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Shylock.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, I entreat you home with me to dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I humbly do desire your Grace of pardon,</line>
<line form="verse">I must away this night toward Padua,</line>
<line form="verse">And it is meet I presently set forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am sorry that your leisure serves you not.</line>
<line form="verse">Antonio, gratify this gentleman,</line>
<line form="verse">For in my mind you are much bound to him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Duke and his Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Most worthy gentleman, I and my friend</line>
<line form="verse">Have by your wisdom been this day acquitted</line>
<line form="verse">Of grievous penalties, in lieu whereof</line>
<line form="verse">Three thousand ducats, due unto the Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">We freely cope your courteous pains withal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And stand indebted, over and above,</line>
<line form="verse">In love and service to you evermore.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He is well paid that is well satisfied,</line>
<line form="verse">And I, delivering you, am satisfied,</line>
<line form="verse">And therein do account myself well paid.</line>
<line form="verse">My mind was never yet more mercenary.</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you know me when we meet again;</line>
<line form="verse">I wish you well, and so I take my leave.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dear sir, of force I must attempt you further.</line>
<line form="verse">Take some remembrance of us as a tribute,</line>
<line form="verse">Not as fee. Grant me two things, I pray you,</line>
<line form="verse">Not to deny me, and to pardon me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You press me far, and therefore I will yield.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Antonio.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Give me your gloves, I&#8217;ll wear them for your sake,</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To Bassanio.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And for your love I&#8217;ll take this ring from you.</line>
<line form="verse">Do not draw back your hand, I&#8217;ll take no more,</line>
<line form="verse">And you in love shall not deny me this!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This ring, good sir, alas, it is a trifle!</line>
<line form="verse">I will not shame myself to give you this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will have nothing else but only this,</line>
<line form="verse">And now methinks I have a mind to it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s more depends on this than on the value.</line>
<line form="verse">The dearest ring in Venice will I give you,</line>
<line form="verse">And find it out by proclamation;</line>
<line form="verse">Only for this, I pray you pardon me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I see, sir, you are liberal in offers.</line>
<line form="verse">You taught me first to beg, and now methinks</line>
<line form="verse">You teach me how a beggar should be answer&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good sir, this ring was given me by my wife,</line>
<line form="verse">And when she put it on, she made me vow</line>
<line form="verse">That I should neither sell, nor give, nor lose it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That &#8217;scuse serves many men to save their gifts,</line>
<line form="verse">And if your wife be not a mad woman,</line>
<line form="verse">And know how well I have deserv&#8217;d this ring,</line>
<line form="verse">She would not hold out enemy forever</line>
<line form="verse">For giving it to me. Well, peace be with you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Portia and Nerissa.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Lord Bassanio, let him have the ring.</line>
<line form="verse">Let his deservings and my love withal</line>
<line form="verse">Be valued &#8217;gainst your wive&#8217;s commandement.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, Gratiano, run and overtake him;</line>
<line form="verse">Give him the ring, and bring him, if thou canst,</line>
<line form="verse">Unto Antonio&#8217;s house. Away, make haste.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Gratiano.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Come, you and I will thither presently,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the morning early will we both</line>
<line form="verse">Fly toward Belmont. Come, Antonio.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>



<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Venice. A street.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Portia, Nerissa, Gratiano)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Gratiano catches up with Portia and Nerissa as they search for Shylock&#8217;s house. Portia receives the ring with thanks while Nerissa plans to get the ring off her husband&#8217;s finger as well.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Portia and Nerissa disguised as before.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Inquire the Jew&#8217;s house out, give him this deed,</line>
<line form="verse">And let him sign it. We&#8217;ll away tonight,</line>
<line form="verse">And be a day before our husbands home.</line>
<line form="verse">This deed will be well welcome to Lorenzo.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Gratiano.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair sir, you are well o&#8217;erta&#8217;en.</line>
<line form="verse">My Lord Bassanio upon more advice</line>
<line form="verse">Hath sent you here this ring, and doth entreat</line>
<line form="verse">Your company at dinner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">That cannot be.</line>
<line form="verse">His ring I do accept most thankfully,</line>
<line form="verse">And so I pray you tell him; furthermore,</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you show my youth old Shylock&#8217;s house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That will I do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Sir, I would speak with you.</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Portia.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll see if I can get my husband&#8217;s ring,</line>
<line form="verse">Which I did make him swear to keep forever.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside to Nerissa.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Thou mayst, I warrant. We shall have old swearing</line>
<line form="verse">That they did give the rings away to men;</line>
<line form="verse">But we&#8217;ll outface them, and outswear them too.&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Away, make haste. Thou know&#8217;st where I will tarry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, good sir, will you show me to this house?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Belmont. Outside Portia&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lorenzo, Jessica, Stephano, Launcelot, Musicians, Portia, Nerissa, Bassanio, Antonio, Gratiano, Followers)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lorenzo and Jessica have a mock quarrel, comparing themselves to great lovers of the past. Stephano announces that Portia and Nerissa are on their way back, and Launcelot informs them that Bassanio is also returning. Lorenzo calls for music, and he and Jessica listen until Portia and Nerissa arrive. Portia tells them to make sure that no-one tells Bassanio she has been away. Bassanio and Gratiano arrive, along with Antonio, who is introduced to Portia. Peace is broken when Gratiano and Nerissa begin a furious quarrel over the ring he gave to the lawyer&#8217;s clerk. Portia announces her confidence that Bassanio would not have done so, but her husband is forced to admit that he did. Antonio attempts to reconcile the couples, seeing this all as his fault. Portia finally admits the whole story, to widespread wide-eyed amazement. She is also able to tell Antonio that some of his ships have made it back, and that he is therefore not ruined after all, while Nerissa informs Lorenzo and Jessica of how they will inherit all Shylock&#8217;s goods on his death. As Gratiano makes bawdy comments, everyone goes into the house to unravel the whole story.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lorenzo and Jessica.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The moon shines bright. In such a night as this,</line>
<line form="verse">When the sweet wind did gently kiss the trees,</line>
<line form="verse">And they did make no noise, in such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Troilus methinks mounted the Troyan walls,</line>
<line form="verse">And sigh&#8217;d his soul toward the Grecian tents,</line>
<line form="verse">Where Cressid lay that night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Did Thisby fearfully o&#8217;ertrip the dew,</line>
<line form="verse">And saw the lion&#8217;s shadow ere himself,</line>
<line form="verse">And ran dismayed away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Stood Dido with a willow in her hand</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the wild sea-banks, and waft her love</line>
<line form="verse">To come again to Carthage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Medea gathered the enchanted herbs</line>
<line form="verse">That did renew old Aeson.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Did Jessica steal from the wealthy Jew,</line>
<line form="verse">And with an unthrift love did run from Venice,</line>
<line form="verse">As far as Belmont.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Did young Lorenzo swear he lov&#8217;d her well,</line>
<line form="verse">Stealing her soul with many vows of faith,</line>
<line form="verse">And ne&#8217;er a true one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">In such a night</line>
<line form="verse">Did pretty Jessica (like a little shrow)</line>
<line form="verse">Slander her love, and he forgave it her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would out-night you, did nobody come;</line>
<line form="verse">But hark, I hear the footing of a man.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Stephano.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Who comes so fast in silence of the night?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STEPH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A friend! What friend? Your name, I pray you, friend?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STEPH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stephano is my name, and I bring word</line>
<line form="verse">My mistress will before the break of day</line>
<line form="verse">Be here at Belmont. She doth stray about</line>
<line form="verse">By holy crosses, where she kneels and prays</line>
<line form="verse">For happy wedlock hours.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Who comes with her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STEPH.</speaker>
<line form="verse">None but a holy hermit and her maid.</line>
<line form="verse">I pray you, is my master yet return&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He is not, nor we have not heard from him.</line>
<line form="verse">But go we in, I pray thee, Jessica,</line>
<line form="verse">And ceremoniously let us prepare</line>
<line form="verse">Some welcome for the mistress of the house.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Clown Launcelot.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Sola, sola! Wo ha, ho! Sola, sola!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Who calls?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Sola! Did you see Master Lorenzo? Master Lorenzo, sola, sola!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Leave hollowing, man&#8212;here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Sola! Where, where?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LAUN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Tell him there&#8217;s a post come from my master, with his horn full of good news. My master will be here ere morning.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet soul, let&#8217;s in, and there expect their coming.</line>
<line form="verse">And yet no matter; why should we go in?</line>
<line form="verse">My friend Stephano, signify, I pray you,</line>
<line form="verse">Within the house, your mistress is at hand,</line>
<line form="verse">And bring your music forth into the air.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Stephano.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">How sweet the moonlight sleeps upon this bank!</line>
<line form="verse">Here will we sit, and let the sounds of music</line>
<line form="verse">Creep in our ears. Soft stillness and the night</line>
<line form="verse">Become the touches of sweet harmony.</line>
<line form="verse">Sit, Jessica. Look how the floor of heaven</line>
<line form="verse">Is thick inlaid with patens of bright gold.</line>
<line form="verse">There&#8217;s not the smallest orb which thou behold&#8217;st</line>
<line form="verse">But in his motion like an angel sings,</line>
<line form="verse">Still quiring to the young-ey&#8217;d cherubins;</line>
<line form="verse">Such harmony is in immortal souls,</line>
<line form="verse">But whilst this muddy vesture of decay</line>
<line form="verse">Doth grossly close it in, we cannot hear it.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Musicians.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Come ho, and wake Diana with a hymn,</line>
<line form="verse">With sweetest touches pierce your mistress&#8217; ear,</line>
<line form="verse">And draw her home with music.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Play Music.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>JES.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am never merry when I hear sweet music.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The reason is, your spirits are attentive;</line>
<line form="verse">For do but note a wild and wanton herd</line>
<line form="verse">Or race of youthful and unhandled colts,</line>
<line form="verse">Fetching mad bounds, bellowing and neighing loud,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is the hot condition of their blood,</line>
<line form="verse">If they but hear perchance a trumpet sound,</line>
<line form="verse">Or any air of music touch their ears,</line>
<line form="verse">You shall perceive them make a mutual stand,</line>
<line form="verse">Their savage eyes turn&#8217;d to a modest gaze,</line>
<line form="verse">By the sweet power of music; therefore the poet</line>
<line form="verse">Did feign that Orpheus drew trees, stones, and floods;</line>
<line form="verse">Since nought so stockish, hard, and full of rage,</line>
<line form="verse">But music for the time doth change his nature.</line>
<line form="verse">The man that hath no music in himself,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor is not moved with concord of sweet sounds,</line>
<line form="verse">Is fit for treasons, stratagems, and spoils;</line>
<line form="verse">The motions of his spirit are dull as night,</line>
<line form="verse">And his affections dark as Erebus</line>
<line form="verse">Let no such man be trusted. Mark the music.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Portia and Nerissa.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That light we see is burning in my hall.</line>
<line form="verse">How far that little candle throws his beams!</line>
<line form="verse">So shines a good deed in a naughty world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">When the moon shone, we did not see the candle.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So doth the greater glory dim the less:</line>
<line form="verse">A substitute shines brightly as a king</line>
<line form="verse">Until a king be by, and then his state</line>
<line form="verse">Empties itself, as doth an inland brook</line>
<line form="verse">Into the main of waters. Music, hark!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is your music, madam, of the house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nothing is good, I see, without respect;</line>
<line form="verse">Methinks it sounds much sweeter than by day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Silence bestows that virtue on it, madam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The crow doth sing as sweetly as the lark</line>
<line form="verse">When neither is attended; and I think</line>
<line form="verse">The nightingale, if she should sing by day</line>
<line form="verse">When every goose is cackling, would be thought</line>
<line form="verse">No better a musician than the wren.</line>
<line form="verse">How many things by season season&#8217;d are</line>
<line form="verse">To their right praise and true perfection!</line>
<line form="verse">Peace ho! The Moon sleeps with Endymion,</line>
<line form="verse">And would not be awak&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music ceases.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">That is the voice,</line>
<line form="verse">Or I am much deceiv&#8217;d, of Portia.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He knows me as the blind man knows the cuckoo,</line>
<line form="verse">By the bad voice!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Dear lady, welcome home!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We have been praying for our husbands&#8217; welfare,</line>
<line form="verse">Which speed we hope the better for our words.</line>
<line form="verse">Are they return&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Madam, they are not yet;</line>
<line form="verse">But there is come a messenger before,</line>
<line form="verse">To signify their coming.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Go in, Nerissa.</line>
<line form="verse">Give order to my servants that they take</line>
<line form="verse">No note at all of our being absent hence&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor you, Lorenzo&#8212;Jessica, nor you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">A tucket sounds.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your husband is at hand, I hear his trumpet.</line>
<line form="verse">We are no tell-tales, madam, fear you not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This night methinks is but the daylight sick,</line>
<line form="verse">It looks a little paler. &#8217;Tis a day,</line>
<line form="verse">Such as the day is when the sun is hid.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bassanio, Antonio, Gratiano, and their Followers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">We should hold day with the Antipodes,</line>
<line form="verse">If you would walk in absence of the sun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let me give light, but let me not be light,</line>
<line form="verse">For a light wife doth make a heavy husband,</line>
<line form="verse">And never be Bassanio so for me&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">But God sort all! You are welcome home, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I thank you, madam. Give welcome to my friend;</line>
<line form="verse">This is the man, this is Antonio,</line>
<line form="verse">To whom I am so infinitely bound.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You should in all sense be much bound to him,</line>
<line form="verse">For as I hear he was much bound for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No more than I am well acquitted of.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, you are very welcome to our house.</line>
<line form="verse">It must appear in other ways than words,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore I scant this breathing courtesy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To Nerissa.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">By yonder moon I swear you do me wrong;</line>
<line form="verse">In faith, I gave it to the judge&#8217;s clerk.</line>
<line form="verse">Would he were gelt that had it, for my part,</line>
<line form="verse">Since you do take it, love, so much at heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A quarrel ho already! What&#8217;s the matter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">About a hoop of gold, a paltry ring</line>
<line form="verse">That she did give me, whose posy was</line>
<line form="verse">For all the world like cutler&#8217;s poetry</line>
<line form="verse">Upon a knife, &#8220;Love me, and leave me not.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What talk you of the posy or the value?</line>
<line form="verse">You swore to me, when I did give it you,</line>
<line form="verse">That you would wear it till your hour of death,</line>
<line form="verse">And that it should lie with you in your grave.</line>
<line form="verse">Though not for me, yet for your vehement oaths,</line>
<line form="verse">You should have been respective and have kept it.</line>
<line form="verse">Gave it a judge&#8217;s clerk! No, God&#8217;s my judge,</line>
<line form="verse">The clerk will ne&#8217;er wear hair on &#8217;s face that had it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He will, and if he live to be a man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, if a woman live to be a man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, by this hand, I gave it to a youth,</line>
<line form="verse">A kind of boy, a little scrubbed boy,</line>
<line form="verse">No higher than thyself, the judge&#8217;s clerk,</line>
<line form="verse">A prating boy, that begg&#8217;d it as a fee.</line>
<line form="verse">I could not for my heart deny it him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You were to blame, I must be plain with you,</line>
<line form="verse">To part so slightly with your wive&#8217;s first gift,</line>
<line form="verse">A thing stuck on with oaths upon your finger,</line>
<line form="verse">And so riveted with faith unto your flesh.</line>
<line form="verse">I gave my love a ring, and made him swear</line>
<line form="verse">Never to part with it, and here he stands.</line>
<line form="verse">I dare be sworn for him he would not leave it,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor pluck it from his finger, for the wealth</line>
<line form="verse">That the world masters. Now, in faith, Gratiano,</line>
<line form="verse">You give your wife too unkind a cause of grief;</line>
<line form="verse">And &#8217;twere to me I should be mad at it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Why, I were best to cut my left hand off,</line>
<line form="verse">And swear I lost the ring defending it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Lord Bassanio gave his ring away</line>
<line form="verse">Unto the judge that begg&#8217;d it, and indeed</line>
<line form="verse">Deserv&#8217;d it too; and then the boy, his clerk,</line>
<line form="verse">That took some pains in writing, he begg&#8217;d mine,</line>
<line form="verse">And neither man nor master would take aught</line>
<line form="verse">But the two rings.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">What ring gave you, my lord?</line>
<line form="verse">Not that, I hope, which you receiv&#8217;d of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If I could add a lie unto a fault,</line>
<line form="verse">I would deny it; but you see my finger</line>
<line form="verse">Hath not the ring upon it, it is gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Even so void is your false heart of truth.</line>
<line form="verse">By heaven, I will ne&#8217;er come in your bed</line>
<line form="verse">Until I see the ring!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Nor I in yours</line>
<line form="verse">Till I again see mine!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Sweet Portia,</line>
<line form="verse">If you did know to whom I gave the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">If you did know for whom I gave the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">And would conceive for what I gave the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">And how unwillingly I left the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">When nought would be accepted but the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">You would abate the strength of your displeasure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If you had known the virtue of the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">Or half her worthiness that gave the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">Or your own honor to contain the ring,</line>
<line form="verse">You would not then have parted with the ring.</line>
<line form="verse">What man is there so much unreasonable,</line>
<line form="verse">If you had pleas&#8217;d to have defended it</line>
<line form="verse">With any terms of zeal, wanted the modesty</line>
<line form="verse">To urge the thing held as a ceremony?</line>
<line form="verse">Nerissa teaches me what to believe&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll die for&#8217;t but some woman had the ring!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, by my honor, madam, by my soul,</line>
<line form="verse">No woman had it, but a civil doctor,</line>
<line form="verse">Which did refuse three thousand ducats of me,</line>
<line form="verse">And begg&#8217;d the ring, the which I did deny him,</line>
<line form="verse">And suffer&#8217;d him to go displeas&#8217;d away&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Even he that had held up the very life</line>
<line form="verse">Of my dear friend. What should I say, sweet lady?</line>
<line form="verse">I was enforc&#8217;d to send it after him,</line>
<line form="verse">I was beset with shame and courtesy,</line>
<line form="verse">My honor would not let ingratitude</line>
<line form="verse">So much besmear it. Pardon me, good lady,</line>
<line form="verse">For by these blessed candles of the night,</line>
<line form="verse">Had you been there, I think you would have begg&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The ring of me to give the worthy doctor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let not that doctor e&#8217;er come near my house.</line>
<line form="verse">Since he hath got the jewel that I loved,</line>
<line form="verse">And that which you did swear to keep for me,</line>
<line form="verse">I will become as liberal as you,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll not deny him any thing I have,</line>
<line form="verse">No, not my body nor my husband&#8217;s bed.</line>
<line form="verse">Know him I shall, I am well sure of it.</line>
<line form="verse">Lie not a night from home. Watch me like Argus;</line>
<line form="verse">If you do not, if I be left alone,</line>
<line form="verse">Now by mine honor, which is yet mine own,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll have that doctor for my bedfellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I his clerk; therefore be well advis&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">How you do leave me to mine own protection.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well, do you so; let not me take him then,</line>
<line form="verse">For if I do, I&#8217;ll mar the young clerk&#8217;s pen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am th&#8217; unhappy subject of these quarrels.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sir, grieve not you, you are welcome notwithstanding.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Portia, forgive me this enforced wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the hearing of these many friends</line>
<line form="verse">I swear to thee, even by thine own fair eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein I see myself&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Mark you but that!</line>
<line form="verse">In both my eyes he doubly sees himself,</line>
<line form="verse">In each eye, one. Swear by your double self,</line>
<line form="verse">And there&#8217;s an oath of credit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Nay, but hear me.</line>
<line form="verse">Pardon this fault, and by my soul I swear</line>
<line form="verse">I never more will break an oath with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I once did lend my body for his wealth,</line>
<line form="verse">Which but for him that had your husband&#8217;s ring</line>
<line form="verse">Had quite miscarried. I dare be bound again,</line>
<line form="verse">My soul upon the forfeit, that your lord</line>
<line form="verse">Will never more break faith advisedly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then you shall be his surety. Give him this,</line>
<line form="verse">And bid him keep it better than the other.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, Lord Bassanio, swear to keep this ring.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">By heaven, it is the same I gave the doctor!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I had it of him. Pardon me, Bassanio,</line>
<line form="verse">For by this ring, the doctor lay with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And pardon me, my gentle Gratiano,</line>
<line form="verse">For that same scrubbed boy, the doctor&#8217;s clerk,</line>
<line form="verse">In lieu of this last night did lie with me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, this is like the mending of highways</line>
<line form="verse">In summer, where the ways are fair enough.</line>
<line form="verse">What, are we cuckolds ere we have deserv&#8217;d it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Speak not so grossly, you are all amaz&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">Here is a letter, read it at your leisure.</line>
<line form="verse">It comes from Padua, from Bellario.</line>
<line form="verse">There you shall find that Portia was the doctor,</line>
<line form="verse">Nerissa there her clerk. Lorenzo here</line>
<line form="verse">Shall witness I set forth as soon as you,</line>
<line form="verse">And even but now return&#8217;d; I have not yet</line>
<line form="verse">Enter&#8217;d my house. Antonio, you are welcome,</line>
<line form="verse">And I have better news in store for you</line>
<line form="verse">Than you expect. Unseal this letter soon;</line>
<line form="verse">There you shall find three of your argosies</line>
<line form="verse">Are richly come to harbor suddenly.</line>
<line form="verse">You shall not know by what strange accident</line>
<line form="verse">I chanced on this letter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">I am dumb.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were you the doctor, and I knew you not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Were you the clerk that is to make me cuckold?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, but the clerk that never means to do it,</line>
<line form="verse">Unless he live until he be a man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BASS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet doctor, you shall be my bedfellow&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">When I am absent, then lie with my wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ANT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet lady, you have given me life and living,</line>
<line form="verse">For here I read for certain that my ships</line>
<line form="verse">Are safely come to road.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">How now, Lorenzo?</line>
<line form="verse">My clerk hath some good comforts too for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>NER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and I&#8217;ll give them him without a fee.</line>
<line form="verse">There do I give to you and Jessica,</line>
<line form="verse">From the rich Jew, a special deed of gift,</line>
<line form="verse">After his death, of all he dies possess&#8217;d of.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LOR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair ladies, you drop manna in the way</line>
<line form="verse">Of starved people.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POR.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">It is almost morning,</line>
<line form="verse">And yet I am sure you are not satisfied</line>
<line form="verse">Of these events at full. Let us go in,</line>
<line form="verse">And charge us there upon inter&#8217;gatories,</line>
<line form="verse">And we will answer all things faithfully.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>GRA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let it be so. The first inter&#8217;gatory</line>
<line form="verse">That my Nerissa shall be sworn on is,</line>
<line form="verse">Whether till the next night she had rather stay,</line>
<line form="verse">Or go to bed now, being two hours to day.</line>
<line form="verse">But were the day come, I should wish it dark</line>
<line form="verse">Till I were couching with the doctor&#8217;s clerk.</line>
<line form="verse">Well, while I live I&#8217;ll fear no other thing</line>
<line form="verse">So sore, as keeping safe Nerissa&#8217;s ring.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>