<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Midsummer Night&#8217;s Dream">A Midsummer Night&#8217;s Dream</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="A Midsummer Night&#8217;s Dream">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="THE.">Theseus, Duke of Athens</persname>
<persdescription>Theseus, the Duke of Athens, has recently won a war against the Amazons, and to reward himself for his victory is going to marry their queen Hippolyta, whether she likes it or not. This is not the first time he has ravished a woman, and he has also at times loved and then abandoned others. Though he is reasonably sympathetic to Hermia&#8217;s conundrum, he insists on upholding the law as he knows it rather than making any exceptions. He nevertheless does not fully approve of how Egeus and Demetrius act. He enjoys hunting and has a taste for listening to his hounds bark to the echo. He is not above teasing young folks found sleeping in the wood, and uses his authority against Egeus once Demetrius renounces his claim on Hermia. He is not imaginative, or at least he is enough of a rationalist to disbelieve the truth of strange tales. He has an affection for his more simple subjects and their unpracticed efforts to please him. What happens on the morning of his wedding to Hippolyta can be discovered in <persnameref>The Two Noble Kinsmen</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EGE.">Egeus</persname>
<persdescription>Egeus is a courtier at Theseus&#8217;s court and his master of revels. A sterling defender of old-fashioned patriarchy, he intends either to have his daughter Hermia marry the man he choose or to execute her. He has no fondness at all for Lysander, who shows him scant respect, and calls for him to be prosecuted when he finds Hermia with him in the woods, but he must accept Theseus&#8217;s decision to the contrary. He presents the various entertainment options for the evening of the wedding, discouraging as best he can the Duke from choosing the Mechanicals&#8217; play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LYS.">Lysander</persname>
<persdescription>Lysander is a young man of Athens, of good family and fortune. He has a mocking tongue on him. In love with Hermia, he convinces her to flee with him to the house of his aunt, who dotes on him, and who lives outside the reach of Athenian law. He gets them lost in the woods on their way, to the extent that they need to sleep. He rather hopes to cuddle up with Hermia, but she will have none of it and sends him to sleep on his own. Awakening with Puck&#8217;s love juice in his eyes just in time to see Helena, he begins to make extravagant love to her. He enters a bitter rivalry with Demetrius over her, insults Hermia, and rushes off to fight a duel with the other man. Once Puck makes all well, he can scarcely tell just what has happened to him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DEM.">Demetrius</persname>
<persdescription>Demetrius is not the most admirable of young men. Having wooed Helena and won her heart, he shifts his attentions to Hermia, who will have none of him, but whose father favors him. Told by Helena of Hermia and Lysander&#8217;s flight, he follows them to the woods, though deeply irritated by his inability to shake Helena from his coattails. He threatens her with abandonment and possibly molestation, but to no avail. His attempts to woo Hermia as she distraughtly seeks Lysander are no more successful. When Puck&#8217;s love juice makes him fall in love with Helena, he is as extravagant as Lysander in his praises of her, and runs off to fight a duel with the other man for her sake. When the lovers wake with their senses restored, he admits to Theseus that he is in love with Helena, and that he was contracted to her before he ever tried to make a match with Hermia.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PHIL.">Philostrate</persname>
<persdescription>Philostrate is Theseus&#8217;s Master of the Revels. The Duke sends him to encourage everybody in Athens to celebrate his wedding and have a festive time during the four days leading up to the ceremony. He brings Theseus the list of possible entertainments. Unimpressed by the Mechanicals&#8217; play, he unsccessfully attempts to dissuade Theseus from choosing it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="QUIN., PRO.">Quince</persname>
<persdescription>Peter Quince is a carpenter with literary pretensions who organizes some fellow workers into preparing a play he has written to present to Theseus and Hippolyta on their wedding day (in which he presents the Prologue). He is well-respected by his fellows, and Bottom sets great store by his writing abilities. He is able to keep Bottom under at least some control.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BOT.">Bottom</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="PYR.">Pyramus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Bottom the weaver is a take-charge sort of fellow, and a great stage ham who wishes to play all the parts he can in Quince&#8217;s play. In the end, he agrees to stick to Pyramus only. Beyond this, he finds some problems in the script and suggests the way to mend them. Given an ass&#8217;s head by Puck, he does not realize it in the faintest. Despite his stagey pretensions, he is an honest, down-to-earth man, and though confused by Titania&#8217;s intention is perfectly courteous and friendly to the fairies she set to serve him. He talks enough that Titania has the fairies render him dumb. He is more interested in having a good meal, listening to rural music, conversing with the fairies and having a nap than sleeping with Titania. Waking back in his normal form, he recalls his night as a dream of such intensity that he wishes to have Quince turn it to a ballad. He is beloved by his fellows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FLU.">Flute</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="THIS.">Thisbe</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Flute is a bellows-mender, a young man whose facial hair is only just beginning to grow. His voice may be unbroken. He accepts to play Thisbe in Quince&#8217;s play despite not wishing to play a woman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SNOUT.">Snout</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="WALL.">Wall</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Snout is a tinker cast as Pyramus&#8217;s father and the Wall in Quince&#8217;s play. He is cautious about the possibility of displeasing his social betters, and finds several grounds on which to tinker with the play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SNUG.">Snug</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="LION.">Lion</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Snug the joiner is not the most quick-witted of fellows, and is therefore cast as the lion to avoid his having to learn lines. To satisfy Snout and Bottom&#8217;s concerns of frightening the ladies of the court, however, he is given eight lines to reassure them that he is not, in fact, a lion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="STAR.">Starveling</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="MOON.">Moonshine</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Starveling the tailor portrays Moonshine in Quince&#8217;s play. He is interrupted by the courtiers&#8217; comments, and in the end merely summarizes his speech rather than giving it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HIP.">Hippolyta</persname>
<persdescription>Hippolyta is Queen of the Amazons. Having been defeated in battle by Theseus, she is now betrothed to him. Being an Amazon, it is to be expected that she is a great huntress, and that she will enjoy the sound of the baying of Theseus&#8217;s hounds, which he intends to have her hear during the hunt. She warns him that her standards for such concerts are high. She is more convinced by the lovers&#8217; tale than Theseus is, pointing to the evidence of their change of heart. She has no taste for the humiliation of her inferiors, but she is also blunt and unable to hide her opinion of the Mechanicals&#8217; play. She reappears in <persnameref>The Two Noble Kinsmen</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HER.">Hermia</persname>
<persdescription>Hermia is Egeus&#8217;s daughter. In love with Lysander, she refuses to marry Demetrius despite the threat of death for her refusal. She speaks up to praise Lysander to the Duke, and swears to live a nun rather than marry Demetrius. She agrees to run away with her lover to his aunt&#8217;s, beyond the reach of Athenian law. Lost in the forest on the way, she is demure and insists that Lysander not sleep next to her, which ends up causing no end of trouble. Waking to find him gone, she is frightened that Demetrius may have killed him, and rants at him in fine fashion. She has always had a fierce temper. She is darkish of skin, short, and has bright eyes. She and Helena were inseparable friends as children, and it is only the misfortune of Demetrius&#8217;s misplaced love that has separated them; this leads her to believe that Helena is part of a prank being pulled on her by all three of the others when Puck makes a mess of things.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HEL.">Helena</persname>
<persdescription>Helena is a young lady of Athens. She was wooed by Demetrius and remains obsessively, even masochistically in love with him. Fair-skinned and tall, she feels very put-upon and mopes a great deal, but not without good reason. When Hermia and Lysander tell her of their plan to run away, she decides to betray them to Demetrius simply because this will give her a chance to see him again. Despite her deep childhood friendship with Hermia, she is willing to believe the worst of her when she thinks herself mocked. She runs away from the others to return to Athens, but needs to rest on the way. Come morning, Demetrius is in love with her again, and all is well.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OBE.">Oberon</persname>
<persdescription>Oberon is King of Fairies. Proud, angry, and vengeful, he quarrels with Titania for the sake of a changeling boy, and on being refused decides to humiliate her into obedience. He is interested enough in mortals to decide to make happy a lovelorn girl passing by at the time that he hits on this idea for forging a reconciliation with his Queen. He is fond of Puck, but not blind to his anarchic tendencies, and suspects him of causing the lovers&#8217; confusion willfully. He drugs Titania in her sleep to make her fall in love with some monstrous creature, and uses her infatuation to take the changeling boy from her. Having done so, he removes his spell and reconciles himself with her. They then go to bless Theseus&#8217;s house on his wedding night, promising good fortune to all the wedded couples.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="TITA.">Titania</persname>
<persdescription>Titania is Queen of Fairies. Her quarrel with Oberon disturbs nature, but in memory of her votaress she still refuses to give up the boy who is at the quarrel&#8217;s root. Charmed by Oberon, she is entranced by Bottom in his transformed shape, she promises him the world to have him stay by her, though she has him charmed dumb when he spends too much time chatting to the attendants she gives him. She is so besotted that when Oberon asks her for the changeling boy again, she gives him up without a second thought. With the charm taken off her, she is reconciled with Oberon, and goes with him to bless Theseus&#8217;s house on his wedding night. She is proud, obstinate, and careful of her duties, and faithful to the memory of a dead mortal friend.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PUCK.">Puck</persname>
<persdescription>Puck, or Robin Goodfellow, is an amoral prankster of a spirit. Oberon&#8217;s jester, he delights in practical jokes, transforming Bottom for a lark and making him the object of Titania&#8217;s love. When he makes a mistake in carrying out Oberon&#8217;s commands, he is not repentant, and merely enjoys the greater chaos he has caused. He can counterfeit the voices of humans to perfection, can blacken the night, and is occasionally used by Oberon as a janitor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="PEAS.">Peaseblossom</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. FAIRIES.">All Fairies</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Peaseblossom is a fairy of Titania&#8217;s court. Commanded by Titania, it is one of the ones to attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COB.">Cobweb</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. FAIRIES.">All Fairies</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Cobweb is a fairy of Titania&#8217;s court. Commanded by Titania, it is one of the ones to attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MOTH.">Moth</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. FAIRIES.">All Fairies</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Moth is a fairy of Titania&#8217;s court. Commanded by Titania, it is one of the ones to attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MUS.">Mustardseed</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. FAIRIES.">All Fairies</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Mustardseed is a fairy of Titania&#8217;s court. Commanded by Titania, it is one of the ones to attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="FAIRY.">A Fairy</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CHORUS.">Fairy Chorus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>A Fairy is one of Titania&#8217;s servants, charged with spreading the dew. She recognizes Puck, and is not fond of Oberon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="1. FAIRY.">First Fairy</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CHORUS.">Fairy Chorus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Fairy sings a charm to keep Titania&#8217;s sleeping place safe. The First and Second Fairies may be part of the quartet that later attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="2. FAIRY.">Second Fairy</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CHORUS.">Fairy Chorus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Fairy sings a charm to keep Titania&#8217;s sleeping place safe. The First and Second Fairies may be part of the quartet that later attend on Bottom.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>

<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in the palace of Theseus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Theseus, Hippolyta, Philostrate, Egeus, Hermia, Lysander, Demetrius, Helena)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Duke Theseus orders Philostrate to stir up merriment in the streets of Athens before his wedding to Hippolyta, the Queen of the Amazons he defeated in battle. Egeus brings in his daughter Hermia in order to ask the Duke to force her to marry Demetrius, his choice for her husband. Hermia is insisting on marrying Lysander instead, and Egeus begs permission to either force her to wed Demetrius, or to have her killed, as is his right by the law. Theseus gives Hermia until his own wedding to either give in or become a nun. Lysander argues his case, pointing out that he is in all ways equal to Demetrius and that the latter had earlier promised to marry Helena, but Theseus will not go against the law. Left alone, the two lovers lament their fate. Lysander comes up with a plan to flee to an aunt of his, who lives outside the boundaries of Athens and where they could therefore be safely married. They tell this plan to Helena, who is lovesick for Demetrius. Learning that the two runaways will be meeting in the wood that night, she decides to tell Demetrius, in the hopes of winning his favor.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Theseus, Hippolyta, Philostrate, with others.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, fair Hippolyta, our nuptial hour</line>
<line form="verse">Draws on apace. Four happy days bring in</line>
<line form="verse">Another moon; but O, methinks, how slow</line>
<line form="verse">This old moon wanes! She lingers my desires,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a step-dame, or a dowager,</line>
<line form="verse">Long withering out a young man&#8217;s revenue.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Four days will quickly steep themselves in night;</line>
<line form="verse">Four nights will quickly dream away the time;</line>
<line form="verse">And then the moon, like to a silver bow</line>
<line form="verse">New bent in heaven, shall behold the night</line>
<line form="verse">Of our solemnities.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Go, Philostrate,</line>
<line form="verse">Stir up the Athenian youth to merriments,</line>
<line form="verse">Awake the pert and nimble spirit of mirth,</line>
<line form="verse">Turn melancholy forth to funerals:</line>
<line form="verse">The pale companion is not for our pomp.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Philostrate.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hippolyta, I woo&#8217;d thee with my sword,</line>
<line form="verse">And won thy love doing thee injuries;</line>
<line form="verse">But I will wed thee in another key,</line>
<line form="verse">With pomp, with triumph, and with revelling.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Egeus and his daughter Hermia and Lysander and Demetrius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Happy be Theseus, our renowned Duke!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thanks, good Egeus. What&#8217;s the news with thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Full of vexation come I, with complaint</line>
<line form="verse">Against my child, my daughter Hermia.</line>
<line form="verse">Stand forth, Demetrius. My noble lord,</line>
<line form="verse">This man hath my consent to marry her.</line>
<line form="verse">Stand forth, Lysander. And, my gracious Duke,</line>
<line form="verse">This man hath bewitch&#8217;d the bosom of my child.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou, thou, Lysander, thou hast given her rhymes,</line>
<line form="verse">And interchang&#8217;d love-tokens with my child;</line>
<line form="verse">Thou hast by moonlight at her window sung</line>
<line form="verse">With faining voice verses of faining love,</line>
<line form="verse">And stol&#8217;n the impression of her fantasy</line>
<line form="verse">With bracelets of thy hair, rings, gawds, conceits,</line>
<line form="verse">Knacks, trifles, nosegays, sweetmeats&#8212;messengers</line>
<line form="verse">Of strong prevailment in unhardened youth.</line>
<line form="verse">With cunning hast thou filch&#8217;d my daughter&#8217;s heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Turn&#8217;d her obedience (which is due to me)</line>
<line form="verse">To stubborn harshness. And, my gracious Duke,</line>
<line form="verse">Be it so she will not here before your Grace</line>
<line form="verse">Consent to marry with Demetrius,</line>
<line form="verse">I beg the ancient privilege of Athens:</line>
<line form="verse">As she is mine, I may dispose of her;</line>
<line form="verse">Which shall be either to this gentleman,</line>
<line form="verse">Or to her death, according to our law</line>
<line form="verse">Immediately provided in that case.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What say you, Hermia? Be advis&#8217;d, fair maid.</line>
<line form="verse">To you your father should be as a god;</line>
<line form="verse">One that compos&#8217;d your beauties; yea, and one</line>
<line form="verse">To whom you are but as a form in wax,</line>
<line form="verse">By him imprinted, and within his power,</line>
<line form="verse">To leave the figure, or disfigure it.</line>
<line form="verse">Demetrius is a worthy gentleman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So is Lysander.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">In himself he is;</line>
<line form="verse">But in this kind, wanting your father&#8217;s voice,</line>
<line form="verse">The other must be held the worthier.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would my father look&#8217;d but with my eyes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Rather your eyes must with his judgment look.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I do entreat your Grace to pardon me.</line>
<line form="verse">I know not by what power I am made bold,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor how it may concern my modesty,</line>
<line form="verse">In such a presence here to plead my thoughts;</line>
<line form="verse">But I beseech your Grace that I may know</line>
<line form="verse">The worst that may befall me in this case,</line>
<line form="verse">If I refuse to wed Demetrius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Either to die the death, or to abjure</line>
<line form="verse">Forever the society of men.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore, fair Hermia, question your desires,</line>
<line form="verse">Know of your youth, examine well your blood,</line>
<line form="verse">Whether (if you yield not to your father&#8217;s choice)</line>
<line form="verse">You can endure the livery of a nun,</line>
<line form="verse">For aye to be in shady cloister mew&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">To live a barren sister all your life,</line>
<line form="verse">Chaunting faint hymns to the cold fruitless moon.</line>
<line form="verse">Thrice blessed they that master so their blood</line>
<line form="verse">To undergo such maiden pilgrimage;</line>
<line form="verse">But earthlier happy is the rose distill&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Than that which withering on the virgin thorn</line>
<line form="verse">Grows, lives, and dies in single blessedness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So will I grow, so live, so die, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Ere I will yield my virgin patent up</line>
<line form="verse">Unto his lordship, whose unwished yoke</line>
<line form="verse">My soul consents not to give sovereignty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Take time to pause, and by the next new moon&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">The sealing-day betwixt my love and me</line>
<line form="verse">For everlasting bond of fellowship&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Upon that day either prepare to die</line>
<line form="verse">For disobedience to your father&#8217;s will,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else to wed Demetrius, as he would,</line>
<line form="verse">Or on Diana&#8217;s altar to protest</line>
<line form="verse">For aye austerity and single life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Relent, sweet Hermia, and, Lysander, yield</line>
<line form="verse">Thy crazed title to my certain right.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You have her father&#8217;s love, Demetrius,</line>
<line form="verse">Let me have Hermia&#8217;s; do you marry him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Scornful Lysander, true, he hath my love;</line>
<line form="verse">And what is mine, my love shall render him.</line>
<line form="verse">And she is mine, and all my right of her</line>
<line form="verse">I do estate unto Demetrius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am, my lord, as well deriv&#8217;d as he,</line>
<line form="verse">As well possess&#8217;d; my love is more than his;</line>
<line form="verse">My fortunes every way as fairly rank&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">(If not with vantage) as Demetrius&#8217;;</line>
<line form="verse">And (which is more than all these boasts can be)</line>
<line form="verse">I am belov&#8217;d of beauteous Hermia.</line>
<line form="verse">Why should not I then prosecute my right?</line>
<line form="verse">Demetrius, I&#8217;ll avouch it to his head,</line>
<line form="verse">Made love to Nedar&#8217;s daughter, Helena,</line>
<line form="verse">And won her soul; and she, sweet lady, dotes,</line>
<line form="verse">Devoutly dotes, dotes in idolatry,</line>
<line form="verse">Upon this spotted and inconstant man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I must confess that I have heard so much,</line>
<line form="verse">And with Demetrius thought to have spoke thereof;</line>
<line form="verse">But, being over-full of self-affairs,</line>
<line form="verse">My mind did lose it. But, Demetrius, come,</line>
<line form="verse">And come, Egeus, you shall go with me;</line>
<line form="verse">I have some private schooling for you both.</line>
<line form="verse">For you, fair Hermia, look you arm yourself</line>
<line form="verse">To fit your fancies to your father&#8217;s will;</line>
<line form="verse">Or else the law of Athens yields you up</line>
<line form="verse">(Which by no means we may extenuate)</line>
<line form="verse">To death, or to a vow of single life.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, my Hippolyta; what cheer, my love?</line>
<line form="verse">Demetrius and Egeus, go along;</line>
<line form="verse">I must employ you in some business</line>
<line form="verse">Against our nuptial, and confer with you</line>
<line form="verse">Of something nearly that concerns yourselves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With duty and desire we follow you.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt. Manent Lysander and Hermia.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, my love? Why is your cheek so pale?</line>
<line form="verse">How chance the roses there do fade so fast?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Belike for want of rain; which I could well</line>
<line form="verse">Beteem them from the tempest of my eyes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay me! For aught that I could ever read,</line>
<line form="verse">Could ever hear by tale or history,</line>
<line form="verse">The course of true love never did run smooth;</line>
<line form="verse">But either it was different in blood&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O cross! Too high to be enthrall&#8217;d to low.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Or else misgraffed in respect of years&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O spite! Too old to be engag&#8217;d to young.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Or else it stood upon the choice of friends&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O hell, to choose love by another&#8217;s eyes!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Or if there were a sympathy in choice,</line>
<line form="verse">War, death, or sickness did lay siege to it,</line>
<line form="verse">Making it momentany as a sound,</line>
<line form="verse">Swift as a shadow, short as any dream,</line>
<line form="verse">Brief as the lightning in the collied night,</line>
<line form="verse">That, in a spleen, unfolds both heaven and earth;</line>
<line form="verse">And ere a man hath power to say &#8220;Behold!&#8221;</line>
<line form="verse">The jaws of darkness do devour it up:</line>
<line form="verse">So quick bright things come to confusion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If then true lovers have been ever cross&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">It stands as an edict in destiny.</line>
<line form="verse">Then let us teach our trial patience,</line>
<line form="verse">Because it is a customary cross,</line>
<line form="verse">As due to love as thoughts and dreams and sighs,</line>
<line form="verse">Wishes and tears, poor fancy&#8217;s followers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A good persuasion; therefore hear me, Hermia:</line>
<line form="verse">I have a widow aunt, a dowager,</line>
<line form="verse">Of great revenue, and she hath no child.</line>
<line form="verse">From Athens is her house remote seven leagues;</line>
<line form="verse">And she respects me as her only son.</line>
<line form="verse">There, gentle Hermia, may I marry thee;</line>
<line form="verse">And to that place the sharp Athenian law</line>
<line form="verse">Cannot pursue us. If thou lovest me, then</line>
<line form="verse">Steal forth thy father&#8217;s house tomorrow night;</line>
<line form="verse">And in the wood, a league without the town</line>
<line form="verse">(Where I did meet thee once with Helena</line>
<line form="verse">To do observance to a morn of May),</line>
<line form="verse">There will I stay for thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">My good Lysander,</line>
<line form="verse">I swear to thee, by Cupid&#8217;s strongest bow,</line>
<line form="verse">By his best arrow with the golden head,</line>
<line form="verse">By the simplicity of Venus&#8217; doves,</line>
<line form="verse">By that which knitteth souls and prospers loves,</line>
<line form="verse">And by that fire which burn&#8217;d the Carthage queen</line>
<line form="verse">When the false Troyan under sail was seen,</line>
<line form="verse">By all the vows that ever men have broke</line>
<line form="verse">(In number more than ever women spoke),</line>
<line form="verse">In that same place thou hast appointed me</line>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow truly will I meet with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Keep promise, love. Look, here comes Helena.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Helena.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">God speed fair Helena! Whither away?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Call you me fair? That fair again unsay.</line>
<line form="verse">Demetrius loves your fair, O happy fair!</line>
<line form="verse">Your eyes are lodestars, and your tongue&#8217;s sweet air</line>
<line form="verse">More tuneable than lark to shepherd&#8217;s ear</line>
<line form="verse">When wheat is green, when hawthorn buds appear.</line>
<line form="verse">Sickness is catching; O, were favor so,</line>
<line form="verse">Yours would I catch, fair Hermia, ere I go;</line>
<line form="verse">My ear should catch your voice, my eye your eye,</line>
<line form="verse">My tongue should catch your tongue&#8217;s sweet melody.</line>
<line form="verse">Were the world mine, Demetrius being bated,</line>
<line form="verse">The rest I&#8217;ll give to be to you translated.</line>
<line form="verse">O, teach me how you look, and with what art</line>
<line form="verse">You sway the motion of Demetrius&#8217; heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I frown upon him; yet he loves me still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O that your frowns would teach my smiles such skill!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I give him curses; yet he gives me love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O that my prayers could such affection move!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The more I hate, the more he follows me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The more I love, the more he hateth me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">His folly, Helena, is no fault of mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">None but your beauty; would that fault were mine!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Take comfort; he no more shall see my face;</line>
<line form="verse">Lysander and myself will fly this place.</line>
<line form="verse">Before the time I did Lysander see,</line>
<line form="verse">Seem&#8217;d Athens as a paradise to me;</line>
<line form="verse">O then, what graces in my love do dwell,</line>
<line form="verse">That he hath turn&#8217;d a heaven unto a hell!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Helen, to you our minds we will unfold:</line>
<line form="verse">Tomorrow night, when Phoebe doth behold</line>
<line form="verse">Her silver visage in the wat&#8217;ry glass,</line>
<line form="verse">Decking with liquid pearl the bladed grass</line>
<line form="verse">(A time that lovers&#8217; flights doth still conceal),</line>
<line form="verse">Through Athens gates have we devis&#8217;d to steal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And in the wood, where often you and I</line>
<line form="verse">Upon faint primrose beds were wont to lie,</line>
<line form="verse">Emptying our bosoms of their counsel sweet,</line>
<line form="verse">There my Lysander and myself shall meet;</line>
<line form="verse">And thence from Athens turn away our eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">To seek new friends and stranger companies.</line>
<line form="verse">Farewell, sweet playfellow, pray thou for us;</line>
<line form="verse">And good luck grant thee thy Demetrius!</line>
<line form="verse">Keep word, Lysander; we must starve our sight</line>
<line form="verse">From lovers&#8217; food till morrow deep midnight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will, my Hermia.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Hermia.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Helena, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>:</line>
<line form="verse">As you on him, Demetrius dote on you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lysander.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How happy some o&#8217;er other some can be!</line>
<line form="verse">Through Athens I am thought as fair as she.</line>
<line form="verse">But what of that? Demetrius thinks not so;</line>
<line form="verse">He will not know what all but he do know;</line>
<line form="verse">And as he errs, doting on Hermia&#8217;s eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">So I, admiring of his qualities.</line>
<line form="verse">Things base and vile, holding no quantity,</line>
<line form="verse">Love can transpose to form and dignity.</line>
<line form="verse">Love looks not with the eyes but with the mind;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore is wing&#8217;d Cupid painted blind.</line>
<line form="verse">Nor hath Love&#8217;s mind of any judgment taste;</line>
<line form="verse">Wings, and no eyes, figure unheedy haste;</line>
<line form="verse">And therefore is Love said to be a child,</line>
<line form="verse">Because in choice he is so oft beguil&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">As waggish boys in game themselves forswear,</line>
<line form="verse">So the boy Love is perjur&#8217;d every where;</line>
<line form="verse">For ere Demetrius look&#8217;d on Hermia&#8217;s eyne,</line>
<line form="verse">He hail&#8217;d down oaths that he was only mine;</line>
<line form="verse">And when this hail some heat from Hermia felt,</line>
<line form="verse">So he dissolv&#8217;d, and show&#8217;rs of oaths did melt.</line>
<line form="verse">I will go tell him of fair Hermia&#8217;s flight;</line>
<line form="verse">Then to the wood will he tomorrow night</line>
<line form="verse">Pursue her; and for this intelligence</line>
<line form="verse">If I have thanks, it is a dear expense.</line>
<line form="verse">But herein mean I to enrich my pain,</line>
<line form="verse">To have his sight thither and back again.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in Quince&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Quince, Snug, Bottom, Flute, Snout, Starveling)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>A group of craftsmen meet to rehearse the play they hope to be asked to perform at Theseus&#8217;s wedding. Quince the carpenter, who has written the play, assigns the various roles, having to keep down Bottom the weaver, who wants to play everything. They plan to meet the next night in the wood so that no-one will see them rehearse.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Quince the carpenter and Snug the joiner and Bottom the weaver and Flute the bellows-mender and Snout the tinker and Starveling the tailor.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Is all our company here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You were best to call them generally, man by man, according to the scrip.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here is the scroll of every man&#8217;s name, which is thought fit, through all Athens, to play in our enterlude before the Duke and the Duchess, on his wedding-day at night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">First, good Peter Quince, say what the play treats on; then read the names of the actors; and so grow to a point.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Marry, our play is The most lamentable comedy and most cruel death of Pyramus and Thisby.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A very good piece of work, I assure you, and a merry. Now, good Peter Quince, call forth your actors by the scroll. Masters, spread yourselves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Answer as I call you. Nick Bottom the weaver.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ready. Name what part I am for, and proceed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You, Nick Bottom, are set down for Pyramus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What is Pyramus? A lover, or a tyrant?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A lover, that kills himself most gallant for love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That will ask some tears in the true performing of it. If I do it, let the audience look to their eyes. I will move storms; I will condole in some measure. To the rest&#8212;yet my chief humor is for a tyrant. I could play Ercles rarely, or a part to tear a cat in, to make all split.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;The raging rocks</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And shivering shocks</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Shall break the locks</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Of prison gates;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And Phibbus&#8217; car</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Shall shine from far,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And make and mar</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>The foolish Fates.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="prose">This was lofty! Now name the rest of the players. This is Ercles&#8217; vein, a tyrant&#8217;s vein; a lover is more condoling.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Francis Flute the bellows-mender.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here, Peter Quince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Flute, you must take Thisby on you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What is Thisby? A wand&#8217;ring knight?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is the lady that Pyramus must love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay, faith; let not me play a woman; I have a beard coming.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That&#8217;s all one; you shall play it in a mask, and you may speak as small as you will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And I may hide my face, let me play Thisby too. I&#8217;ll speak in a monstrous little voice, &#8220;Thisne! Thisne! Ah, Pyramus, my lover dear! Thy Thisby dear, and lady dear!&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No, no, you must play Pyramus; and, Flute, you Thisby.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well, proceed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Robin Starveling the tailor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STAR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here, Peter Quince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Robin Starveling, you must play Thisby&#8217;s mother. Tom Snout the tinker.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Here, Peter Quince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You, Pyramus&#8217; father; myself, Thisby&#8217;s father; Snug the joiner, you the lion&#8217;s part. And I hope here is a play fitted.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNUG.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Have you the lion&#8217;s part written? Pray you, if it be, give it me, for I am slow of study.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You may do it extempore, for it is nothing but roaring.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Let me play the lion too. I will roar, that I will do any man&#8217;s heart good to hear me. I will roar, that I will make the Duke say, &#8220;Let him roar again; let him roar again.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">the Duchess and the ladies, that they would shrike; and that were enough to hang us all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line form="prose">That would hang us, every mother&#8217;s son.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I grant you, friends, if you should fright the ladies out of their wits, they would have no more discretion but to hang us; but I will aggravate my voice so that I will roar you as gently as any sucking dove; I will roar you and &#8217;twere any nightingale.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You can play no part but Pyramus; for Pyramus is a sweet-fac&#8217;d man; a proper man as one shall see in a summer&#8217;s day; a most lovely gentleman-like man: therefore you must needs play Pyramus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well; I will undertake it. What beard were I best to play it in?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, what you will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I will discharge it in either your straw-color beard, your orange-tawny beard, your purple-in-grain beard, or your French-crown-color beard, your perfit yellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Some of your French crowns have no hair at all; and then you will play barefac&#8217;d. But, masters, here are your parts, and I am to entreat you, request you, and desire you, to con them by tomorrow night; and meet me in the palace wood, a mile without the town, by moonlight; there will we rehearse; for if we meet in the city, we shall be dogg&#8217;d with company, and our devices known. In the meantime I will draw a bill of properties, such as our play wants. I pray you fail me not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">We will meet, and there we may rehearse most obscenely and courageously. Take pains, be perfit; <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">At the Duke&#8217;s oak we meet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Enough; hold, or cut bow-strings.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>In the woods near Athens.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Fairy, Puck, King Oberon, Queen Titania, Demetrius, Helena)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Next night. Robin Goodfellow, the Puck, meets a fairy, and learns that Titania, Queen of the Fairies, is coming to the very place where Oberon, the King, is planning to hold his revels. He explains that there is a great quarrel between the two over a changeling boy. The two monarchs enter and meet, immediately renewing the quarrel, accusing each other of infidelity with Theseus and Hippolyta respectively. Titania absolutely refuses to hand over the changeling to Oberon, explaining that the boy&#8217;s mother was one of her votaresses. Furious, Oberon decides on revenge, and sends Puck to fetch a flower that will enable him to make Titania fall in love with an animal until she gives up the changeling. At this point he sees Demetrius, who is searching through the woods for Lysander and Hermia and is being dogged by Helena, who absolutely refuses to leave him, no matter how badly he treats her. Oberon decides that he will use some of the juice from the flower to make Demetrius love her. When Puck returns with the flower, Oberon gives him some of the juice and orders him to find the Athenian man and drip it in his eyes.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Fairy at one door and Robin Goodfellow (Puck) at another.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How now, spirit, whither wander you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FAIRY.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Over hill, over dale,</line>
<line type="lyric">Thorough bush, thorough brier,</line>
<line type="lyric">Over park, over pale,</line>
<line type="lyric">Thorough flood, thorough fire,</line>
<line type="lyric">I do wander every where,</line>
<line type="lyric">Swifter than the moon&#8217;s sphere;</line>
<line type="lyric">And I serve the Fairy Queen,</line>
<line type="lyric">To dew her orbs upon the green.</line>
<line type="lyric">The cowslips tall her pensioners be,</line>
<line type="lyric">In their gold coats spots you see:</line>
<line type="lyric">Those be rubies, fairy favors,</line>
<line type="lyric">In those freckles live their savors.</line>
<line form="verse">I must go seek some dewdrops here,</line>
<line form="verse">And hang a pearl in every cowslip&#8217;s ear.</line>
<line form="verse">Farewell, thou lob of spirits; I&#8217;ll be gone.</line>
<line form="verse">Our Queen and all her elves come here anon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The King doth keep his revels here tonight;</line>
<line form="verse">Take heed the Queen come not within his sight;</line>
<line form="verse">For Oberon is passing fell and wrath,</line>
<line form="verse">Because that she as her attendant hath</line>
<line form="verse">A lovely boy stolen from an Indian king;</line>
<line form="verse">She never had so sweet a changeling.</line>
<line form="verse">And jealous Oberon would have the child</line>
<line form="verse">Knight of his train, to trace the forests wild;</line>
<line form="verse">But she, perforce, withholds the loved boy,</line>
<line form="verse">Crowns him with flowers, and makes him all her joy.</line>
<line form="verse">And now they never meet in grove or green,</line>
<line form="verse">By fountain clear, or spangled starlight sheen,</line>
<line form="verse">But they do square, that all their elves for fear</line>
<line form="verse">Creep into acorn-cups, and hide them there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FAIRY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Either I mistake your shape and making quite,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else you are that shrewd and knavish sprite</line>
<line form="verse">Call&#8217;d Robin Goodfellow. Are not you he</line>
<line form="verse">That frights the maidens of the villagery,</line>
<line form="verse">Skim milk, and sometimes labor in the quern,</line>
<line form="verse">And bootless make the breathless huswife churn,</line>
<line form="verse">And sometime make the drink to bear no barm,</line>
<line form="verse">Mislead night-wanderers, laughing at their harm?</line>
<line form="verse">Those that Hobgoblin call you, and sweet Puck,</line>
<line form="verse">You do their work, and they shall have good luck.</line>
<line form="verse">Are not you he?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Thou speakest aright;</line>
<line form="verse">I am that merry wanderer of the night.</line>
<line form="verse">I jest to Oberon and make him smile</line>
<line form="verse">When I a fat and bean-fed horse beguile,</line>
<line form="verse">Neighing in likeness of a filly foal;</line>
<line form="verse">And sometime lurk I in a gossip&#8217;s bowl,</line>
<line form="verse">In very likeness of a roasted crab,</line>
<line form="verse">And when she drinks, against her lips I bob,</line>
<line form="verse">And on her withered dewlop pour the ale.</line>
<line form="verse">The wisest aunt, telling the saddest tale,</line>
<line form="verse">Sometime for three-foot stool mistaketh me;</line>
<line form="verse">Then slip I from her bum, down topples she,</line>
<line form="verse">And &#8220;tailor&#8221; cries, and falls into a cough;</line>
<line form="verse">And then the whole quire hold their hips and loff,</line>
<line form="verse">And waxen in their mirth, and neeze, and swear</line>
<line form="verse">A merrier hour was never wasted there.</line>
<line form="verse">But room, fairy! Here comes Oberon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FAIRY.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And here my mistress. Would that he were gone!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the King of Fairies Oberon at one door with his Train, and the Queen Titania at another with hers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ill met by moonlight, proud Titania.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, jealous Oberon? Fairies, skip hence&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I have forsworn his bed and company.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tarry, rash wanton! Am not I thy lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then I must be thy lady; but I know</line>
<line form="verse">When thou hast stolen away from fairy land,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the shape of Corin sat all day,</line>
<line form="verse">Playing on pipes of corn, and versing love,</line>
<line form="verse">To amorous Phillida. Why art thou here</line>
<line form="verse">Come from the farthest steep of India?</line>
<line form="verse">But that, forsooth, the bouncing Amazon,</line>
<line form="verse">Your buskin&#8217;d mistress, and your warrior love,</line>
<line form="verse">To Theseus must be wedded, and you come</line>
<line form="verse">To give their bed joy and prosperity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How canst thou thus for shame, Titania,</line>
<line form="verse">Glance at my credit with Hippolyta,</line>
<line form="verse">Knowing I know thy love to Theseus?</line>
<line form="verse">Didst not thou lead him through the glimmering night</line>
<line form="verse">From Perigenia, whom he ravished?</line>
<line form="verse">And make him with fair Aegles break his faith,</line>
<line form="verse">With Ariadne, and Antiopa?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These are the forgeries of jealousy;</line>
<line form="verse">And never, since the middle summer&#8217;s spring,</line>
<line form="verse">Met we on hill, in dale, forest, or mead,</line>
<line form="verse">By paved fountain or by rushy brook,</line>
<line form="verse">Or in the beached margent of the sea,</line>
<line form="verse">To dance our ringlets to the whistling wind,</line>
<line form="verse">But with thy brawls thou hast disturb&#8217;d our sport.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore the winds, piping to us in vain,</line>
<line form="verse">As in revenge, have suck&#8217;d up from the sea</line>
<line form="verse">Contagious fogs; which, falling in the land,</line>
<line form="verse">Hath every pelting river made so proud</line>
<line form="verse">That they have overborne their continents.</line>
<line form="verse">The ox hath therefore stretch&#8217;d his yoke in vain,</line>
<line form="verse">The ploughman lost his sweat, and the green corn</line>
<line form="verse">Hath rotted ere his youth attain&#8217;d a beard.</line>
<line form="verse">The fold stands empty in the drowned field,</line>
<line form="verse">And crows are fatted with the murrion flock;</line>
<line form="verse">The nine men&#8217;s morris is fill&#8217;d up with mud,</line>
<line form="verse">And the quaint mazes in the wanton green,</line>
<line form="verse">For lack of tread, are undistinguishable.</line>
<line form="verse">The human mortals want their winter here;</line>
<line form="verse">No night is now with hymn or carol blest.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore the moon (the governess of floods),</line>
<line form="verse">Pale in her anger, washes all the air,</line>
<line form="verse">That rheumatic diseases do abound.</line>
<line form="verse">And thorough this distemperature, we see</line>
<line form="verse">The seasons alter: hoary-headed frosts</line>
<line form="verse">Fall in the fresh lap of the crimson rose,</line>
<line form="verse">And on old Hiems&#8217; thin and icy crown</line>
<line form="verse">An odorous chaplet of sweet summer buds</line>
<line form="verse">Is, as in mockery, set; the spring, the summer,</line>
<line form="verse">The childing autumn, angry winter, change</line>
<line form="verse">Their wonted liveries; and the mazed world,</line>
<line form="verse">By their increase, now knows not which is which.</line>
<line form="verse">And this same progeny of evils comes</line>
<line form="verse">From our debate, from our dissension;</line>
<line form="verse">We are their parents and original.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do you amend it then; it lies in you.</line>
<line form="verse">Why should Titania cross her Oberon?</line>
<line form="verse">I do but beg a little changeling boy,</line>
<line form="verse">To be my henchman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Set your heart at rest;</line>
<line form="verse">The fairy land buys not the child of me.</line>
<line form="verse">His mother was a vot&#8217;ress of my order,</line>
<line form="verse">And in the spiced Indian air, by night,</line>
<line form="verse">Full often hath she gossip&#8217;d by my side,</line>
<line form="verse">And sat with me on Neptune&#8217;s yellow sands,</line>
<line form="verse">Marking th&#8217; embarked traders on the flood;</line>
<line form="verse">When we have laugh&#8217;d to see the sails conceive</line>
<line form="verse">And grow big-bellied with the wanton wind;</line>
<line form="verse">Which she, with pretty and with swimming gait,</line>
<line form="verse">Following (her womb then rich with my young squire)</line>
<line form="verse">Would imitate, and sail upon the land</line>
<line form="verse">To fetch me trifles, and return again,</line>
<line form="verse">As from a voyage, rich with merchandise.</line>
<line form="verse">But she, being mortal, of that boy did die,</line>
<line form="verse">And for her sake do I rear up her boy;</line>
<line form="verse">And for her sake I will not part with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">How long within this wood intend you stay?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Perchance till after Theseus&#8217; wedding-day.</line>
<line form="verse">If you will patiently dance in our round,</line>
<line form="verse">And see our moonlight revels, go with us;</line>
<line form="verse">If not, shun me, and I will spare your haunts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Give me that boy, and I will go with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not for thy fairy kingdom. Fairies, away!</line>
<line form="verse">We shall chide downright, if I longer stay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Titania and her Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Well; go thy way. Thou shalt not from this grove</line>
<line form="verse">Till I torment thee for this injury.</line>
<line form="verse">My gentle Puck, come hither. Thou rememb&#8217;rest</line>
<line form="verse">Since once I sat upon a promontory,</line>
<line form="verse">And heard a mermaid on a dolphin&#8217;s back</line>
<line form="verse">Uttering such dulcet and harmonious breath</line>
<line form="verse">That the rude sea grew civil at her song,</line>
<line form="verse">And certain stars shot madly from their spheres,</line>
<line form="verse">To hear the sea-maid&#8217;s music?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">I remember.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">That very time I saw (but thou couldst not),</line>
<line form="verse">Flying between the cold moon and the earth,</line>
<line form="verse">Cupid all arm&#8217;d. A certain aim he took</line>
<line form="verse">At a fair vestal throned by the west,</line>
<line form="verse">And loos&#8217;d his love-shaft smartly from his bow,</line>
<line form="verse">As it should pierce a hundred thousand hearts;</line>
<line form="verse">But I might see young Cupid&#8217;s fiery shaft</line>
<line form="verse">Quench&#8217;d in the chaste beams of the wat&#8217;ry moon,</line>
<line form="verse">And the imperial vot&#8217;ress passed on,</line>
<line form="verse">In maiden meditation, fancy-free.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet mark&#8217;d I where the bolt of Cupid fell.</line>
<line form="verse">It fell upon a little western flower,</line>
<line form="verse">Before milk-white, now purple with love&#8217;s wound,</line>
<line form="verse">And maidens call it love-in-idleness.</line>
<line form="verse">Fetch me that flow&#8217;r; the herb I showed thee once.</line>
<line form="verse">The juice of it on sleeping eyelids laid</line>
<line form="verse">Will make or man or woman madly dote</line>
<line form="verse">Upon the next live creature that it sees.</line>
<line form="verse">Fetch me this herb, and be thou here again</line>
<line form="verse">Ere the leviathan can swim a league.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll put a girdle round about the earth</line>
<line form="verse">In forty minutes.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Having once this juice,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll watch Titania when she is asleep,</line>
<line form="verse">And drop the liquor of it in her eyes;</line>
<line form="verse">The next thing then she waking looks upon</line>
<line form="verse">(Be it on lion, bear, or wolf, or bull,</line>
<line form="verse">On meddling monkey, or on busy ape),</line>
<line form="verse">She shall pursue it with the soul of love.</line>
<line form="verse">And ere I take this charm from off her sight</line>
<line form="verse">(As I can take it with another herb),</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll make her render up her page to me.</line>
<line form="verse">But who comes here? I am invisible,</line>
<line form="verse">And I will overhear their conference.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Demetrius, Helena following him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I love thee not; therefore pursue me not.</line>
<line form="verse">Where is Lysander and fair Hermia?</line>
<line form="verse">The one I&#8217;ll slay; the other slayeth me.</line>
<line form="verse">Thou toldst me they were stol&#8217;n unto this wood;</line>
<line form="verse">And here am I, and wode within this wood,</line>
<line form="verse">Because I cannot meet my Hermia.</line>
<line form="verse">Hence, get thee gone, and follow me no more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You draw me, you hard-hearted adamant;</line>
<line form="verse">But yet you draw not iron, for my heart</line>
<line form="verse">Is true as steel. Leave you your power to draw,</line>
<line form="verse">And I shall have no power to follow you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do I entice you? Do I speak you fair?</line>
<line form="verse">Or rather do I not in plainest truth</line>
<line form="verse">Tell you I do not nor I cannot love you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And even for that do I love you the more;</line>
<line form="verse">I am your spaniel; and, Demetrius,</line>
<line form="verse">The more you beat me, I will fawn on you.</line>
<line form="verse">Use me but as your spaniel; spurn me, strike me,</line>
<line form="verse">Neglect me, lose me; only give me leave,</line>
<line form="verse">Unworthy as I am, to follow you.</line>
<line form="verse">What worser place can I beg in your love</line>
<line form="verse">(And yet a place of high respect with me)</line>
<line form="verse">Than to be used as you use your dog?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Tempt not too much the hatred of my spirit,</line>
<line form="verse">For I am sick when I do look on thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I am sick when I look not on you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You do impeach your modesty too much,</line>
<line form="verse">To leave the city and commit yourself</line>
<line form="verse">Into the hands of one that loves you not;</line>
<line form="verse">To trust the opportunity of night,</line>
<line form="verse">And the ill counsel of a desert place,</line>
<line form="verse">With the rich worth of your virginity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Your virtue is my privilege. For that</line>
<line form="verse">It is not night when I do see your face,</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore I think I am not in the night,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor doth this wood lack worlds of company,</line>
<line form="verse">For you in my respect are all the world.</line>
<line form="verse">Then how can it be said I am alone,</line>
<line form="verse">When all the world is here to look on me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll run from thee, and hide me in the brakes,</line>
<line form="verse">And leave thee to the mercy of wild beasts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The wildest hath not such a heart as you.</line>
<line form="verse">Run when you will; the story shall be chang&#8217;d:</line>
<line form="verse">Apollo flies, and Daphne holds the chase;</line>
<line form="verse">The dove pursues the griffin; the mild hind</line>
<line form="verse">Makes speed to catch the tiger&#8212;bootless speed,</line>
<line form="verse">When cowardice pursues and valor flies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will not stay thy questions. Let me go;</line>
<line form="verse">Or if thou follow me, do not believe</line>
<line form="verse">But I shall do thee mischief in the wood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, in the temple, in the town, the field,</line>
<line form="verse">You do me mischief. Fie, Demetrius!</line>
<line form="verse">Your wrongs do set a scandal on my sex.</line>
<line form="verse">We cannot fight for love, as men may do.</line>
<line form="verse">We should be woo&#8217;d, and were not made to woo.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Demetrius.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll follow thee and make a heaven of hell,</line>
<line form="verse">To die upon the hand I love so well.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fare thee well, nymph. Ere he do leave this grove,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt fly him, and he shall seek thy love.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Hast thou the flower there? Welcome, wanderer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, there it is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">I pray thee give it me.</line>
<line form="verse">I know a bank where the wild thyme blows,</line>
<line form="verse">Where oxlips and the nodding violet grows,</line>
<line form="verse">Quite over-canopied with luscious woodbine,</line>
<line form="verse">With sweet musk-roses and with eglantine;</line>
<line form="verse">There sleeps Titania sometime of the night,</line>
<line form="verse">Lull&#8217;d in these flowers with dances and delight;</line>
<line form="verse">And there the snake throws her enamell&#8217;d skin,</line>
<line form="verse">Weed wide enough to wrap a fairy in;</line>
<line form="verse">And with the juice of this I&#8217;ll streak her eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">And make her full of hateful fantasies.</line>
<line form="verse">Take thou some of it, and seek through this grove:</line>
<line form="verse">A sweet Athenian lady is in love</line>
<line form="verse">With a disdainful youth; anoint his eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">But do it when the next thing he espies</line>
<line form="verse">May be the lady. Thou shalt know the man</line>
<line form="verse">By the Athenian garments he hath on.</line>
<line form="verse">Effect it with some care, that he may prove</line>
<line form="verse">More fond on her than she upon her love;</line>
<line form="verse">And look thou meet me ere the first cock crow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fear not, my lord! Your servant shall do so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Another part of the woods near Athens.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Titania, Fairies, Oberon, Lysander, Hermia, Puck, Demetrius, Helena)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Titania lies herself down to sleep, lulled by the charms sung by her attendant fairies. When they leave, Oberon sneaks up on his queen and pours the love-juice into her eyes. The weary Lysander and Hermia appear, and exhaustedly decide to sleep. Hermia insists that Lysander lie a little away from her, for decency&#8217;s sake. They fall asleep, and Puck, passing by, believes that he has finally found the Athenian he has been ordered to enchant, and therefore puts his love-juice on Lysander&#8217;s eyes. Demetrius, still searching, is distracted by still being followed by Helena, and misses his prey as he shakes her off. She sees Lysander, who is sleeping so deeply she is afraid he is dead. Finally, she manages to wake him, and, under the charm of the love-juice, he instantly falls head over heels in love with her. She is convinced that he is mocking her, and deeply hurt. She leaves, and he pursues her, abandoning Hermia, who awakes to find herself alone and decides to seek for him.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Titania, Queen of Fairies, with her Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come, now a roundel and a fairy song;</line>
<line form="verse">Then, for the third part of a minute, hence,</line>
<line form="verse">Some to kill cankers in the musk-rose buds,</line>
<line form="verse">Some war with rere-mice for their leathren wings</line>
<line form="verse">To make my small elves coats, and some keep back</line>
<line form="verse">The clamorous owl, that nightly hoots and wonders</line>
<line form="verse">At our quaint spirits. Sing me now asleep;</line>
<line form="verse">Then to your offices, and let me rest.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Fairies sing.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FAIRY.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">You spotted snakes with double tongue,</line>
<line type="lyric">Thorny hedgehogs, be not seen,</line>
<line type="lyric">Newts and blind-worms, do no wrong,</line>
<line type="lyric">Come not near our fairy queen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHORUS.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Philomele, with melody,</line>
<line type="lyric">Sing in our sweet lullaby,</line>
<line type="lyric">Lulla, lulla, lullaby, lulla, lulla, lullaby.</line>
<line type="lyric">Never harm,</line>
<line type="lyric">Nor spell, nor charm,</line>
<line type="lyric">Come our lovely lady nigh.</line>
<line type="lyric">So good night, with lullaby.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. FAIRY.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Weaving spiders, come not here;</line>
<line type="lyric">Hence, you long-legg&#8217;d spinners, hence!</line>
<line type="lyric">Beetles black, approach not near;</line>
<line type="lyric">Worm nor snail, do no offense.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CHORUS.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Philomele, with melody, etc.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. FAIRY.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Hence, away! Now all is well.</line>
<line type="lyric">One aloof stand sentinel.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Fairies. Titania sleeps.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Oberon and squeezes the flower on Titania&#8217;s eyelids.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">What thou seest when thou dost wake,</line>
<line type="lyric">Do it for thy true-love take;</line>
<line type="lyric">Love and languish for his sake.</line>
<line type="lyric">Be it ounce, or cat, or bear,</line>
<line type="lyric">Pard, or boar with bristled hair,</line>
<line type="lyric">In thy eye that shall appear</line>
<line type="lyric">When thou wak&#8217;st, it is thy dear:</line>
<line type="lyric">Wake when some vile thing is near.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair love, you faint with wand&#8217;ring in the wood;</line>
<line form="verse">And to speak troth I have forgot our way.</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll rest us, Hermia, if you think it good,</line>
<line form="verse">And tarry for the comfort of the day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be&#8217;t so, Lysander. Find you out a bed;</line>
<line form="verse">For I upon this bank will rest my head.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">One turf shall serve as pillow for us both,</line>
<line form="verse">One heart, one bed, two bosoms, and one troth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay, good Lysander; for my sake, my dear,</line>
<line form="verse">Lie further off yet; do not lie so near.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, take the sense, sweet, of my innocence!</line>
<line form="verse">Love takes the meaning in love&#8217;s conference:</line>
<line form="verse">I mean, that my heart unto yours is knit,</line>
<line form="verse">So that but one heart we can make of it;</line>
<line form="verse">Two bosoms interchained with an oath,</line>
<line form="verse">So then two bosoms and a single troth.</line>
<line form="verse">Then by your side no bed-room me deny;</line>
<line form="verse">For lying so, Hermia, I do not lie.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lysander riddles very prettily.</line>
<line form="verse">Now much beshrew my manners and my pride,</line>
<line form="verse">If Hermia meant to say Lysander lied.</line>
<line form="verse">But, gentle friend, for love and courtesy,</line>
<line form="verse">Lie further off, in humane modesty;</line>
<line form="verse">Such separation as may well be said</line>
<line form="verse">Becomes a virtuous bachelor and a maid,</line>
<line form="verse">So far be distant; and good night, sweet friend.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy love ne&#8217;er alter till thy sweet life end!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Amen, amen, to that fair prayer, say I,</line>
<line form="verse">And then end life when I end loyalty!</line>
<line form="verse">Here is my bed; sleep give thee all his rest!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">With half that wish the wisher&#8217;s eyes be press&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They sleep.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Through the forest have I gone,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">But Athenian found I none,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">On whose eyes I might approve</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">This flower&#8217;s force in stirring love.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Night and silence&#8212;Who is here?</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Weeds of Athens he doth wear:</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">This is he, my master said,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Despised the Athenian maid;</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">And here the maiden, sleeping sound,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">On the dank and dirty ground.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Pretty soul, she durst not lie</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Near this lack-love, this kill-courtesy.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Churl, upon thy eyes I throw</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">All the power this charm doth owe.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">When thou wak&#8217;st, let love forbid</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Sleep his seat on thy eyelid.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">So awake when I am gone,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">For I must now to Oberon.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Demetrius and Helena, running.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay&#8212;though thou kill me, sweet Demetrius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I charge thee hence, and do not haunt me thus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, wilt thou darkling leave me? Do not so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, on thy peril; I alone will go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, I am out of breath in this fond chase!</line>
<line form="verse">The more my prayer, the lesser is my grace.</line>
<line form="verse">Happy is Hermia, wheresoe&#8217;er she lies,</line>
<line form="verse">For she hath blessed and attractive eyes.</line>
<line form="verse">How came her eyes so bright? Not with salt tears;</line>
<line form="verse">If so, my eyes are oft&#8217;ner wash&#8217;d than hers.</line>
<line form="verse">No, no; I am as ugly as a bear;</line>
<line form="verse">For beasts that meet me run away for fear.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore no marvel though Demetrius</line>
<line form="verse">Do, as a monster, fly my presence thus.</line>
<line form="verse">What wicked and dissembling glass of mine</line>
<line form="verse">Made me compare with Hermia&#8217;s sphery eyne!</line>
<line form="verse">But who is here? Lysander! On the ground?</line>
<line form="verse">Dead, or asleep? I see no blood, no wound.</line>
<line form="verse">Lysander, if you live, good sir, awake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Awaking.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">And run through fire I will for thy sweet sake.</line>
<line form="verse">Transparent Helena, nature shows art,</line>
<line form="verse">That through thy bosom makes me see thy heart.</line>
<line form="verse">Where is Demetrius? O, how fit a word</line>
<line form="verse">Is that vile name to perish on my sword!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do not say so, Lysander, say not so.</line>
<line form="verse">What though he love your Hermia? Lord, what though?</line>
<line form="verse">Yet Hermia still loves you; then be content.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Content with Hermia? No; I do repent</line>
<line form="verse">The tedious minutes I with her have spent.</line>
<line form="verse">Not Hermia, but Helena I love.</line>
<line form="verse">Who will not change a raven for a dove?</line>
<line form="verse">The will of man is by his reason sway&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">And reason says you are the worthier maid.</line>
<line form="verse">Things growing are not ripe until their season,</line>
<line form="verse">So I, being young, till now ripe not to reason;</line>
<line form="verse">And touching now the point of human skill,</line>
<line form="verse">Reason becomes the marshal to my will,</line>
<line form="verse">And leads me to your eyes, where I o&#8217;erlook</line>
<line form="verse">Love&#8217;s stories written in Love&#8217;s richest book.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wherefore was I to this keen mockery born?</line>
<line form="verse">When at your hands did I deserve this scorn?</line>
<line form="verse">Is&#8217;t not enough, is&#8217;t not enough, young man,</line>
<line form="verse">That I did never, no, nor never can,</line>
<line form="verse">Deserve a sweet look from Demetrius&#8217; eye,</line>
<line form="verse">But you must flout my insufficiency?</line>
<line form="verse">Good troth, you do me wrong (good sooth, you do)</line>
<line form="verse">In such disdainful manner me to woo.</line>
<line form="verse">But fare you well; perforce I must confess</line>
<line form="verse">I thought you lord of more true gentleness.</line>
<line form="verse">O that a lady, of one man refus&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">Should of another therefore be abus&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">She sees not Hermia. Hermia, sleep thou there,</line>
<line form="verse">And never mayst thou come Lysander near!</line>
<line form="verse">For as a surfeit of the sweetest things</line>
<line form="verse">The deepest loathing to the stomach brings,</line>
<line form="verse">Or as the heresies that men do leave</line>
<line form="verse">Are hated most of those they did deceive,</line>
<line form="verse">So thou, my surfeit and my heresy,</line>
<line form="verse">Of all be hated, but the most of me!</line>
<line form="verse">And, all my powers, address your love and might</line>
<line form="verse">To honor Helen and to be her knight.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>



<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Starting up.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Help me, Lysander, help me! Do thy best</line>
<line form="verse">To pluck this crawling serpent from my breast!</line>
<line form="verse">Ay me, for pity! What a dream was here!</line>
<line form="verse">Lysander, look how I do quake with fear.</line>
<line form="verse">Methought a serpent eat my heart away,</line>
<line form="verse">And you sate smiling at his cruel prey.</line>
<line form="verse">Lysander! What, remov&#8217;d? Lysander! Lord!</line>
<line form="verse">What, out of hearing gone? No sound, no word?</line>
<line form="verse">Alack, where are you? Speak, and if you hear;</line>
<line form="verse">Speak, of all loves! I swoon almost with fear.</line>
<line form="verse">No? Then I well perceive you are not nigh:</line>
<line form="verse">Either death, or you, I&#8217;ll find immediately.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>In the woods.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Quince, Snug, Bottom, Flute, Snout, Starveling, Puck, Peaseblossom, Cobweb, Moth, Mustardseed)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Bottom and the others meet to rehearse, not knowing that they are near Titania&#8217;s bower, and begin to work out difficulties in the script. Fearful of offending or scaring the ladies at court, they decide to add a prologue to the play, explaining that the lion is not a real one. Likewise, parts for Moonshine and the Wall are added and assigned. As they begin to go through the play, Puck happens upon them, and is vastly amused. Seeing a chance to play mischief, he waits until Bottom exits and changes his head into a donkey&#8217;s; when Bottom returns, the others fly in fear, pushed on by Puck. Bottom stolidly believes that they are playing a practical joke on him, not even noticing his transformation. Refusing to play along, he sits down and sings to himself making a racket that wakes Titania  who seeing him, instantly falls in love with him. She begins to woo him, while he, with great common sense, declines to see any truth in her flowery compliments. She calls in fairies to attend on him, and has him led into her bower.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Clowns: Quince, Snug, Bottom, Flute, Snout, and Starveling.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Are we all met?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Pat, pat; and here&#8217;s a marvail&#8217;s convenient place for our rehearsal. This green plot shall be our stage, this hawthorn brake our tiring-house, and we will do it in action as we will do it before the Duke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Peter Quince!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What sayest thou, bully Bottom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">There are things in this comedy of Pyramus and Thisby that will never please. First, Pyramus must draw a sword to kill himself; which the ladies cannot abide. How answer you that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">By&#8217;r lakin, a parlous fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STAR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I believe we must leave the killing out, when all is done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not a whit! I have a device to make all well. Write me a prologue, and let the prologue seem to say we will do no harm with our swords, and that Pyramus is not kill&#8217;d indeed; and for the more better assurance, tell them that I Pyramus am not Pyramus, but Bottom the weaver. This will put them out of fear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well; we will have such a prologue, and it shall be written in eight and six.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No; make it two more; let it be written in eight and eight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Will not the ladies be afeard of the lion?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STAR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I fear it, I promise you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Masters, you ought to consider with yourselves, to bring in (God shield us!) a lion among ladies, is a most dreadful thing; for there is not a more fearful wild-fowl than your lion living; and we ought to look to&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Therefore another prologue must tell he is not a lion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nay; you must name his name, and half his face must be seen through the lion&#8217;s neck, and he himself muse speak through, saying thus, or to the same defect: &#8220;Ladies,&#8221; or &#8220;Fair ladies, I would wish you,&#8221; or &#8220;I would request you,&#8221; or &#8220;I would entreat you, not to fear, not to tremble: my life for yours. If you think I come hither as a lion, it were pity of my life. No! I am no such thing; I am a man as other men are&#8221;; and there indeed let him name his name, and tell them plainly he is Snug the joiner.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well; it shall be so. But there is two hard things: that is, to bring the moonlight into a chamber; for you know, Pyramus and Thisby meet by moonlight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Doth the moon shine that night we play our play?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A calendar, a calendar! Look in the almanac. Find out moonshine, find out moonshine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yes; it doth shine that night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why then may you leave a casement of the great chamber window (where we play) open; and the moon may shine in at the casement.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay; or else one must come in with a bush of thorns and a lantern, and say he comes to disfigure, or to present, the person of Moonshine. Then, there is another thing: we must have a wall in the great chamber; for Pyramus and Thisby (says the story) did talk through the chink of a wall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You can never bring in a wall. What say you, Bottom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Some man or other must present Wall; and let him have some plaster, or some loam, or some rough-cast about him, to signify wall; or let him hold his fingers thus, and through that cranny shall Pyramus and Thisby whisper.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If that may be, then all is well. Come, sit down, every mother&#8217;s son, and rehearse your parts. Pyramus, you begin. When you have spoken your speech, enter into that brake; and so every one according to his cue.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck, behind.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What hempen home-spuns have we swagg&#8217;ring here,</line>
<line form="verse">So near the cradle of the Fairy Queen?</line>
<line form="verse">What, a play toward? I&#8217;ll be an auditor,</line>
<line form="verse">An actor too perhaps, if I see cause.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Speak, Pyramus. Thisby, stand forth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Thisby, the flowers of odious savors sweet&#8221;&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Odorous, odorous.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">&#8212;&#8220;odors savors sweet;</line>
<line form="verse">So hath thy breath, my dearest Thisby dear.</line>
<line form="verse">But hark; a voice! Stay thou but here a while,</line>
<line form="verse">And by and by I will to thee appear.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A stranger Pyramus than e&#8217;er played here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Must I speak now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ay, marry, must you; for you must understand he goes but to see a noise that he heard, and is to come again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">&#8220;Most radiant Pyramus, most lily-white of hue,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Of color like the red rose on triumphant brier,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Most brisky juvenal, and eke most lovely Jew,</line>
<line form="rhyme">As true as truest horse, that yet would never tire,</line>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll meet thee, Pyramus, at Ninny&#8217;s tomb.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">&#8220;Ninus&#8217; tomb,&#8221; man. Why, you must not speak that yet. That you answer to Pyramus. You speak all your part at once, cues and all. Pyramus, enter. Your cue is past; it is &#8220;never tire.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O&#8212;&#8220;As true as truest horse, that yet would never tire.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck, and Bottom with an ass&#8217;s head.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;If I were fair, Thisby, I were only thine.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O monstrous! O strange! We are haunted.</line>
<line form="verse">Pray, masters, fly, masters! Help!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Quince, Snug, Flute, Snout, and Starveling.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll follow you, I&#8217;ll lead you about a round,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Through bog, through bush, through brake, through brier:</line>
<line form="rhyme">Sometime a horse I&#8217;ll be, sometime a hound,</line>
<line form="rhyme">A hog, a headless bear, sometime a fire,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And neigh, and bark, and grunt, and roar, and burn,</line>
<line form="rhyme">Like horse, hound, hog, bear, fire, at every turn.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why do they run away? This is a knavery of them to make me afeard.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Snout.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SNOUT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">O Bottom, thou art chang&#8217;d! What do I see on thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What do you see? You see an ass-head of your own, do you?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Snout.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Quince.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Bless thee. Bottom, bless thee! Thou art translated.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I see their knavery. This is to make an ass of me, to fright me, if they could; but I will not stir from this place, do what they can. I will walk up and down here, and I will sing, that they shall hear I am not afraid.</line>
<stagedir type="song">Sings.</stagedir>
<line type="lyric">The woosel cock so black of hue,</line>
<line type="lyric">With orange-tawny bill,</line>
<line type="lyric">The throstle with his note so true,</line>
<line type="lyric">The wren with little quill&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Awaking.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">What angel wakes me from my flow&#8217;ry bed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<stagedir type="song">Sings.</stagedir>
<line type="lyric">The finch, the sparrow, and the lark,</line>
<line type="lyric">The plain-song cuckoo grey,</line>
<line type="lyric">Whose note full many a man doth mark,</line>
<line type="lyric">And dares not answer nay&#8212;</line>
<line form="prose">For indeed, who would set his wit to so foolish a bird? Who would give a bird the lie, though he cry &#8220;cuckoo&#8221; never so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray thee, gentle mortal, sing again.</line>
<line form="verse">Mine ear is much enamored of thy note;</line>
<line form="verse">So is mine eye enthralled to thy shape;</line>
<line form="verse">And thy fair virtue&#8217;s force (perforce) doth move me</line>
<line form="verse">On the first view to say, to swear, I love thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Methinks, mistress, you should have little reason for that. And yet, to say the truth, reason and love keep little company together now-a-days. The more the pity that some honest neighbors will not make them friends. Nay, I can gleek upon occasion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou art as wise as thou art beautiful.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not so, neither; but if I had wit enough to get out of this wood, I have enough to serve mine owe turn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme">Out of this wood do not desire to go;</line>
<line form="rhyme">Thou shalt remain here, whether thou wilt or no.</line>
<line form="rhyme">I am a spirit of no common rate;</line>
<line form="rhyme">The summer still doth tend upon my state;</line>
<line form="rhyme">And I do love thee; therefore go with me.</line>
<line form="rhyme">I&#8217;ll give thee fairies to attend on thee;</line>
<line form="rhyme">And they shall fetch thee jewels from the deep,</line>
<line form="rhyme">And sing while thou on pressed flowers dost sleep.</line>
<line form="rhyme">And I will purge thy mortal grossness so,</line>
<line form="rhyme">That thou shalt like an aery spirit go.</line>
<line form="rhyme">Peaseblossom! Cobweb! Moth! And Mustardseed!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter four Fairies&#8212;Peaseblossom, Cobweb, Moth, and Mustardseed.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PEAS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ready.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COB.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="2">And I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOTH.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MUS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">And I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL. FAIRIES.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">Where shall we go?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be kind and courteous to this gentleman,</line>
<line form="verse">Hop in his walks and gambol in his eyes;</line>
<line form="verse">Feed him with apricocks and dewberries,</line>
<line form="verse">With purple grapes, green figs, and mulberries;</line>
<line form="verse">The honey-bags steal from the humble-bees,</line>
<line form="verse">And for night-tapers crop their waxen thighs,</line>
<line form="verse">And light them at the fiery glow-worm&#8217;s eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">To have my love to bed and to arise;</line>
<line form="verse">And pluck the wings from painted butterflies,</line>
<line form="verse">To fan the moonbeams from his sleeping eyes.</line>
<line form="verse">Nod to him, elves, and do him courtesies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PEAS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hail, mortal!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MOTH.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MUS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Hail!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I cry your worships mercy, heartily. I beseech your worship&#8217;s name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Cobweb.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I shall desire you of more acquaintance, good Master Cobweb. If I cut my finger, I shall make bold with you. Your name, honest gentleman?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PEAS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Peaseblossom.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I pray you commend me to Mistress Squash, your mother, and to Master Peascod, your father. Good Master Peaseblossom, I shall desire you of more acquaintance too. Your name, I beseech you, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MUS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Mustardseed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Good Master Mustardseed, I know your patience well. That same cowardly, giant-like ox-beef hath devour&#8217;d many a gentleman of your house. I promise you your kindred hath made my eyes water ere now. I desire you of more acquaintance, good Master Mustardseed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come wait upon him; lead him to my bower.</line>
<line form="verse">The moon methinks looks with a wat&#8217;ry eye;</line>
<line form="verse">And when she weeps, weeps every little flower,</line>
<line form="verse">Lamenting some enforced chastity.</line>
<line form="verse">Tie up my lover&#8217;s tongue, bring him silently.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Another part of the woods.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Oberon, Puck, Demetrius, Hermia, Lysander, Helena)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Puck reports to Oberon that Titania has fallen for a half-man, half-ass, and Oberon is delighted with this development. Puck also claims to have fulfilled the order to charm the Athenian, but as Demetrius and Hermia enter, it becomes apparent that he got the wrong man. Demetrius begs Hermia to grant him her favor, but Hermia can think only of Lysander. She leaves him, and, disconsolate, he lies down to sleep. Oberon is furious and suspects that Puck has done this deliberately, but Puck points out that Oberon didn&#8217;t exactly describe Demetrius very well. Oberon tells him to find Helena, and while he is gone puts love-juice on Demetrius&#8217;s eyes. Lysander and Helena latter, he wooing her loudly, she rejecting him, and the noise wakes Demetrius, who seeing her is instantly enamored. Helena is even more convinced that a cruel prank is being played on her. As the two men quarrel, Hermia enters, searching for Lysander, and is appalled to find him rejecting her. Helena immediately believes that Hermia is in on the prank, while Hermia soon comes to believe that Helena has seduced Lysander, and a general fight breaks out. Lysander and Demetrius exit to duel, while the ladies go their separate ways. Oberon orders Puck to make things right by distracting the men during their fight and finding an occasion to use an antidote to the love-juice on Lysander. Imitating both their voices, Puck keeps them from meeting each other, until they are exhausted and lie down to sleep. The ladies too come and lie down nearby, and Puck applies the antidote to Lysander&#8217;s eyes.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King of Fairies Oberon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I wonder if Titania be awak&#8217;d;</line>
<line form="verse">Then what it was that next came in her eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Which she must dote on in extremity.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Here comes my messenger. How now, mad spirit?</line>
<line form="verse">What night-rule now about this haunted grove?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My mistress with a monster is in love.</line>
<line form="verse">Near to her close and consecrated bower,</line>
<line form="verse">While she was in her dull and sleeping hour,</line>
<line form="verse">A crew of patches, rude mechanicals,</line>
<line form="verse">That work for bread upon Athenian stalls,</line>
<line form="verse">Were met together to rehearse a play</line>
<line form="verse">Intended for great Theseus&#8217; nuptial day.</line>
<line form="verse">The shallowest thick-skin of that barren sort,</line>
<line form="verse">Who Pyramus presented, in their sport,</line>
<line form="verse">Forsook his scene, and ent&#8217;red in a brake;</line>
<line form="verse">When I did him at this advantage take,</line>
<line form="verse">An ass&#8217;s nole I fixed on his head.</line>
<line form="verse">Anon his Thisby must be answered,</line>
<line form="verse">And forth my mimic comes. When they him spy,</line>
<line form="verse">As wild geese that the creeping fowler eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Or russet-pated choughs, many in sort</line>
<line form="verse">(Rising and cawing at the gun&#8217;s report),</line>
<line form="verse">Sever themselves and madly sweep the sky,</line>
<line form="verse">So, at his sight, away his fellows fly;</line>
<line form="verse">And at our stamp, here o&#8217;er and o&#8217;er one falls;</line>
<line form="verse">He murder cries, and help from Athens calls.</line>
<line form="verse">Their sense thus weak, lost with their fears thus strong,</line>
<line form="verse">Made senseless things begin to do them wrong,</line>
<line form="verse">For briers and thorns at their apparel snatch;</line>
<line form="verse">Some sleeves, some hats, from yielders all things catch.</line>
<line form="verse">I led them on in this distracted fear,</line>
<line form="verse">And left sweet Pyramus translated there;</line>
<line form="verse">When in that moment (so it came to pass)</line>
<line form="verse">Titania wak&#8217;d, and straightway lov&#8217;d an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This falls out better than I could devise.</line>
<line form="verse">But hast thou yet latch&#8217;d the Athenian&#8217;s eyes</line>
<line form="verse">With the love-juice, as I did bid thee do?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I took him sleeping (that is finish&#8217;d too)</line>
<line form="verse">And the Athenian woman by his side;</line>
<line form="verse">That when he wak&#8217;d, of force she must be ey&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Demetrius and Hermia.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stand close; this is the same Athenian.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is the woman; but not this the man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, why rebuke you him that loves you so?</line>
<line form="verse">Lay breath so bitter on your bitter foe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now I but chide; but I should use thee worse,</line>
<line form="verse">For thou (I fear) hast given me cause to curse.</line>
<line form="verse">If thou hast slain Lysander in his sleep,</line>
<line form="verse">Being o&#8217;er shoes in blood, plunge in the deep,</line>
<line form="verse">And kill me too.</line>
<line form="verse">The sun was not so true unto the day</line>
<line form="verse">As he to me. Would he have stolen away</line>
<line form="verse">From sleeping Hermia? I&#8217;ll believe as soon</line>
<line form="verse">This whole earth may be bor&#8217;d, and that the moon</line>
<line form="verse">May through the centre creep, and so displease</line>
<line form="verse">Her brother&#8217;s noontide with th&#8217; Antipodes.</line>
<line form="verse">It cannot be but thou hast murd&#8217;red him;</line>
<line form="verse">So should a murderer look&#8212;so dead, so grim.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So should the murdered look, and so should I,</line>
<line form="verse">Pierc&#8217;d through the heart with your stern cruelty.</line>
<line form="verse">Yet you, the murderer, look as bright, as clear,</line>
<line form="verse">As yonder Venus in her glimmering sphere.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What&#8217;s this to my Lysander? Where is he?</line>
<line form="verse">Ah, good Demetrius, wilt thou give him me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I had rather give his carcass to my hounds.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Out, dog, out, cur! Thou driv&#8217;st me past the bounds</line>
<line form="verse">Of maiden&#8217;s patience. Hast thou slain him then?</line>
<line form="verse">Henceforth be never numb&#8217;red among men!</line>
<line form="verse">O, once tell true; tell true, even for my sake!</line>
<line form="verse">Durst thou have look&#8217;d upon him being awake?</line>
<line form="verse">And hast thou kill&#8217;d him sleeping? O brave touch!</line>
<line form="verse">Could not a worm, an adder, do so much?</line>
<line form="verse">An adder did it! For with doubler tongue</line>
<line form="verse">Than thine, thou serpent, never adder stung.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You spend your passion on a mispris&#8217;d mood.</line>
<line form="verse">I am not guilty of Lysander&#8217;s blood;</line>
<line form="verse">Nor is he dead, for aught that I can tell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray thee, tell me then that he is well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And if I could, what should I get therefore?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A privilege never to see me more.</line>
<line form="verse">And from thy hated presence part I so:</line>
<line form="verse">See me no more, whether he be dead or no.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is no following her in this fierce vein.</line>
<line form="verse">Here therefore for a while I will remain.</line>
<line form="verse">So sorrow&#8217;s heaviness doth heavier grow</line>
<line form="verse">For debt that bankrout sleep doth sorrow owe;</line>
<line form="verse">Which now in some slight measure it will pay,</line>
<line form="verse">If for his tender here I make some stay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Lie down and sleep.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What hast thou done? Thou hast mistaken quite,</line>
<line form="verse">And laid the love-juice on some true-love&#8217;s sight.</line>
<line form="verse">Of thy misprision must perforce ensue</line>
<line form="verse">Some true love turn&#8217;d, and not a false turn&#8217;d true.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Then fate o&#8217;errules, that one man holding troth,</line>
<line form="verse">A million fail, confounding oath on oath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">About the wood go swifter than the wind,</line>
<line form="verse">And Helena of Athens look thou find.</line>
<line form="verse">All fancy-sick she is and pale of cheer</line>
<line form="verse">With sighs of love, that costs the fresh blood dear.</line>
<line form="verse">By some illusion see thou bring her here.</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll charm his eyes against she do appear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I go, I go, look how I go,</line>
<line form="verse">Swifter than arrow from the Tartar&#8217;s bow.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Flower of this purple dye,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Hit with Cupid&#8217;s archery,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Sink in apple of his eye.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">When his love he doth espy,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Let her shine as gloriously</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">As the Venus of the sky.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">When thou wak&#8217;st, if she be by,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Beg of her for remedy.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Captain of our fairy band,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Helena is here at hand,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">And the youth, mistook by me,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Pleading for a lover&#8217;s fee.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Shall we their fond pageant see?</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Lord, what fools these mortals be!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Stand aside. The noise they make</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Will cause Demetrius to awake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Then will two at once woo one;</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">That must needs be sport alone.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">And those things do best please me</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">That befall prepost&#8217;rously.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lysander and Helena.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why should you think that I should woo in scorn?</line>
<line form="verse">Scorn and derision never come in tears.</line>
<line form="verse">Look when I vow, I weep; and vows so born,</line>
<line form="verse">In their nativity all truth appears.</line>
<line form="verse">How can these things in me seem scorn to you,</line>
<line form="verse">Bearing the badge of faith to prove them true?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You do advance your cunning more and more;</line>
<line form="verse">When truth kills truth, O devilish-holy fray!</line>
<line form="verse">These vows are Hermia&#8217;s. Will you give her o&#8217;er?</line>
<line form="verse">Weigh oath with oath, and you will nothing weigh.</line>
<line form="verse">Your vows to her and me, put in two scales,</line>
<line form="verse">Will even weigh; and both as light as tales.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I had no judgment when to her I swore.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nor none, in my mind, now you give her o&#8217;er.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Demetrius loves her; and he loves not you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Awaking.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">O Helen, goddess, nymph, perfect, divine!</line>
<line form="verse">To what, my love, shall I compare thine eyne?</line>
<line form="verse">Crystal is muddy. O, how ripe in show</line>
<line form="verse">Thy lips, those kissing cherries, tempting grow!</line>
<line form="verse">That pure congealed white, high Taurus&#8217; snow,</line>
<line form="verse">Fann&#8217;d with the eastern wind, turns to a crow</line>
<line form="verse">When thou hold&#8217;st up thy hand. O, let me kiss</line>
<line form="verse">This princess of pure white, this seal of bliss!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O spite! O hell! I see you all are bent</line>
<line form="verse">To set against me for your merriment.</line>
<line form="verse">If you were civil and knew courtesy,</line>
<line form="verse">You would not do me thus much injury.</line>
<line form="verse">Can you not hate me, as I know you do,</line>
<line form="verse">But you must join in souls to mock me too?</line>
<line form="verse">If you were men, as men you are in show,</line>
<line form="verse">You would not use a gentle lady so;</line>
<line form="verse">To vow, and swear, and superpraise my parts,</line>
<line form="verse">When I am sure you hate me with your hearts.</line>
<line form="verse">You both are rivals, and love Hermia;</line>
<line form="verse">And now both rivals, to mock Helena.</line>
<line form="verse">A trim exploit, a manly enterprise,</line>
<line form="verse">To conjure tears up in a poor maid&#8217;s eyes</line>
<line form="verse">With your derision! None of noble sort</line>
<line form="verse">Would so offend a virgin, and extort</line>
<line form="verse">A poor soul&#8217;s patience, all to make you sport.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You are unkind, Demetrius; be not so;</line>
<line form="verse">For you love Hermia; this you know I know.</line>
<line form="verse">And here, with all good will, with all my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">In Hermia&#8217;s love I yield you up my part;</line>
<line form="verse">And yours of Helena to me bequeath,</line>
<line form="verse">Whom I do love, and will do till my death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Never did mockers waste more idle breath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lysander, keep thy Hermia; I will none.</line>
<line form="verse">If e&#8217;er I lov&#8217;d her, all that love is gone.</line>
<line form="verse">My heart to her but as guest-wise sojourn&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And now to Helen is it home return&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">There to remain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Helen, it is not so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Disparage not the faith thou dost not know,</line>
<line form="verse">Lest, to thy peril, thou aby it dear.</line>
<line form="verse">Look where thy love comes; yonder is thy dear.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Hermia.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Dark night, that from the eye his function takes,</line>
<line form="verse">The ear more quick of apprehension makes;</line>
<line form="verse">Wherein it doth impair the seeing sense,</line>
<line form="verse">It pays the hearing double recompense,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou art not by mine eye, Lysander, found;</line>
<line form="verse">Mine ear, I thank it, brought me to thy sound.</line>
<line form="verse">But why unkindly didst thou leave me so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why should he stay, whom love doth press to go?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What love could press Lysander from my side?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lysander&#8217;s love, that would not let him bide&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">Fair Helena! Who more engilds the night</line>
<line form="verse">Than all yon fiery oes and eyes of light.</line>
<line form="verse">Why seek&#8217;st thou me? Could not this make thee know,</line>
<line form="verse">The hate I bare thee made me leave thee so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You speak not as you think. It cannot be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Lo! She is one of this confederacy.</line>
<line form="verse">Now I perceive, they have conjoin&#8217;d all three</line>
<line form="verse">To fashion this false sport, in spite of me.</line>
<line form="verse">Injurious Hermia, most ungrateful maid!</line>
<line form="verse">Have you conspir&#8217;d, have you with these contriv&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">To bait me with this foul derision?</line>
<line form="verse">Is all the counsel that we two have shar&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">The sisters&#8217; vows, the hours that we have spent,</line>
<line form="verse">When we have chid the hasty-footed time</line>
<line form="verse">For parting us&#8212;O, is all forgot?</line>
<line form="verse">All school-days friendship, childhood innocence?</line>
<line form="verse">We, Hermia, like two artificial gods,</line>
<line form="verse">Have with our needles created both one flower,</line>
<line form="verse">Both on one sampler, sitting on one cushion,</line>
<line form="verse">Both warbling of one song, both in one key,</line>
<line form="verse">As if our hands, our sides, voices, and minds</line>
<line form="verse">Had been incorporate. So we grew together,</line>
<line form="verse">Like to a double cherry, seeming parted,</line>
<line form="verse">But yet an union in partition,</line>
<line form="verse">Two lovely berries moulded on one stem;</line>
<line form="verse">So with two seeming bodies, but one heart,</line>
<line form="verse">Two of the first, like coats in heraldry,</line>
<line form="verse">Due but to one, and crowned with one crest.</line>
<line form="verse">And will you rent our ancient love asunder,</line>
<line form="verse">To join with men in scorning your poor friend?</line>
<line form="verse">It is not friendly, &#8217;tis not maidenly.</line>
<line form="verse">Our sex, as well as I, may chide you for it,</line>
<line form="verse">Though I alone do feel the injury.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am amazed at your passionate words.</line>
<line form="verse">I scorn you not; it seems that you scorn me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Have you not set Lysander, as in scorn,</line>
<line form="verse">To follow me and praise my eyes and face?</line>
<line form="verse">And made your other love, Demetrius</line>
<line form="verse">(Who even but now did spurn me with his foot),</line>
<line form="verse">To call me goddess, nymph, divine and rare,</line>
<line form="verse">Precious, celestial? Wherefore speaks he this</line>
<line form="verse">To her he hates? And wherefore doth Lysander</line>
<line form="verse">Deny your love (so rich within his soul)</line>
<line form="verse">And tender me (forsooth) affection,</line>
<line form="verse">But by your setting on, by your consent?</line>
<line form="verse">What though I be not so in grace as you,</line>
<line form="verse">So hung upon with love, so fortunate</line>
<line form="verse">(But miserable most, to love unlov&#8217;d)?</line>
<line form="verse">This you should pity rather than despise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I understand not what you mean by this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, do! Persever, counterfeit sad looks,</line>
<line form="verse">Make mouths upon me when I turn my back,</line>
<line form="verse">Wink each at other, hold the sweet jest up;</line>
<line form="verse">This sport, well carried, shall be chronicled.</line>
<line form="verse">If you have any pity, grace, or manners,</line>
<line form="verse">You would not make me such an argument.</line>
<line form="verse">But fare ye well; &#8217;tis partly my own fault,</line>
<line form="verse">Which death, or absence, soon shall remedy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Stay, gentle Helena; hear my excuse,</line>
<line form="verse">My love, my life, my soul, fair Helena!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O excellent!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Sweet, do not scorn her so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If she cannot entreat, I can compel.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou canst compel no more than she entreat.</line>
<line form="verse">Thy threats have no more strength than her weak prays.</line>
<line form="verse">Helen, I love thee, by my life I do!</line>
<line form="verse">I swear by that which I will lose for thee,</line>
<line form="verse">To prove him false that says I love thee not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I say I love thee more than he can do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If thou say so, withdraw, and prove it too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Quick, come!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Lysander, whereto tends all this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Away, you Ethiop!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">No, no; he&#8217;ll</line>
<line form="verse">Seem to break loose&#8212;take on as you would follow,</line>
<line form="verse">But yet come not. You are a tame man, go!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hang off, thou cat, thou bur! Vile thing, let loose;</line>
<line form="verse">Or I will shake thee from me like a serpent!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why are you grown so rude? What change is this,</line>
<line form="verse">Sweet love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Thy love? Out, tawny Tartar, out!</line>
<line form="verse">Out, loathed med&#8217;cine! O hated potion, hence!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Do you not jest?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Yes, sooth; and so do you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Demetrius, I will keep my word with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I would I had your bond, for I perceive</line>
<line form="verse">A weak bond holds you. I&#8217;ll not trust your word.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Should I hurt her, strike her, kill her dead?</line>
<line form="verse">Although I hate her, I&#8217;ll not harm her so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What? Can you do me greater harm than hate?</line>
<line form="verse">Hate me, wherefore? O me, what news, my love!</line>
<line form="verse">Am not I Hermia? Are not you Lysander?</line>
<line form="verse">I am as fair now as I was erewhile.</line>
<line form="verse">Since night you lov&#8217;d me; yet since night you left me:</line>
<line form="verse">Why then, you left me (O, the gods forbid!)</line>
<line form="verse">In earnest, shall I say?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Ay, by my life;</line>
<line form="verse">And never did desire to see thee more.</line>
<line form="verse">Therefore be out of hope, of question, of doubt;</line>
<line form="verse">Be certain! Nothing truer; &#8217;tis no jest</line>
<line form="verse">That I do hate thee, and love Helena.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O me, you juggler, you canker-blossom,</line>
<line form="verse">You thief of love! What, have you come by night</line>
<line form="verse">And stol&#8217;n my love&#8217;s heart from him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="8">Fine, i&#8217; faith!</line>
<line form="verse">Have you no modesty, no maiden shame,</line>
<line form="verse">No touch of bashfulness? What, will you tear</line>
<line form="verse">Impatient answers from my gentle tongue?</line>
<line form="verse">Fie, fie, you counterfeit, you puppet, you!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Puppet&#8221;? Why so? Ay, that way goes the game.</line>
<line form="verse">Now I perceive that she hath made compare</line>
<line form="verse">Between our statures: she hath urg&#8217;d her height,</line>
<line form="verse">And with her personage, her tall personage,</line>
<line form="verse">Her height, forsooth, she hath prevail&#8217;d with him.</line>
<line form="verse">And are you grown so high in his esteem,</line>
<line form="verse">Because I am so dwarfish and so low?</line>
<line form="verse">How low am I, thou painted maypole? Speak!</line>
<line form="verse">How low am I? I am not yet so low</line>
<line form="verse">But that my nails can reach unto thine eyes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I pray you, though you mock me, gentlemen,</line>
<line form="verse">Let her not hurt me. I was never curst;</line>
<line form="verse">I have no gift at all in shrewishness;</line>
<line form="verse">I am a right maid for my cowardice.</line>
<line form="verse">Let her not strike me. You perhaps may think,</line>
<line form="verse">Because she is something lower than myself,</line>
<line form="verse">That I can match her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">&#8220;Lower&#8221;? Hark again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Good Hermia, do not be so bitter with me.</line>
<line form="verse">I evermore did love you, Hermia,</line>
<line form="verse">Did ever keep your counsels, never wrong&#8217;d you;</line>
<line form="verse">Save that, in love unto Demetrius,</line>
<line form="verse">I told him of your stealth unto this wood.</line>
<line form="verse">He followed you; for love I followed him.</line>
<line form="verse">But he hath chid me hence, and threat&#8217;ned me</line>
<line form="verse">To strike me, spurn me, nay, to kill me too.</line>
<line form="verse">And now, so you will let me quiet go,</line>
<line form="verse">To Athens will I bear my folly back,</line>
<line form="verse">And follow you no further. Let me go.</line>
<line form="verse">You see how simple and how fond I am.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, get you gone. Who is&#8217;t that hinders you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A foolish heart, that I leave here behind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, with Lysander?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">With Demetrius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Be not afraid; she shall not harm thee, Helena.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No, sir; she shall not, though you take her part.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, when she is angry, she is keen and shrewd!</line>
<line form="verse">She was a vixen when she went to school;</line>
<line form="verse">And though she be but little, she is fierce.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8220;Little&#8221; again? Nothing but &#8220;low&#8221; and &#8220;little&#8221;?</line>
<line form="verse">Why will you suffer her to flout me thus?</line>
<line form="verse">Let me come to her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Get you gone, you dwarf;</line>
<line form="verse">You minimus, of hind&#8217;ring knot-grass made;</line>
<line form="verse">You bead, you acorn.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">You are too officious</line>
<line form="verse">In her behalf that scorns your services.</line>
<line form="verse">Let her alone; speak not of Helena,</line>
<line form="verse">Take not her part. For if thou dost intend</line>
<line form="verse">Never so little show of love to her,</line>
<line form="verse">Thou shalt aby it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Now she holds me not;</line>
<line form="verse">Now follow, if thou dar&#8217;st, to try whose right,</line>
<line form="verse">Of thine or mine, is most in Helena.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Follow? Nay; I&#8217;ll go with thee, cheek by jowl.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lysander and Demetrius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You, mistress, all this coil is long of you.</line>
<line form="verse">Nay, go not back.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I will not trust you, I,</line>
<line form="verse">Nor longer stay in your curst company.</line>
<line form="verse">Your hands than mine are quicker for a fray;</line>
<line form="verse">My legs are longer though, to run away.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I am amaz&#8217;d, and know not what to say.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This is thy negligence. Still thou mistak&#8217;st,</line>
<line form="verse">Or else commit&#8217;st thy knaveries willfully.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Believe me, king of shadows, I mistook.</line>
<line form="verse">Did not you tell me I should know the man</line>
<line form="verse">By the Athenian garments he had on?</line>
<line form="verse">And so far blameless proves my enterprise,</line>
<line form="verse">That I have &#8217;nointed an Athenian&#8217;s eyes;</line>
<line form="verse">And so far am I glad it so did sort,</line>
<line form="verse">As this their jangling I esteem a sport.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou seest these lovers seek a place to fight;</line>
<line form="verse">Hie therefore, Robin, overcast the night;</line>
<line form="verse">The starry welkin cover thou anon</line>
<line form="verse">With drooping fog as black as Acheron,</line>
<line form="verse">And lead these testy rivals so astray</line>
<line form="verse">As one come not within another&#8217;s way.</line>
<line form="verse">Like to Lysander sometime frame thy tongue;</line>
<line form="verse">Then stir Demetrius up with bitter wrong;</line>
<line form="verse">And sometime rail thou like Demetrius;</line>
<line form="verse">And from each other look thou lead them thus,</line>
<line form="verse">Till o&#8217;er their brows death-counterfeiting sleep</line>
<line form="verse">With leaden legs and batty wings doth creep.</line>
<line form="verse">Then crush this herb into Lysander&#8217;s eye;</line>
<line form="verse">Whose liquor hath this virtuous property,</line>
<line form="verse">To take from thence all error with his might,</line>
<line form="verse">And make his eyeballs roll with wonted sight.</line>
<line form="verse">When they next wake, all this derision</line>
<line form="verse">Shall seem a dream and fruitless vision,</line>
<line form="verse">And back to Athens shall the lovers wend</line>
<line form="verse">With league whose date till death shall never end.</line>
<line form="verse">Whiles I in this affair do thee employ,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll to my queen and beg her Indian boy;</line>
<line form="verse">And then I will her charmed eye release</line>
<line form="verse">From monster&#8217;s view, and all things shall be peace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My fairy lord, this must be done with haste,</line>
<line form="verse">For Night&#8217;s swift dragons cut the clouds full fast,</line>
<line form="verse">And yonder shines Aurora&#8217;s harbinger,</line>
<line form="verse">At whose approach, ghosts, wand&#8217;ring here and there,</line>
<line form="verse">Troop home to churchyards. Damned spirits all,</line>
<line form="verse">That in crossways and floods have burial,</line>
<line form="verse">Already to their wormy beds are gone.</line>
<line form="verse">For fear lest day should look their shames upon,</line>
<line form="verse">They willfully themselves exile from light,</line>
<line form="verse">And must for aye consort with black-brow&#8217;d Night.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But we are spirits of another sort.</line>
<line form="verse">I with the Morning&#8217;s love have oft made sport,</line>
<line form="verse">And like a forester, the groves may tread</line>
<line form="verse">Even till the eastern gate, all fiery red,</line>
<line form="verse">Opening on Neptune with fair blessed beams,</line>
<line form="verse">Turns into yellow gold his salt green streams.</line>
<line form="verse">But notwithstanding, haste, make no delay;</line>
<line form="verse">We may effect this business yet ere day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Up and down, up and down,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">I will lead them up and down;</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">I am fear&#8217;d in field and town.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Goblin, lead them up and down.</line>
<line form="verse">Here comes one.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lysander.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Where art thou, proud Demetrius? Speak thou now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here, villain, drawn and ready. Where art thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I will be with thee straight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Follow me then</line>
<line form="verse">To plainer ground.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lysander, as following the voice.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Demetrius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Lysander, speak again!</line>
<line form="verse">Thou runaway, thou coward, art thou fled?</line>
<line form="verse">Speak! In some bush? Where dost thou hide thy head?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thou coward, art thou bragging to the stars,</line>
<line form="verse">Telling the bushes that thou look&#8217;st for wars,</line>
<line form="verse">And wilt not come? Come, recreant, come, thou child,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll whip thee with a rod. He is defil&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">That draws a sword on thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Yea, art thou there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Follow my voice; we&#8217;ll try no manhood here.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lysander.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He goes before me, and still dares me on.</line>
<line form="verse">When I come where he calls, then he is gone.</line>
<line form="verse">The villain is much lighter-heel&#8217;d than I;</line>
<line form="verse">I followed fast, but faster he did fly,</line>
<line form="verse">That fallen am I in dark uneven way,</line>
<line form="verse">And here will rest me.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Lie down.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="5">Come, thou gentle day!</line>
<line form="verse">For if but once thou show me thy grey light,</line>
<line form="verse">I&#8217;ll find Demetrius and revenge this spite.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Sleeps.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck and Demetrius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ho, ho, ho! Coward, why com&#8217;st thou not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Abide me, if thou dar&#8217;st; for well I wot</line>
<line form="verse">Thou run&#8217;st before me, shifting every place,</line>
<line form="verse">And dar&#8217;st not stand, nor look me in the face.</line>
<line form="verse">Where art thou now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Come hither; I am here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Nay then thou mock&#8217;st me. Thou shalt buy this dear,</line>
<line form="verse">If ever I thy face by daylight see.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, go thy way. Faintness constraineth me</line>
<line form="verse">To measure out my length on this cold bed.</line>
<line form="verse">By day&#8217;s approach look to be visited.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Lies down and sleeps.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Helena.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O weary night, O long and tedious night,</line>
<line form="verse">Abate thy hours! Shine, comforts, from the east,</line>
<line form="verse">That I may back to Athens by daylight,</line>
<line form="verse">From these that my poor company detest.</line>
<line form="verse">And sleep, that sometimes shuts up sorrow&#8217;s eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Steal me a while from mine own company.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Sleep.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Yet but three? Come one more;</line>
<line type="lyric">Two of both kinds makes up four.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Hermia.</stagedir>
<line type="lyric">Here she comes, curst and sad.</line>
<line type="lyric">Cupid is a knavish lad,</line>
<line type="lyric">Thus to make poor females mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Never so weary, never so in woe,</line>
<line form="verse">Bedabbled with the dew and torn with briers,</line>
<line form="verse">I can no further crawl, no further go;</line>
<line form="verse">My legs can keep no pace with my desires.</line>
<line form="verse">Here will I rest me till the break of day.</line>
<line form="verse">Heavens shield Lysander, if they mean a fray!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Lies down and sleeps.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">On the ground,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Sleep sound;</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">I&#8217;ll apply,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">To your eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Gentle lover, remedy.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Squeezing the juice on Lysander&#8217;s eyes.</stagedir>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">When thou wak&#8217;st,</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Thou tak&#8217;st</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">True delight</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">In the sight</line>
<line form="verse">Of thy former lady&#8217;s eye;</line>
<line form="verse">And the country proverb known,</line>
<line form="verse">That every man should take his own,</line>
<line form="verse">In your waking shall be shown.</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Jack shall have Jill;</line>
<line form="rhyme" type="lyric">Nought shall go ill:</line>
<line form="verse">The man shall have his mare again, and all shall be well.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Another part of the woods.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Titania, Bottom, Peaseblossom, Cobweb, Moth, Mustardseed, Oberon, Puck, Theseus, Hippolyta, Egeus, Attendants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Titania continues to make Bottom as comfortable as she can, having food brought to him and any sort of music he cares for. They lie down and sleep, and Puck and Oberon approach. Oberon reveals that he easily gained custody of the changeling from the distracted Titania, and is now ready to remove the enchantment from her, which he does. The couple are reconciled, and plan to bless Theseus&#8217;s house after his wedding, while Puck removes the ass-head from Bottom. The fairies leave, and the lovers are discovered sleeping on the ground by Theseus and his court, who are out hunting. Waking the four with hunting horns, Theseus mocks them before asking how it is that they are now all in amity. The four cannot explain, feeling that everything that has passed was simply a dream, but Demetrius insists he is now in love with Helena, and Theseus rejects Egeus&#8217;s call for punishment on Lysander. The four reassure each other that they are awake now and follow the court. Bottom wakes, and considers the dream which he thinks he has had, which he realizes cannot be explained in words, but makes plans to have Quince make a ballad out of it all the same.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Queen of Fairies Titania and Clown Bottom, and Fairies Peaseblossom, Cobweb, Moth, Mustardseed, and others, attending, and the King Oberon behind them unseen.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come sit thee down upon this flow&#8217;ry bed,</line>
<line form="verse">While I thy amiable cheeks do coy,</line>
<line form="verse">And stick musk-roses in thy sleek smooth head,</line>
<line form="verse">And kiss thy fair large ears, my gentle joy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where&#8217;s Peaseblossom?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PEAS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ready.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Scratch my head, Peaseblossom. Where&#8217;s <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french> Cobweb?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>COB.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ready.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose"><french xml:lang="fr">Mounsieur</french> Cobweb, good <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>, get you your weapons in your hand, and kill me a red-hipp&#8217;d humble-bee on the top of a thistle; and, good <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>, bring me the honey-bag. Do not fret yourself too much in the action, <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>; and, good <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>, have a care the honey-bag break not, I would be loath to have you overflowen with a honey-bag, signior. Where&#8217;s <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french> Mustardseed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MUS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Ready.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Give me your neaf, <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french> Mustardseed. Pray you, leave your curtsy, good <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MUS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What&#8217;s your will?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Nothing, good <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>, but to help Cavalery Cobweb to scratch. I must to the barber&#8217;s, <french xml:lang="fr">mounsieur</french>; for methinks I am marvail&#8217;s hairy about the face; and I am such a tender ass, if my hair do but tickle me, I must scratch.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">What, wilt thou hear some music, my sweet love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I have a reasonable good ear in music. Let&#8217;s have the tongs and the bones.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music. Tongs. Rural music.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Or say, sweet love, what thou desirest to eat.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Truly, a peck of provender; I could munch your good dry oats. Methinks I have a great desire to a bottle of hay. Good hay, sweet hay, hath no fellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I have a venturous fairy that shall seek</line>
<line form="verse">The squirrel&#8217;s hoard, and fetch thee new nuts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I had rather have a handful or two of dried peas. But, I pray you, let none of your people stir me; I have an exposition of sleep come upon me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sleep thou, and I will wind thee in my arms.</line>
<line form="verse">Fairies, be gone, and be all ways away.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Fairies.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">So doth the woodbine the sweet honeysuckle</line>
<line form="verse">Gently entwist; the female ivy so</line>
<line form="verse">Enrings the barky fingers of the elm.</line>
<line form="verse">O, how I love thee! How I dote on thee!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They sleep.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Advancing.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Welcome, good Robin. Seest thou this sweet sight?</line>
<line form="verse">Her dotage now I do begin to pity.</line>
<line form="verse">For meeting her of late behind the wood,</line>
<line form="verse">Seeking sweet favors for this hateful fool,</line>
<line form="verse">I did upbraid her, and fall out with her.</line>
<line form="verse">For she his hairy temples then had rounded</line>
<line form="verse">With coronet of fresh and fragrant flowers;</line>
<line form="verse">And that same dew which sometime on the buds</line>
<line form="verse">Was wont to swell like round and orient pearls,</line>
<line form="verse">Stood now within the pretty flouriets&#8217; eyes,</line>
<line form="verse">Like tears that did their own disgrace bewail.</line>
<line form="verse">When I had at my pleasure taunted her,</line>
<line form="verse">And she in mild terms begg&#8217;d my patience,</line>
<line form="verse">I then did ask of her her changeling child;</line>
<line form="verse">Which straight she gave me, and her fairy sent</line>
<line form="verse">To bear him to my bower in fairy land.</line>
<line form="verse">And now I have the boy, I will undo</line>
<line form="verse">This hateful imperfection of her eyes.</line>
<line form="verse">And, gentle Puck, take this transformed scalp</line>
<line form="verse">From off the head of this Athenian swain,</line>
<line form="verse">That he, awaking when the other do,</line>
<line form="verse">May all to Athens back again repair,</line>
<line form="verse">And think no more of this night&#8217;s accidents</line>
<line form="verse">But as the fierce vexation of a dream.</line>
<line form="verse">But first I will release the Fairy Queen.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Touching her eyes.</stagedir>
<line type="lyric">Be as thou wast wont to be;</line>
<line type="lyric">See as thou wast wont to see.</line>
<line type="lyric">Dian&#8217;s bud o&#8217;er Cupid&#8217;s flower</line>
<line type="lyric">Hath such force and blessed power.</line>
<line form="verse">Now, my Titania, wake you, my sweet queen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My Oberon, what visions have I seen!</line>
<line form="verse">Methought I was enamor&#8217;d of an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There lies your love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">How came these things to pass?</line>
<line form="verse">O, how mine eyes do loathe his visage now!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Silence a while. Robin, take off this head.</line>
<line form="verse">Titania, music call, and strike more dead</line>
<line form="verse">Than common sleep of all these five the sense.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Music, ho, music, such as charmeth sleep!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music, still.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Now, when thou wak&#8217;st, with thine own fool&#8217;s eyes peep.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sound, music!</line>

<stagedir type="song">Louder music.</stagedir>
<line form="verse" offset="3">Come, my queen, take hands with me,</line>
<line form="verse">And rock the ground whereon these sleepers be.</line>
<line form="verse">Now thou and I are new in amity,</line>
<line form="verse">And will tomorrow midnight solemnly</line>
<line form="verse">Dance in Duke Theseus&#8217; house triumphantly,</line>
<line form="verse">And bless it to all fair prosperity.</line>
<line form="verse">There shall the pairs of faithful lovers be</line>
<line form="verse">Wedded, with Theseus, all in jollity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Fairy King, attend and mark;</line>
<line type="lyric">I do hear the morning lark.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Then, my queen, in silence sad,</line>
<line type="lyric">Trip we after night&#8217;s shade.</line>
<line type="lyric">We the globe can compass soon,</line>
<line type="lyric">Swifter than the wand&#8217;ring moon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Come, my lord, and in our flight,</line>
<line type="lyric">Tell me how it came this night</line>
<line type="lyric">That I sleeping here was found,</line>
<line type="lyric">With these mortals on the ground.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Exeunt. Wind horn within.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Theseus, Hippolyta, Egeus, and all his Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, one of you, find out the forester,</line>
<line form="verse">For now our observation is perform&#8217;d,</line>
<line form="verse">And since we have the vaward of the day,</line>
<line form="verse">My love shall hear the music of my hounds.</line>
<line form="verse">Uncouple in the western valley, let them go.</line>
<line form="verse">Dispatch, I say, and find the forester.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit an Attendant.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">We will, fair queen, up to the mountain&#8217;s top,</line>
<line form="verse">And mark the musical confusion</line>
<line form="verse">Of hounds and echo in conjunction.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I was with Hercules and Cadmus once,</line>
<line form="verse">When in a wood of Crete they bay&#8217;d the bear</line>
<line form="verse">With hounds of Sparta. Never did I hear</line>
<line form="verse">Such gallant chiding; for besides the groves,</line>
<line form="verse">The skies, the fountains, every region near</line>
<line form="verse">Seem all one mutual cry. I never heard</line>
<line form="verse">So musical a discord, such sweet thunder.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My hounds are bred out of the Spartan kind;</line>
<line form="verse">So flew&#8217;d, so sanded; and their heads are hung</line>
<line form="verse">With ears that sweep away the morning dew;</line>
<line form="verse">Crook-knee&#8217;d, and dewlapp&#8217;d like Thessalian bulls;</line>
<line form="verse">Slow in pursuit; but match&#8217;d in mouth like bells,</line>
<line form="verse">Each under each. A cry more tuneable</line>
<line form="verse">Was never hollow&#8217;d to, nor cheer&#8217;d with horn,</line>
<line form="verse">In Crete, in Sparta, nor in Thessaly.</line>
<line form="verse">Judge when you hear. But soft! What nymphs are these?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, this&#8217; my daughter here asleep,</line>
<line form="verse">And this Lysander, this Demetrius is,</line>
<line form="verse">This Helena, old Nedar&#8217;s Helena.</line>
<line form="verse">I wonder of their being here together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">No doubt they rose up early to observe</line>
<line form="verse">The rite of May; and hearing our intent,</line>
<line form="verse">Came here in grace of our solemnity.</line>
<line form="verse">But speak, Egeus, is not this the day</line>
<line form="verse">That Hermia should give answer of her choice?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">It is, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Go, bid the huntsmen wake them with their horns.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit an Attendant. Shout within. Wind horns. They all start up.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Good morrow, friends. Saint Valentine is past;</line>
<line form="verse">Begin these wood-birds but to couple now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Pardon, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They kneel.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I pray you all, stand up.</line>
<line form="verse">I know you two are rival enemies.</line>
<line form="verse">How comes this gentle concord in the world,</line>
<line form="verse">That hatred is so far from jealousy</line>
<line form="verse">To sleep by hate and fear no enmity?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, I shall reply amazedly,</line>
<line form="verse">Half sleep, half waking; but, as yet, I swear,</line>
<line form="verse">I cannot truly say how I came here.</line>
<line form="verse">But, as I think&#8212;for truly would I speak,</line>
<line form="verse">And now I do bethink me, so it is&#8212;</line>
<line form="verse">I came with Hermia hither. Our intent</line>
<line form="verse">Was to be gone from Athens, where we might,</line>
<line form="verse">Without the peril of the Athenian law&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>EGE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Enough, enough, my lord; you have enough.</line>
<line form="verse">I beg the law, the law, upon his head.</line>
<line form="verse">They would have stol&#8217;n away, they would, Demetrius,</line>
<line form="verse">Thereby to have defeated you and me:</line>
<line form="verse">You of your wife, and me of my consent,</line>
<line form="verse">Of my consent that she should be your wife.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My lord, fair Helen told me of their stealth,</line>
<line form="verse">Of this their purpose hither to this wood,</line>
<line form="verse">And I in fury hither followed them,</line>
<line form="verse">Fair Helena in fancy following me.</line>
<line form="verse">But, my good lord, I wot not by what power</line>
<line form="verse">(But by some power it is), my love to Hermia</line>
<line form="verse">(Melted as the snow) seems to me now</line>
<line form="verse">As the remembrance of an idle gaud,</line>
<line form="verse">Which in my childhood I did dote upon;</line>
<line form="verse">And all the faith, the virtue of my heart,</line>
<line form="verse">The object and the pleasure of mine eye,</line>
<line form="verse">Is only Helena. To her, my lord,</line>
<line form="verse">Was I betrothed ere I saw Hermia;</line>
<line form="verse">But like a sickness did I loathe this food;</line>
<line form="verse">But, as in health, come to my natural taste,</line>
<line form="verse">Now I do wish it, love it, long for it,</line>
<line form="verse">And will forevermore be true to it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Fair lovers, you are fortunately met;</line>
<line form="verse">Of this discourse we more will hear anon.</line>
<line form="verse">Egeus, I will overbear your will;</line>
<line form="verse">For in the temple, by and by, with us</line>
<line form="verse">These couples shall eternally be knit.</line>
<line form="verse">And, for the morning now is something worn,</line>
<line form="verse">Our purpos&#8217;d hunting shall be set aside.</line>
<line form="verse">Away with us to Athens. Three and three,</line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll hold a feast in great solemnity.</line>
<line form="verse">Come, Hippolyta.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Theseus, Hippolyta, Egeus, and Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">These things seem small and undistinguishable,</line>
<line form="verse">Like far-off mountains turned into clouds.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Methinks I see these things with parted eye,</line>
<line form="verse">When every thing seems double.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="7">So methinks;</line>
<line form="verse">And I have found Demetrius like a jewel,</line>
<line form="verse">Mine own, and not mine own.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="6">Are you sure</line>
<line form="verse">That we are awake? It seems to me</line>
<line form="verse">That yet we sleep, we dream. Do not you think</line>
<line form="verse">The Duke was here, and bid us follow him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HER.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Yea, and my father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HEL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">And Hippolyta.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And he did bid us follow to the temple.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why then, we are awake. Let&#8217;s follow him,</line>
<line form="verse">And by the way let&#8217;s recount our dreams.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lovers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Awaking.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">When my cue comes, call me, and I will answer. My next is, &#8220;Most fair Pyramus.&#8221; Heigh-ho! Peter Quince! Flute the bellows-mender! Snout the tinker! Starveling! God&#8217;s my life, stol&#8217;n hence, and left me asleep! I have had a most rare vision. I have had a dream, past the wit of man to say what dream it was. Man is but an ass, if he go about t&#8217; expound this dream. Methought I was&#8212;there is no man can tell what. Methought I was, and methought I had&#8212;but man is but a patch&#8217;d fool, if he will offer to say what methought I had. The eye of man hath not heard, the ear of man hath not seen, man&#8217;s hand is not able to taste, his tongue to conceive, nor his heart to report, what my dream was. I will get Peter Quince to write a ballet of this dream. It shall be call&#8217;d &#8220;Bottom&#8217;s Dream,&#8221; because it hath no bottom; and I will sing it in the latter end of a play, before the Duke. Peradventure, to make it the more gracious, I shall sing it at her death.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in Quince&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Quince, Thisby Flute, Snout, Starveling, Snug, Bottom)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The actors are anxious about Bottom&#8217;s whereabouts, as they cannot put on their play without him. As they sink into despair, Bottom joins them, and tells them that they have indeed been chosen to present their play for the newlyweds.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Quince, Thisby Flute, and the rabble Snout, Starveling.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Have you sent to Bottom&#8217;s house? Is he come home yet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>STAR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He cannot be heard of. Out of doubt he is transported.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If he come not, then the play is marr&#8217;d. It goes not forward, doth it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is not possible. You have not a man in all Athens able to discharge Pyramus but he.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No, he hath simply the best wit of any handicraft man in Athens.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Yea, and the best person too; and he is a very paramour for a sweet voice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">You must say &#8220;paragon.&#8221; A paramour is (God bless us!) a thing of naught.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Snug the joiner.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SNUG.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Masters, the Duke is coming from the temple, and there is two or three lords and ladies more married. If our sport had gone forward, we had all been made men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLU.</speaker>
<line form="prose">O sweet bully Bottom! Thus hath he lost sixpence a day during his life; he could not have scap&#8217;d sixpence a day. And the Duke had not given him sixpence a day for playing Pyramus, I&#8217;ll be hang&#8217;d. He would have deserv&#8217;d it. Sixpence a day in Pyramus, or nothing.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Bottom.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Where are these lads? Where are these hearts?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Bottom! O most courageous day! O most happy hour!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Masters, I am to discourse wonders; but ask me not what; for if I tell you, I am no true Athenian. I will tell you every thing, right as it fell out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>QUIN.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Let us hear, sweet Bottom.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not a word of me. All that I will tell you is, that the Duke hath din&#8217;d. Get your apparel together, good strings to your beards, new ribands to your pumps; meet presently at the palace; every man look o&#8217;er his part; for the short and the long is, our play is preferr&#8217;d. In any case, let Thisby have clean linen; and let not him that plays the lion pare his nails, for they shall hang out for the lion&#8217;s claws. And, most dear actors, eat no onions nor garlic, for we are to utter sweet breath; and I do not doubt but to hear them say, it is a sweet comedy. No more words. Away, go, away!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in the palace of Theseus.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Theseus, Hippolyta, Philostrate, Lords, Attendants, Lysander, Demetrius, Hermia, Helena, Quince, Pyramus, Thisby, Lion, Moonshine, Puck, Oberon, Titania)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Theseus and Hippolyta discuss the story they have heard from the lovers, though Theseus dismisses its truth. The lovers, like their rulers now married, come in, and Theseus asks to find out what entertainment they shall have before bedtime. He dismisses many of the options, finally choosing the artisans&#8217; play, despite Philostrate&#8217;s insistence that it is unworthy. Hippolyta wonders at Theseus&#8217;s choice, since Philostrate insists that the men can&#8217;t act, but the Duke argues that their humble willingness to try will outweigh their inadequacy. As the play begins, the audience begins to comment. Overwrought and overacted, and endlessly interrupted by the actors&#8217; apologies to the audience, the play is unintentionally hilarious, to the delight of Theseus&#8217;s court. The comments grow crueler and crueler, but the actors are undeterred. Once the actors finish the dance that ends the play, it is midnight, and Theseus orders all to go to bed. Once the humans have left, the fairies enter, blessing the house and promising a quiet night to all its occupants. Left alone, Puck begs the audience&#8217;s forgiveness for any offense.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Theseus, Hippolyta, and Philostrate, Lords, and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tis strange, my Theseus, that these lovers speak of.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">More strange than true. I never may believe</line>
<line form="verse">These antic fables, nor these fairy toys.</line>
<line form="verse">Lovers and madmen have such seething brains,</line>
<line form="verse">Such shaping fantasies, that apprehend</line>
<line form="verse">More than cool reason ever comprehends.</line>
<line form="verse">The lunatic, the lover, and the poet</line>
<line form="verse">Are of imagination all compact.</line>
<line form="verse">One sees more devils than vast hell can hold;</line>
<line form="verse">That is the madman. The lover, all as frantic,</line>
<line form="verse">Sees Helen&#8217;s beauty in a brow of Egypt.</line>
<line form="verse">The poet&#8217;s eye, in a fine frenzy rolling,</line>
<line form="verse">Doth glance from heaven to earth, from earth to heaven;</line>
<line form="verse">And as imagination bodies forth</line>
<line form="verse">The forms of things unknown, the poet&#8217;s pen</line>
<line form="verse">Turns them to shapes, and gives to aery nothing</line>
<line form="verse">A local habitation and a name.</line>
<line form="verse">Such tricks hath strong imagination,</line>
<line form="verse">That if it would but apprehend some joy,</line>
<line form="verse">It comprehends some bringer of that joy;</line>
<line form="verse">Or in the night, imagining some fear,</line>
<line form="verse">How easy is a bush suppos&#8217;d a bear!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">But all the story of the night told over,</line>
<line form="verse">And all their minds transfigur&#8217;d so together,</line>
<line form="verse">More witnesseth than fancy&#8217;s images,</line>
<line form="verse">And grows to something of great constancy;</line>
<line form="verse">But howsoever, strange and admirable.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter lovers, Lysander, Demetrius, Hermia, and Helena.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Here come the lovers, full of joy and mirth.</line>
<line form="verse">Joy, gentle friends, joy and fresh days of love</line>
<line form="verse">Accompany your hearts!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="5">More than to us</line>
<line form="verse">Wait in your royal walks, your board, your bed!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Come now; what masques, what dances shall we have,</line>
<line form="verse">To wear away this long age of three hours</line>
<line form="verse">Between our after-supper and bed-time?</line>
<line form="verse">Where is our usual manager of mirth?</line>
<line form="verse">What revels are in hand? Is there no play</line>
<line form="verse">To ease the anguish of a torturing hour?</line>
<line form="verse">Call Philostrate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">Here, mighty Theseus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Say, what abridgment have you for this evening?</line>
<line form="verse">What masque? What music? How shall we beguile</line>
<line form="verse">The lazy time, if not with some delight?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">There is a brief how many sports are ripe.</line>
<line form="verse">Make choice of which your Highness will see first.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Giving a paper.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;The battle with the Centaurs, to be sung</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>By an Athenian eunuch to the harp.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">We&#8217;ll none of that: that have I told my love,</line>
<line form="verse">In glory of my kinsman Hercules.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;The riot of the tipsy Bacchanals,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Tearing the Thracian singer in their rage.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">That is an old device; and it was play&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">When I from Thebes came last a conqueror.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;The thrice three Muses mourning for the death</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Of Learning, late deceas&#8217;d in beggary.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">That is some satire, keen and critical,</line>
<line form="verse">Not sorting with a nuptial ceremony.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>&#8220;A tedious brief scene of young Pyramus</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>And his love Thisby; very tragical mirth.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line form="verse">Merry and tragical? Tedious and brief?</line>
<line form="verse">That is hot ice and wondrous strange snow.</line>
<line form="verse">How shall we find the concord of this discord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">A play there is, my lord, some ten words long,</line>
<line form="verse">Which is as brief as I have known a play;</line>
<line form="verse">But by ten words, my lord, it is too long,</line>
<line form="verse">Which makes it tedious; for in all the play</line>
<line form="verse">There is not one word apt, one player fitted.</line>
<line form="verse">And tragical, my noble lord, it is;</line>
<line form="verse">For Pyramus therein doth kill himself;</line>
<line form="verse">Which when I saw rehears&#8217;d, I must confess,</line>
<line form="verse">Made mine eyes water; but more merry tears</line>
<line form="verse">The passion of loud laughter never shed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">What are they that do play it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Hard-handed men that work in Athens here,</line>
<line form="verse">Which never labor&#8217;d in their minds till now;</line>
<line form="verse">And now have toiled their unbreathed memories</line>
<line form="verse">With this same play, against your nuptial.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And we will hear it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">No, my noble lord,</line>
<line form="verse">It is not for you. I have heard it over,</line>
<line form="verse">And it is nothing, nothing in the world;</line>
<line form="verse">Unless you can find sport in their intents,</line>
<line form="verse">Extremely stretch&#8217;d, and conn&#8217;d with cruel pain,</line>
<line form="verse">To do you service.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse" offset="4">I will hear that play;</line>
<line form="verse">For never any thing can be amiss,</line>
<line form="verse">When simpleness and duty tender it.</line>
<line form="verse">Go bring them in; and take your places, ladies.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Philostrate.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I love not to see wretchedness o&#8217;ercharged,</line>
<line form="verse">And duty in his service perishing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Why, gentle sweet, you shall see no such thing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">He says they can do nothing in this kind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">The kinder we, to give them thanks for nothing.</line>
<line form="verse">Our sport shall be to take what they mistake;</line>
<line form="verse">And what poor duty cannot do, noble respect</line>
<line form="verse">Takes it in might, not merit.</line>
<line form="verse">Where I have come, great clerks have purposed</line>
<line form="verse">To greet me with premeditated welcomes;</line>
<line form="verse">Where I have seen them shiver and look pale,</line>
<line form="verse">Make periods in the midst of sentences,</line>
<line form="verse">Throttle their practic&#8217;d accent in their fears,</line>
<line form="verse">And in conclusion dumbly have broke off,</line>
<line form="verse">Not paying me a welcome. Trust me, sweet,</line>
<line form="verse">Out of this silence yet I pick&#8217;d a welcome;</line>
<line form="verse">And in the modesty of fearful duty</line>
<line form="verse">I read as much as from the rattling tongue</line>
<line form="verse">Of saucy and audacious eloquence.</line>
<line form="verse">Love, therefore, and tongue-tied simplicity</line>
<line form="verse">In least speak most, to my capacity.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Philostrate.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PHIL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">So please your Grace, the Prologue is address&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Let him approach.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Flourish trumpet.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Quince for the Prologue.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="QUIN.">PRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">If we offend, it is with our good will.</line>
<line form="verse">That you should think, we come not to offend,</line>
<line form="verse">But with good will. To show our simple skill,</line>
<line form="verse">That is the true beginning of our end.</line>
<line form="verse">Consider then, we come but in despite.</line>
<line form="verse">We do not come, as minding to content you,</line>
<line form="verse">Our true intent is. All for your delight</line>
<line form="verse">We are not here. That you should here repent you,</line>
<line form="verse">The actors are at hand; and, by their show,</line>
<line form="verse">You shall know all, that you are like to know.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This fellow doth not stand upon points.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He hath rid his prologue like a rough colt; he knows not the stop. A good moral, my lord: it is not enough to speak, but to speak true.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Indeed he hath play&#8217;d on this prologue like a child on a recorder&#8212;a sound, but not in government.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">His speech was like a tangled chain; nothing impair&#8217;d, but all disorder&#8217;d. Who is next?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter with a Trumpet before them Pyramus and Thisby and Wall and Moonshine and Lion.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="QUIN.">PRO.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Gentles, perchance you wonder at this show;</line>
<line form="verse">But wonder on till truth make all things plain.</line>
<line form="verse">This man is Pyramus, if you would know;</line>
<line form="verse">This beauteous lady Thisby is certain.</line>
<line form="verse">This man, with lime and rough-cast, doth present</line>
<line form="verse">Wall, that vile Wall, which did these lovers sunder;</line>
<line form="verse">And through Wall&#8217;s chink, poor souls, they are content</line>
<line form="verse">To whisper. At the which let no man wonder.</line>
<line form="verse">This man, with lantern, dog, and bush of thorn,</line>
<line form="verse">Presenteth Moonshine; for if you will know,</line>
<line form="verse">By moonshine did these lovers think no scorn</line>
<line form="verse">To meet at Ninus&#8217; tomb, there, there to woo.</line>
<line form="verse">This grisly beast, which Lion hight by name,</line>
<line form="verse">The trusty Thisby, coming first by night,</line>
<line form="verse">Did scare away, or rather did affright;</line>
<line form="verse">And as she fled, her mantle she did fall,</line>
<line form="verse">Which Lion vile with bloody mouth did stain.</line>
<line form="verse">Anon comes Pyramus, sweet youth and tall,</line>
<line form="verse">And finds his trusty Thisby&#8217;s mantle slain;</line>
<line form="verse">Whereat, with blade, with bloody blameful blade,</line>
<line form="verse">He bravely broach&#8217;d his boiling bloody breast;</line>
<line form="verse">And Thisby, tarrying in mulberry shade,</line>
<line form="verse">His dagger drew, and died. For all the rest,</line>
<line form="verse">Let Lion, Moonshine, Wall, and lovers twain</line>
<line form="verse">At large discourse, while here they do remain.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Pyramus, Thisby, Lion, and Moonshine.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I wonder if the lion be to speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No wonder, my lord; one lion may, when many asses do.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="SNOUT.">WALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">In this same enterlude it doth befall</line>
<line form="verse">That I, one Snout by name, present a wall;</line>
<line form="verse">And such a wall, as I would have you think,</line>
<line form="verse">That had in it a crannied hole or chink,</line>
<line form="verse">Through which the lovers, Pyramus and Thisby,</line>
<line form="verse">Did whisper often, very secretly.</line>
<line form="verse">This loam, this rough-cast, and this stone doth show</line>
<line form="verse">That I am that same wall; the truth is so;</line>
<line form="verse">And this the cranny is, right and sinister,</line>
<line form="verse">Through which the fearful lovers are to whisper.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Would you desire lime and hair to speak better?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It is the wittiest partition that ever I heard discourse, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Pyramus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Pyramus draws near the wall. Silence!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O grim-look&#8217;d night! O night with hue so black!</line>
<line form="verse">O night, which ever art when day is not!</line>
<line form="verse">O night, O night! Alack, alack, alack,</line>
<line form="verse">I fear my Thisby&#8217;s promise is forgot!</line>
<line form="verse">And thou, O wall, O sweet, O lovely wall,</line>
<line form="verse">That stand&#8217;st between her father&#8217;s ground and mine!</line>
<line form="verse">Thou wall, O wall, O sweet and lovely wall,</line>
<line form="verse">Show me thy chink, to blink through with mine eyne!</line>

<stagedir type="action">Wall holds up his fingers.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">Thanks, courteous wall; Jove shield thee well for this!</line>
<line form="verse">But what see I? No Thisby do I see.</line>
<line form="verse">O wicked wall, through whom I see no bliss!</line>
<line form="verse">Curs&#8217;d be thy stones for thus deceiving me!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The wall methinks, being sensible, should curse again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No, in truth, sir, he should not. &#8220;Deceiving me&#8221; is Thisby&#8217;s cue. She is to enter now, and I am to spy her through the wall. You shall see it will fall pat as I told you. Yonder she comes.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Thisby.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O wall, full often hast thou heard my moans,</line>
<line form="verse">For parting my fair Pyramus and me!</line>
<line form="verse">My cherry lips have often kiss&#8217;d thy stones,</line>
<line form="verse">Thy stones with lime and hair knit up in thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I see a voice! Now will I to the chink,</line>
<line form="verse">To spy and I can hear my Thisby&#8217;s face.</line>
<line form="verse">Thisby!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">My love thou art, my love I think.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Think what thou wilt, I am thy lover&#8217;s grace;</line>
<line form="verse">And, like Limander, am I trusty still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">And I, like Helen, till the Fates me kill.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Not Shafalus to Procrus was so true.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">As Shafalus to Procrus, I to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, kiss me through the hole of this vild wall!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">I kiss the wall&#8217;s hole, not your lips at all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Wilt thou at Ninny&#8217;s tomb meet me straightway?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse">&#8217;Tide life, &#8217;tide death, I come without delay.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Pyramus and Thisby.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="SNOUT.">WALL.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Thus have I, Wall, my part discharged so;</line>
<line form="verse">And being done, thus Wall away doth go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Now is the moon used between the two neighbors.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No remedy, my lord, when walls are so willful to hear without warning.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This is the silliest stuff that ever I heard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The best in this kind are but shadows; and the worst are no worse, if imagination amend them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It must be your imagination then, and not theirs.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">If we imagine no worse of them than they of themselves, they may pass for excellent men. Here come two noble beasts in, a man and a lion.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lion and Moonshine.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="SNUG.">LION.</speaker>
<line form="verse">You, ladies, you, whose gentle hearts do fear</line>
<line form="verse">The smallest monstrous mouse that creeps on floor,</line>
<line form="verse">May now, perchance, both quake and tremble here,</line>
<line form="verse">When lion rough in wildest rage doth roar.</line>
<line form="verse">Then know that I as Snug the joiner am</line>
<line form="verse">A lion fell, nor else no lion&#8217;s dam,</line>
<line form="verse">For, if I should, as lion, come in strife</line>
<line form="verse">Into this place, &#8217;twere pity on my life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A very gentle beast, and of a good conscience.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">The very best at a beast, my lord, that e&#8217;er I saw.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This lion is a very fox for his valor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">True; and a goose for his discretion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Not so, my lord; for his valor cannot carry his discretion, and the fox carries the goose.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">His discretion, I am sure, cannot carry his valor; for the goose carries not the fox. It is well; leave it to his discretion, and let us listen to the Moon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="STAR.">MOON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This lanthorn doth the horned moon present&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He should have worn the horns on his head.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He is no crescent, and his horns are invisible within the circumference.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="STAR.">MOON.</speaker>
<line form="verse">This lanthorn doth the horned moon present;</line>
<line form="verse">Myself the man i&#8217; th&#8217; moon do seem to be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This is the greatest error of all the rest. The man should be put into the lanthorn. How is it else the man i&#8217; th&#8217; moon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">He dares not come there for the candle; for, you see, it is already in snuff.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">I am a-weary of this moon. Would he would change!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">It appears, by his small light of discretion, that he is in the wane; but yet in courtesy, in all reason, we must stay the time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Proceed, Moon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="STAR.">MOON.</speaker>
<line form="prose">All that I have to say is to tell you that the lanthorn is the moon, I the man i&#8217; th&#8217; moon, this thorn-bush my thorn-bush, and this dog my dog.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Why, all these should be in the lanthorn; for all these are in the moon. But silence! Here comes Thisby.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Thisby.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This is old Ninny&#8217;s tomb. Where is my love?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="SNUG.">LION.</speaker>
<line form="prose">O!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The Lion roars. Thisby runs off.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well roar&#8217;d, Lion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well run, Thisby.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well shone, Moon. Truly, the moon shines with a good grace.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The Lion shakes Thisby&#8217;s mantle.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Well mous&#8217;d, Lion.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Pyramus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And then came Pyramus.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lion.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And so the lion vanish&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Sweet Moon, I thank thee for thy sunny beams;</line>
<line form="verse">I thank thee, Moon, for shining now so bright;</line>
<line form="verse">For by thy gracious, golden, glittering gleams,</line>
<line form="verse">I trust to take of truest Thisby sight.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>But stay! O spite!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>But mark, poor knight,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>What dreadful dole is here!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Eyes, do you see?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>How can it be?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>O dainty duck! O dear!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Thy mantle good,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>What, stain&#8217;d with blood?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Approach, ye Furies fell!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>O Fates, come, come,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Cut thread and thrum,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Quail, crush, conclude, and quell!</recite></line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">This passion, and the death of a dear friend, would go near to make a man look sad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Beshrew my heart, but I pity the man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="BOT.">PYR.</speaker>
<line form="verse">O, wherefore, Nature, didst thou lions frame?</line>
<line form="verse">Since lion vild hath here deflow&#8217;r&#8217;d my dear;</line>
<line form="verse">Which is&#8212;no, no&#8212;which was the fairest dame</line>
<line form="verse">That liv&#8217;d, that lov&#8217;d, that lik&#8217;d, that look&#8217;d with cheer.</line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Come, tears, confound,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Out, sword, and wound</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>The pap of Pyramus;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Ay, that left pap,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Where heart doth hop.</recite></line>

<stagedir type="fight">Stabs himself.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>Thus die I, thus, thus, thus.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Now am I dead,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Now am I fled;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>My soul is in the sky.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Tongue, lose thy light,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Moon, take thy flight,</recite></line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Moonshine.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>Now die, die, die, die, die.</recite></line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="PYR.">Dies.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No die, but an ace, for him; for he is but one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Less than an ace, man; for he is dead, he is nothing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">With the help of a surgeon he might yet recover, and yet prove an ass.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">How chance Moonshine is gone before Thisby comes back and finds her lover?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Thisby.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">She will find him by starlight. Here she comes, and her passion ends the play.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HIP.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Methinks she should not use a long one for such a Pyramus. I hope she will be brief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">A mote will turn the balance, which Pyramus, which Thisby, is the better: he for a man. God warr&#8217;nt us; she for a woman. God bless us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LYS.</speaker>
<line form="prose">She hath spied him already with those sweet eyes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="prose">And thus she means, videlicet&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker alias="FLU.">THIS.</speaker>
<line form="verse"><recite>Asleep, my love?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>What, dead, my dove?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>O Pyramus, arise!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Speak, speak! Quite dumb?</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Dead, dead? A tomb</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Must cover thy sweet eyes.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>These lily lips,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>This cherry nose,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>These yellow cowslip cheeks,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Are gone, are gone!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Lovers, make moan;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>His eyes were green as leeks.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>O Sisters Three,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Come, come to me,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>With hands as pale as milk;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Lay them in gore,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Since you have shore</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>With shears his thread of silk.</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Tongue, not a word!</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Come, trusty sword,</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Come, blade, my breast imbrue!</recite></line>

<stagedir type="fight">Stabs herself.</stagedir>
<line form="verse"><recite>And farewell, friends;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite>Thus Thisby ends;</recite></line>
<line form="verse"><recite><french xml:lang="fr">Adieu</french>, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>, <french xml:lang="fr">adieu</french>.</recite></line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="death" actor="THIS.">Dies.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">Moonshine and Lion are left to bury the dead.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>DEM.</speaker>
<line form="verse">Ay, and Wall too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOT.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Starting up.</stagedir>
<line form="prose">No, I assure you, the wall is down that parted their fathers. Will it please you to see the epilogue, or to hear a Bergomask dance between two of our company?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>THE.</speaker>
<line form="prose">No epilogue, I pray you; for your play needs no excuse. Never excuse; for when the players are all dead, there need none to be blam&#8217;d. Marry, if he that writ it had play&#8217;d Pyramus, and hang&#8217;d himself in Thisby&#8217;s garter, it would have been a fine tragedy; and so it is, truly, and very notably discharg&#8217;d. But come, your Bergomask; let your epilogue alone.</line>

<stagedir type="song">A dance.</stagedir>
<line form="verse">The iron tongue of midnight hath told twelve.</line>
<line form="verse">Lovers, to bed, &#8217;tis almost fairy time.</line>
<line form="verse">I fear we shall outsleep the coming morn</line>
<line form="verse">As much as we this night have overwatch&#8217;d.</line>
<line form="verse">This palpable-gross play hath well beguil&#8217;d</line>
<line form="verse">The heavy gait of night. Sweet friends, to bed.</line>
<line form="verse">A fortnight hold we this solemnity,</line>
<line form="verse">In nightly revels and new jollity.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Puck.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Now the hungry lion roars,</line>
<line type="lyric">And the wolf behowls the moon;</line>
<line type="lyric">Whilst the heavy ploughman snores,</line>
<line type="lyric">All with weary task foredone.</line>
<line type="lyric">Now the wasted brands do glow,</line>
<line type="lyric">Whilst the screech owl, screeching loud,</line>
<line type="lyric">Puts the wretch that lies in woe</line>
<line type="lyric">In remembrance of a shroud.</line>
<line type="lyric">Now it is the time of night</line>
<line type="lyric">That the graves, all gaping wide,</line>
<line type="lyric">Every one lets forth his sprite,</line>
<line type="lyric">In the church-way paths to glide.</line>
<line type="lyric">And we fairies, that do run</line>
<line type="lyric">By the triple Hecat&#8217;s team</line>
<line type="lyric">From the presence of the sun,</line>
<line type="lyric">Following darkness like a dream,</line>
<line type="lyric">Now are frolic. Not a mouse</line>
<line type="lyric">Shall disturb this hallowed house.</line>
<line type="lyric">I am sent with broom before,</line>
<line type="lyric">To sweep the dust behind the door.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter King and Queen of Fairies, Oberon and Titania, with all their Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Through the house give glimmering light</line>
<line type="lyric">By the dead and drowsy fire,</line>
<line type="lyric">Every elf and fairy sprite</line>
<line type="lyric">Hop as light as bird from brier,</line>
<line type="lyric">And this ditty, after me,</line>
<line type="lyric">Sing, and dance it trippingly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TITA.</speaker>
<line form="verse">First, rehearse your song by rote,</line>
<line form="verse">To each word a warbling note.</line>
<line form="verse">Hand in hand, with fairy grace,</line>
<line form="verse">Will we sing, and bless this place.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Song and dance.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OBE.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">Now, until the break of day,</line>
<line type="lyric">Through this house each fairy stray.</line>
<line type="lyric">To the best bride-bed will we,</line>
<line type="lyric">Which by us shall blessed be;</line>
<line type="lyric">And the issue, there create,</line>
<line type="lyric">Ever shall be fortunate.</line>
<line type="lyric">So shall all the couples three</line>
<line type="lyric">Ever true in loving be;</line>
<line type="lyric">And the blots of Nature&#8217;s hand</line>
<line type="lyric">Shall not in their issue stand;</line>
<line type="lyric">Never mole, hare-lip, nor scar,</line>
<line type="lyric">Nor mark prodigious, such as are</line>
<line type="lyric">Despised in nativity,</line>
<line type="lyric">Shall upon their children be.</line>
<line type="lyric">With this field-dew consecrate,</line>
<line type="lyric">Every fairy take his gait,</line>
<line type="lyric">And each several chamber bless,</line>
<line type="lyric">Through this palace, with sweet peace,</line>
<line type="lyric">And the owner of it blest</line>
<line type="lyric">Ever shall in safety rest.</line>
<line type="lyric">Trip away; make no stay;</line>
<line type="lyric">Meet me all by break of day.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Oberon, Titania, and Train.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PUCK.</speaker>
<line type="lyric">If we shadows have offended,</line>
<line type="lyric">Think but this, and all is mended,</line>
<line type="lyric">That you have but slumb&#8217;red here</line>
<line type="lyric">While these visions did appear.</line>
<line type="lyric">And this weak and idle theme,</line>
<line type="lyric">No more yielding but a dream,</line>
<line type="lyric">Gentles, do not reprehend.</line>
<line type="lyric">If you pardon, we will mend.</line>
<line type="lyric">And, as I am an honest Puck,</line>
<line type="lyric">If we have unearned luck</line>
<line type="lyric">Now to scape the serpent&#8217;s tongue,</line>
<line type="lyric">We will make amends ere long;</line>
<line type="lyric">Else the Puck a liar call.</line>
<line type="lyric">So, good night unto you all.</line>
<line type="lyric">Give me your hands, if we be friends,</line>
<line type="lyric">And Robin shall restore amends.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>





