<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="plays.xsl"?>

<POEM>
<TITLE>The Passionate Pilgrim</TITLE>
<TITLESHORT>The Passionate Pilgrim</TITLESHORT>
<PLAYWRIGHT>William Shakespeare</PLAYWRIGHT>

<POEMBODY>
<STANZA>

<STANZANUM>I</STANZANUM>
<LINE>When my love swears that she is made of truth,</LINE>
<LINE>I do believe her (though I know she lies)</LINE>
<LINE>That she might think me some untutor&#8217;d youth,</LINE>
<LINE>Unskillful in the world&#8217;s false forgeries.</LINE>
<LINE>Thus vainly thinking that she thinks me young,</LINE>
<LINE>Although I know my years be past the best,</LINE>
<LINE>I smiling credit her false-speaking tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>Outfacing faults in love with love&#8217;s ill rest.</LINE>
<LINE>But wherefore says my love that she is young?</LINE>
<LINE>And wherefore say not I that I am old?</LINE>
<LINE>O, love&#8217;s best habit&#8217;s in a soothing tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>And age in love, loves not to have years told.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Therefore I&#8217;ll lie with love, and love with me,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Since that our faults in love thus smother&#8217;d be.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>II</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Two loves I have, of comfort and despair,</LINE>
<LINE>That like two spirits do suggest me still:</LINE>
<LINE>My better angel is a man (right fair),</LINE>
<LINE>My worser spirit a woman (color&#8217;d ill).</LINE>
<LINE>To win me soon to hell, my female evil</LINE>
<LINE>Tempteth my better angel from my side;</LINE>
<LINE>And would corrupt my saint to be a devil,</LINE>
<LINE>Wooing his purity with her fair pride.</LINE>
<LINE>And whether that my angel be turn&#8217;d fiend,</LINE>
<LINE>Suspect I may (yet not directly tell):</LINE>
<LINE>For being both to me, both to each friend,</LINE>
<LINE>I guess one angel in another&#8217;s hell:</LINE>
<COUPLET>The truth I shall not know, but live in doubt,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Till my bad angel fire my good one out.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>III</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Did not the heavenly rhetoric of thine eye,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;Gainst whom the world could not hold argument,</LINE>
<LINE>Persuade my heart to this false perjury?</LINE>
<LINE>Vows for thee broke deserve not punishment.</LINE>
<LINE>A woman I forswore; but I will prove,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou being a goddess, I forswore not thee:</LINE>
<LINE>My vow was earthly, thou a heavenly love;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy grace being gain&#8217;d cures all disgrace in me.</LINE>
<LINE>My vow was breath, and breath a vapor is,</LINE>
<LINE>Then thou, fair sun, that on this earth doth shine,</LINE>
<LINE>Exhal&#8217;st this vapor vow, in thee it is:</LINE>
<LINE>If broken, then it is no fault of mine.</LINE>
<COUPLET>If by me broke, what fool is not so wise</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>To break an oath, to win a paradise?</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>IV</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Sweet Cytherea, sitting by a brook</LINE>
<LINE>With young Adonis, lovely, fresh, and green,</LINE>
<LINE>Did court the lad with many a lovely look,</LINE>
<LINE>Such looks as none could look but beauty&#8217;s queen.</LINE>
<LINE>She told him stories to delight his ear;</LINE>
<LINE>She show&#8217;d him favors to allure his eye;</LINE>
<LINE>To win his heart she touch&#8217;d him here and there—</LINE>
<LINE>Touches so soft still conquer chastity.</LINE>
<LINE>But whether unripe years did want conceit,</LINE>
<LINE>Or he refus&#8217;d to take her figured proffer,</LINE>
<LINE>The tender nibbler would not touch the bait,</LINE>
<LINE>But smile and jest at every gentle offer.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Then fell she on her back, fair queen, and toward:</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>He rose and ran away, ah, fool too froward!</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>V</STANZANUM>
<LINE>If love make me forsworn, how shall I swear to love?</LINE>
<LINE>O, never faith could hold, if not to beauty vowed:</LINE>
<LINE>Though to myself forsworn, to thee I&#8217;ll constant prove;</LINE>
<LINE>Those thoughts to me like oaks, to thee like osiers bowed.</LINE>
<LINE>Study his bias leaves, and makes his book thine eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Where all those pleasures live that art can comprehend.</LINE>
<LINE>If knowledge be the mark, to know thee shall suffice:</LINE>
<LINE>Well learned is that tongue that well can thee commend,</LINE>
<LINE>All ignorant that soul that sees thee without wonder,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is to me some praise, that I thy parts admire.</LINE>
<LINE>Thine eye Jove&#8217;s lightning seems, thy voice his dreadful thunder,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, not to anger bent, is music and sweet fire.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Celestial as thou art, O, do not love that wrong:</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>To sing heaven&#8217;s praise with such an earthly tongue.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>VI</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Scarce had the sun dried up the dewy morn,</LINE>
<LINE>And scarce the herd gone to the hedge for shade,</LINE>
<LINE>When Cytherea (all in love forlorn)</LINE>
<LINE>A longing tarriance for Adonis made</LINE>
<LINE>Under an osier growing by a brook,</LINE>
<LINE>A brook where Adon us&#8217;d to cool his spleen.</LINE>
<LINE>Hot was the day, she hotter that did look</LINE>
<LINE>For his approach, that often there had been.</LINE>
<LINE>Anon he comes, and throws his mantle by,</LINE>
<LINE>And stood stark naked on the brook&#8217;s green brim.</LINE>
<LINE>The sun look&#8217;d on the world with glorious eye,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet not so wistly as this queen on him.</LINE>
<COUPLET>He spying her, bounc&#8217;d in, whereas he stood;</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>&#8220;O Jove,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;why was not I a flood?&#8221;</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>VII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Fair is my love, but not so fair as fickle,</LINE>
<LINE>Mild as a dove, but neither true nor trusty,</LINE>
<LINE>Brighter than glass, and yet as glass is brittle,</LINE>
<LINE>Softer than wax, and yet as iron rusty:</LINE>
<COUPLET>A lily pale, with damask dye to grace her,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>None fairer, nor none falser to deface her.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Her lips to mine how often hath she joined,</LINE>
<LINE>Between each kiss her oaths of true love swearing!</LINE>
<LINE>How many tales to please me hath she coined,</LINE>
<LINE>Dreading my love, the loss whereof still fearing!</LINE>
<COUPLET>Yet in the mids of all her pure protestings,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Her faith, her oaths, her tears, and all were jestings.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>She burnt with love, as straw with fire flameth,</LINE>
<LINE>She burnt out love, as soon as straw out-burneth;</LINE>
<LINE>She fram&#8217;d the love, and yet she foil&#8217;d the framing,</LINE>
<LINE>She bade love last, and yet she fell a-turning.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Was this a lover, or a lecher whether?</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Bad in the best, though excellent in neither.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>VIII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>If music and sweet poetry agree,</LINE>
<LINE>As they must needs (the sister and the brother),</LINE>
<LINE>Then must the love be great &#8217;twixt thee and me,</LINE>
<LINE>Because thou lov&#8217;st the one, and I the other.</LINE>
<LINE>Dowland to thee is dear, whose heavenly touch</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the lute doth ravish human sense;</LINE>
<LINE>Spenser to me, whose deep conceit is such</LINE>
<LINE>As passing all conceit, needs no defense.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou lov&#8217;st to hear the sweet melodious sound</LINE>
<LINE>That Phoebus&#8217; lute, the queen of music, makes;</LINE>
<LINE>And I in deep delight am chiefly drown&#8217;d</LINE>
<LINE>When as himself to singing he betakes.</LINE>
<COUPLET>One god is god of both (as poets feign),</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>One knight loves both, and both in thee remain.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>IX</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Fair was the morn when the fair queen of love,</LINE>
<LINE>[. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ]</LINE>
<LINE>Paler for sorrow than her milk-white dove,</LINE>
<LINE>For Adon&#8217;s sake, a youngster proud and wild,</LINE>
<LINE>Her stand she takes upon a steep-up hill.</LINE>
<LINE>Anon Adonis comes with horn and hounds;</LINE>
<LINE>She, silly queen, with more than love&#8217;s good will,</LINE>
<LINE>Forbade the boy he should not pass those grounds.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Once,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;did I see a fair sweet youth</LINE>
<LINE>Here in these brakes deep-wounded with a boar,</LINE>
<LINE>Deep in the thigh, a spectacle of ruth!</LINE>
<LINE>See, in my thigh,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;here was the sore.&#8221;</LINE>
<COUPLET>She showed hers, he saw more wounds than one,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>And blushing fled, and left her all alone.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>X</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Sweet rose, fair flower, untimely pluck&#8217;d, soon vaded,</LINE>
<LINE>Pluck&#8217;d in the bud, and vaded in the spring!</LINE>
<LINE>Bright orient pearl, alack, too timely shaded!</LINE>
<LINE>Fair creature, kill&#8217;d too soon by death&#8217;s sharp sting!</LINE>
<COUPLET>Like a green plum that hangs upon a tree,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>And falls (through wind) before the fall should be.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>I weep for thee, and yet no cause I have,</LINE>
<LINE>For why: thou lefts me nothing in thy will;</LINE>
<LINE>And yet thou lefts me more than I did crave,</LINE>
<LINE>For why: I craved nothing of thee still.</LINE>
<COUPLET>O yes, dear friend, I pardon crave of thee,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Thy discontent thou didst bequeath to me.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XI</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Venus, with Adonis sitting by her,</LINE>
<LINE>Under a myrtle shade began to woo him.</LINE>
<LINE>She told the youngling how god Mars did try her,</LINE>
<LINE>And as he fell to her, she fell to him.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Even thus,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;the warlike god embrac&#8217;d me,&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>And then she clipt Adonis in her arms;</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Even thus,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;the warlike god unlac&#8217;d me,&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>As if the boy should use like loving charms;</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Even thus,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;he seized on my lips,&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>And with her lips on his did act the seizure:</LINE>
<LINE>And as she fetched breath, away he skips,</LINE>
<LINE>And would not take her meaning nor her pleasure.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Ah, that I had my lady at this bay:</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>To kiss and clip me till I run away!</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Crabbed age and youth cannot live together:</LINE>
<LINE>Youth is full of pleasance, age is full of care,</LINE>
<LINE>Youth like summer morn, age like winter weather,</LINE>
<LINE>Youth like summer brave, age like winter bare.</LINE>
<LINE>Youth is full of sport, age&#8217;s breath is short,</LINE>
<COUPLET>Youth is nimble, age is lame,</COUPLET>
<LINE>Youth is hot and bold, age is weak and cold,</LINE>
<COUPLET>Youth is wild, and age is tame.</COUPLET>
<LINE>Age, I do abhor thee, youth, I do adore thee:</LINE>
<COUPLET>O, my love, my love is young!</COUPLET>
<LINE>Age, I do defy thee. O sweet shepherd, hie thee,</LINE>
<COUPLET>For methinks thou stays too long.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XIII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Beauty is but a vain and doubtful good,</LINE>
<LINE>A shining gloss that vadeth suddenly,</LINE>
<LINE>A flower that dies when first it gins to bud,</LINE>
<LINE>A brittle glass that&#8217;s broken presently:</LINE>
<COUPLET>A doubtful good, a gloss, a glass, a flower,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Lost, vaded, broken, dead within an hour.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>And as goods lost are seld or never found,</LINE>
<LINE>As vaded gloss no rubbing will refresh,</LINE>
<LINE>As flowers dead lie withered on the ground,</LINE>
<LINE>As broken glass no cement can redress:</LINE>
<COUPLET>So beauty blemish&#8217;d once, forever lost,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>In spite of physic, painting, pain, and cost.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XIV</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Good night, good rest, ah, neither be my share!</LINE>
<LINE>She bade good night that kept my rest away,</LINE>
<LINE>And daff&#8217;d me to a cabin hang&#8217;d with care,</LINE>
<LINE>To descant on the doubts of my decay.</LINE>
<COUPLET>&#8220;Farewell,&#8221; quoth she, &#8220;and come again tomorrow.&#8221;</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Fare well I could not, for I supp&#8217;d with sorrow.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Yet at my parting sweetly did she smile,</LINE>
<LINE>In scorn or friendship, nill I conster whether.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;T may be she joy&#8217;d to jest at my exile,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8217;T may be again, to make me wander thither:</LINE>
<COUPLET>&#8220;Wander,&#8221; a word for shadows like myself,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>As take the pain but cannot pluck the pelf.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Lord, how mine eyes throw gazes to the east!</LINE>
<LINE>My heart doth charge the watch; the morning rise</LINE>
<LINE>Doth cite each moving sense from idle rest,</LINE>
<LINE>Not daring trust the office of mine eyes.</LINE>
<COUPLET>While Philomela sits and sings, I sit and mark,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>And wish her lays were tuned like the lark.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>For she doth welcome daylight with her ditty,</LINE>
<LINE>And drives away dark dreaming night.</LINE>
<LINE>The night so pack&#8217;d, I post unto my pretty;</LINE>
<LINE>Heart hath his hope, and eyes their wished sight:</LINE>
<COUPLET>Sorrow chang&#8217;d to solace, and solace mix&#8217;d with sorrow;</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>For why, she sight, and bade me come tomorrow.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Were I with her, the night would post too soon,</LINE>
<LINE>But now are minutes added to the hours;</LINE>
<LINE>To spite me now, each minute seems a moon,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet not for me, shine sun to succor flowers!</LINE>
<COUPLET>Pack night, peep day; good day, of night now borrow:</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Short night tonight, and length thyself tomorrow.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<SUBTITLE>Sonnets to Sundry Notes of Music</SUBTITLE>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XV</STANZANUM>
<LINE>It was a lording&#8217;s daughter, the fairest one of three,</LINE>
<LINE>That liked of her master, as well as well might be,</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Till looking on an Englishman, the fairest that eye could see,</LINE>
<COUPLET>Her fancy fell a-turning.</COUPLET>
<LINE>Long was the combat doubtful, that love with love did fight,</LINE>
<LINE>To leave the master loveless, or kill the gallant knight:</LINE>
<LINE>To put in practice either, alas, it was a spite</LINE>
<COUPLET>Unto the silly damsel!</COUPLET>
<LINE>But one must be refused; more mickle was the pain,</LINE>
<LINE>That nothing could be used, to turn them both to gain,</LINE>
<LINE>For of the two the trusty knight was wounded with disdain:</LINE>
<COUPLET>Alas, she could not help it!</COUPLET>
<LINE>Thus art with arms contending was victor of the day,</LINE>
<LINE>Which by a gift of learning did bear the maid away:</LINE>
<LINE>Then lullaby, the learned man hath got the lady gay,</LINE>
<COUPLET>For now my song is ended.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XVI</STANZANUM>
<LINE>On a day (alack the day!)</LINE>
<LINE>Love, whose month was ever May,</LINE>
<LINE>Spied a blossom passing fair,</LINE>
<LINE>Playing in the wanton air.</LINE>
<LINE>Through the velvet leaves the wind</LINE>
<LINE>All unseen gan passage find,</LINE>
<LINE>That the lover, sick to death,</LINE>
<LINE>Wish&#8217;d himself the heavens&#8217; breath.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Air,&#8221; quoth he, &#8220;thy cheeks may blow,</LINE>
<LINE>Air, would I might triumph so!</LINE>
<LINE>But (alas) my hand hath sworn</LINE>
<LINE>Ne&#8217;er to pluck thee from thy thorn,</LINE>
<LINE>Vow (alack) for youth unmeet,</LINE>
<LINE>Youth, so apt to pluck a sweet.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou for whom Jove would swear</LINE>
<LINE>Juno but an Ethiope were,</LINE>
<LINE>And deny himself for Jove,</LINE>
<LINE>Turning mortal for thy love.&#8221;</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XVII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>My flocks feed not, my ewes breed not,</LINE>
<LINE>My rams speed not, all is amiss;</LINE>
<LINE>Love is dying, faith&#8217;s defying,</LINE>
<LINE>Heart&#8217;s denying, causer of this.</LINE>
<LINE>All my merry jigs are quite forgot,</LINE>
<LINE>All my lady&#8217;s love is lost, God wot.</LINE>
<LINE>Where her faith was firmly fix&#8217;d in love,</LINE>
<LINE>There a nay is plac&#8217;d without remove.</LINE>
<COUPLET>One silly cross wrought all my loss,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>O frowning Fortune, cursed, fickle dame!</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>For now I see inconstancy</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>More in women than in men remain.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>In black mourn I, all fears scorn I,</LINE>
<LINE>Love hath forlorn me, living in thrall;</LINE>
<LINE>Heart is bleeding, all help needing,</LINE>
<LINE>O cruel speeding, fraughted with gall.</LINE>
<LINE>My shepherd&#8217;s pipe can sound no deal,</LINE>
<LINE>My wether&#8217;s bell rings doleful knell,</LINE>
<LINE>My curtal dog, that wont to have play&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>Plays not at all, but seems afraid;</LINE>
<COUPLET>With sighs so deep procures to weep,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>In howling wise, to see my doleful plight.</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>How sighs resound through heartless ground,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Like a thousand vanquish&#8217;d men in bloody fight!</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Clear wells spring not, sweet birds sing not,</LINE>
<LINE>Green plants bring not forth their dye;</LINE>
<LINE>Herds stands weeping, flocks all sleeping,</LINE>
<LINE>Nymphs back peeping fearfully.</LINE>
<LINE>All our pleasure known to us poor swains,</LINE>
<LINE>All our merry meetings on the plains,</LINE>
<LINE>All our evening sport from us is fled,</LINE>
<LINE>All our love is lost, for Love is dead.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Farewell, sweet lass, thy like ne&#8217;er was</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>For a sweet content, the cause of all my moan.</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Poor Corydon must live alone,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Other help for him I see that there is none.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XVIII</STANZANUM>
<LINE>When as thine eye hath chose the dame,</LINE>
<LINE>And stall&#8217;d the deer that thou shouldst strike,</LINE>
<LINE>Let reason rule things worthy blame,</LINE>
<LINE>As well as fancy, partial might.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Take counsel of some wiser head,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>Neither too young nor yet unwed.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>And when thou com&#8217;st thy tale to tell,</LINE>
<LINE>Smooth not thy tongue with filed talk,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest she some subtile practice smell—</LINE>
<LINE>A cripple soon can find a halt—</LINE>
<COUPLET>But plainly say thou lov&#8217;st her well,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>And set her person forth to sale.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>And to her will frame all thy ways,</LINE>
<LINE>Spare not to spend, and chiefly there</LINE>
<LINE>Where thy desert may merit praise,</LINE>
<LINE>By ringing in thy lady&#8217;s ear.</LINE>
<COUPLET>The strongest castle, tower, and town,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>The golden bullet beats it down.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Serve always with assured trust,</LINE>
<LINE>And in thy suit be humble true;</LINE>
<LINE>Unless thy lady prove unjust,</LINE>
<LINE>Press never thou to choose anew.</LINE>
<COUPLET>When time shall serve, be thou not slack</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>To proffer, though she put thee back.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>What though her frowning brows be bent,</LINE>
<LINE>Her cloudy looks will calm yer night,</LINE>
<LINE>And then too late she will repent,</LINE>
<LINE>That thus dissembled her delight;</LINE>
<COUPLET>And twice desire, yer it be day,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>That which with scorn she put away.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>What though she strive to try her strength,</LINE>
<LINE>And ban and brawl, and say thee nay,</LINE>
<LINE>Her feeble force will yield at length,</LINE>
<LINE>When craft hath taught her thus to say:</LINE>
<COUPLET>&#8220;Had women been so strong as men,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>In faith, you had not had it then.&#8221;</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>The wiles and guiles that women work,</LINE>
<LINE>Dissembled with an outward show,</LINE>
<LINE>The tricks and toys that in them lurk,</LINE>
<LINE>The cock that treads them shall not know.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Have you not heard it said full oft,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>A woman&#8217;s nay doth stand for nought?</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>Think women still to strive with men,</LINE>
<LINE>To sin and never for to saint:</LINE>
<LINE>There is no heaven, be holy then,</LINE>
<LINE>When time with age shall them attaint.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Were kisses all the joys in bed,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>One woman would another wed.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>But soft, enough—too much, I fear—</LINE>
<LINE>Lest that my mistress hear my song;</LINE>
<LINE>She will not stick to round me on th&#8217; ear,</LINE>
<LINE>To teach my tongue to be so long.</LINE>
<COUPLET>Yet will she blush, here be it said,</COUPLET>
<COUPLET>To hear her secrets so bewray&#8217;d.</COUPLET>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XIX</STANZANUM>
<LINE>Live with me and be my love,</LINE>
<LINE>And we will all the pleasures prove</LINE>
<LINE>That hills and valleys, dales and fields,</LINE>
<LINE>And all the craggy mountains yield.</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>There will we sit upon the rocks,</LINE>
<LINE>And see the shepherds feed their flocks,</LINE>
<LINE>By shallow rivers, by whose falls</LINE>
<LINE>Melodious birds sing madrigals.</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>There will I make thee a bed of roses,</LINE>
<LINE>With a thousand fragrant posies,</LINE>
<LINE>A cap of flowers, and a kirtle</LINE>
<LINE>Embroidered all with leaves of myrtle;</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>A belt of straw and ivy buds,</LINE>
<LINE>With coral clasps and amber studs:</LINE>
<LINE>And if these pleasures may thee move,</LINE>
<LINE>Then live with me, and be my love.</LINE>
</STANZA>

<SUBTITLE>Love&#8217;s Answer</SUBTITLE>

<STANZA>
<LINE>If that the world and love were young,</LINE>
<LINE>And truth in every shepherd&#8217;s tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>These pretty pleasures might me move,</LINE>
<LINE>To live with thee and be thy love.</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<STANZANUM>XX</STANZANUM>
<LINE>As it fell upon a day,</LINE>
<LINE>In the merry month of May,</LINE>
<LINE>Sitting in a pleasant shade,</LINE>
<LINE>Which a grove of myrtles made,</LINE>
<LINE>Beasts did leap and birds did sing,</LINE>
<LINE>Trees did grow and plants did spring;</LINE>
<LINE>Every thing did banish moan,</LINE>
<LINE>Save the nightingale alone.</LINE>
<LINE>She, poor bird, as all forlorn,</LINE>
<LINE>Lean&#8217;d her breast up-till a thorn,</LINE>
<LINE>And there sung the dolefull&#8217;st ditty,</LINE>
<LINE>That to hear it was great pity.</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Fie, fie, fie,&#8221; now would she cry,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Tereu, tereu,&#8221; by and by;</LINE>
<LINE>That to hear her so complain,</LINE>
<LINE>Scarce I could from tears refrain;</LINE>
<LINE>For her griefs, so lively shown,</LINE>
<LINE>Made me think upon mine own.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, thought I, thou mourn&#8217;st in vain,</LINE>
<LINE>None takes pity on thy pain.</LINE>
<LINE>Senseless trees, they cannot hear thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Ruthless bears, they will not cheer thee.</LINE>
<LINE>King Pandion, he is dead:</LINE>
<LINE>All thy friends are lapp&#8217;d in lead;</LINE>
<LINE>All thy fellow birds do sing,</LINE>
<LINE>Careless of thy sorrowing.</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst as fickle Fortune smil&#8217;d,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou and I were both beguil&#8217;d.</LINE>
<LINE>Every one that flatters thee</LINE>
<LINE>Is no friend in misery.</LINE>
<LINE>Words are easy, like the wind,</LINE>
<LINE>Faithful friends are hard to find:</LINE>
<LINE>Every man will be thy friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst thou hast wherewith to spend;</LINE>
<LINE>But if store of crowns be scant,</LINE>
<LINE>No man will supply thy want.</LINE>
<LINE>If that one be prodigal,</LINE>
<LINE>Bountiful they will him call;</LINE>
</STANZA>

<STANZA>
<LINE>And with such-like flattering,</LINE>
<LINE>&#8220;Pity but he were a king!&#8221;</LINE>
<LINE>If he be addict to vice,</LINE>
<LINE>Quickly him they will entice;</LINE>
<LINE>If to women he be bent,</LINE>
<LINE>They have at commandement.</LINE>
<LINE>But if Fortune once do frown,</LINE>
<LINE>Then farewell his great renown;</LINE>
<LINE>They that fawn&#8217;d on him before</LINE>
<LINE>Use his company no more.</LINE>
<LINE>He that is thy friend indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>He will help thee in thy need:</LINE>
<LINE>If thou sorrow, he will weep;</LINE>
<LINE>If thou wake, he cannot sleep;</LINE>
<LINE>Thus of every grief in heart</LINE>
<LINE>He with thee doth bear a part.</LINE>
<LINE>These are certain signs to know</LINE>
<LINE>Faithful friend from flatt&#8217;ring foe.</LINE>
</STANZA>


</POEMBODY>


<AUTHORDETAILS>
<AUTHOR>PlayShakespeare.com</AUTHOR>
<AUTHORURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com</AUTHORURL>
<COPYRIGHT>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</COPYRIGHT>
<VERSION>3.1</VERSION>
<LICENSE>GFDL License 1.3</LICENSE>
<LICENSEURL>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</LICENSEURL>
<TERMSURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com/about-us</TERMSURL>
</AUTHORDETAILS>

</POEM>
