<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play>
<title short="Timon of Athens">The Life of Timon of Athens</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare</playwright>

<personae playtitle="Timon of Athens">
<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TIM.">Timon of Athens</persname>
<persdescription>Timon of Athens is a rich man of Athens with absolutely no sense of scale, either in prosperity or in misery. He believes that one can buy friendship, and showers rich gifts on anybody who attends his feasts &#8212; and anybody can simply walk in off the street to join them. His chief fault is his generosity and his belief in the goodness of man; he refuses to look at his accounts because he trusts that his steward, Flavius, is honest. He refuses to see debts to him repaid, and is convinced that anyone he has been kind to will naturally return the favor. An open and honest man, he has no understanding of hypocrisy and therefore no defense against flattery, which he takes at face value because he himself means everything he says. The discovery that he has managed to spend his entire fortune startles him, but it is not until nobody will help that he becomes disturbed. Harassed by creditors, he gives way to anger soon becoming as extravagant in his hatred for those who have disappointed him as he was in his gifts to them. He thereafter refuses to see any good in humanity and spends most of his time cursing it. He goes to live in a cave, and when he accidentally digs up a hidden pile of gold, he gives it to soldiers planning to sack Athens, to prostitutes and thieves, enjoining them to continue in their acts and grow worse at them until the entire world is destroyed. Finally dying, and as happy to do so as he is capable of being happy, he writes his own epitaph, a final insult to the whole of humanity &#8212; a curious conflation of the two parts of his personality, both requesting anonymity and making sure passers-by know his name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ALCIB.">Alcibiades</persname>
<persdescription>Alcibiades is a young Athenian captain, a great soldier who has won many victories for Athens. He best loves war, but he is a true friend of Timon&#8217;s and a generous man. He attempts to save the life of one of his soldiers who in a temper killed another man, but is unsuccessful before the Senate of old, unyielding men. He is angered that they will not take his past services into account when he pleads with them, and rashly suggests that they are growing forgetful, leaving him exiled. He then rejoins his army, intent on conquering Athens in revenge. He is extremely proud and looks down on the senators as a pack of usurers. Horrified at how hard Timon has fallen, he attempts to help him, but is rebuffed. He uses Timon&#8217;s name as an excuse in his propaganda, and hopes to bring him onto his side just as the senators hope to, but his messenger arrives too late. He is threatening enough that the senators crumble and simply hand Athens over to him without fighting, and then magnanimous, as they were not. Alcibiades has a very simple view of the world, and within that view is an upright and decent man, is somewhat reckless.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="APEM.">Apemantus</persname>
<persdescription>Apemantus is a professional cynic, a snarling, nasty man who insults everybody he meets without appearing to derive any pleasure from doing so. He sees through flattery and refuses gifts from Timon, eating only poorly at his table. Though he pretends to like nobody, Apemantus strives to make Timon realize just how foolishly he is acting, but does not give his advice in the most diplomatic manner. When Timon loses all his wealth and becomes a misanthrope in the forest, it becomes evident that Apemantus is something of a poseur, who does not appreciate the fact that someone is stealing his role. Even though he claims to love no-one but himself, Apemantus still tries to feed Timon in the forest, only to be rejected by a man who now hates humanity even more than he does himself. The discovery that it is possible to be even nastier than he is enrages Apemantus, who tells everybody that Timon has found some gold so that he will be beset by visitors.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAPH.">Caphis</persname>
<persdescription>Caphis is the servant of a Senator who also dabbles in usury and has lent Timon a great deal of money. He is sent to obtain repayment, but is put off for an entire month by Flavius, until Caphis finally presents his bill to Timon directly, in the public street. He does not much like the task of asking a man for money, but holds his ground and refuses to be delayed any further.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="CUP.">Cupid</persname>
<persdescription>Cupid is one of the Ladies who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast, and explains the idea to Timon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. BAN.">First Bandit</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL BAN.">All Bandits</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Bandit does not see why a ruined man should be left any money at all, but insists he is not a thief. He realizes that Timon&#8217;s advice to continue stealing is not given out of kindness, but thinks that there&#8217;s no point in giving up robbery while there&#8217;s a war on.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. BAN.">Second Bandit</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL BAN.">All Bandits</persname>
	<persname short="ALL OTHER BAN.">All Other Bandits</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Bandit has heard that Timon has some treasure on him and brings his fellows to find him, but insists that he is not a thief. Timon&#8217;s advice to continue thieving is so nasty that he decides to turn honest.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. BAN.">Third Bandit</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL BAN.">All Bandits</persname>
	<persname short="ALL OTHER BAN.">All Other Bandits</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Bandit has seen Timon before; like his fellows, he insists that he is not a thief. Timon&#8217;s advice to continue stealing is so nasty it almost convinces him to give up his job as a robber.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. LADY. MASK.">First Lady Amazon Masker</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LADY. MASK.">All Lady Amazon Maskers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>First Lady Amazon Masker is one of the Ladies who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast, and disclaims his praise.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ALL LADY. MASK.">Lady Amazon Maskers</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Amazon Maskers [mute roles] are a group of women who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. LORD.">First Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. LORD. AND 2. LORD.">Both First and Second Lords</persname>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Lord is an Athenian gentleman, one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who thinks nothing of simply walking off the street to eat at Timon&#8217;s table and receiving rich gifts from him with no more repayment than flattery. He refuses to help Timon out in his need, claiming to have no money on hand at the time, and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. A fatuous, greedy, and rather silly fellow, he fails to see the problem in refusing to help Timon while still wearing a jewel the latter gave him in his cap when visiting him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. LORD.">Second Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. LORD. AND 2. LORD.">Both First and Second Lords</persname>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Lord is an Athenian gentleman, one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who thinks nothing of simply walking off the street to eat at Timon&#8217;s table and receiving rich gifts from him with no more repayment than flattery. He refuses to help Timon out in his need, claiming to have no money on hand at the time, and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is fatuous and greedy, though unlike some of the other lords, he does show some (extremely faint) concern for Timon&#8217;s mental state. He is also aware that Timon&#8217;s fortune will not last, and that therefore one had best make the best use of it while one can.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. LORD.">Third Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Lord is one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who refuses to help him out when he is in need and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is aware that Timon&#8217;s fortunes cannot last and that therefore one had best make use of it while one can. A gossip, he is less concerned about Timon&#8217;s mental state than about the state of his own hat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. LORD.">Fourth Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fourth Lord is one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who refuses to help him out when he is in need and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is completely oblivious to the fact that Timon has some reason to be ticked off at his so-called friends.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. SEN.">First Senator</persname>
<persdescription>The First Senator is an old man, one of the members of government who refuses to help Timon when he is in need. He also offers windy reasons for applying laws strictly without mitigation, without considering greater concerns. His ill-considered exiling of Alcibiades puts all of Athens in danger. Due to this he is forced to plead with Timon for help against Alcibiades when the panic-struck Athenians want Timon as a dictator to save them from the rebels. He is unsuccessful. In the end he surrenders to Alcibiades to save the city.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. SEN.">Second Senator</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Senator is an old man, one of the members of government who refuses to help Timon when he is in need, and refuses to pay any attention to Alcibiades&#8217;s pleas for one of his men&#8217;s life. As a result, he is forced to plead with Timon for help against Alcibiades when the panic-struck Athenians want Timon as a dictator to save them from the rebels. He is unsuccessful. In the end he surrenders to Alcibiades to save the city.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. SEN.">Third Senator</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Senator practices usury on the side, and is deeply concerned about how much money Timon spends. Realizing that Timon&#8217;s endless parties can only result in his bankruptcy, he decides to call in his debts while Timon may still have some money left to pay them back, setting off the collapse of Timon&#8217;s credit. He is shocked at Alcibiades&#8217;s suggestion that he and the other old senators are growing forgetful. He is terrified of the arrival of the exile&#8217;s army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. SEN.">Fourth Senator</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Senator is terrified of the arrival of Alcibiades&#8217;s army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. STRAN.">First Stranger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Stranger has his ear to the ground and knows what is happening to Timon&#8217;s fortunes before some of Timon&#8217;s supposed friends do. He is shocked that Lucius refuses to help the other man, and swears that had he been as well used by Timon as Lucius had, he would have helped. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. STRAN.">Second Stranger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Stranger (Hostilius) is shocked that Lucullus has refused to help Timon out, and gossips to Lucius about it. He takes Lucius&#8217;s measure when the latter also refuses to help.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. STRAN.">Third Stranger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Stranger is appalled at Lucius&#8217;s refusal to help Timon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FLAM.">Flaminius</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="THREE SERVANTS.">Three Servants</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Flaminius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, sent to request fifty talents from Lucullus when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. An honest man, he refuses to be bribed, and is horrified at Lucullus&#8217;s refusal to help Timon. He tries to keep Timon away from direct contact with his creditors&#8217; servants, but is unsuccessful. He brings Lucullus&#8217;s invitation to a hunting party to Timon, along with some hunting greyhounds.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FLAV.">Flavius</persname>
<persdescription>Flavius is Timon&#8217;s Steward, and the head of his household, and the man best aware of just how much his master spends. The state of Timon&#8217;s accounts brings him to despair, as does his inability to get Timon to understand that he is essentially bankrupt and that giving costly presents to anyone who shows up for dinner is not really an option. Timon&#8217;s last barrier against his creditors, he is forever putting off the debt collectors while he tries to find the money to pay them back and get it through Timon&#8217;s thick skull that he is in serious financial trouble. He even goes so far as to ask the Senate for help in Timon&#8217;s name without being asked to; due to their refusal, he is skeptical of Timon&#8217;s belief that his friends will help him. Flavius dearly loves his master and is deeply loyal to him. When the money finally runs entirely out and Timon leaves Athens, Flavius gives what he has to his fellow servants and goes off to find his vanished master. This ends up making his fortune, but does not make him happy. Easily moved to tears, Flavius admires goodness and is rather depressed by how little there is of it in the world. He leads the Senators to Timon&#8217;s cave for the sake of Athens, but has no great hope of their success.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FOOL.">Fool</persname>
<persdescription>A Fool speaks truth in riddles, and has a good mocking tongue. He is not afraid of criticizing his mistress behind her back. Though he insults people, he appears downright kind when he is in Apemantus&#8217;s company.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HOR.">Hortensius</persname>
<persdescription>Hortensius is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to recover a debt. He does not like his task, given that he is fully aware that Timon has given his master gifts worth far more than the borrowed sum. He attempts to do the job all the same, but soon realizes that the odds of getting any money back are rather low, and that Timon is no longer entirely sane.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ISID. SERV.">Isidore&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Isidore&#8217;s Servant is the servant of a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money. He is sent to recover the sum from Timon, but is unable to get past Flavius, who puts him off time and again. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JEW.">Jeweller</persname>
<persdescription>A Jeweller [possibly named Titus] is a flattering man who brings Timon a jewel, knowing that the latter will buy it no matter the cost.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUCIL.">Lucilius</persname>
<persdescription>Lucilius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, a younger man who has served his master well for some years now. One of his tasks is serving at table. He is in love with the Old Athenian&#8217;s daughter, and visits her at night. His fortune is made when Timon finds out that the Old Athenian disapproves of the match because of Lucilius&#8217;s poverty; Timon proceeds to enrich him. He is suitably grateful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUC.">Lucius</persname>
<persdescription>Lucius is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering friends who is only generous to rich people. Quite shamelessly hypocritical, he refuses to help Timon in his need by pretending not to have enough money on him, even though he has just accuses everybody else who refused to help false friends. He then has the audacity to send his servant to ask for repayment of an earlier loan.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUC. SERV.">Lucius&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Lucius&#8217;s Servant is sent by his master to recover some money from Timon, and is well aware that the man is essentially bankrupt. He finds his task, and that of the various other servants on similar errands, rather unethical, as Timon has spent more on the various creditors than he has borrowed from them. Nevertheless, he does his best to get the money back.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUCUL.">Lucullus</persname>
<persdescription>Lucullus is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering and not particularly generous friends, though he does send him some hunting hounds when he invites Timon to hunt with him. He is a sleazy flatterer who attempts to get out of helping Timon by bribing Flaminius to say he didn&#8217;t see him. He lets himself off the hook by claiming to have warned Timon to be a bit more careful with his money.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LUCUL. SERV.">Lucullus&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Lucullus&#8217;s Servant is trusted by his master, but not so much that Lucullus will attempt to offer a bribe in his presence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MER.">Merchant</persname>
<persdescription>A Merchant is a flattering man who attends Timon&#8217;s feast and is well aware of what Apemantus is like.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger informs the Senate of just how bad the situation with Alcibiades&#8217;s approaching army is, and also informs them that Alcibiades too is seeking Timon&#8217;s support.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS. VENT.">Messenger from Ventidius</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger from Ventidius comes to beg Timon to pay off the debt when Ventidius is arrested for non-repayment of five talents, a huge sum.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OLD ATH.">Old Athenian</persname>
<persdescription>An Old Athenian is a rich, upright, honorable and crusty old man with a healthy respect for his own position in life. Insistent that his only daughter shall marry a rich man to match his own position, he loves her enough to swear to disown her if she marries Lucilius, a mere servant. He is however perfectly happy to accept the young man as his son-in-law once Timon enriches him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PAIN.">Painter</persname>
<persdescription>A Painter is a starving artist in need of patronage who, along with his fellow crawler the Poet, hopes to get money off Timon by flattering him. He cannot decide whether to be self-deprecating about his art or not, and is rather affected about his calling. He is also quite open about the financial realities of life and the need to sell oneself &#8212; at least to other artists. The moment he hears that the ruined Timon has found gold, he runs to try his old tricks and get some money off of him, hypocritically swearing that he has come to visit simply out of friendship &#8212; with unexpected results, though he does get some gold out of it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PHI.">Philotus</persname>
<persdescription>Philotus is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to recover the debt, though he has little hope of doing so.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PHRY.">Phrynia</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.">Both Phrynia and Timan</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Phrynia is one of Alcibiades&#8217;s mistresses, accompanying him and his army as he marches on Athens. Timon accuses her of being a prostitute riddled with venereal disease, and she insults him back, but is willing to listen to his cursing so long as he gives her gold.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="POET.">Poet</persname>
<persdescription>A Poet is a verse-maker who lives by acquiring the support (and therefore money) of rich men whom he praises in his poems. Somewhat wiser to the ways of the world than his companion crawler the Painter, he attempts to warn Timon of the possibility that his luck might not hold and that his so-call friends are not true ones. Affected and afflicted by false modesty, he pretends not to work at his poetry and that what he produces is merely trifles, though he clearly hopes they will be taken otherwise. The moment he hears that the ruined Timon has found gold, he runs to try his old tricks and get some money off of him, hypocritically swearing that he has come to visit simply out of friendship &#8212; with unexpected results, though he does get some gold out of it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SEM.">Sempronius</persname>
<persdescription>Sempronius is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering friends, and a very proud man who considers himself insulted to be asked for help after others instead of first. Or, at least, that&#8217;s his excuse for not helping Timon in his need.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SER.">Servilius</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="THREE SERVANTS.">Three Servants</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Servilius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, sent to request fifty talents from Lucius when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. He appears to accept Lucius&#8217;s word that he doesn&#8217;t have enough money on him to help out. He announces to Timon that Lucius has sent him some horses and he also announces the arrival of some Senators at Timon&#8217;s feast.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SOLD.">Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>A Soldier is sent by Alcibiades to find Timon and ask for his support in his attack on Athens, but only finds Timon&#8217;s grave. He is illiterate, but knows the value of words, and brings a cast of the inscription on the tomb to his general.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="TIMAN.">Timandra</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.">Both Phrynia and Timan</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Timandra is one of Alcibiades&#8217;s mistresses, accompanying him and his army as he marches on Athens. She has heard of Timon, who accuses her of being riddled with venereal disease. Though insulted by him, she is willing to listen to his cursing so long as he gives her gold.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TIM. PAGE.">Timon&#8217;s Page</persname>
<persdescription>Timon&#8217;s Page is sent to bring two letters, one to Timon and one to Alcibiades. As he cannot read, he mixes the two up and is forced to ask Apemantus for help. He stands up reasonably well to the cynic&#8217;s insults.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TIM. SERV.">Timon&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="THREE SERVANTS.">Three Servants</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Timon&#8217;s Servant is sent to request fifty talents of Sempronius when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. He is appalled when Sempronius refuses to help his master.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="TIT.">Titus</persname>
<persdescription>Titus is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to ask for repayment on that debt. He is rather skeptical about the whole process, being quite aware that Timon has spent more on the various creditors than they have lent to him, and does not mind pointing this out. Nevertheless, he does his best to do his job.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. VAR. SERV.">Varro&#8217;s First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Varro&#8217;s First Servant works for a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money (3,000 crowns), who is sent to recover a sum that&#8217;s been due for six weeks. He makes a weak attempt to match wits with the Fool, and knows quite well what is likely to happen if Apemantus starts to speak. Sent back with a second servant when he fails to get the money back, he is aware of the unfairness of what is happening to Timon. He is not overly fond of his master.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. VAR. SERV.">Varro&#8217;s Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Varro&#8217;s Second Servant works for a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money (3,000 crowns), and is sent along with Varro&#8217;s First Servant to recover the sum when the latter is unsuccessful in getting the money back on his own. He is not particularly sympathetic to the out-of-work Flavius.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="VEN.">Ventidius</persname>
<persdescription>Ventidius is a friend of Timon&#8217;s who tends to live beyond his means, to the extent that he ends up in prison for debt. Luckily for him, Timon is foolishly generous and immediately pays the debt. Inheriting his father&#8217;s wealth, he does offer to repay this one debt, but may not be particularly surprised when Timon refuses to take them. Growing less foolish with his money after he is rich, he declines to help Timon in his need.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>


<act num="1">
<acttitle>Act 1</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A hall in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Poet, Painter, Jeweller, Merchant, Senators, Lord Timon, Messenger, Lucilius, Servants, Old Athenian, Apemantus, Messenger from Ventidius, Alcibiades, Lords)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>A poet and a painter, waiting at Timon&#8217;s house to suck up to him, comment to each other on Timon&#8217;s generosity. They flatter each other over the mutual excellence of what they plan to offer to him. Timonwalks by, followed by the Senators of Athens. The poet notes that his poem warns Timon that Fortune may turn against him some day. Timon pays out bail money for a friend, enriches one of his servants so that he can marry a rich man&#8217;s daughter, and accepts the gifts brought to him. The snarling cynic Apemantus comes in and rails at all of Timon&#8217;s suitors, believe all Athenians to be knaves and accusing the poet of being nothing but a flatterer, but Timon pays him little attention. Alcibiades arrives with a group of friends, who are all invited to join in at Timon&#8217;s feast. They all go in. Two lords, arriving late, have to deal with Apemantus before going in.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Poet, Painter, Jeweller, Merchant, at several doors.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Good day, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="3">I am glad y&#8217; are well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>I have not seen you long, how goes the world?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>It wears, sir, as it grows.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Ay, that&#8217;s well known;</line>
<line>But what particular rarity? What strange,</line>
<line>Which manifold record not matches? See,</line>
<line>Magic of bounty! All these spirits thy power</line>
<line>Hath conjur&#8217;d to attend. I know the merchant.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>I know them both; th&#8217; other&#8217;s a jeweller.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>O, &#8217;tis a worthy lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Nay, that&#8217;s most fix&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>A most incomparable man, breath&#8217;d, as it were,</line>
<line>To an untirable and continuate goodness;</line>
<line>He passes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line>I have a jewel here&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>O, pray let&#8217;s see&#8217;t. For the Lord Timon, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line>If he will touch the estimate. But for that&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Reciting to himself.</stagedir>
<line>&#8220;When we for recompense have prais&#8217;d the vild,</line>
<line>It stains the glory in that happy verse</line>
<line>Which aptly sings the good.&#8221;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Looking on the jewel.</stagedir>
<line offset="6">&#8217;Tis a good form.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line>And rich. Here is a water, look ye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>You are rapt, sir, in some work, some dedication</line>
<line>To the great lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="4">A thing slipp&#8217;d idlely from me.</line>
<line>Our poesy is as a gum, which oozes</line>
<line>From whence &#8217;tis nourish&#8217;d. The fire i&#8217; th&#8217; flint</line>
<line>Shows not till it be strook; our gentle flame</line>
<line>Provokes itself and like the current flies</line>
<line>Each bound it chases. What have you there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>A picture, sir. When comes your book forth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Upon the heels of my presentment, sir.</line>
<line>Let&#8217;s see your piece.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">&#8217;Tis a good piece.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>So &#8217;tis. This comes off well and excellent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>Indifferent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="3">Admirable! How this grace</line>
<line>Speaks his own standing! What a mental power</line>
<line>This eye shoots forth! How big imagination</line>
<line>Moves in this lip! To th&#8217; dumbness of the gesture</line>
<line>One might interpret.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>It is a pretty mocking of the life.</line>
<line>Here is a touch; is&#8217;t good?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="5">I will say of it,</line>
<line>It tutors nature. Artificial strife</line>
<line>Lives in these touches, livelier than life.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter certain Senators and pass over.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>How this lord is followed!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>The senators of Athens, happy men!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>Look, more!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>You see this confluence, this great flood of visitors.</line>
<line>I have, in this rough work, shap&#8217;d out a man</line>
<line>Whom this beneath world doth embrace and hug</line>
<line>With amplest entertainment. My free drift</line>
<line>Halts not particularly, but moves itself</line>
<line>In a wide sea of wax; no levell&#8217;d malice</line>
<line>Infects one comma in the course I hold,</line>
<line>But flies an eagle flight, bold, and forth on,</line>
<line>Leaving no tract behind.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>How shall I understand you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="6">I will unbolt to you.</line>
<line>You see how all conditions, how all minds,</line>
<line>As well of glib and slipp&#8217;ry creatures as</line>
<line>Of grave and austere quality, tender down</line>
<line>Their services to Lord Timon. His large fortune,</line>
<line>Upon his good and gracious nature hanging,</line>
<line>Subdues and properties to his love and tendance</line>
<line>All sorts of hearts; yea, from the glass-fac&#8217;d flatterer</line>
<line>To Apemantus, that few things loves better</line>
<line>Than to abhor himself; even he drops down</line>
<line>The knee before him, and returns in peace</line>
<line>Most rich in Timon&#8217;s nod.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">I saw them speak together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Sir, I have upon a high and pleasant hill</line>
<line>Feign&#8217;d Fortune to be thron&#8217;d. The base o&#8217; th&#8217; mount</line>
<line>Is rank&#8217;d with all deserts, all kind of natures,</line>
<line>That labor on the bosom of this sphere</line>
<line>To propagate their states. Amongst them all,</line>
<line>Whose eyes are on this sovereign lady fix&#8217;d,</line>
<line>One do I personate of Lord Timon&#8217;s frame,</line>
<line>Whom Fortune with her ivory hand wafts to her,</line>
<line>Whose present grace to present slaves and servants</line>
<line>Translates his rivals.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">&#8217;Tis conceiv&#8217;d to scope.</line>
<line>This throne, this Fortune, and this hill, methinks,</line>
<line>With one man beckon&#8217;d from the rest below,</line>
<line>Bowing his head against the steepy mount</line>
<line>To climb his happiness, would be well express&#8217;d</line>
<line>In our condition.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Nay, sir, but hear me on:</line>
<line>All those which were his fellows but of late&#8212;</line>
<line>Some better than his value&#8212;on the moment</line>
<line>Follow his strides, his lobbies fill with tendance,</line>
<line>Rain sacrificial whisperings in his ear,</line>
<line>Make sacred even his stirrup, and through him</line>
<line>Drink the free air.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Ay, marry, what of these?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>When Fortune in her shift and change of mood</line>
<line>Spurns down her late beloved, all his dependants</line>
<line>Which labor&#8217;d after him to the mountain&#8217;s top</line>
<line>Even on their knees and hands, let him slip down,</line>
<line>Not one accompanying his declining foot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis common:</line>
<line>A thousand moral paintings I can show</line>
<line>That shall demonstrate these quick blows of Fortune&#8217;s</line>
<line>More pregnantly than words. Yet you do well</line>
<line>To show Lord Timon that mean eyes have seen</line>
<line>The foot above the head.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Trumpets sound. Enter Lord Timon, addressing himself courteously to every suitor, a Messenger from Ventidius talking with him; Lucilius and other Servants following.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Imprison&#8217;d is he, say you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. VENT.</speaker>
<line>Ay, my good lord, five talents is his debt,</line>
<line>His means most short, his creditors most strait.</line>
<line>Your honorable letter he desires</line>
<line>To those have shut him up, which failing,</line>
<line>Periods his comfort.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Noble Ventidius! Well;</line>
<line>I am not of that feather to shake off</line>
<line>My friend when he must need me. I do know him</line>
<line>A gentleman that well deserves a help,</line>
<line>Which he shall have. I&#8217;ll pay the debt and free him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. VENT.</speaker>
<line>Your lordship ever binds him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Commend me to him. I will send his ransom,</line>
<line>And being enfranchis&#8217;d, bid him come to me;</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis not enough to help the feeble up,</line>
<line>But to support him after. Fare you well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS. VENT.</speaker>
<line>All happiness to your honor!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter an Old Athenian.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>Lord Timon, hear me speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Freely, good father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>Thou hast a servant nam&#8217;d Lucilius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I have so. What of him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>Most noble Timon, call the man before thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Attends he here, or no? Lucilius!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCIL.</speaker>
<line>Here, at your lordship&#8217;s service.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>This fellow here, Lord Timon, this thy creature,</line>
<line>By night frequents my house. I am a man</line>
<line>That from my first have been inclin&#8217;d to thrift,</line>
<line>And my estate deserves an heir more rais&#8217;d</line>
<line>Than one which holds a trencher.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Well; what further?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>One only daughter have I, no kin else,</line>
<line>On whom I may confer what I have got.</line>
<line>The maid is fair, a&#8217; th&#8217; youngest for a bride,</line>
<line>And I have bred her at my dearest cost</line>
<line>In qualities of the best. This man of thine</line>
<line>Attempts her love. I prithee, noble lord,</line>
<line>Join with me to forbid him her resort,</line>
<line>Myself have spoke in vain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">The man is honest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>Therefore he will be, Timon.</line>
<line>His honesty rewards him in itself,</line>
<line>It must not bear my daughter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Does she love him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>She is young and apt.</line>
<line>Our own precedent passions do instruct us</line>
<line>What levity&#8217;s in youth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To Lucilius.</stagedir>
<line offset="5">Love you the maid?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCIL.</speaker>
<line>Ay, my good lord, and she accepts of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>If in her marriage my consent be missing,</line>
<line>I call the gods to witness, I will choose</line>
<line>Mine heir from forth the beggars of the world,</line>
<line>And dispossess her all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">How shall she be endowed,</line>
<line>If she be mated with an equal husband?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line>Three talents on the present; in future, all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>This gentleman of mine hath serv&#8217;d me long;</line>
<line>To build his fortune I will strain a little,</line>
<line>For &#8217;tis a bond in men. Give him thy daughter;</line>
<line>What you bestow, in him I&#8217;ll counterpoise,</line>
<line>And make him weigh with her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>OLD ATH.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Most noble lord,</line>
<line>Pawn me to this your honor, she is his.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>My hand to thee, mine honor on my promise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCIL.</speaker>
<line>Humbly I thank your lordship. Never may</line>
<line>That state or fortune fall into my keeping,</line>
<line>Which is not owed to you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit with Old Athenian.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Vouchsafe my labor, and long live your lordship!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I thank you, you shall hear from me anon.</line>
<line>Go not away. What have you there, my friend?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>A piece of painting, which I do beseech</line>
<line>Your lordship to accept.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Painting is welcome.</line>
<line>The painting is almost the natural man;</line>
<line>For since dishonor traffics with man&#8217;s nature,</line>
<line>He is but outside; these pencill&#8217;d figures are</line>
<line>Even such as they give out. I like your work,</line>
<line>And you shall find I like it. Wait attendance</line>
<line>Till you hear further from me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">The gods preserve ye!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Well fare you, gentleman; give me your hand,</line>
<line>We must needs dine together.&#8212;Sir, your jewel</line>
<line>Hath suffered under praise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line offset="5">What, my lord, dispraise?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>A mere saciety of commendations;</line>
<line>If I should pay you for&#8217;t as &#8217;tis extoll&#8217;d,</line>
<line>It would unclew me quite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line offset="5">My lord, &#8217;tis rated</line>
<line>As those which sell would give; but you well know,</line>
<line>Things of like value differing in the owners</line>
<line>Are prized by their masters. Believe&#8217;t, dear lord,</line>
<line>You mend the jewel by the wearing it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Well mock&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Apemantus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>No, my good lord, he speaks the common tongue</line>
<line>Which all men speak with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Look who comes here; will you be chid?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line>We&#8217;ll bear, with your lordship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line offset="6">He&#8217;ll spare none.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Good morrow to thee, gentle Apemantus!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Till I be gentle, stay thou for thy good morrow&#8212;</line>
<line>When thou art Timon&#8217;s dog, and these knaves honest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Why dost thou call them knaves? Thou know&#8217;st them not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Are they not Athenians?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Then I repent not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>JEW.</speaker>
<line>You know me, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou know&#8217;st I do, I call&#8217;d thee by thy name.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Thou art proud, Apemantus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Of nothing so much as that I am not like Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Whither art going?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>To knock out an honest Athenian&#8217;s brains.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>That&#8217;s a deed thou&#8217;t die for.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Right, if doing nothing be death by th&#8217; law.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>How lik&#8217;st thou this picture, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>The best, for the innocence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Wrought he not well that painted it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>He wrought better that made the painter, and yet he&#8217;s but a filthy piece of work.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>Y&#8217; are a dog.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thy mother&#8217;s of my generation; what&#8217;s she, if I be a dog?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Wilt dine with me, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>No; I eat not lords.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>And thou shouldst, thou&#8217;dst anger ladies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>O, they eat lords; so they come by great bellies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>That&#8217;s a lascivious apprehension.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>So thou apprehend&#8217;st it, take it for thy labor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>How dost thou like this jewel, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Not so well as plain-dealing, which will not cast a man a doit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What dost thou think &#8217;tis worth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Not worth my thinking. How now, poet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>How now, philosopher?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou liest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Art not one?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Then I lie not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Art not a poet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Then thou liest: look in thy last work, where thou hast feign&#8217;d him a worthy fellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>That&#8217;s not feign&#8217;d, he is so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Yes, he is worthy of thee, and to pay thee for thy labor. He that loves to be flatter&#8217;d is worthy o&#8217; th&#8217; flatterer. Heavens, that I were a lord!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What wouldst do then, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>E&#8217;en as Apemantus does now: hate a lord with my heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What, thyself?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Ay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Wherefore?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>That I had no angry wit to be a lord. Art not thou a merchant?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>Ay, Apemantus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Traffic confound thee, if the gods will not!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MER.</speaker>
<line>If traffic do it, the gods do it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Traffic&#8217;s thy god, and thy god confound thee!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Trumpet sounds. Enter a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What trumpet&#8217;s that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis Alcibiades, and some twenty horse,</line>
<line>All of companionship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Pray entertain them, give them guide to us.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt some Attendants.</stagedir>
<line>You must needs dine with me; go not you hence</line>
<line>Till I have thank&#8217;d you. When dinner&#8217;s done,</line>
<line>Show me this piece. I am joyful of your sights.</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Alcibiades with the rest.</stagedir>
<line>Most welcome, sir!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">So, so; there!</line>
<line>Aches contract and starve your supple joints!</line>
<line>That there should be small love amongest these sweet knaves,</line>
<line>And all this courtesy! The strain of man&#8217;s bred out</line>
<line>Into baboon and monkey.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Sir, you have sav&#8217;d my longing, and I feed</line>
<line>Most hungerly on your sight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Right welcome, sir!</line>
<line>Ere we depart, we&#8217;ll share a bounteous time</line>
<line>In different pleasures. Pray you let us in.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt all but Apemantus.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter two Lords.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>What time a&#8217; day is&#8217;t, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Time to be honest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>That time serves still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>The most accursed thou, that still omit&#8217;st it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Thou art going to Lord Timon&#8217;s feast?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Ay, to see meat fill knaves, and wine heat fools.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Fare thee well, fare thee well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou art a fool to bid me farewell twice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Why, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Shouldst have kept one to thyself, for I mean to give thee none.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Hang thyself!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>No, I will do nothing at thy bidding; make thy requests to thy friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Away, unpeaceable dog, or I&#8217;ll spurn thee hence!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I will fly, like a dog, the heels a&#8217; th&#8217; ass.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>He&#8217;s opposite to humanity. Come, shall we in</line>
<line>And taste Lord Timon&#8217;s bounty? He outgoes</line>
<line>The very heart of kindness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>He pours it out: Plutus, the god of gold,</line>
<line>Is but his steward. No meed but he repays</line>
<line>Sevenfold above itself; no gift to him</line>
<line>But breeds the giver a return exceeding</line>
<line>All use of quittance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line offset="4">The noblest mind he carries</line>
<line>That ever govern&#8217;d man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Long may he live in fortunes! Shall we in?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll keep you company.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>A banqueting-room in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Flavius, Lord Timon, States, Athenian Lords, Alcibiades, Ventidius, Apemantus, Servants, Cupid, Ladies)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>At a feast of Timon&#8217;s, Ventidius, who was freed from jail thanks to Timon&#8217;s generosity, has inherited from his father and tries to pay Timon back. Timon refuses to hear of it. Apemantus too is present; Timon welcomes him but the cynic insists he only wants to be kicked out. Timon rolls his eyes and pays him no heed, letting him have a table by himself, from where he comments bitterly on all that follows. Timon gives a speech in praise of friendship. Some ladies come in to present a masque to Timon. Timon sends his steward Flavius to fetch a casket of jewels for him to distribute. Flavius is worried that Timon&#8217;s generosity is bankrupting him. He tries to tell his master this, but Timon doesn&#8217;t want to hear of anything concerning him. Presents from Lords Lucullus and Lucius and announced to Timon. Flavius complains to himself that Timon refuses to know what the state of his finances is, and thus doesn&#8217;t know that he has no money left. Timon bids farewell to his guests, giving them anything they&#8217;ve ever said they liked. Timon tells Apemantus that he&#8217;d be good to him as well if he were only a bit nicer, but Apemantus refuses to be bribed into silence; Timon refuses to listen to him when he begins to rail against the high life.</scenedescription>
<stagedir type="action">Hoboys playing loud music. A great banquet serv&#8217;d in, Flavius and others attending; and then enter Lord Timon, the States, the Athenian Lords, Alcibiades, and Ventidius, which Timon redeem&#8217;d from prison. Then comes, dropping after all, Apemantus, discontentedly, like himself.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>VEN.</speaker>
<line>Most honored Timon,</line>
<line>It hath pleas&#8217;d the gods to remember my father&#8217;s age,</line>
<line>And call him to long peace.</line>
<line>He is gone happy, and has left me rich.</line>
<line>Then, as in grateful virtue I am bound</line>
<line>To your free heart, I do return those talents,</line>
<line>Doubled with thanks and service, from whose help</line>
<line>I deriv&#8217;d liberty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="3">O, by no means,</line>
<line>Honest Ventidius. You mistake my love;</line>
<line>I gave it freely ever, and there&#8217;s none</line>
<line>Can truly say he gives if he receives.</line>
<line>If our betters play at that game, we must not dare</line>
<line>To imitate them; faults that are rich are fair.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VEN.</speaker>
<line>A noble spirit!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="3">Nay, my lords,</line>
<line>Ceremony was but devis&#8217;d at first</line>
<line>To set a gloss on faint deeds, hollow welcomes,</line>
<line>Recanting goodness, sorry ere &#8217;tis shown;</line>
<line>But where there is true friendship, there needs none.</line>
<line>Pray sit, more welcome are ye to my fortunes</line>
<line>Than my fortunes to me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">They sit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>My lord, we always have confess&#8217;d it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Ho, ho, confess&#8217;d it? Hang&#8217;d it, have you not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>O, Apemantus, you are welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">No;</line>
<line>You shall not make me welcome.</line>
<line>I come to have thee thrust me out of doors.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Fie, th&#8217; art a churl. Ye have got a humor there</line>
<line>Does not become a man, &#8217;tis much to blame.</line>
<line>They say, my lords, &#8220;<latin xml:lang="la">Ira furor brevis est</latin>,&#8221;</line>
<line>But yond man is very angry. Go,</line>
<line>Let him have a table by himself,</line>
<line>For he does neither affect company,</line>
<line>Nor is he fit for&#8217;t indeed.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Let me stay at thine apperil, Timon.</line>
<line>I come to observe, I give thee warning on&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I take no heed of thee; th&#8217; art an Athenian, therefore welcome. I myself would have no power; prithee let my meat make thee silent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I scorn thy meat, &#8217;twould choke me; for I should ne&#8217;er flatter thee. O you gods! What a number of men eats Timon, and he sees &#8217;em not! It grieves me to see so many dip their meat in one man&#8217;s blood, and all the madness is, he cheers them up too.</line>
<line>I wonder men dare trust themselves with men.</line>
<line>Methinks they should invite them without knives:</line>
<line>Good for their meat, and safer for their lives.</line>
<line>There&#8217;s much example for&#8217;t: the fellow that sits next him, now parts bread with him, pledges the breath of him in a divided draught, is the readiest man to kill him; &#8217;t &#8217;as been prov&#8217;d. If I were a huge man, I should fear to drink at meals,</line>
<line>Lest they should spy my windpipe&#8217;s dangerous notes:</line>
<line>Great men should drink with harness on their throats.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>My lord, in heart; and let the health go round.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Let it flow this way, my good lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Flow this way? A brave fellow! He keeps his tides well. Those healths will make thee and thy state look ill, Timon.</line>
<line>Here&#8217;s that which is too weak to be a sinner,</line>
<line>Honest water, which ne&#8217;er left man i&#8217; th&#8217; mire.</line>
<line>This and my food are equals, there&#8217;s no odds;</line>
<line>Feasts are too proud to give thanks to the gods.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Apemantus&#8217; grace.</stagedir>
<line><recite>Immortal gods, I crave no pelf,</recite></line>
<line><recite>I pray for no man but myself.</recite></line>
<line><recite>Grant I may never prove so fond,</recite></line>
<line><recite>To trust man on his oath or bond;</recite></line>
<line><recite>Or a harlot for her weeping,</recite></line>
<line><recite>Or a dog that seems a-sleeping,</recite></line>
<line><recite>Or a keeper with my freedom,</recite></line>
<line><recite>Or my friends, if I should need &#8217;em.</recite></line>
<line><recite>Amen. So fall to&#8217;t:</recite></line>
<line><recite>Rich men sin, and I eat root.</recite></line>

<stagedir type="action">Eats and drinks.</stagedir>
<line>Much good dich thy good heart, Apemantus!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Captain Alcibiades, your heart&#8217;s in the field now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>My heart is ever at your service, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>You had rather be at a breakfast of enemies than a dinner of friends.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>So they were bleeding new, my lord, there&#8217;s no meat like &#8217;em; I could wish my best friend at such a feast.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Would all those flatterers were thine enemies then, that then thou mightst kill &#8217;em&#8212;and bid me to &#8217;em!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Might we but have that happiness, my lord, that you would once use our hearts, whereby we might express some part of our zeals, we should think ourselves forever perfect.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>O, no doubt, my good friends, but the gods themselves have provided that I shall have much help from you: how had you been my friends else? Why have you that charitable title from thousands, did not you chiefly belong to my heart? I have told more of you to myself than you can with modesty speak in your own behalf; and thus far I confirm you. O you gods, think I, what need we have any friends, if we should ne&#8217;er have need of &#8217;em? They were the most needless creatures living, should we ne&#8217;er have use for &#8217;em; and would most resemble sweet instruments hung up in cases, that keeps their sounds to themselves. Why, I have often wish&#8217;d myself poorer, that I might come nearer to you. We are born to do benefits; and what better or properer can we call our own than the riches of our friends? O, what a precious comfort &#8217;tis to have so many like brothers commanding one another&#8217;s fortunes! O, joy&#8217;s e&#8217;en made away ere&#8217;t can be born! Mine eyes cannot hold out water, methinks. To forget their faults, I drink to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou weep&#8217;st to make them drink, Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Joy had the like conception in our eyes,</line>
<line>And at that instant like a babe sprung up.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Ho, ho! I laugh to think that babe a bastard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I promise you, my lord, you mov&#8217;d me much.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Much!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Sound tucket within.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What means that trump?</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Flaminius.</stagedir>
<line offset="5">How now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Please you, my lord, there are certain ladies most desirous of admittance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ladies? What are their wills?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>There comes with them a forerunner, my lord, which bears that office to signify their pleasures.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I pray let them be admitted.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Flaminius.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Cupid.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CUP.</speaker>
<line>Hail to thee, worthy Timon, and to all</line>
<line>That of his bounties taste! The five best senses</line>
<line>Acknowledge thee their patron, and come freely</line>
<line>To gratulate thy plenteous bosom. There,</line>
<line>Taste, touch, all, pleas&#8217;d from thy table rise;</line>
<line>They only now come but to feast thine eyes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>They&#8217;re welcome all, let &#8217;em have kind admittance.</line>
<line>Music, make their welcome!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Cupid.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>You see, my lord, how ample y&#8217; are belov&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="song">Music. Enter Cupid with the masque of Ladies, as Amazons, with lutes in their hands, dancing and playing.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Hoy-day,</line>
<line>What a sweep of vanity comes this way!</line>
<line>They dance? They are madwomen.</line>
<line>Like madness is the glory of this life,</line>
<line>As this pomp shows to a little oil and root.</line>
<line>We make ourselves fools to disport ourselves,</line>
<line>And spend our flatteries to drink those men</line>
<line>Upon whose age we void it up again</line>
<line>With poisonous spite and envy.</line>
<line>Who lives that&#8217;s not depraved or depraves?</line>
<line>Who dies that bears not one spurn to their graves</line>
<line>Of their friends&#8217; gift?</line>
<line>I should fear those that dance before me now</line>
<line>Would one day stamp upon me. &#8217;T &#8217;as been done;</line>
<line>Men shut their doors against a setting sun.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The Lords rise from table, with much adoring of Timon, and to show their loves, each single out an Amazon, and all dance, men with women, a lofty strain or two to the hoboys, and cease.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>You have done our pleasures much grace, fair ladies,</line>
<line>Set a fair fashion on our entertainment,</line>
<line>Which was not half so beautiful and kind;</line>
<line>You have added worth unto&#8217;t and lustre,</line>
<line>And entertain&#8217;d me with mine own device.</line>
<line>I am to thank you for&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LADY. MASK.</speaker>
<line>My lord, you take us even at the best.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Faith, for the worst is filthy, and would not hold taking, I doubt me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ladies, there is an idle banquet attends you,</line>
<line>Please you to dispose yourselves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL LADY. MASK.</speaker>
<line>Most thankfully, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Cupid and Ladies.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Flavius!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>My lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="2">The little casket bring me hither.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Yes, my lord.</line>

<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line offset="3">More jewels yet?</line>
<line>There is no crossing him in &#8217;s humor,</line>
<line>Else I should tell him well (i&#8217; faith, I should),</line>
<line>When all&#8217;s spent, he&#8217;ld be cross&#8217;d then, and he could.</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis pity bounty had not eyes behind,</line>
<line>That man might ne&#8217;er be wretched for his mind.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 
<stagedir type="enter">Enter Flaminius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Where be our men?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Here, my lord, in readiness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Our horses!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Flavius with the casket. Exit Flaminius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="3">O my friends! I have one word</line>
<line>To say to you. Look you, my good lord,</line>
<line>I must entreat you honor me so much</line>
<line>As to advance this jewel; accept it and wear it,</line>
<line>Kind my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I am so far already in your gifts&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL.</speaker>
<line>So are we all.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>My lord, there are certain nobles of the Senate</line>
<line>Newly alighted, and come to visit you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>They are fairly welcome.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">I beseech your honor,</line>
<line>Vouchsafe me a word, it does concern you near.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Near? Why then another time I&#8217;ll hear thee.</line>
<line>I prithee let&#8217;s be provided to show them entertainment.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line>I scarce know how.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>May it please your honor, Lord Lucius</line>
<line>(Out of his free love) hath presented to you</line>
<line>Four milk-white horses, trapp&#8217;d in silver.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I shall accept them fairly; let the presents</line>
<line>Be worthily entertain&#8217;d.</line>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servilius.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Flaminius.</stagedir>
<line offset="5">How now? What news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Please you, my lord, that honorable gentleman, Lord Lucullus, entreats your company tomorrow to hunt with him, and has sent your honor two brace of greyhounds.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll hunt with him, and let them be receiv&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Not without fair reward.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Flaminius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line offset="5">What will this come to?</line>
<line>He commands us to provide, and give great gifts,</line>
<line>And all out of an empty coffer;</line>
<line>Nor will he know his purse, or yield me this,</line>
<line>To show him what a beggar his heart is,</line>
<line>Being of no power to make his wishes good.</line>
<line>His promises fly so beyond his state</line>
<line>That what he speaks is all in debt: he owes</line>
<line>For ev&#8217;ry word. He is so kind that he now</line>
<line>Pays interest for&#8217;t; his land&#8217;s put to their books.</line>
<line>Well, would I were gently put out of office</line>
<line>Before I were forc&#8217;d out!</line>
<line>Happier is he that has no friend to feed</line>
<line>Than such that do e&#8217;en enemies exceed.</line>
<line>I bleed inwardly for my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">You do yourselves</line>
<line>Much wrong, you bate too much of your own merits.</line>
<line>Here, my lord, a trifle of our love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>With more than common thanks I will receive it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>O, he&#8217;s the very soul of bounty!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>And now I remember, my lord, you gave</line>
<line>Good words the other day of a bay courser</line>
<line>I rode on. &#8217;Tis yours, because you lik&#8217;d it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>O, I beseech you pardon me, my lord, in that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>You may take my word, my lord; I know no man</line>
<line>Can justly praise but what he does affect.</line>
<line>I weigh my friend&#8217;s affection with mine own.</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll tell you true, I&#8217;ll call to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL LORDS.</speaker>
<line offset="7">O, none so welcome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I take all and your several visitations</line>
<line>So kind to heart, &#8217;tis not enough to give;</line>
<line>Methinks, I could deal kingdoms to my friends,</line>
<line>And ne&#8217;er be weary. Alcibiades,</line>
<line>Thou art a soldier, therefore seldom rich,</line>
<line>It comes in charity to thee; for all thy living</line>
<line>Is &#8217;mongst the dead, and all the lands thou hast</line>
<line>Lie in a pitch&#8217;d field.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Ay, defil&#8217;d land, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>We are so virtuously bound&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">And so</line>
<line>Am I to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line offset="3">So infinitely endear&#8217;d&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>All to you. Lights, more lights!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line offset="7">The best of happiness,</line>
<line>Honor, and fortunes keep with you, Lord Timon!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ready for his friends.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Lords and others. Apemantus and Timon remain.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">What a coil&#8217;s here!</line>
<line>Serving of becks and jutting-out of bums!</line>
<line>I doubt whether their legs be worth the sums</line>
<line>That are given for &#8217;em. Friendship&#8217;s full of dregs;</line>
<line>Methinks false hearts should never have sound legs.</line>
<line>Thus honest fools lay out their wealth on curtsies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Now, Apemantus, if thou wert not sullen,</line>
<line>I would be good to thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>No, I&#8217;ll nothing; for if I should be brib&#8217;d too, there would be none left to rail upon thee, and then thou wouldst sin the faster. Thou giv&#8217;st so long, Timon (I fear me), thou wilt give away thyself in paper shortly. What needs these feasts, pomps, and vainglories?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Nay, and you begin to rail on society once, I am sworn not to give regard to you. Farewell, and come with better music.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>So; thou wilt not hear me now, thou shalt not then. I&#8217;ll lock thy heaven from thee.</line>
<line>O that men&#8217;s ears should be</line>
<line>To counsel deaf, but not to flattery!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="2">
<acttitle>Act 2</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in a Senator&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Senator, Caphis)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>A worried Senator tallies up how much he knows Timon owes, and seeing that Timon is still living extravagantly decides to call in his own debt before Timon is unable to pay. He sends a servant to get the money, telling him not to be put off.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Senator with papers in his hand.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SEN.</speaker>
<line>And late, five thousand; to Varro and to Isidore</line>
<line>He owes nine thousand, besides my former sum,</line>
<line>Which makes it five and twenty. Still in motion</line>
<line>Of raging waste? It cannot hold, it will not.</line>
<line>If I want gold, steal but a beggar&#8217;s dog</line>
<line>And give it Timon, why, the dog coins gold.</line>
<line>If I would sell my horse and buy twenty more</line>
<line>Better than he, why, give my horse to Timon,</line>
<line>Ask nothing, give it him, it foals me straight</line>
<line>And able horses. No porter at his gate,</line>
<line>But rather one that smiles and still invites</line>
<line>All that pass by. It cannot hold, no reason</line>
<line>Can sound his state in safety. Caphis ho!</line>
<line>Caphis, I say!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Caphis.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line offset="3">Here, sir, what is your pleasure?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEN.</speaker>
<line>Get on your cloak and haste you to Lord Timon;</line>
<line>Importune him for my moneys, be not ceas&#8217;d</line>
<line>With slight denial; nor then silenc&#8217;d when</line>
<line>&#8220;Commend me to your master&#8221; and the cap</line>
<line>Plays in the right hand, thus&#8212;but tell him</line>
<line>My uses cry to me; I must serve my turn</line>
<line>Out of mine own. His days and times are past,</line>
<line>And my reliances on his fracted dates</line>
<line>Have smit my credit. I love and honor him,</line>
<line>But must not break my back to heal his finger.</line>
<line>Immediate are my needs, and my relief</line>
<line>Must not be toss&#8217;d and turn&#8217;d to me in words,</line>
<line>But find supply immediate. Get you gone,</line>
<line>Put on a most importunate aspect,</line>
<line>A visage of demand; for I do fear,</line>
<line>When every feather sticks in his own wing,</line>
<line>Lord Timon will be left a naked gull,</line>
<line>Which flashes now a phoenix. Get you gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>I go, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEN.</speaker>
<line>Ay, go, sir; take the bonds along with you,</line>
<line>And have the dates in. Come!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line offset="6">I will, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="9">Go.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A hall in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Steward Flavius, Caphis, Servants of Isidore and Varro, Timon, Alcibiades, Apemantus, Fool, Page, Flaminius, Servilius, Timon&#8217;s Servant)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Flavius is distracted by the sheer number of bills being given to him. When Timon comes in from hunting he is importuned by a number of servants handing in their respective masters&#8217; calls for repayment. He cannot understand their pressure. Flavius asks the servants for a bit of time so he can explain matters to Timon, and they agree. They pass the time mocking and being mocked by Apemantus. Timon and Flavius return, the master upbraiding Flavius for not telling him earlier just how poor he actually is and Flavius pointing out that he tried but Timon would never listen. Timon orders Flavius to sell all of Timon&#8217;s land, but it has all been mortgaged already. Flavius lectures him until Timon finally stops him. He reassures himself with the thought that at least he spent out of generosity. He sends servants to ask some of his friends to help him out. Flavius tells him he has tried this already, but Timon is certain they will not desert him.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Steward Flavius with many bills in his hand.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>No care, no stop, so senseless of expense,</line>
<line>That he will neither know how to maintain it,</line>
<line>Nor cease his flow of riot. Takes no accompt</line>
<line>How things go from him, nor resumes no care</line>
<line>Of what is to continue. Never mind</line>
<line>Was to be so unwise, to be so kind.</line>
<line>What shall be done, he will not hear, till feel.</line>
<line>I must be round with him, now he comes from hunting.</line>
<line>Fie, fie, fie, fie!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Caphis and the Servants of Isidore and Varro.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Good even, Varro. What,</line>
<line>You come for money?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Is&#8217;t not your business too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>It is; and yours too, Isidore?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ISID. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="6">It is so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Would we were all discharg&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="6">I fear it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Here comes the lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon and his Train with Alcibiades.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>So soon as dinner&#8217;s done, we&#8217;ll forth again,</line>
<line>My Alcibiades.&#8212;With me, what is your will?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>My lord, here is a note of certain dues.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Dues? Whence are you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Of Athens here, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Go to my steward.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Please it your lordship, he hath put me off</line>
<line>To the succession of new days this month.</line>
<line>My master is awak&#8217;d by great occasion</line>
<line>To call upon his own, and humbly prays you</line>
<line>That with your other noble parts You&#8217;ll suit</line>
<line>In giving him his right.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Mine honest friend,</line>
<line>I prithee but repair to me next morning.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Nay, good my lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Contain thyself, good friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>One Varro&#8217;s servant, my good lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ISID. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="7">From Isidore;</line>
<line>He humbly prays your speedy payment.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>If you did know, my lord, my master&#8217;s wants&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Twas due on forfeiture, my lord, six weeks</line>
<line>And past.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ISID. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="2">Your steward puts me off, my lord,</line>
<line>And I am sent expressly to your lordship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Give me breath.</line>
<line>I do beseech you, good my lords, keep on,</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll wait upon you instantly.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Alcibiades and Lords.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="speak">To Flavius.</stagedir>
<line offset="6">Come hither. Pray you,</line>
<line>How goes the world, that I am thus encount&#8217;red</line>
<line>With clamorous demands of debt, broken bonds,</line>
<line>And the detention of long since due debts,</line>
<line>Against my honor?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Please you, gentlemen,</line>
<line>The time is unagreeable to this business.</line>
<line>Your importunacy cease till after dinner,</line>
<line>That I may make his lordship understand</line>
<line>Wherefore you are not paid.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Do so, my friends. See them well entertain&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Pray draw near.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Apemantus and Fool.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Stay, stay, here comes the Fool with</line>
<line>Apemantus, let&#8217;s ha&#8217; some sport with &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Hang him, he&#8217;ll abuse us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ISID. SERV.</speaker>
<line>A plague upon him, dog!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>How dost, Fool?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Dost dialogue with thy shadow?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>I speak not to thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>No, &#8217;tis to thyself.</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To the Fool.</stagedir>
<line>Come away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ISID. SERV.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To Varro&#8217;s Servant.</stagedir>
<line>There&#8217;s the Fool hangs on your back already.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>No, thou stand&#8217;st single, th&#8217; art not on him yet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>CAPH.</speaker>
<line>Where&#8217;s the Fool now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>He last ask&#8217;d the question. Poor rogues, and usurers&#8217; men, bawds between gold and want!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>What are we, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Asses.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>Why?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>That you ask me what you are, and do not know yourselves. Speak to &#8217;em, Fool.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>How do you, gentlemen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>Gramercies, good Fool; how does your mistress?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>She&#8217;s e&#8217;en setting on water to scald such chickens as you are. Would we could see you at Corinth!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Good, gramercy.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon&#8217;s Page.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>Look you, here comes my master&#8217;s page.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. PAGE.</speaker>
<stagedir type="speak">To the Fool.</stagedir>
<line>Why, how now, captain? What do you in this wise company? How dost thou, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Would I had a rod in my mouth, that I might answer thee profitably.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. PAGE.</speaker>
<line>Prithee, Apemantus, read me the superscription of these letters, I know not which is which.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Canst not read?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. PAGE.</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>There will little learning die then that day thou art hang&#8217;d. This is to Lord Timon, this to Alcibiades. Go, thou wast born a bastard, and thou&#8217;t die a bawd.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. PAGE.</speaker>
<line>Thou wast whelp&#8217;d a dog, and thou shalt famish a dog&#8217;s death. Answer not, I am gone.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>E&#8217;en so thou outrun&#8217;st grace. Fool, I will go with you to Lord Timon&#8217;s.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>Will you leave me there?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>If Timon stay at home. You three serve three usurers?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>Ay, would they serv&#8217;d us!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>So would I&#8212;as good a trick as ever hangman serv&#8217;d thief.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>Are you three usurers&#8217; men?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>Ay, Fool.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>I think no usurer but has a fool to his servant; my mistress is one, and I am her fool. When men come to borrow of your masters, they approach sadly, and go away merry; but they enter my master&#8217;s house merrily, and go away sadly. The reason of this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>I could render one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Do it then, that we may account thee a whoremaster and a knave, which notwithstanding, thou shalt be no less esteem&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>What is a whoremaster, Fool?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>A fool in good clothes, and something like thee. &#8217;Tis a spirit; sometime&#8217;t appears like a lord, sometime like a lawyer, sometime like a philosopher, with two stones more than &#8217;s artificial one. He is very often like a knight; and, generally, in all shapes that man goes up and down in from fourscore to thirteen, this spirit walks in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Thou art not altogether a fool.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>Nor thou altogether a wise man; as much foolery as I have, so much wit thou lack&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>That answer might have become Apemantus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL SERV.</speaker>
<line>Aside, aside, here comes Lord Timon.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon and Steward Flavius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Come with me, Fool, come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FOOL.</speaker>
<line>I do not always follow lover, elder brother, and woman; sometime the philosopher.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Apemantus and Fool.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Pray you walk near, I&#8217;ll speak with you anon.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Servants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>You make me marvel wherefore ere this time</line>
<line>Had you not fully laid my state before me,</line>
<line>That I might so have rated my expense</line>
<line>As I had leave of means.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">You would not hear me;</line>
<line>At many leisures I propos&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Go to!</line>
<line>Perchance some single vantages you took,</line>
<line>When my indisposition put you back,</line>
<line>And that unaptness made your minister</line>
<line>Thus to excuse yourself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">O my good lord,</line>
<line>At many times I brought in my accompts,</line>
<line>Laid them before you; you would throw them off,</line>
<line>And say you found them in mine honesty.</line>
<line>When for some trifling present you have bid me</line>
<line>Return so much, I have shook my head, and wept;</line>
<line>Yea, &#8217;gainst th&#8217; authority of manners, pray&#8217;d you</line>
<line>To hold your hand more close. I did endure</line>
<line>Not seldom, nor no slight checks, when I have</line>
<line>Prompted you in the ebb of your estate</line>
<line>And your great flow of debts. My lov&#8217;d lord,</line>
<line>Though you hear now (too late), yet now&#8217;s a time:</line>
<line>The greatest of your having lacks a half</line>
<line>To pay your present debts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Let all my land be sold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis all engag&#8217;d, some forfeited and gone,</line>
<line>And what remains will hardly stop the mouth</line>
<line>Of present dues. The future comes apace;</line>
<line>What shall defend the interim? And at length</line>
<line>How goes our reck&#8217;ning?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>To Lacedaemon did my land extend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>O my good lord, the world is but a word;</line>
<line>Were it all yours to give it in a breath,</line>
<line>How quickly were it gone!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">You tell me true.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>If you suspect my husbandry or falsehood,</line>
<line>Call me before th&#8217; exactest auditors,</line>
<line>And set me on the proof. So the gods bless me,</line>
<line>When all our offices have been oppress&#8217;d</line>
<line>With riotous feeders, when our vaults have wept</line>
<line>With drunken spilth of wine, when every room</line>
<line>Hath blaz&#8217;d with lights and bray&#8217;d with minstrelsy,</line>
<line>I have retir&#8217;d me to a wasteful cock,</line>
<line>And set mine eyes at flow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Prithee no more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Heavens, have I said, the bounty of this lord!</line>
<line>How many prodigal bits have slaves and peasants</line>
<line>This night englutted! Who is not Timon&#8217;s?</line>
<line>What heart, head, sword, force, means, but is Lord Timon&#8217;s?</line>
<line>Great Timon! Noble, worthy, royal Timon!</line>
<line>Ah, when the means are gone that buy this praise,</line>
<line>The breath is gone whereof this praise is made.</line>
<line>Feast-won, fast-lost; one cloud of winter show&#8217;rs,</line>
<line>These flies are couch&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Come, sermon me no further.</line>
<line>No villainous bounty yet hath pass&#8217;d my heart;</line>
<line>Unwisely, not ignobly, have I given.</line>
<line>Why dost thou weep? Canst thou the conscience lack</line>
<line>To think I shall lack friends? Secure thy heart;</line>
<line>If I would broach the vessels of my love,</line>
<line>And try the argument of hearts, by borrowing,</line>
<line>Men and men&#8217;s fortunes could I frankly use</line>
<line>As I can bid thee speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Assurance bless your thoughts!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>And in some sort these wants of mine are crown&#8217;d,</line>
<line>That I account them blessings; for by these</line>
<line>Shall I try friends. You shall perceive how you</line>
<line>Mistake my fortunes; I am wealthy in my friends.</line>
<line>Within there! Flaminius! Servilius!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter three servants: Flaminius, Servilius, and Timon&#8217;s Servant.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>THREE SERVANTS.</speaker>
<line>My lord? My lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I will dispatch you severally: to Servilius you to Lord Lucius; to Flaminius to Lord Lucullus you&#8212;I hunted with his honor today; to the other you to Sempronius. Commend me to their loves; and I am proud, say, that my occasions have found time to use &#8217;em toward a supply of money. Let the request be fifty talents.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>As you have said, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt the three servants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line>Lord Lucius and Lucullus? Humh!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Go you, sir, to the senators&#8212;</line>
<line>Of whom, even to the state&#8217;s best health, I have</line>
<line>Deserv&#8217;d this hearing&#8212;bid &#8217;em send o&#8217; th&#8217; instant</line>
<line>A thousand talents to me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">I have been bold</line>
<line>(For that I knew it the most general way)</line>
<line>To them to use your signet and your name,</line>
<line>But they do shake their heads, and I am here</line>
<line>No richer in return.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Is&#8217;t true? Can &#8217;t be?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>They answer, in a joint and corporate voice,</line>
<line>That now they are at fall, want treasure, cannot</line>
<line>Do what they would, are sorry; you are honorable,</line>
<line>But yet they could have wish&#8217;d&#8212;they know not&#8212;</line>
<line>Something hath been amiss&#8212;a noble nature</line>
<line>May catch a wrench&#8212;would all were well&#8212;&#8217;tis pity&#8212;</line>
<line>And so, intending other serious matters,</line>
<line>After distasteful looks, and these hard fractions,</line>
<line>With certain half-caps and cold-moving nods,</line>
<line>They froze me into silence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">You gods, reward them!</line>
<line>Prithee, man, look cheerly. These old fellows</line>
<line>Have their ingratitude in them hereditary:</line>
<line>Their blood is cak&#8217;d, &#8217;tis cold, it seldom flows;</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis lack of kindly warmth they are not kind;</line>
<line>And nature, as it grows again toward earth,</line>
<line>Is fashion&#8217;d for the journey, dull and heavy.</line>
<line>Go to Ventidius. (Prithee be not sad,</line>
<line>Thou art true and honest; ingeniously I speak,</line>
<line>No blame belongs to thee.) Ventidius lately</line>
<line>Buried his father, by whose death he&#8217;s stepp&#8217;d</line>
<line>Into a great estate. When he was poor,</line>
<line>Imprison&#8217;d, and in scarcity of friends,</line>
<line>I clear&#8217;d him with five talents. Greet him from me,</line>
<line>Bid him suppose some good necessity</line>
<line>Touches his friend, which craves to be rememb&#8217;red</line>
<line>With those five talents. That had, give&#8217;t these fellows</line>
<line>To whom &#8217;tis instant due. Nev&#8217;r speak or think</line>
<line>That Timon&#8217;s fortunes &#8217;mong his friends can sink.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>I would I could not think it! That thought is bounty&#8217;s foe;</line>
<line>Being free itself, it thinks all others so.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="3">
<acttitle>Act 3</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in Lucullus&#8217; house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Flaminius, Lucullus, Lucullus&#8217;s Servant)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Lucullus is disappointed when Timon&#8217;s servant Flaminius comes to him not with a gift but with a request for a loan. He berates Timon for his prodigality and states that it is no time to lend money just for friendship. He tries to bribe Flaminius into denying that they saw each other. Flaminius is disgusted.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Flaminius waiting to speak with a lord Lucullus from his master, enters Lucullus&#8217;s Servant to him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL. SERV.</speaker>
<line>I have told my lord of you, he is coming down to you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>I thank you, sir.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lucullus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Here&#8217;s my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line>One of Lord Timon&#8217;s men? A gift, I warrant. Why, this hits right; I dreamt of a silver basin and ew&#8217;r tonight.&#8212;Flaminius, honest Flaminius, you are very respectively welcome, sir. Fill me some wine.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lucullus&#8217;s Servant.</stagedir>
<line>And how does that honorable, complete, free-hearted gentleman of Athens, thy very bountiful good lord and master?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>His health is well, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<line>I am right glad that his health is well, sir; and what hast thou there under thy cloak, pretty Flaminius?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Faith, nothing but an empty box, sir, which, in my lord&#8217;s behalf, I come to entreat your honor to supply; who, having great and instant occasion to use fifty talents, hath sent to your lordship to furnish him, nothing doubting your present assistance therein.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<line>La, la, la, la! &#8220;nothing doubting,&#8221; says he? Alas, good lord! A noble gentleman &#8217;tis, if he would not keep so good a house. Many a time and often I ha&#8217; din&#8217;d with him, and told him on&#8217;t, and come again to supper to him of purpose to have him spend less, and yet he would embrace no counsel, take no warning by my coming. Every man has his fault, and honesty is his. I ha&#8217; told him on&#8217;t, but I could ne&#8217;er get him from&#8217;t.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lucullus&#8217;s Servant with wine.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Please your lordship, here is the wine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<line>Flaminius, I have noted thee always wise. Here&#8217;s to thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Your lordship speaks your pleasure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<line>I have observ&#8217;d thee always for a towardly prompt spirit&#8212;give thee thy due&#8212;and one that knows what belongs to reason; and canst use the time well, if the time use thee well. Good parts in thee!</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To Servant.</stagedir>
<line>Get you gone, sirrah.</line>
<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lucullus&#8217;s Servant.</stagedir>
<line>Draw nearer, honest Flaminius. Thy lord&#8217;s a bountiful gentleman, but thou art wise, and thou know&#8217;st well enough (although thou com&#8217;st to me) that this is no time to lend money, especially upon bare friendship without security. Here&#8217;s three solidares for thee; good boy, wink at me, and say thou saw&#8217;st me not. Fare thee well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Is&#8217;t possible the world should so much differ,</line>
<line>And we alive that lived? Fly, damned baseness,</line>
<line>To him that worships thee!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Throwing the money back.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUCUL.</speaker>
<line>Ha? Now I see thou art a fool, and fit for thy master.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Lucullus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>May these add to the number that may scald thee!</line>
<line>Let molten coin be thy damnation,</line>
<line>Thou disease of a friend, and not himself!</line>
<line>Has friendship such a faint and milky heart,</line>
<line>It turns in less than two nights? O you gods!</line>
<line>I feel my master&#8217;s passion. This slave</line>
<line>Unto his honor has my lord&#8217;s meat in him;</line>
<line>Why should it thrive and turn to nutriment</line>
<line>When he is turn&#8217;d to poison?</line>
<line>O, may diseases only work upon&#8217;t!</line>
<line>And when he&#8217;s sick to death, let not that part of nature</line>
<line>Which my lord paid for, be of any power</line>
<line>To expel sickness, but prolong his hour!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A public place.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Lucius, Three Strangers, Servilius)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Three strangers tell Lucius that Timon is broke, but Lucius finds it hard to believe. He professes outrage that Lucullus refused to help him. Immediately after Lucius says that he would never refuse to help Timon out, Timon&#8217;s servant Servilius approaches and asks him for a loan. Lucius pretends that he has no money available and therefore can&#8217;t help. The strangers comment on Lucius&#8217;s hypocrisy and ingratitude.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Lucius with three Strangers.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>Who, the Lord Timon? He is my very good friend, and an honorable gentleman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>We know him for no less, though we are but strangers to him. But I can tell you one thing, my lord, and which I hear from common rumors, now Lord Timon&#8217;s happy hours are done and past, and his estate shrinks from him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>Fie, no, do not believe it; he cannot want for money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>But believe you this, my lord, that not long ago one of his men was with the Lord Lucullus to borrow so many talents, nay, urg&#8217;d extremely for&#8217;t, and show&#8217;d what necessity belong&#8217;d to&#8217;t, and yet was denied.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>How?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>I tell you, denied, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>What a strange case was that! Now before the gods, I am asham&#8217;d on&#8217;t. Denied that honorable man? There was very little honor show&#8217;d in&#8217;t. For my own part, I must needs confess, I have receiv&#8217;d some small kindnesses from him, as money, plate, jewels, and such like trifles&#8212;nothing comparing to his&#8212;yet had he mistook him and sent to me, I should ne&#8217;er have denied his occasion so many talents.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>See, by good hap, yonder&#8217;s my lord; I have sweat to see his honor. My honor&#8217;d lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>Servilius? You are kindly met, sir. Fare thee well, commend me to thy honorable virtuous lord, my very exquisite friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>May it please your honor, my lord hath sent&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>Ha? What has he sent? I am so much endear&#8217;d to that lord: he&#8217;s ever sending. How shall I thank him, think&#8217;st thou? And what has he sent now?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>H&#8217;as only sent his present occasion now, my lord; requesting your lordship to supply his instant use with so many talents.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>I know his lordship is but merry with me;</line>
<line>He cannot want fifty&#8212;five hundred talents.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>But in the mean time he wants less, my lord.</line>
<line>If his occasion were not virtuous,</line>
<line>I should not urge it half so faithfully.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>Dost thou speak seriously, Servilius?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>Upon my soul, &#8217;tis true, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<line>What a wicked beast was I to disfurnish myself against such a good time, when I might ha&#8217; shown myself honorable! How unluckily it happ&#8217;ned that I should purchase the day before for a little part, and undo a great deal of honor! Servilius, now before the gods, I am not able to do (the more beast, I say!)&#8212;I was sending to use Lord Timon myself, these gentlemen can witness; but I would not, for the wealth of Athens, I had done&#8217;t now. Commend me bountifully to his good lordship, and I hope his honor will conceive the fairest of me, because I have no power to be kind. And tell him this from me, I count it one of my greatest afflictions, say, that I cannot pleasure such an honorable gentleman. Good Servilius, will you befriend me so far as to use mine own words to him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>Yes, sir, I shall.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Calling after him.</stagedir>
<line>I&#8217;ll look you out a good turn, Servilius.&#8212;</line>
<line>True, as you said, Timon is shrunk indeed,</line>
<line>And he that&#8217;s once denied will hardly speed.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>Do you observe this, Hostilius?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. STRAN.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Ay, too well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>Why, this is the world&#8217;s soul, and just of the same piece</line>
<line>Is every flatterer&#8217;s sport. Who can call him</line>
<line>His friend that dips in the same dish? For, in</line>
<line>My knowing, Timon has been this lord&#8217;s father,</line>
<line>And kept his credit with his purse;</line>
<line>Supported his estate, nay, Timon&#8217;s money</line>
<line>Has paid his men their wages. He ne&#8217;er drinks</line>
<line>But Timon&#8217;s silver treads upon his lip,</line>
<line>And yet&#8212;O, see the monstrousness of man</line>
<line>When he looks out in an ungrateful shape!&#8212;</line>
<line>He does deny him (in respect of his)</line>
<line>What charitable men afford to beggars.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. STRAN.</speaker>
<line>Religion groans at it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. STRAN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">For mine own part,</line>
<line>I never tasted Timon in my life,</line>
<line>Nor came any of his bounties over me</line>
<line>To mark me for his friend; yet, I protest,</line>
<line>For his right noble mind, illustrious virtue,</line>
<line>And honorable carriage,</line>
<line>Had his necessity made use of me,</line>
<line>I would have put my wealth into donation,</line>
<line>And the best half should have return&#8217;d to him,</line>
<line>So much I love his heart. But I perceive</line>
<line>Men must learn now with pity to dispense,</line>
<line>For policy sits above conscience.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in Sempronius&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Timon&#8217;s Servant, Sempronius)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>One of Timon&#8217;s servants asks Sempronius to help Timon out, but Sempronius feels insulted that he was asked last, and, taking this as a slight, refuses to help as a point of honor. The servant comments on his hypocrisy, but realizes that Timon is out of people to ask for aid.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon&#8217;s Servant with Sempronius, another of Timon&#8217;s friends.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SEM.</speaker>
<line>Must he needs trouble me in&#8217;t&#8212;hum!&#8212;&#8217;bove all others?</line>
<line>He might have tried Lord Lucius or Lucullus;</line>
<line>And now Ventidius is wealthy too,</line>
<line>Whom he redeem&#8217;d from prison. All these</line>
<line>Owes their estates unto him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="6">My lord,</line>
<line>They have all been touch&#8217;d and found base metal,</line>
<line>For they have all denied him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SEM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">How? Have they denied him?</line>
<line>Has Ventidius and Lucullus denied him,</line>
<line>And does he send to me? Three? Humh!</line>
<line>It shows but little love or judgment in him.</line>
<line>Must I be his last refuge? His friends, like physicians,</line>
<line>Thrive, give him over; must I take th&#8217; cure upon me?</line>
<line>H&#8217;as much disgrac&#8217;d me in&#8217;t, I&#8217;m angry at him,</line>
<line>That might have known my place. I see no sense for&#8217;t,</line>
<line>But his occasions might have wooed me first;</line>
<line>For, in my conscience, I was the first man</line>
<line>That e&#8217;er received gift from him;</line>
<line>And does he think so backwardly of me now,</line>
<line>That I&#8217;ll requite it last? No!</line>
<line>So it may prove an argument of laughter</line>
<line>To th&#8217; rest, and &#8217;mongst lords I be thought a fool.</line>
<line>I&#8217;d rather than the worth of thrice the sum</line>
<line>H&#8217;ad sent to me first, but for my mind&#8217;s sake;</line>
<line>I&#8217;d such a courage to do him good. But now return,</line>
<line>And with their faint reply this answer join:</line>
<line>Who bates mine honor shall not know my coin.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Excellent! Your lordship&#8217;s a goodly villain. The devil knew not what he did when he made man politic; he cross&#8217;d himself by&#8217;t; and I cannot think but, in the end, the villainies of man will set him clear. How fairly this lord strives to appear foul! Takes virtuous copies to be wicked; like those that under hot ardent zeal would set whole realms on fire; of such a nature is his politic love.</line>
<line>This was my lord&#8217;s best hope, now all are fled,</line>
<line>Save only the gods. Now his friends are dead,</line>
<line>Doors, that were ne&#8217;er acquainted with their wards</line>
<line>Many a bounteous year, must be employ&#8217;d</line>
<line>Now to guard sure their master.</line>
<line>And this is all a liberal course allows:</line>
<line>Who cannot keep his wealth must keep his house.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A hall in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Varro&#8217;s two Servants, Titus, Servants of Timon&#8217;s creditors, Lucius&#8217; Servant, Hortensius, Philotus, Flaminius, Steward Flavius, Servilius, Timon)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>All of Timon&#8217;s creditors&#8217; servants throng the hall of Timon&#8217;s house, waiting for him. Flavius tries to sneak out but is recognized, and tells them bluntly that there&#8217;s no money for them here. They refuse to believe Servilius when he claims that Timon is sick, as they think this is just a trick to avoid them. Timon comes out in a rage and they press on him, and it becomes clear to them that they will not be receiving anything. They leave. Timon sends Flavius to invite all of his so-called friends to another feast. Flavius protests that there&#8217;s no money for one, but Timon tells him that he&#8217;ll manage.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Varro&#8217;s two Servants, meeting Titus and others, all servants of Timon&#8217;s creditors, to wait for his coming out. Then enter Lucius&#8217; Servant and Hortensius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Well met, good morrow, Titus and Hortensius.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>The like to you, kind Varro.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Lucius!</line>
<line>What, do we meet together?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Ay, and I think</line>
<line>One business does command us all; for mine</line>
<line>Is money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>So is theirs and ours.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Philotus.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">And, sir, Philotus too!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line>Good day at once.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Welcome, good brother.</line>
<line>What do you think the hour?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Laboring for nine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>So much?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line offset="2">Is not my lord seen yet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Not yet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line>I wonder on&#8217;t, he was wont to shine at seven.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Ay, but the days are wax&#8217;d shorter with him.</line>
<line>You must consider that a prodigal course</line>
<line>Is like the sun&#8217;s, but not like his recoverable,</line>
<line>I fear. &#8217;Tis deepest winter in Lord Timon&#8217;s purse;</line>
<line>That is, one may reach deep enough and yet</line>
<line>Find little.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line offset="3">I am of your fear for that.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll show you how t&#8217; observe a strange event.</line>
<line>Your lord sends now for money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Most true, he does.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>And he wears jewels now of Timon&#8217;s gift,</line>
<line>For which I wait for money.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line>It is against my heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Mark how strange it shows,</line>
<line>Timon in this should pay more than he owes;</line>
<line>And e&#8217;en as if your lord should wear rich jewels</line>
<line>And send for money for &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;m weary of this charge, the gods can witness.</line>
<line>I know my lord hath spent of Timon&#8217;s wealth,</line>
<line>And now ingratitude makes it worse than stealth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Yes, mine&#8217;s three thousand crowns; what&#8217;s yours?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Five thousand mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis much deep, and it should seem by th&#8217; sum</line>
<line>Your master&#8217;s confidence was above mine,</line>
<line>Else surely his had equall&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Flaminius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>One of Lord Timon&#8217;s men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Flaminius? Sir, a word. Pray is my lord ready to come forth?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>No, indeed he is not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>We attend his lordship; pray signify so much.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>I need not tell him that, he knows you are too diligent.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Steward Flavius in a cloak, muffled.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Ha! Is not that his steward muffled so?</line>
<line>He goes away in a cloud; call him, call him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>Do you hear, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>By your leave, sir&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>What do ye ask of me, my friend?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>We wait for certain money here, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="8">Ay,</line>
<line>If money were as certain as your waiting,</line>
<line>&#8217;Twere sure enough.</line>
<line>Why then preferr&#8217;d you not your sums and bills</line>
<line>When your false masters eat of my lord&#8217;s meat?</line>
<line>Then they could smile, and fawn upon his debts,</line>
<line>And take down th&#8217; int&#8217;rest into their glutt&#8217;nous maws.</line>
<line>You do yourselves but wrong to stir me up,</line>
<line>Let me pass quietly.</line>
<line>Believe&#8217;t, my lord and I have made an end:</line>
<line>I have no more to reckon, he to spend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Ay, but this answer will not serve.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>If &#8217;twill not serve, &#8217;tis not so base as you,</line>
<line>For you serve knaves.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>How? What does his cashier&#8217;d worship mutter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>No matter what, he&#8217;s poor, and that&#8217;s revenge enough. Who can speak broader than he that has no house to put his head in? Such may rail against great buildings.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>O, here&#8217;s Servilius; now we shall know some answer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line>If I might beseech you, gentlemen, to repair some other hour, I should derive much from&#8217;t; for take&#8217;t of my soul, my lord leans wondrously to discontent. His comfortable temper has forsook him, he&#8217;s much out of health, and keeps his chamber.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Many do keep their chambers are not sick;</line>
<line>And if it be so far beyond his health,</line>
<line>Methinks he should the sooner pay his debts,</line>
<line>And make a clear way to the gods.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Good gods!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>We cannot take this for answer, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="action">Within.</stagedir>
<line>Servilius, help! My lord, my lord!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon in a rage, Flaminius following.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What, are my doors oppos&#8217;d against my passage?</line>
<line>Have I been ever free, and must my house</line>
<line>Be my retentive enemy? My jail?</line>
<line>The place which I have feasted, does it now</line>
<line>(Like all mankind) show me an iron heart?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Put in now, Titus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>My lord, here is my bill.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Here&#8217;s mine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line>And mine, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH 1. VAR. SERV. AND 2. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>And ours, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHI.</speaker>
<line>All our bills.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Knock me down with &#8217;em, cleave me to the girdle!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Alas, my lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Cut my heart in sums.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIT.</speaker>
<line>Mine, fifty talents.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Tell out my blood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>LUC. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Five thousand crowns, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Five thousand drops pays that. What yours? And yours?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>My lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. VAR. SERV.</speaker>
<line>My lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Tear me, take me, and the gods fall upon you!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Timon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>HOR.</speaker>
<line>Faith, I perceive our masters may throw their caps at their money. These debts may well be call&#8217;d desperate ones, for a madman owes &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon and Flavius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>They have e&#8217;en put my breath from me, the slaves.</line>
<line>Creditors? Devils!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>My dear lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What if it should be so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>My lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll have it so. My steward!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Here, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>So fitly? Go, bid all my friends again,</line>
<line>Lucius, Lucullus, and Sempronius&#8212;all.</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll once more feast the rascals.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="7">O my lord,</line>
<line>You only speak from your distracted soul;</line>
<line>There&#8217;s not so much left to furnish out</line>
<line>A moderate table.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Be it not in thy care;</line>
<line>Go, I charge thee, invite them all, let in the tide</line>
<line>Of knaves once more; my cook and I&#8217;ll provide.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="5">
<scenetitle>Scene 5</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. The Senate House.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Senators, Alcibiades, Attendants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Alcibiades pleads before the Senate for the life of one of his soldiers who has been condemned to death, arguing that his crime was committed in the heat of the moment and that sending him back to war would allow him to redeem himself. The Senators refuse all his pleading, and when he continues and goes too far, they exile him. Furious, he plans to take his soldiers and wage war against Athens on his own account.</scenedescription>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter three Senators at one door, Alcibiades meeting them, with Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>My lord, you have my voice to&#8217;t; the fault&#8217;s</line>
<line>Bloody; &#8217;tis necessary he should die.</line>
<line>Nothing emboldens sin so much as mercy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>Most true; the law shall bruise &#8217;em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Honor, health, and compassion to the Senate!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>Now, captain?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I am an humble suitor to your virtues;</line>
<line>For pity is the virtue of the law,</line>
<line>And none but tyrants use it cruelly.</line>
<line>It pleases time and fortune to lie heavy</line>
<line>Upon a friend of mine, who in hot blood</line>
<line>Hath stepp&#8217;d into the law, which is past depth</line>
<line>To those that (without heed) do plunge into&#8217;t.</line>
<line>He is a man (setting his fate aside)</line>
<line>Of comely virtues;</line>
<line>Nor did he soil the fact with cowardice</line>
<line>(An honor in him which buys out his fault),</line>
<line>But with a noble fury and fair spirit,</line>
<line>Seeing his reputation touch&#8217;d to death,</line>
<line>He did oppose his foe;</line>
<line>And with such sober and unnoted passion</line>
<line>He did behoove his anger, ere &#8217;twas spent,</line>
<line>As if he had but prov&#8217;d an argument.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>You undergo too strict a paradox,</line>
<line>Striving to make an ugly deed look fair.</line>
<line>Your words have took such pains as if they labor&#8217;d</line>
<line>To bring manslaughter into form, and set quarrelling</line>
<line>Upon the head of valor; which indeed</line>
<line>Is valor misbegot, and came into the world</line>
<line>When sects and factions were newly born.</line>
<line>He&#8217;s truly valiant that can wisely suffer</line>
<line>The worst that man can breathe, and make his wrongs</line>
<line>His outsides, to wear them like his raiment, carelessly,</line>
<line>And ne&#8217;er prefer his injuries to his heart,</line>
<line>To bring it into danger.</line>
<line>If wrongs be evils and enforce us kill,</line>
<line>What folly &#8217;tis to hazard life for ill!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>My lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="2">You cannot make gross sins look clear;</line>
<line>To revenge is no valor, but to bear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>My lords, then, under favor, pardon me</line>
<line>If I speak like a captain.</line>
<line>Why do fond men expose themselves to battle,</line>
<line>And not endure all threats? Sleep upon&#8217;t,</line>
<line>And let the foes quietly cut their throats</line>
<line>Without repugnancy? If there be</line>
<line>Such valor in the bearing, what make we</line>
<line>Abroad? Why then, women are more valiant</line>
<line>That stay at home, if bearing carry it;</line>
<line>And the ass more captain than the lion, the fellow</line>
<line>Loaden with irons wiser than the judge,</line>
<line>If wisdom be in suffering. O my lords,</line>
<line>As you are great, be pitifully good.</line>
<line>Who cannot condemn rashness in cold blood?</line>
<line>To kill, I grant, is sin&#8217;s extremest gust,</line>
<line>But in defense, by mercy, &#8217;tis most just.</line>
<line>To be in anger is impiety;</line>
<line>But who is man that is not angry?</line>
<line>Weigh but the crime with this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>You breathe in vain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="4">In vain? His service done</line>
<line>At Lacedaemon and Byzantium</line>
<line>Were a sufficient briber for his life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>What&#8217;s that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="3">Why, I say, my lords, h&#8217;as done fair service,</line>
<line>And slain in fight many of your enemies.</line>
<line>How full of valor did he bear himself</line>
<line>In the last conflict, and made plenteous wounds!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>He has made too much plenty with &#8217;em.</line>
<line>He&#8217;s a sworn rioter; he has a sin that often</line>
<line>Drowns him and takes his valor prisoner.</line>
<line>If there were no foes, that were enough</line>
<line>To overcome him. In that beastly fury</line>
<line>He has been known to commit outrages</line>
<line>And cherish factions. &#8217;Tis inferr&#8217;d to us,</line>
<line>His days are foul and his drink dangerous.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>He dies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="2">Hard fate! He might have died in war.</line>
<line>My lords, if not for any parts in him&#8212;</line>
<line>Though his right arm might purchase his own time</line>
<line>And be in debt to none&#8212;yet more to move you,</line>
<line>Take my deserts to his, and join &#8217;em both;</line>
<line>And for I know your reverend ages love</line>
<line>Security, I&#8217;ll pawn my victories, all</line>
<line>My honor to you, upon his good returns.</line>
<line>If by this crime he owes the law his life,</line>
<line>Why, let the war receive&#8217;t in valiant gore,</line>
<line>For law is strict, and war is nothing more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>We are for law, he dies, urge it no more</line>
<line>On height of our displeasure. Friend, or brother,</line>
<line>He forfeits his own blood that spills another.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Must it be so? It must not be. My lords,</line>
<line>I do beseech you know me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>How?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Call me to your remembrances.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="7">What?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I cannot think but your age has forgot me,</line>
<line>It could not else be I should prove so base</line>
<line>To sue and be denied such common grace.</line>
<line>My wounds ache at you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Do you dare our anger?</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis in few words, but spacious in effect:</line>
<line>We banish thee forever.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Banish me?</line>
<line>Banish your dotage, banish usury,</line>
<line>That makes the Senate ugly!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>If after two days&#8217; shine Athens contain thee,</line>
<line>Attend our weightier judgment. And not to swell our spirit,</line>
<line>He shall be executed presently.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Senators.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Now the gods keep you old enough that you may live</line>
<line>Only in bone, that none may look on you!</line>
<line>I&#8217;m worse than mad. I have kept back their foes,</line>
<line>While they have told their money, and let out</line>
<line>Their coin upon large interest&#8212;I myself</line>
<line>Rich only in large hurts. All those, for this?</line>
<line>Is this the balsom that the usuring Senate</line>
<line>Pours into captains&#8217; wounds? Banishment!</line>
<line>It comes not ill; I hate not to be banish&#8217;d,</line>
<line>It is a cause worthy my spleen and fury,</line>
<line>That I may strike at Athens. I&#8217;ll cheer up</line>
<line>My discontented troops, and lay for hearts.</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis honor with most lands to be at odds;</line>
<line>Soldiers should brook as little wrongs as gods.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="6">
<scenetitle>Scene 6</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A banqueting-room in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Servants, Senators, Lords, Timon, Attendants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Timon&#8217;s false friends arrive at Timon&#8217;s, convincing themselves that Timon&#8217;s requests for help the other day were only to test them. They apologize to Timon for not sending him any money, all explaining that they had no ready money on them at the time. Timon tells them to think nothing of it and seats them. He speaks a grace, and then uncovers the dishes, which have nothing in them but warm water and stones. He throws the water at them while cursing at them and driving them out of his house. Once he has gone, they sneak back in to pick up their belongings, including, in one case, an expensive jewel that Timon gave to him the other day. They assure each other that Timon is clearly mad.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="action">Music. Tables set out: Servants attending.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="enter">Enter divers friends of Timon, Senators and other Lords, at several doors.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>The good time of day to you, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I also wish it to you. I think this honorable lord did but try us this other day.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Upon that were my thoughts tiring when we encount&#8217;red. I hope it is not so low with him as he made it seem in the trial of his several friends.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>It should not be, by the persuasion of his new feasting.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I should think so. He hath sent me an earnest inviting, which many my near occasions did urge me to put off; but he hath conjur&#8217;d me beyond them, and I must needs appear.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>In like manner was I in debt to my importunate business, but he would not hear my excuse. I am sorry, when he sent to borrow of me, that my provision was out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I am sick of that grief too, as I understand how all things go.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Every man here&#8217;s so. What would he have borrow&#8217;d of you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>A thousand pieces.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>A thousand pieces?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>What of you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>He sent to me, sir&#8212;Here he comes.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon and Attendants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>With all my heart, gentlemen both; and how fare you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Ever at the best, hearing well of your lordship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>The swallow follows not summer more willing than we your lordship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line> Nor more willingly leaves winter, such summer birds are men.&#8212;Gentlemen, our dinner will not recompense this long stay; feast your ears with the music awhile, if they will fare so harshly o&#8217; th&#8217; trumpet&#8217;s sound; we shall to&#8217;t presently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I hope it remains not unkindly with your lordship that I return&#8217;d you an empty messenger.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>O, sir, let it not trouble you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>My noble lord&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ah, my good friend, what cheer?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The banquet brought in.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>My most honorable lord, I am e&#8217;en sick of shame that, when your lordship this other day sent to me, I was so unfortunate a beggar.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Think not on&#8217;t, sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>If you had sent but two hours before&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Let it not cumber your better remembrance.&#8212;Come, bring in all together!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>All cover&#8217;d dishes!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Royal cheer, I warrant you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Doubt not that, if money and the season can yield it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>How do you? What&#8217;s the news?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Alcibiades is banish&#8217;d: hear you of it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH 1. LORD. AND 2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Alcibiades banish&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis so, be sure of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>How? How?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I pray you, upon what?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>My worthy friends, will you draw near?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll tell you more anon. Here&#8217;s a noble feast toward.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>This is the old man still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Will&#8217;t hold? Will&#8217;t hold?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>It does; but time will&#8212;and so&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I do conceive.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Each man to his stool, with that spur as he would to the lip of his mistress; your diet shall be in all places alike. Make not a city feast of it, to let the meat cool ere we can agree upon the first place; sit, sit. The gods require our thanks.</line>
<line>You great benefactors, sprinkle our society with thankfulness. For your own gifts, make yourselves prais&#8217;d; but reserve still to give, lest your deities be despis&#8217;d. Lend to each man enough, that one need not lend to another; for were your godheads to borrow of men, men would forsake the gods. Make the meat be belov&#8217;d more than the man that gives it. Let no assembly of twenty be without a score of villains. If there sit twelve women at the table, let a dozen of them be&#8212;as they are. The rest of your fees, O gods&#8212;the senators of Athens, together with the common lag of people&#8212;what is amiss in them, you gods, make suitable for destruction. For these my present friends, as they are to me nothing, so in nothing bless them, and to nothing are they welcome.</line>
<line>Uncover, dogs, and lap!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The dishes are uncovered and seen to be full of warm water.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOME SPEAK.</speaker>
<line>What does his lordship mean?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SOME OTHER.</speaker>
<line>I know not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>May you a better feast never behold,</line>
<line>You knot of mouth-friends! Smoke and lukewarm water</line>
<line>Is your perfection. This is Timon&#8217;s last,</line>
<line>Who, stuck and spangled with your flatteries,</line>
<line>Washes it off, and sprinkles in your faces</line>
<line>Your reeking villainy.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Throwing the water in their faces.</stagedir>
<line>Live loath&#8217;d, and long,</line>
<line>Most smiling, smooth, detested parasites,</line>
<line>Courteous destroyers, affable wolves, meek bears,</line>
<line>You fools of fortune, trencher-friends, time&#8217;s flies,</line>
<line>Cap-and-knee slaves, vapors, and minute-jacks!</line>
<line>Of man and beast the infinite malady</line>
<line>Crust you quite o&#8217;er! What, dost thou go?</line>
<line>Soft, take thy physic first&#8212;thou too&#8212;and thou;</line>
<line>Stay, I will lend thee money, borrow none.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Throws the dishes at them, and drives them out.</stagedir>
<line>What? All in motion? Henceforth be no feast</line>
<line>Whereat a villain&#8217;s not a welcome guest.</line>
<line>Burn house! Sink Athens! Henceforth hated be</line>
<line>Of Timon man and all humanity!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Senators with other Lords again.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>How now, my lords?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Know you the quality of Lord Timon&#8217;s fury?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Push, did you see my cap?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4. LORD.</speaker>
<line>I have lost my gown.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>He&#8217;s but a mad lord, and nought but humors sways him. He gave me a jewel th&#8217; other day, and now he has beat it out of my hat. Did you see my jewel?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Did you see my cap?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Here &#8217;tis,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Here lies my gown.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Let&#8217;s make no stay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. LORD.</speaker>
<line>Lord Timon&#8217;s mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. LORD.</speaker>
<line offset="4">I feel&#8217;t upon my bones.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4. LORD.</speaker>
<line>One day he gives us diamonds, next day stones.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt the Senators and other Lords.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="4">
<acttitle>Act 4</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Outside the walls of Athens.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Timon)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Timon has left Athens, and as he walks out of it he takes the time to curse its walls and all within it, wishing that anarchy will descend on it, with all good things lost and only evil holding sway.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Let me look back upon thee. O thou wall</line>
<line>That girdles in those wolves, dive in the earth,</line>
<line>And fence not Athens! Matrons, turn incontinent!</line>
<line>Obedience, fail in children! Slaves and fools,</line>
<line>Pluck the grave wrinkled Senate from the bench,</line>
<line>And minister in their steads! To general filths</line>
<line>Convert o&#8217; th&#8217; instant, green virginity!</line>
<line>Do&#8217;t in your parents&#8217; eyes! Bankrupts, hold fast;</line>
<line>Rather than render back, out with your knives,</line>
<line>And cut your trusters&#8217; throats! Bound servants, steal;</line>
<line>Large-handed robbers your grave masters are,</line>
<line>And pill by law. Maid, to thy master&#8217;s bed,</line>
<line>Thy mistress is o&#8217; th&#8217; brothel! Son of sixteen,</line>
<line>Pluck the lin&#8217;d crutch from thy old limping sire,</line>
<line>With it beat out his brains! Piety, and fear,</line>
<line>Religion to the gods, peace, justice, truth,</line>
<line>Domestic awe, night-rest, and neighborhood,</line>
<line>Instruction, manners, mysteries, and trades,</line>
<line>Degrees, observances, customs, and laws,</line>
<line>Decline to your confounding contraries;</line>
<line>And yet confusion live! Plagues incident to men,</line>
<line>Your potent and infectious fevers heap</line>
<line>On Athens, ripe for stroke! Thou cold sciatica,</line>
<line>Cripple our senators, that their limbs may halt</line>
<line>As lamely as their manners! Lust, and liberty,</line>
<line>Creep in the minds and marrows of our youth,</line>
<line>That &#8217;gainst the stream of virtue they may strive,</line>
<line>And drown themselves in riot! Itches, blains,</line>
<line>Sow all th&#8217; Athenian bosoms, and their crop</line>
<line>Be general leprosy! Breath, infect breath,</line>
<line>That their society (as their friendship) may</line>
<line>Be merely poison! Nothing I&#8217;ll bear from thee</line>
<line>But nakedness, thou detestable town!</line>
<line>Take thou that too, with multiplying bans!</line>
<line>Timon will to the woods, where he shall find</line>
<line>Th&#8217; unkindest beast more kinder than mankind.</line>
<line>The gods confound (hear me, you good gods all)</line>
<line>Th&#8217; Athenians both within and out that wall!</line>
<line>And grant, as Timon grows, his hate may grow</line>
<line>To the whole race of mankind, high and low!</line>
<line>Amen.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Athens. A room in Timon&#8217;s house.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Steward Flavius, Timon&#8217;s Servants)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Timon&#8217;s former servants bid farewell to one another, remembering what a good master he was. Flavius divides up his money between them, and they all agree to remain friends. Flavius resolves to find Timon and serve him for as long as he can.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Steward Flavius with two of Timon&#8217;s Servants, Flaminius and Servilius.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line>Hear you, Master Steward, where&#8217;s our master?</line>
<line>Are we undone, cast off, nothing remaining?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Alack, my fellows, what should I say to you?</line>
<line>Let me be recorded by the righteous gods,</line>
<line>I am as poor as you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Such a house broke?</line>
<line>So noble a master fall&#8217;n, all gone, and not</line>
<line>One friend to take his fortune by the arm,</line>
<line>And go along with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>SER.</speaker>
<line offset="5">As we do turn our backs</line>
<line>From our companion thrown into his grave,</line>
<line>So his familiars to his buried fortunes</line>
<line>Slink all away, leave their false vows with him,</line>
<line>Like empty purses pick&#8217;d; and his poor self,</line>
<line>A dedicated beggar to the air,</line>
<line>With his disease of all-shunn&#8217;d poverty,</line>
<line>Walks, like contempt, alone. More of our fellows.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter other Servants.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>All broken implements of a ruin&#8217;d house.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM. SERV.</speaker>
<line>Yet do our hearts wear Timon&#8217;s livery,</line>
<line>That see I by our faces; we are fellows still,</line>
<line>Serving alike in sorrow. Leak&#8217;d is our bark,</line>
<line>And we, poor mates, stand on the dying deck,</line>
<line>Hearing the surges threat; we must all part</line>
<line>Into this sea of air.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Good fellows all,</line>
<line>The latest of my wealth I&#8217;ll share amongst you.</line>
<line>Where ever we shall meet, for Timon&#8217;s sake</line>
<line>Let&#8217;s yet be fellows. Let&#8217;s shake our heads, and say,</line>
<line>As &#8217;twere a knell unto our master&#8217;s fortunes,</line>
<line>&#8220;We have seen better days.&#8221; Let each take some;</line>

<stagedir type="action">Giving them money.</stagedir>
<line>Nay, put out all your hands. Not one word more:</line>
<line>Thus part we rich in sorrow, parting poor.</line>

<stagedir type="action">Embrace, and part several ways.</stagedir>
<line>O, the fierce wretchedness that glory brings us!</line>
<line>Who would not wish to be from wealth exempt,</line>
<line>Since riches point to misery and contempt?</line>
<line>Who would be so mock&#8217;d with glory, or to live</line>
<line>But in a dream of friendship,</line>
<line>To have his pomp, and all what state compounds,</line>
<line>But only painted, like his varnish&#8217;d friends?</line>
<line>Poor honest lord, brought low by his own heart,</line>
<line>Undone by goodness! Strange, unusual blood,</line>
<line>When man&#8217;s worst sin is, he does too much good!</line>
<line>Who then dares to be half so kind again?</line>
<line>For bounty, that makes gods, do still mar men.</line>
<line>My dearest lord, blest to be most accurs&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Rich only to be wretched, thy great fortunes</line>
<line>Are made thy chief afflictions. Alas, kind lord,</line>
<line>He&#8217;s flung in rage from this ingrateful seat</line>
<line>Of monstrous friends; nor has he with him to</line>
<line>Supply his life, or that which can command it.</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll follow and inquire him out.</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll ever serve his mind with my best will;</line>
<line>Whilst I have gold, I&#8217;ll be his steward still.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Woods and cave near the seashore.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Timon, Alcibiades, Phrynia and Timandra, Apemantus, Bandits, Steward Flavius)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Timon is living in a cave in the woods; he curses the world as he digs to find roots to eat. Instead, he comes across a bag of gold. He hides it again as Alcibiades, his two mistresses and his army march in. Alcibiades does not at first recognize Timon, whose ruin he has not heard of. He tries to do Timon some good, but the misanthrope merely snarls at him and insults him. Timon refuses to take Alcibiades&#8217;s gold, though he wishes him luck in his war against Athens, though hoping that once Alcibiades has vanquished he&#8217;ll be destroyed as well. Timon offers Alcibiades some of the gold he found to pay the soldiers. The two women crawlingly ask him for gold, and he gives it to them while calling them whores and telling them to infect all humanity with their diseases. Alcibiades and his company leave, to Timon&#8217;s relief. He continues digging for food, and finds a root just as Apemantus arrives, looking for him. Aemantus accuses Timon of being a poseur and of aping him, and counsels him to become a flatterer instead. They rival each other in their loathing of mankind, and hatred of one another. Apemantus finally leaves, but to revenge himself announces that he&#8217;ll tell everyone that Timon has gold, so that he&#8217;ll never be left alone. A group of thieves soon arrive to steal Timon&#8217;s gold, but he gives them a sermon on why thieving is good and encourages them to engage in wholesale looting. They are so disturbed by his rant that they decide to become honest men, and leave. Flavius arrives, having finally found Timon. He is distressed at Timon&#8217;s pitiable state and insists that he still wants to serve his former master. Timon admits that there may be such a thing as an honest man, and excepts him from his misanthropic view of humanity, but still offers him gold on the condition that he will live away from the rest of mankind. Flavius asks to be allowed to stay with Timon, but Timon refuses.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon in the woods.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>O blessed breeding sun, draw from the earth</line>
<line>Rotten humidity; below thy sister&#8217;s orb</line>
<line>Infect the air! Twinn&#8217;d brothers of one womb,</line>
<line>Whose procreation, residence, and birth</line>
<line>Scarce is dividant, touch them with several fortunes,</line>
<line>The greater scorns the lesser. Not nature</line>
<line>(To whom all sores lay siege) can bear great fortune</line>
<line>But by contempt of nature.</line>
<line>Raise me this beggar, and deny&#8217;t that lord,</line>
<line>The senator shall bear contempt hereditary,</line>
<line>The beggar native honor.</line>
<line>It is the paster lards the brother&#8217;s sides,</line>
<line>The want that makes him lean. Who dares? Who dares</line>
<line>In purity of manhood stand upright</line>
<line>And say, &#8220;This man&#8217;s a flatterer&#8221;? If one be,</line>
<line>So are they all; for every grize of fortune</line>
<line>Is smooth&#8217;d by that below. The learned pate</line>
<line>Ducks to the golden fool. All&#8217;s obliquy;</line>
<line>There&#8217;s nothing level in our cursed natures</line>
<line>But direct villainy. Therefore be abhorr&#8217;d</line>
<line>All feasts, societies, and throngs of men!</line>
<line>His semblable, yea, himself, Timon disdains;</line>
<line>Destruction fang mankind! Earth, yield me roots!</line>

<stagedir type="action">Digging.</stagedir>
<line>Who seeks for better of thee, sauce his palate</line>
<line>With thy most operant poison! What is here?</line>
<line>Gold? Yellow, glittering, precious gold?</line>
<line>No, gods, I am no idle votarist;</line>
<line>Roots, you clear heavens! Thus much of this will make</line>
<line>Black white, foul fair, wrong right,</line>
<line>Base noble, old young, coward valiant.</line>
<line>Ha, you gods! Why this? What this, you gods? Why, this</line>
<line>Will lug your priests and servants from your sides,</line>
<line>Pluck stout men&#8217;s pillows from below their heads.</line>
<line>This yellow slave</line>
<line>Will knit and break religions, bless th&#8217; accurs&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Make the hoar leprosy ador&#8217;d, place thieves,</line>
<line>And give them title, knee, and approbation</line>
<line>With senators on the bench. This is it</line>
<line>That makes the wappen&#8217;d widow wed again;</line>
<line>She, whom the spittle-house and ulcerous sores</line>
<line>Would cast the gorge at, this embalms and spices</line>
<line>To th&#8217; April day again. Come, damn&#8217;d earth,</line>
<line>Thou common whore of mankind, that puts odds</line>
<line>Among the rout of nations, I will make thee</line>
<line>Do thy right nature.</line>

<stagedir type="action">March afar off.</stagedir>
<line>Ha? A drum? Th&#8217; art quick,</line>
<line>But yet I&#8217;ll bury thee; thou&#8217;t go, strong thief,</line>
<line>When gouty keepers of thee cannot stand.</line>
<line>Nay, stay thou out for earnest.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Keeping some gold.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Alcibiades, with Drum and Fife, in warlike manner, and Phrynia and Timandra.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>What art thou there? Speak.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>A beast, as thou art. The canker gnaw thy heart,</line>
<line>For showing me again the eyes of man!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>What is thy name? Is man so hateful to thee,</line>
<line>That art thyself a man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I am Misanthropos, and hate mankind.</line>
<line>For thy part, I do wish thou wert a dog,</line>
<line>That I might love thee something.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="7">I know thee well;</line>
<line>But in thy fortunes am unlearn&#8217;d and strange.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I know thee too, and more than that I know thee</line>
<line>I not desire to know. Follow thy drum,</line>
<line>With man&#8217;s blood paint the ground, gules, gules,</line>
<line>Religious canons, civil laws are cruel;</line>
<line>Then what should war be? This fell whore of thine</line>
<line>Hath in her more destruction than thy sword,</line>
<line>For all her cherubin look.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PHRY.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Thy lips rot off!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I will not kiss thee, then the rot returns</line>
<line>To thine own lips again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>How came the noble Timon to this change?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>As the moon does, by wanting light to give:</line>
<line>But then renew I could not, like the moon;</line>
<line>There were no suns to borrow of.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Noble Timon,</line>
<line>What friendship may I do thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">None, but to</line>
<line>Maintain my opinion.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="4">What is it, Timon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Promise me friendship, but perform none. If thou wilt not promise, the gods plague thee, for thou art a man! If thou dost perform, confound thee, for thou art a man!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I have heard in some sort of thy miseries.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Thou saw&#8217;st them, when I had prosperity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I see them now, then was a blessed time.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>As thine is now, held with a brace of harlots.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIMAN.</speaker>
<line>Is this th&#8217; Athenian minion, whom the world</line>
<line>Voic&#8217;d so regardfully?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Art thou Timandra?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIMAN.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Be a whore still. They love thee not that use thee;</line>
<line>Give them diseases, leaving with thee their lust.</line>
<line>Make use of thy salt hours, season the slaves</line>
<line>For tubs and baths, bring down rose-cheek&#8217;d youth</line>
<line>To the tub-fast and the diet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIMAN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Hang thee, monster!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Pardon him, sweet Timandra, for his wits</line>
<line>Are drown&#8217;d and lost in his calamities.</line>
<line>I have but little gold of late, brave Timon,</line>
<line>The want whereof doth daily make revolt</line>
<line>In my penurious band. I have heard, and griev&#8217;d,</line>
<line>How cursed Athens, mindless of thy worth,</line>
<line>Forgetting thy great deeds when neighbor states,</line>
<line>But for thy sword and fortune, trod upon them&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I prithee beat thy drum and get thee gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I am thy friend, and pity thee, dear Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>How dost thou pity him whom thou dost trouble?</line>
<line>I had rather be alone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Why, fare thee well;</line>
<line>Here is some gold for thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Keep it, I cannot eat it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>When I have laid proud Athens on a heap&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Warr&#8217;st thou &#8217;gainst Athens?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Ay, Timon, and have cause.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>The gods confound them all in thy conquest,</line>
<line>And thee after, when thou hast conquer&#8217;d!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Why me, Timon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">That by killing of villains</line>
<line>Thou wast born to conquer my country.</line>
<line>Put up thy gold. Go on&#8212;here&#8217;s gold&#8212;go on;</line>
<line>Be as a planetary plague when Jove</line>
<line>Will o&#8217;er some high-vic&#8217;d city hang his poison</line>
<line>In the sick air. Let not thy sword skip one.</line>
<line>Pity not honor&#8217;d age for his white beard,</line>
<line>He is an usurer. Strike me the counterfeit matron,</line>
<line>It is her habit only that is honest,</line>
<line>Herself&#8217;s a bawd. Let not the virgin&#8217;s cheek</line>
<line>Make soft thy trenchant sword; for those milk paps,</line>
<line>That through the window-bars bore at men&#8217;s eyes,</line>
<line>Are not within the leaf of pity writ,</line>
<line>But set them down horrible traitors. Spare not the babe,</line>
<line>Whose dimpled smiles from fools exhaust their mercy;</line>
<line>Think it a bastard, whom the oracle</line>
<line>Hath doubtfully pronounc&#8217;d the throat shall cut,</line>
<line>And mince it sans remorse. Swear against objects,</line>
<line>Put armor on thine ears and on thine eyes,</line>
<line>Whose proof nor yells of mothers, maids, nor babes,</line>
<line>Nor sight of priests in holy vestments bleeding,</line>
<line>Shall pierce a jot. There&#8217;s gold to pay thy soldiers,</line>
<line>Make large confusion; and thy fury spent,</line>
<line>Confounded be thyself! Speak not, be gone.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Hast thou gold yet? I&#8217;ll take the gold thou givest me,</line>
<line>Not all thy counsel.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Dost thou, or dost thou not, heaven&#8217;s curse upon thee!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.</speaker>
<line>Give us some gold, good Timon; hast thou more?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Enough to make a whore forswear her trade,</line>
<line>And to make whores, a bawd. Hold up, you sluts,</line>
<line>Your aprons mountant. You are not oathable,</line>
<line>Although I know You&#8217;ll swear, terribly swear</line>
<line>Into strong shudders and to heavenly agues</line>
<line>Th&#8217; immortal gods that hear you. Spare your oaths;</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll trust to your conditions, be whores still.</line>
<line>And he whose pious breath seeks to convert you,</line>
<line>Be strong in whore, allure him, burn him up,</line>
<line>Let your close fire predominate his smoke,</line>
<line>And be no turncoats; yet may your pains six months</line>
<line>Be quite contrary. And thatch your poor thin roofs</line>
<line>With burdens of the dead&#8212;some that were hang&#8217;d,</line>
<line>No matter; wear them, betray with them. Whore still,</line>
<line>Paint till a horse may mire upon your face:</line>
<line>A pox of wrinkles!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Well, more gold&#8212;what then?</line>
<line>Believe&#8217;t that we&#8217;ll do any thing for gold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Consumptions sow</line>
<line>In hollow bones of man, strike their sharp shins,</line>
<line>And mar men&#8217;s spurring. Crack the lawyer&#8217;s voice,</line>
<line>That he may never more false title plead,</line>
<line>Nor sound his quillets shrilly; hoar the flamen,</line>
<line>That scolds against the quality of flesh</line>
<line>And not believes himself. Down with the nose,</line>
<line>Down with it flat; take the bridge quite away</line>
<line>Of him that, his particular to foresee,</line>
<line>Smells from the general weal. Make curl&#8217;d-pate ruffians bald,</line>
<line>And let the unscarr&#8217;d braggarts of the war</line>
<line>Derive some pain from you. Plague all,</line>
<line>That your activity may defeat and quell</line>
<line>The source of all erection. There&#8217;s more gold.</line>
<line>Do you damn others, and let this damn you,</line>
<line>And ditches grave you all!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.</speaker>
<line>More counsel with more money, bounteous Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>More whore, more mischief first; I have given you earnest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Strike up the drum towards Athens! Farewell, Timon!</line>
<line>If I thrive well, I&#8217;ll visit thee again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>If I hope well, I&#8217;ll never see thee more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>I never did thee harm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Yes, thou spok&#8217;st well of me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Call&#8217;st thou that harm?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Men daily find it. Get thee away, and take</line>
<line>Thy beagles with thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="4">We but offend him. Strike!</line>
</speech>
<stagedir type="exit">Drum beats. Exeunt Alcibiades, Phrynia, and Timandra.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>That nature being sick of man&#8217;s unkindness</line>
<line>Should yet be hungry! Common mother, thou</line>

<stagedir type="action">Digging.</stagedir>
<line>Whose womb unmeasurable and infinite breast</line>
<line>Teems and feeds all; whose self-same mettle,</line>
<line>Whereof thy proud child (arrogant man) is puff&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Engenders the black toad and adder blue,</line>
<line>The gilded newt and eyeless venom&#8217;d worm,</line>
<line>With all th&#8217; abhorred births below crisp heaven</line>
<line>Whereon Hyperion&#8217;s quick&#8217;ning fire doth shine:</line>
<line>Yield him who all the human sons do hate,</line>
<line>From forth thy plenteous bosom, one poor root!</line>
<line>Ensear thy fertile and conceptious womb,</line>
<line>Let it no more bring out ingrateful man!</line>
<line>Go great with tigers, dragons, wolves, and bears,</line>
<line>Teem with new monsters, whom thy upward face</line>
<line>Hath to the marbled mansion all above</line>
<line>Never presented!&#8212;O, a root, dear thanks!&#8212;</line>
<line>Dry up thy marrows, vines, and plough-torn leas,</line>
<line>Whereof ingrateful man, with liquorish draughts</line>
<line>And morsels unctious, greases his pure mind,</line>
<line>That from it all consideration slips&#8212;</line>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Apemantus.</stagedir>
<line>More man? Plague, plague!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I was directed hither. Men report</line>
<line>Thou dost affect my manners, and dost use them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis then, because thou dost not keep a dog,</line>
<line>Whom I would imitate. Consumption catch thee!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>This is in thee a nature but infected,</line>
<line>A poor unmanly melancholy sprung</line>
<line>From change of future. Why this spade? This place?</line>
<line>This slave-like habit? And these looks of care?</line>
<line>Thy flatterers yet wear silk, drink wine, lie soft,</line>
<line>Hug their diseas&#8217;d perfumes, and have forgot</line>
<line>That ever Timon was. Shame not these woods</line>
<line>By putting on the cunning of a carper.</line>
<line>Be thou a flatterer now, and seek to thrive</line>
<line>By that which has undone thee; hinge thy knee,</line>
<line>And let his very breath whom thou&#8217;lt observe</line>
<line>Blow off thy cap; praise his most vicious strain,</line>
<line>And call it excellent. Thou wast told thus;</line>
<line>Thou gav&#8217;st thine ears (like tapsters that bade welcome)</line>
<line>To knaves and all approachers. &#8217;Tis most just</line>
<line>That thou turn rascal; hadst thou wealth again,</line>
<line>Rascals should have&#8217;t. Do not assume my likeness.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Were I like thee, I&#8217;d throw away myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou hast cast away thyself, being like thyself,</line>
<line>A madman so long, now a fool. What, think&#8217;st</line>
<line>That the bleak air, thy boisterous chamberlain,</line>
<line>Will put thy shirt on warm? Will these moist trees,</line>
<line>That have outliv&#8217;d the eagle, page thy heels</line>
<line>And skip when thou point&#8217;st out? Will the cold brook,</line>
<line>Candied with ice, caudle thy morning taste</line>
<line>To cure thy o&#8217;ernight&#8217;s surfeit? Call the creatures</line>
<line>Whose naked natures live in all the spite</line>
<line>Of wreakful heaven, whose bare unhoused trunks,</line>
<line>To the conflicting elements expos&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Answer mere nature; bid them flatter thee.</line>
<line>O, thou shalt find&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">A fool of thee. Depart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I love thee better now than e&#8217;er I did.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I hate thee worse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Why?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Thou flatter&#8217;st misery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I flatter not, but say thou art a caitiff.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Why dost thou seek me out?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">To vex thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Always a villain&#8217;s office, or a fool&#8217;s.</line>
<line>Dost please thyself in&#8217;t?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Ay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">What, a knave too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>If thou didst put this sour cold habit on</line>
<line>To castigate thy pride, &#8217;twere well; but thou</line>
<line>Dost it enforcedly. Thou&#8217;dst courtier be again,</line>
<line>Wert thou not beggar. Willing misery</line>
<line>Outlives incertain pomp, is crown&#8217;d before:</line>
<line>The one is filling still, never complete;</line>
<line>The other, at high wish. Best state, contentless,</line>
<line>Hath a distracted and most wretched being,</line>
<line>Worse than the worst, content.</line>
<line>Thou shouldst desire to die, being miserable.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Not by his breath that is more miserable.</line>
<line>Thou art a slave, whom Fortune&#8217;s tender arm</line>
<line>With favor never clasp&#8217;d, but bred a dog.</line>
<line>Hadst thou like us from our first swath proceeded</line>
<line>The sweet degrees that this brief world affords</line>
<line>To such as may the passive drugs of it</line>
<line>Freely command, thou wouldst have plung&#8217;d thyself</line>
<line>In general riot, melted down thy youth</line>
<line>In different beds of lust, and never learn&#8217;d</line>
<line>The icy precepts of respect, but followed</line>
<line>The sug&#8217;red game before thee. But myself,</line>
<line>Who had the world as my confectionary,</line>
<line>The mouths, the tongues, the eyes, and hearts of men</line>
<line>At duty, more than I could frame employment;</line>
<line>That numberless upon me stuck as leaves</line>
<line>Do on the oak, have with one winter&#8217;s brush</line>
<line>Fell from their boughs, and left me open, bare,</line>
<line>For every storm that blows&#8212;I to bear this,</line>
<line>That never knew but better, is some burden:</line>
<line>Thy nature did commence in sufferance, time</line>
<line>Hath made thee hard in&#8217;t. Why shouldst thou hate men?</line>
<line>They never flatter&#8217;d thee. What hast thou given?</line>
<line>If thou wilt curse, thy father (that poor rag)</line>
<line>Must be thy subject, who in spite put stuff</line>
<line>To some she-beggar and compounded thee</line>
<line>Poor rogue hereditary. Hence, be gone!</line>
<line>If thou hadst not been born the worst of men,</line>
<line>Thou hadst been a knave and flatterer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="8">Art thou proud yet?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ay, that I am not thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">I, that I was</line>
<line>No prodigal.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="3">I, that I am one now.</line>
<line>Were all the wealth I have shut up in thee,</line>
<line>I&#8217;ld give thee leave to hang it. Get thee gone.</line>
<line>That the whole life of Athens were in this!</line>
<line>Thus would I eat it.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Eating a root.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Here, I will mend thy feast.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Offering him another.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>First mend my company, take away thyself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>So I shall mend mine own, by th&#8217; lack of thine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis not well mended so, it is but botch&#8217;d;</line>
<line>If not, I would it were.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>What wouldst thou have to Athens?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Thee thither in a whirlwind. If thou wilt,</line>
<line>Tell them there I have gold; look, so I have.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Here is no use for gold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">The best, and truest;</line>
<line>For here it sleeps, and does no hired harm.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Where liest a&#8217; nights, Timon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Under that&#8217;s above me.</line>
<line>Where feed&#8217;st thou a&#8217; days, Apemantus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Where my stomach finds meat, or, rather, where I eat it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Would poison were obedient and knew my mind!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Where wouldst thou send it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>To sauce thy dishes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>The middle of humanity thou never knewest, but the extremity of both ends. When thou wast in thy gilt and thy perfume, they mock&#8217;d thee for too much curiosity; in thy rags thou know&#8217;st none, but art despis&#8217;d for the contrary. There&#8217;s a medlar for thee, eat it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>On what I hate I feed not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Dost hate a medlar?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ay, though it look like thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>And th&#8217; hadst hated meddlers sooner, thou shouldst have lov&#8217;d thyself better now. What man didst thou ever know unthrift that was belov&#8217;d after his means?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Who, without those means thou talk&#8217;st of, didst thou ever know belov&#8217;d?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Myself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I understand thee: thou hadst some means to keep a dog.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>What things in the world canst thou nearest compare to thy flatterers?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Women nearest, but men&#8212;men are the things themselves. What wouldst thou do with the world, Apemantus, if it lay in thy power?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Give it the beasts, to be rid of the men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Wouldst thou have thyself fall in the confusion of men, and remain a beast with the beasts?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Ay, Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>A beastly ambition, which the gods grant thee t&#8217; attain to! If thou wert the lion, the fox would beguile thee; if thou wert the lamb, the fox would eat thee; if thou wert the fox, the lion would suspect thee, when peradventure thou wert accus&#8217;d by the ass; if thou wert the ass, thy dullness would torment thee, and still thou liv&#8217;dst but as a breakfast to the wolf; if thou wert the wolf, thy greediness would afflict thee, and oft thou shouldst hazard thy life for thy dinner; wert thou the unicorn, pride and wrath would confound thee and make thine own self the conquest of thy fury; wert thou a bear, thou wouldst be kill&#8217;d by the horse; wert thou a horse, thou wouldst be seiz&#8217;d by the leopard; wert thou a leopard, thou wert germane to the lion, and the spots of thy kindred were jurors on thy life; all thy safety were remotion and thy defense absence. What beast couldst thou be, that were not subject to a beast? And what a beast art thou already, that seest not thy loss in transformation!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>If thou couldst please me with speaking to me, thou mightst have hit upon it here. The commonwealth of Athens is become a forest of beasts.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>How has the ass broke the wall, that thou art out of the city?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Yonder comes a poet and a painter; the plague of company light upon thee! I will fear to catch it, and give way. When I know not what else to do, I&#8217;ll see thee again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>When there is nothing living but thee, thou shalt be welcome. I had rather be a beggar&#8217;s dog than Apemantus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Thou art the cap of all the fools alive.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Would thou wert clean enough to spit upon!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>A plague on thee, thou art too bad to curse!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>All villains that do stand by thee are pure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>There is no leprosy but what thou speak&#8217;st.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>If I name thee.</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll beat thee, but I should infect my hands.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>I would my tongue could rot them off!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Away, thou issue of a mangy dog!</line>
<line>Choler does kill me that thou art alive;</line>
<line>I swound to see thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Would thou wouldst burst!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Away, thou tedious rogue!</line>
<line>I am sorry I shall lose a stone by thee.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Throws a stone at him.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Beast!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Slave!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>Toad!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Rogue, rogue, rogue!</line>
<line>I am sick of this false world, and will love nought</line>
<line>But even the mere necessities upon&#8217;t.</line>
<line>Then, Timon, presently prepare thy grave;</line>
<line>Lie where the light foam of the sea may beat</line>
<line>Thy grave-stone daily; make thine epitaph,</line>
<line>That death in me at others&#8217; lives may laugh.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To the gold.</stagedir>
<line>O thou sweet king-killer, and dear divorce</line>
<line>&#8217;Twixt natural son and sire! Thou bright defiler</line>
<line>Of Hymen&#8217;s purest bed! Thou valiant Mars!</line>
<line>Thou ever young, fresh, lov&#8217;d, and delicate wooer,</line>
<line>Whose blush doth thaw the consecrated snow</line>
<line>That lies on Dian&#8217;s lap! Thou visible god,</line>
<line>That sold&#8217;rest close impossibilities,</line>
<line>And mak&#8217;st them kiss! That speak&#8217;st with every tongue</line>
<line>To every purpose! O thou touch of hearts,</line>
<line>Think thy slave man rebels, and by thy virtue</line>
<line>Set them into confounding odds, that beasts</line>
<line>May have the world in empire!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Would &#8217;twere so!</line>
<line>But not till I am dead. I&#8217;ll say th&#8217; hast gold;</line>
<line>Thou wilt be throng&#8217;d to shortly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Throng&#8217;d to?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="9">Ay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Thy back, I prithee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Live, and love thy misery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Long live so, and so die. I am quit.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>APEM.</speaker>
<line>More things like men! Eat, Timon, and abhor them.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Apemantus.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Bandits.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. BAN.</speaker>
<line>Where should he have this gold? It is some poor fragment, some slender ort of his remainder. The mere want of gold, and the falling-from of his friends, drove him into this melancholy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. BAN.</speaker>
<line>It is nois&#8217;d he hath a mass of treasure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. BAN.</speaker>
<line>Let us make the assay upon him. If he care not for&#8217;t, he will supply us easily; if he covetously reserve it, how shall &#8217;s get it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. BAN.</speaker>
<line>True; for he bears it not about him, &#8217;tis hid.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. BAN.</speaker>
<line>Is not this he?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL OTHER BAN.</speaker>
<line>Where?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. BAN.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis his description.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. BAN.</speaker>
<line>He; I know him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL OTHER BAN.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Save thee, Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Now, thieves?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL OTHER BAN.</speaker>
<line>Soldiers, not thieves.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Both too, and women&#8217;s sons.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALL BAN.</speaker>
<line>We are not thieves, but men that much do want.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Your greatest want is, you want much of meat.</line>
<line>Why should you want? Behold, the earth hath roots;</line>
<line>Within this mile break forth a hundred springs;</line>
<line>The oaks bear mast, the briers scarlet heps;</line>
<line>The bounteous huswife Nature on each bush</line>
<line>Lays her full mess before you. Want? Why want?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. BAN.</speaker>
<line>We cannot live on grass, on berries, water,</line>
<line>As beasts and birds and fishes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Nor on the beasts themselves, the birds and fishes;</line>
<line>You must eat men. Yet thanks I must you con</line>
<line>That you are thieves profess&#8217;d, that you work not</line>
<line>In holier shapes; for there is boundless theft</line>
<line>In limited professions. Rascal thieves,</line>
<line>Here&#8217;s gold. Go, suck the subtle blood o&#8217; th&#8217; grape,</line>
<line>Till the high fever seethe your blood to froth,</line>
<line>And so scape hanging. Trust not the physician,</line>
<line>His antidotes are poison, and he slays</line>
<line>More than you rob. Take wealth and lives together,</line>
<line>Do, villains, do, since you protest to do&#8217;t.</line>
<line>Like workmen, I&#8217;ll example you with thievery:</line>
<line>The sun&#8217;s a thief, and with his great attraction</line>
<line>Robs the vast sea; the moon&#8217;s an arrant thief,</line>
<line>And her pale fire she snatches from the sun;</line>
<line>The sea&#8217;s a thief, whose liquid surge resolves</line>
<line>The moon into salt tears; the earth&#8217;s a thief,</line>
<line>That feeds and breeds by a composture stol&#8217;n</line>
<line>From gen&#8217;ral excrement; each thing&#8217;s a thief.</line>
<line>The laws, your curb and whip, in their rough power</line>
<line>Has uncheck&#8217;d theft. Love not yourselves, away,</line>
<line>Rob one another. There&#8217;s more gold. Cut throats,</line>
<line>All that you meet are thieves. To Athens go,</line>
<line>Break open shops; nothing can you steal</line>
<line>But thieves do lose it. Steal less for this I give you,</line>
<line>And gold confound you howsoe&#8217;er! Amen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. BAN.</speaker>
<line>H&#8217;as almost charm&#8217;d me from my profession, by persuading me to it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. BAN.</speaker>
<line>&#8217;Tis in the malice of mankind that he thus advises us, not to have us thrive in our mystery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. BAN.</speaker>
<line>I&#8217;ll believe him as an enemy, and give over my trade.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. BAN.</speaker>
<line>Let us first see peace in Athens. There is no time so miserable but a man may be true.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt Thieves, the Bandits.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the Steward Flavius to Timon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>O you gods!</line>
<line>Is yond despis&#8217;d and ruinous man my lord?</line>
<line>Full of decay and failing? O monument</line>
<line>And wonder of good deeds evilly bestow&#8217;d!</line>
<line>What an alteration of honor has desp&#8217;rate want made!</line>
<line>What vilder thing upon the earth than friends,</line>
<line>Who can bring noblest minds to basest ends!</line>
<line>How rarely does it meet with this time&#8217;s guise,</line>
<line>When man was wish&#8217;d to love his enemies!</line>
<line>Grant I may ever love, and rather woo</line>
<line>Those that would mischief me than those that do!</line>
<line>H&#8217;as caught me in his eye, I will present</line>
<line>My honest grief unto him; and as my lord,</line>
<line>Still serve him with my life. My dearest master!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Away! What art thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Have you forgot me, sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Why dost ask that? I have forgot all men.</line>
<line>Then, if thou grant&#8217;st th&#8217; art a man, I have forgot thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>An honest poor servant of yours.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Then I know thee not.</line>
<line>I never had honest man about me, I; all</line>
<line>I kept were knaves, to serve in meat to villains.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>The gods are witness,</line>
<line>Nev&#8217;r did poor steward wear a truer grief</line>
<line>For his undone lord than mine eyes for you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>What, dost thou weep? Come nearer. Then I love thee,</line>
<line>Because thou art a woman, and disclaim&#8217;st</line>
<line>Flinty mankind, whose eyes do never give</line>
<line>But thorough lust and laughter. Pity&#8217;s sleeping:</line>
<line>Strange times, that weep with laughing, not with weeping!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>I beg of you to know me, good my lord,</line>
<line>T&#8217; accept my grief, and whilst this poor wealth lasts</line>
<line>To entertain me as your steward still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Had I a steward</line>
<line>So true, so just, and now so comfortable?</line>
<line>It almost turns my dangerous nature wild.</line>
<line>Let me behold thy face. Surely, this man</line>
<line>Was born of woman.</line>
<line>Forgive my general and exceptless rashness,</line>
<line>You perpetual-sober gods! I do proclaim</line>
<line>One honest man&#8212;mistake me not, but one;</line>
<line>No more, I pray&#8212;and he&#8217;s a steward.</line>
<line>How fain would I have hated all mankind,</line>
<line>And thou redeem&#8217;st thyself. But all, save thee,</line>
<line>I fell with curses.</line>
<line>Methinks thou art more honest now than wise;</line>
<line>For, by oppressing and betraying me,</line>
<line>Thou mightst have sooner got another service;</line>
<line>For many so arrive at second masters,</line>
<line>Upon their first lord&#8217;s neck. But tell me true</line>
<line>(For I must ever doubt, though ne&#8217;er so sure),</line>
<line>Is not thy kindness subtle, covetous,</line>
<line>If not a usuring kindness, and, as rich men deal gifts,</line>
<line>Expecting in return twenty for one?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>No, my most worthy master, in whose breast</line>
<line>Doubt and suspect, alas, are plac&#8217;d too late;</line>
<line>You should have fear&#8217;d false times when you did feast:</line>
<line>Suspect still comes where an estate is least.</line>
<line>That which I show, heaven knows, is merely love,</line>
<line>Duty, and zeal to your unmatched mind,</line>
<line>Care of your food and living; and believe it,</line>
<line>My most honor&#8217;d lord,</line>
<line>For any benefit that points to me,</line>
<line>Either in hope or present, I&#8217;d exchange</line>
<line>For this one wish, that you had power and wealth</line>
<line>To requite me by making rich yourself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Look thee, &#8217;tis so. Thou singly honest man,</line>
<line>Here, take; the gods out of my misery</line>
<line>Has sent thee treasure. Go, live rich and happy,</line>
<line>But thus condition&#8217;d: thou shalt build from men;</line>
<line>Hate all, curse all, show charity to none,</line>
<line>But let the famish&#8217;d flesh slide from the bone</line>
<line>Ere thou relieve the beggar. Give to dogs</line>
<line>What thou deniest to men. Let prisons swallow &#8217;em,</line>
<line>Debts wither &#8217;em to nothing; be men like blasted woods,</line>
<line>And may diseases lick up their false bloods!</line>
<line>And so farewell and thrive.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">O, let me stay,</line>
<line>And comfort you, my master.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="6">If thou hat&#8217;st curses,</line>
<line>Stay not; fly, whilst thou art blest and free.</line>
<line>Ne&#8217;er see thou man, and let me ne&#8217;er see thee.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt severally.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<act num="5">
<acttitle>Act 5</acttitle>
<scene num="1">
<scenetitle>Scene 1</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The woods. Before Timon&#8217;s cave.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Poet, Painter, Timon, Steward Flavius, Senators)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The poet and the painter, having heard that Timon is distributing gold, come to get their share. Timon overhears them plotting about how they will flatter him. Though he pretends to find them honest, when he gives them gold he beats them for villainy. Flavius leads two Senators to Timon&#8217;s cave, warning them that there&#8217;s no hope of a good welcome, but the Senators insist, since they have promised the Athenians. They tell Timon that the people of Athens want him to return and to run the city, in the hopes that he will be able to save it from Alcibiades. But Timon, after getting their hopes up, informs them that he does not care in the slightest what happens to Athens, and tells them that they should all go hang themselves. The Senators return to Athens to work out how else to save themselves.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Poet and Painter; Timon watching them from his cave.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>As I took note of the place, it cannot be far</line>
<line>Where he abides.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="4">What&#8217;s to be thought of him?</line>
<line>Does the rumor hold for true that he&#8217;s</line>
<line>So full of gold?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="3">Certain. Alcibiades reports it;</line>
<line>Phrynia and Timandra had gold of him.</line>
<line>He likewise enrich&#8217;d poor straggling soldiers with</line>
<line>Great quantity. &#8217;Tis said he gave unto</line>
<line>His steward a mighty sum.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Then this breaking of his</line>
<line>Has been but a try for his friends?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="7">Nothing else.</line>
<line>You shall see him a palm in Athens again, and flourish</line>
<line>With the highest. Therefore, &#8217;tis not amiss</line>
<line>We tender our loves to him in this suppos&#8217;d</line>
<line>Distress of his; it will show honestly in us,</line>
<line>And is very likely to load our purposes</line>
<line>With what they travail for, if it be</line>
<line>A just and true report that goes of his having.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>What have you now to present unto him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>Nothing at this time but my visitation;</line>
<line>Only I will promise him an excellent piece.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>I must serve him so too: tell him of an intent</line>
<line>That&#8217;s coming toward him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Good as the best.</line>
<line>Promising is the very air o&#8217; th&#8217; time;</line>
<line>It opens the eyes of expectation.</line>
<line>Performance is ever the duller for his act,</line>
<line>And but in the plainer and simpler kind of people</line>
<line>The deed of saying is quite out of use.</line>
<line>To promise is most courtly and fashionable;</line>
<line>Performance is a kind of will or testament</line>
<line>Which argues a great sickness in his judgment</line>
<line>That makes it.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon from his cave.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line>Excellent workman! Thou canst not paint a man</line>
<line>So bad as is thyself.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="4">I am thinking</line>
<line>What I shall say I have provided for him.</line>
<line>It must be a personating of himself;</line>
<line>A satire against the softness of prosperity,</line>
<line>With a discovery of the infinite flatteries</line>
<line>That follow youth and opulency.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line offset="7">Must thou needs</line>
<line>Stand for a villain in thine own work?</line>
<line>Wilt thou whip thine own faults in other men?</line>
<line>Do so, I have gold for thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Nay, let&#8217;s seek him:</line>
<line>Then do we sin against our own estate,</line>
<line>When we may profit meet, and come too late.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>True:</line>
<line>When the day serves, before black-corner&#8217;d night,</line>
<line>Find what thou want&#8217;st by free and offer&#8217;d light.</line>
<line>Come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<stagedir type="aside">Aside.</stagedir>
<line>I&#8217;ll meet you at the turn. What a god&#8217;s gold</line>
<line>That he is worshipp&#8217;d in a baser temple</line>
<line>Than where swine feed!</line>
<line>&#8217;Tis thou that rig&#8217;st the bark and plough&#8217;st the foam,</line>
<line>Settlest admired reverence in a slave.</line>
<line>To thee be worship, and thy saints for aye</line>
<line>Be crown&#8217;d with plagues, that thee alone obey!</line>
<line>Fit I meet them.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">Coming forward.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Hail, worthy Timon!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Our late noble master!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Have I once liv&#8217;d to see two honest men?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>Having often of your open bounty tasted,</line>
<line>Hearing you were retir&#8217;d, your friends fall&#8217;n off,</line>
<line>Whose thankless natures (O abhorred spirits!)</line>
<line>Not all the whips of heaven are large enough&#8212;</line>
<line>What, to you,</line>
<line>Whose star-like nobleness gave life and influence</line>
<line>To their whole being! I am rapt and cannot cover</line>
<line>The monstrous bulk of this ingratitude</line>
<line>With any size of words.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Let it go naked, men may see&#8217;t the better.</line>
<line>You that are honest, by being what you are</line>
<line>Make them best seen and known.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="7">He and myself</line>
<line>Have travail&#8217;d in the great show&#8217;r of your gifts,</line>
<line>And sweetly felt it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Ay, you are honest men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>We are hither come to offer you our service.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Most honest men! Why, how shall I requite you?</line>
<line>Can you eat roots and drink cold water? No?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line>What we can do, we&#8217;ll do, to do you service.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Y&#8217; are honest men; y&#8217; have heard that I have gold,</line>
<line>I am sure you have. Speak truth, y&#8217; are honest men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>So it is said, my noble lord, but therefore</line>
<line>Came not my friend nor I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Good honest men! Thou draw&#8217;st a counterfeit</line>
<line>Best in all Athens; th&#8217; art indeed the best,</line>
<line>Thou counterfeit&#8217;st most lively.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line offset="7">So, so, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>E&#8217;en so, sir, as I say.&#8212;And, for thy fiction,</line>
<line>Why, thy verse swells with stuff so fine and smooth</line>
<line>That thou art even natural in thine art.</line>
<line>But for all this, my honest-natur&#8217;d friends,</line>
<line>I must needs say you have a little fault;</line>
<line>Marry, &#8217;tis not monstrous in you, neither wish I</line>
<line>You take much pains to mend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Beseech your honor</line>
<line>To make it known to us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">You&#8217;ll take it ill.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line>Most thankfully, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Will you indeed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line>Doubt it not, worthy lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>There&#8217;s never a one of you but trusts a knave</line>
<line>That mightily deceives you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Do we, my lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Ay, and you hear him cog, see him dissemble,</line>
<line>Know his gross patchery, love him, feed him,</line>
<line>Keep in your bosom; yet remain assur&#8217;d</line>
<line>That he&#8217;s a made-up villain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>PAIN.</speaker>
<line>I know none such, my lord.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>POET.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Nor I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Look you, I love you well, I&#8217;ll give you gold,</line>
<line>Rid me these villains from your companies;</line>
<line>Hang them, or stab them, drown them in a draught,</line>
<line>Confound them by some course, and come to me,</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll give you gold enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line>Name them, my lord, let&#8217;s know them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>You that way and you this; but two in company;</line>
<line>Each man apart, all single and alone,</line>
<line>Yet an arch-villain keeps him company.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To one.</stagedir>
<line>If where thou art, two villains shall not be,</line>
<line>Come not near him.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To the other.</stagedir>
<line>If thou wouldst not reside</line>
<line>But where one villain is, then him abandon.&#8212;</line>
<line>Hence, pack! There&#8217;s gold; you came for gold, ye slaves.</line>

<stagedir type="speak">To one.</stagedir>
<line>You have work for me; there&#8217;s payment, hence!</line>
<stagedir type="speak">To the other.</stagedir>
<line>You are an alcumist, make gold of that.</line>
<line>Out, rascal dogs!</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt both, driven out by Timon, who retires to his cave.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Steward Flavius and two Senators.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>It is vain that you would speak with Timon;</line>
<line>For he is set so only to himself,</line>
<line>That nothing but himself which looks like man</line>
<line>Is friendly with him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Bring us to his cave.</line>
<line>It is our part and promise to th&#8217; Athenians</line>
<line>To speak with Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">At all times alike</line>
<line>Men are not still the same; &#8217;twas time and griefs</line>
<line>That fram&#8217;d him thus. Time with his fairer hand,</line>
<line>Offering the fortunes of his former days,</line>
<line>The former man may make him. Bring us to him,</line>
<line>And chance it as it may.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Here is his cave.</line>
<line>Peace and content be here! Lord Timon! Timon,</line>
<line>Look out and speak to friends. Th&#8217; Athenians</line>
<line>By two of their most reverend Senate greet thee.</line>
<line>Speak to them, noble Timon.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Timon out of his cave.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Thou sun that comforts, burn! Speak and be hang&#8217;d.</line>
<line>For each true word, a blister, and each false</line>
<line>Be as a cantherizing to the root o&#8217; th&#8217; tongue,</line>
<line>Consuming it with speaking!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Worthy Timon&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Of none but such as you, and you of Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>The senators of Athens greet thee, Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I thank them, and would send them back the plague,</line>
<line>Could I but catch it for them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">O, forget</line>
<line>What we are sorry for ourselves in thee.</line>
<line>The senators with one consent of love</line>
<line>Entreat thee back to Athens, who have thought</line>
<line>On special dignities, which vacant lie,</line>
<line>For thy best use and wearing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">They confess</line>
<line>Toward thee forgetfulness too general gross;</line>
<line>Which now the public body, which doth seldom</line>
<line>Play the recanter, feeling in itself</line>
<line>A lack of Timon&#8217;s aid, hath sense withal</line>
<line>Of it own fall, restraining aid to Timon,</line>
<line>And send forth us to make their sorrowed render,</line>
<line>Together with a recompense more fruitful</line>
<line>Than their offense can weigh down by the dram;</line>
<line>Ay, even such heaps and sums of love and wealth</line>
<line>As shall to thee blot out what wrongs were theirs,</line>
<line>And write in thee the figures of their love,</line>
<line>Ever to read them thine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">You witch me in it;</line>
<line>Surprise me to the very brink of tears.</line>
<line>Lend me a fool&#8217;s heart and a woman&#8217;s eyes,</line>
<line>And I&#8217;ll beweep these comforts, worthy senators.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>Therefore so please thee to return with us,</line>
<line>And of our Athens, thine and ours, to take</line>
<line>The captainship, thou shalt be met with thanks,</line>
<line>Allow&#8217;d with absolute power, and thy good name</line>
<line>Live with authority; so soon we shall drive back</line>
<line>Of Alcibiades th&#8217; approaches wild,</line>
<line>Who, like a boar too savage, doth root up</line>
<line>His country&#8217;s peace.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">And shakes his threat&#8217;ning sword</line>
<line>Against the walls of Athens.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Therefore, Timon&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Well, sir, I will; therefore I will, sir, thus:</line>
<line>If Alcibiades kill my countrymen,</line>
<line>Let Alcibiades know this of Timon,</line>
<line>That Timon cares not. But if he sack fair Athens,</line>
<line>And take our goodly aged men by th&#8217; beards,</line>
<line>Giving our holy virgins to the stain</line>
<line>Of contumelious, beastly, mad-brain&#8217;d war,</line>
<line>Then let him know, and tell him Timon speaks it,</line>
<line>In pity of our aged and our youth,</line>
<line>I cannot choose but tell him that I care not,</line>
<line>And let him take&#8217;t at worst&#8212;for their knives care not,</line>
<line>While you have throats to answer. For myself,</line>
<line>There&#8217;s not a whittle in th&#8217; unruly camp</line>
<line>But I do prize it at my love before</line>
<line>The reverend&#8217;st throat in Athens. So I leave you</line>
<line>To the protection of the prosperous gods,</line>
<line>As thieves to keepers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line offset="4">Stay not, all&#8217;s in vain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Why, I was writing of my epitaph;</line>
<line>It will be seen tomorrow. My long sickness</line>
<line>Of health and living now begins to mend,</line>
<line>And nothing brings me all things. Go, live still;</line>
<line>Be Alcibiades your plague, you his,</line>
<line>And last so long enough!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">We speak in vain.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>But yet I love my country, and am not</line>
<line>One that rejoices in the common wrack,</line>
<line>As common bruit doth put it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">That&#8217;s well spoke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Commend me to my loving countrymen&#8212;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>These words become your lips as they pass thorough them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>And enter in our ears like great triumphers</line>
<line>In their applauding gates.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Commend me to them,</line>
<line>And tell them that, to ease them of their griefs,</line>
<line>Their fears of hostile strokes, their aches, losses,</line>
<line>Their pangs of love, with other incident throes</line>
<line>That nature&#8217;s fragile vessel doth sustain</line>
<line>In life&#8217;s uncertain voyage, I will some kindness do them:</line>
<line>I&#8217;ll teach them to prevent wild Alcibiades&#8217; wrath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>I like this well, he will return again.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>I have a tree, which grows here in my close,</line>
<line>That mine own use invites me to cut down,</line>
<line>And shortly must I fell it. Tell my friends,</line>
<line>Tell Athens, in the sequence of degree,</line>
<line>From high to low throughout, that whoso please</line>
<line>To stop affliction, let him take his haste,</line>
<line>Come hither, ere my tree hath felt the axe,</line>
<line>And hang himself. I pray you do my greeting.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>FLAV.</speaker>
<line>Trouble him no further, thus you still shall find him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>TIM.</speaker>
<line>Come not to me again, but say to Athens,</line>
<line>Timon hath made his everlasting mansion</line>
<line>Upon the beached verge of the salt flood,</line>
<line>Who once a day with his embossed froth</line>
<line>The turbulent surge shall cover; thither come,</line>
<line>And let my grave-stone be your oracle.</line>
<line>Lips, let four words go by and language end!</line>
<line>What is amiss, plague and infection mend!</line>
<line>Graves only be men&#8217;s works, and death their gain!</line>
<line>Sun, hide thy beams, Timon hath done his reign.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit Timon.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>His discontents are unremovably</line>
<line>Coupled to nature.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line>Our hope in him is dead. Let us return,</line>
<line>And strain what other means is left unto us</line>
<line>In our dear peril.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">It requires swift foot.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="2">
<scenetitle>Scene 2</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Before the walls of Athens.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Senators, Messenger)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>The other Senators wait to find out if Timon will return. They hear that Alcibiades too has tried to recruit him. The two who went to see Timon return and report their failure.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter two other Senators with a Messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. SEN.</speaker>
<line>Thou hast painfully discover&#8217;d; are his files</line>
<line>As full as thy report?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line offset="4">I have spoke the least.</line>
<line>Besides, his expedition promises</line>
<line>Present approach.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4. SEN.</speaker>
<line>We stand much hazard if they bring not Timon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>MESS.</speaker>
<line>I met a courier, one mine ancient friend,</line>
<line>Whom, though in general part we were oppos&#8217;d,</line>
<line>Yet our old love made a particular force,</line>
<line>And made us speak like friends. This man was riding</line>
<line>From Alcibiades to Timon&#8217;s cave</line>
<line>With letters of entreaty, which imported</line>
<line>His fellowship i&#8217; th&#8217; cause against your city,</line>
<line>In part for his sake mov&#8217;d.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter the other Senators.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>3. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Here come our brothers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line>No talk of Timon, nothing of him expect.</line>
<line>The enemy&#8217;s drum is heard, and fearful scouring</line>
<line>Doth choke the air with dust. In, and prepare:</line>
<line>Ours is the fall, I fear, our foes the snare.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="3">
<scenetitle>Scene 3</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>The woods. A rude tomb near Timon&#8217;s cave.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Soldier)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Alcibiades&#8217;s messenger finds Timon dead.</scenedescription>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter a Soldier in the woods, seeking Timon. A rude tomb seen.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOLD.</speaker>
<line>By all description this should be the place.</line>
<line>Who&#8217;s here? Speak ho! No answer? What is this?</line>

<stagedir type="read">Reads.</stagedir>
<line><recite>&#8220;Timon is dead, who hath outstretch&#8217;d his span:</recite></line>
<line><recite>Some beast read this; there does not live a man.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line>Dead, sure, and this his grave. What&#8217;s on this tomb</line>
<line>I cannot read; the character I&#8217;ll take with wax;</line>
<line>Our captain hath in every figure skill,</line>
<line>An ag&#8217;d interpreter, though young in days.</line>
<line>Before proud Athens he&#8217;s set down by this,</line>
<line>Whose fall the mark of his ambition is.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exit.</stagedir> 

</scene>

<scene num="4">
<scenetitle>Scene 4</scenetitle>
<scenelocation>Before the walls of Athens.</scenelocation>
<scenepersonae>(Alcibiades, Senators, Soldier)</scenepersonae>
<scenedescription>Alcibiades and is army arrive before Athens, and he gives them one last chance to surrender. They plead with him to be merciful and agree to yield if he will promise to. Alcibiades agrees, promising to punish only his own enemies and Timon&#8217;s, and letting the Athenians decide who the latter are. The soldier brings the news that Timon has died, leaving one last curse on his grave. Alcibiades grieves.</scenedescription>
<stagedir type="enter">Trumpets sound. Enter Alcibiades with his powers before Athens.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Sound to this coward and lascivious town</line>
<line>Our terrible approach.</line>
<stagedir type="action">Sounds a parley.</stagedir>
<stagedir type="action">The Senators appear upon the walls.</stagedir>
<line>Till now you have gone on and fill&#8217;d the time</line>
<line>With all licentious measure, making your wills</line>
<line>The scope of justice; till now myself and such</line>
<line>As slept within the shadow of your power</line>
<line>Have wander&#8217;d with our travers&#8217;d arms, and breath&#8217;d</line>
<line>Our sufferance vainly. Now the time is flush,</line>
<line>When crouching marrow in the bearer strong</line>
<line>Cries (of itself) &#8220;No more!&#8221; Now breathless wrong</line>
<line>Shall sit and pant in your great chairs of ease,</line>
<line>And pursy insolence shall break his wind</line>
<line>With fear and horrid flight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Noble and young&#8212;</line>
<line>When thy first griefs were but a mere conceit,</line>
<line>Ere thou hadst power or we had cause of fear,</line>
<line>We sent to thee to give thy rages balm,</line>
<line>To wipe out our ingratitude with loves</line>
<line>Above their quantity.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">So did we woo</line>
<line>Transformed Timon to our city&#8217;s love</line>
<line>By humble message and by promis&#8217;d means.</line>
<line>We were not all unkind, nor all deserve</line>
<line>The common stroke of war.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">These walls of ours</line>
<line>Were not erected by their hands from whom</line>
<line>You have receiv&#8217;d your grief; nor are they such</line>
<line>That these great tow&#8217;rs, trophies, and schools should fall</line>
<line>For private faults in them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Nor are they living</line>
<line>Who were the motives that you first went out;</line>
<line>Shame, that they wanted cunning in excess,</line>
<line>Hath broke their hearts. March, noble lord,</line>
<line>Into our city with thy banners spread;</line>
<line>By decimation, and a tithed death,</line>
<line>If thy revenges hunger for that food</line>
<line>Which nature loathes, take thou the destin&#8217;d tenth,</line>
<line>And by the hazard of the spotted die</line>
<line>Let die the spotted.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="4">All have not offended;</line>
<line>For those that were, it is not square to take</line>
<line>On those that are, revenge; crimes, like lands,</line>
<line>Are not inherited. Then, dear countryman,</line>
<line>Bring in thy ranks, but leave without thy rage;</line>
<line>Spare thy Athenian cradle and those kin</line>
<line>Which in the bluster of thy wrath must fall</line>
<line>With those that have offended; like a shepherd,</line>
<line>Approach the fold and cull th&#8217; infected forth,</line>
<line>But kill not all together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">What thou wilt,</line>
<line>Thou rather shalt enforce it with thy smile</line>
<line>Than hew to&#8217;t with thy sword.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="6">Set but thy foot</line>
<line>Against our rampir&#8217;d gates and they shall ope,</line>
<line>So thou wilt send thy gentle heart before,</line>
<line>To say thou&#8217;t enter friendly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. SEN.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Throw thy glove,</line>
<line>Or any token of thine honor else,</line>
<line>That thou wilt use the wars as thy redress</line>
<line>And not as our confusion, all thy powers</line>
<line>Shall make their harbor in our town till we</line>
<line>Have seal&#8217;d thy full desire.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line offset="5">Then there&#8217;s my glove;</line>
<line>Descend, and open your uncharged ports.</line>
<line>Those enemies of Timon&#8217;s and mine own</line>
<line>Whom you yourselves shall set out for reproof</line>
<line>Fall, and no more; and to atone your fears</line>
<line>With my more noble meaning, not a man</line>
<line>Shall pass his quarter, or offend the stream</line>
<line>Of regular justice in your city&#8217;s bounds,</line>
<line>But shall be remedied to your public laws</line>
<line>At heaviest answer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
<line offset="4">&#8217;Tis most nobly spoken.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<line>Descend, and keep your words.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="action">The Senators descend and open the gates.</stagedir>

<stagedir type="enter">Enter Soldier as a messenger.</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>SOLD.</speaker>
<line>My noble general, Timon is dead,</line>
<line>Entomb&#8217;d upon the very hem o&#8217; th&#8217; sea,</line>
<line>And on his grave-stone this insculpture, which</line>
<line>With wax I brought away, whose soft impression</line>
<line>Interprets for my poor ignorance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>ALCIB.</speaker>
<stagedir type="read">Reads the epitaph.</stagedir>
<line><recite>&#8220;Here lies a wretched corse, of wretched soul bereft;</recite></line>
<line><recite>Seek not my name: a plague consume you, wicked caitiffs left!</recite></line>
<line><recite>Here lie I, Timon, who, alive, all living men did hate;</recite></line>
<line><recite>Pass by and curse thy fill, but pass and stay not here thy gait.&#8221;</recite></line>
<line>These well express in thee thy latter spirits:</line>
<line>Though thou abhorr&#8217;dst in us our human griefs,</line>
<line>Scorn&#8217;dst our brains&#8217; flow, and those our droplets which</line>
<line>From niggard nature fall, yet rich conceit</line>
<line>Taught thee to make vast Neptune weep for aye</line>
<line>On thy low grave, on faults forgiven. Dead</line>
<line>Is noble Timon, of whose memory</line>
<line>Hereafter more. Bring me into your city,</line>
<line>And I will use the olive with my sword:</line>
<line>Make war breed peace, make peace stint war, make each</line>
<line>Prescribe to other as each other&#8217;s leech.</line>
<line>Let our drums strike.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir type="exit">Exeunt.</stagedir> 

</scene>
</act>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.1a</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</play>

