<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<play variant="first-quarto">
<title short="Two Noble Kinsmen">The Two Noble Kinsmen</title>
<playwright>William Shakespeare and John Fletcher</playwright>

<prologue>
<scenetitle>[Prologue]</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>PROLOGVE.</speaker>
<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>

<line>New Playes, and Maydenheads, are neare a kin,</line>
<line>Much follow'd both, for both much mony g'yn,</line>
<line>If they stand sound, and well: And a good Play</line>
<line>(Whose modest Sceanes blush on his marriage day,</line>
<line>And shake to loose his honour) is like hir</line>
<line>That after holy Tye, and first nights stir</line>
<line>Yet still is Modestie, and still retaines</line>
<line>More of the maid to sight, than Husbands paines;</line>
<line>We pray our Play may be so; For I am sure</line>
<line>It has a noble Breeder, and a pure,</line>
<line>A learned, and a Poet never went</line>
<line>More famous yet twixt Po and silver Trent.</line>
<line>Chaucer (of all admir'd) the Story gives,</line>
<line>There constant to Eternity it lives;</line>
<line>If we let fall the Noblenesse of this,</line>
<line>And the first sound this child heare, be a hisse,</line>
<line>How will it shake the bones of that good man,</line>
<line>And make him cry from under ground, O fan</line>
<line>For to say Truth, it were an endlesse thing,</line>
<line>And too ambitious to aspire to him;</line>
<line>Weake as we are, and almost breath lesse swim</line>
<line>In this deepe water. Do but you hold out</line>
<line>Your helping hands, and we shall take about,</line>
<line>And something doe to save us: You shall heare</line>
<line>Sceanes though below his Art, may yet appeare</line>
<line>A little dull time from us, we perceave</line>
<line>Our losses fall so thicke, we must needs leave.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>
</prologue>

<act>
<acttitle>Act I</acttitle>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene i</scenetitle>

<acttitle>Actus Primus.</acttitle>
<stagedir>[ head (her Tresses likewise hanging.) After her Emilia holding]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[The Song, Musicke.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<line>Roses their sharpe spines being gon,</line>
<line>Not royall in their smels alone,</line>
<line>But in their hew.</line>
<line>Maiden Pinckes, of odour faint,</line>
<line>Dazies smel-lesse, yet most quaint</line>
<line>And sweet Time true.</line>
<line>Prim-rose first borne, child of Ver,</line>
<line>Merry Spring times Herbinger,</line>
<line>With her bels dimme.</line>
<line>Oxlips, in their Cradles growing,</line>
<line>Mary-golds, on death beds blowing,</line>
<line>Larkes-heeles trymme.</line>
<line>All deere natures children: sweetely</line>
<line>fore Bride and Bridegroomes feete</line>
<stagedir>[Strew Flowers.]</stagedir>
<line>Blessing their sence.</line>
<line>Not an angle of the aire,</line>
<line>Bird melodious, or bird faire,</line>
<line>Is absent hence.</line>
<line>The Crow, the slaundrous Cuckoe, nor</line>
<line>The boding Raven, nor Chough hee</line>
<line>Nor chattring Pie,</line>
<line>May on our Bridehouse pearch or sing,</line>
<line>Or with them any discord bring</line>
<line>But from it fly.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[ Enter 3. Queenes in Blacke, with vailes staind, with imperiall]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>For pitties sake and true gentilities,</line>
<line>Heare, and respect me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>For your Mothers sake,</line>
<line>And as you wish your womb may thrive with faire ones,</line>
<line>Heare and respect me.</line>
<line>Of cleere virginity, be Advocate</line>
<line>For us, and our distresses: This good deede</line>
<line>Shall raze you out o'th Booke of Trespasses</line>
<line>All you are set downe there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Theseus.</speaker>
<line>Sad Lady rise.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hypol.</speaker>
<line>Stand up.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>No knees to me.</line>
<line>What woman I may steed that is distrest,</line>
<line>Does bind me to her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>What's your request? Deliver you for all.</line>
<line>The Beakes of Ravens, Tallents of the Kights,</line>
<line>And pecks of Crowes, in the fowle feilds of Thebs,</line>
<line>He will not suffer us to burne their bones,</line>
<line>To urne their ashes, nor to take th' offence</line>
<line>Of mortall loathsomenes from the blest eye</line>
<line>Of holy Phaebus, but infects the windes</line>
<line>With stench of our slaine Lords. O pitty Duke,</line>
<line>Thou purger of the earth, draw thy feard Sword</line>
<line>That does good turnes to'th world; give us the Bones</line>
<line>Of our dead Kings, that we may Chappell them;</line>
<line>And of thy boundles goodnes take some note</line>
<line>That for our crowned heades we have no roofe,</line>
<line>Save this which is the Lyons, and the Beares,</line>
<line>And vault to every thing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Pray you kneele not,</line>
<line>I was transported with your Speech, and suffer'd</line>
<line>As wakes my vengeance, and revenge for 'em.</line>
<line>King Capaneus, was your Lord the day</line>
<line>That he should marry you, at such a season,</line>
<line>As now it is with me, I met your Groome,</line>
<line>By Marsis Altar, you were that time faire;</line>
<line>Not Iunos Mantle fairer then your Tresses,</line>
<line>Nor in more bounty spread her. Your wheaten wreathe</line>
<line>Was then nor threashd, nor blasted; Fortune at you</line>
<line>He tumbled downe upon his Nenuan hide</line>
<line>And swore his sinews thawd: O greife, and time,</line>
<line>Fearefull consumers, you will all devoure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>O I hope some God,</line>
<line>Some God hath put his mercy in your manhood</line>
<line>Whereto meel infuse powre, and presse you forth</line>
<line>Our undertaker.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>O no knees, none Widdow,</line>
<line>Vnto the Helmeted-Belona use them,</line>
<line>And pray for me you Souldier.</line>
<line>Troubled I am. <stagedir>[turnes away.]</stagedir>

</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>Honoured Hypolita</line>
<line>Most dreaded Amazonian, that ha'st slaine</line>
<line>The Sith-tuskd-Bore; that with thy Arme as strong</line>
<line>As it is white, wast neere to make the male</line>
<line>To thy sex captive; but that this thy Lord</line>
<line>Borne to uphold Creation, in that honour</line>
<line>First nature stilde it in, shrunke thee into</line>
<line>The bownd thou wast ore-flowing; at once subduing</line>
<line>Thy force, and thy affection: Soldiresse</line>
<line>That equally canst poize sternenes with pitty,</line>
<line>Whom now I know hast much more power on him</line>
<line>Then ever he had on thee, who ow'st his strength,</line>
<line>And his, Love too: who is a Servant for</line>
<line>The Tenour of the Speech. Deere Glasse of Ladies</line>
<line>Bid him that we whom flaming war doth scortch,</line>
<line>Vnder the shaddow of his Sword, may coole us:</line>
<line>Require him he advance it ore our heades;</line>
<line>Speak't in a womans key: like such a woman</line>
<line>As any of us three; weepe ere you faile; lend us a knee;</line>
<line>But touch the ground for us no longer time</line>
<line>Then a Doves motion, when the head's pluckt off:</line>
<line>Tell him if he i'th blood cizd field, lay swolne</line>
<line>Showing the Sun his Teeth; grinning at the Moone</line>
<line>What you would doe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Poore Lady, say no more:</line>
<line>I had as leife trace this good action with you</line>
<line>As that whereto I am going, and never yet</line>
<line>Went I so willing, way. My Lord is taken</line>
<line>Hart deepe with your distresse: Let him consider:</line>
<line>Ile speake anon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>O my petition was <stagedir>[kneele to Emilia.]</stagedir>

</line>
<line>Set downe in yce, which by hot greefe uncandied</line>
<line>Melts into drops, so sorrow wanting forme</line>
<line>Is prest with deeper matter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emilia.</speaker>
<line>Pray stand up,</line>
<line>Your greefe is written in your cheeke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>O woe,</line>
<line>You cannot reade it there; there through my teares,</line>
<line>Like wrinckled peobles in a glasse streame</line>
<line>You may behold 'em (Lady, Lady, alacke)</line>
<line>He that will all the Treasure know o'th earth</line>
<line>Must know the Center too; he that will fish</line>
<line>For my least minnow, let him lead his line</line>
<line>To catch one at my heart. O pardon me,</line>
<line>Extremity that sharpens sundry wits</line>
<line>Makes me a Foole.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emili.</speaker>
<line>Pray you say nothing, pray you,</line>
<line>Who cannot feele, nor see the raine being in't,</line>
<line>Knowes neither wet, nor dry, if that you were</line>
<line>The ground-peece of some Painter, I would buy you</line>
<line>T' instruct me gainst a Capitall greefe indeed</line>
<line>Such heart peirc'd demonstration; but alas</line>
<line>Being a naturall Sister of our Sex</line>
<line>Your sorrow beates so ardently upon me,</line>
<line>That it shall make a counter reflect gainst</line>
<line>My Brothers heart, and warme it to some pitty</line>
<line>Though it were made of stone: pray have good comfort.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Forward to'th Temple, leave not out a Iot</line>
<line>O'th sacred Ceremony.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>O This Celebration</line>
<line>Will long last, and be more costly then,</line>
<line>Your Suppliants war: Remember that your Fame</line>
<line>Knowles in the eare, o'th world: what you doe quickly,</line>
<line>Is not done rashly; your first thought is more.</line>
<line>Then others laboured meditance: your premeditating</line>
<line>More then their actions: But oh Iove, your actions</line>
<line>Soone as they mooves as Asprayes doe the fish,</line>
<line>Subdue before they touch, thinke, deere Duke thinke</line>
<line>What beds our slaine Kings have.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>What greifes our beds</line>
<line>That our deere Lords have none.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>None fit for'th dead:</line>
<line>Those that with Cordes, Knives, drams precipitance,</line>
<line>Weary of this worlds light, have to themselves</line>
<line>Beene deathes most horrid Agents, humaine grace</line>
<line>Affords them dust and shaddow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>But our Lords</line>
<line>Ly blistring fore the visitating Sunne,</line>
<line>And were good Kings, when living.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>It is true, and I will give you comfort,</line>
<line>To give your dead Lords graves:</line>
<line>The which to doe, must make some worke with Creon;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>And that worke presents it selfe to'th doing:</line>
<line>Now twill take forme, the heates are gone to morrow.</line>
<line>Then, booteles toyle must recompence it selfe,</line>
<line>With it's owne sweat; Now he's secure,</line>
<line>Not dreames, we stand before your puissance</line>
<line>Wrinching our holy begging in our eyes</line>
<line>To make petition cleere.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>Now you may take him,</line>
<line>Drunke with his victory.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>And his Army full</line>
<line>Of Bread, and sloth.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Artesius that best knowest</line>
<line>How to draw out fit to this enterprise,</line>
<line>The prim'st for this proceeding, and the number</line>
<line>To carry such a businesse, forth and levy</line>
<line>Our worthiest Instruments, whilst we despatch</line>
<line>This grand act of our life, this daring deede</line>
<line>Of Fate in wedlocke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>Dowagers, take hands</line>
<line>Let us be Widdowes to our woes, delay</line>
<line>Commends us to a famishing hope.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<line>Farewell.</line>
<line>For best solicitation.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Why good Ladies,</line>
<line>This is a service, whereto I am going,</line>
<line>Greater then any was; it more imports me</line>
<line>Then all the actions that I have foregone,</line>
<line>Or futurely can cope.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>The more proclaiming</line>
<line>Our suit shall be neglected, when her Armes</line>
<line>Able to locke Iove from a Synod, shall</line>
<line>By warranting Moone-light corslet thee, oh when</line>
<line>Her twyning Cherries shall their sweetnes fall</line>
<line>Vpon thy tastefull lips, what wilt thou thinke</line>
<line>Of rotten Kings or blubberd Queenes, what care</line>
<line>For what thou feelst not? what thou feelst being able</line>
<line>To make Mars spurne his Drom. O if thou couch</line>
<line>But one night with her, every howre in't will</line>
<line>Take hostage of thee for a hundred, and</line>
<line>Thou shalt remember nothing more, then what</line>
<line>That Banket bids thee too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Though much unlike</line>
<line>You should be so transported, as much sorry</line>
<line>I should be such a Suitour; yet I thinke</line>
<line>Did I not by th' abstayning of my joy</line>
<line>Which breeds a deeper longing, cure their surfeit</line>
<line>That craves a present medcine, I should plucke</line>
<line>All Ladies scandall on me. Therefore Sir</line>
<line>As I shall here make tryall of my prayres,</line>
<line>Either presuming them to have some force,</line>
<line>Or sentencing for ay their vigour dombe,</line>
<line>Prorogue this busines, we are going about, and hang</line>
<line>Your Sheild afore your Heart, about that necke</line>
<line>Which is my Fee, and which I freely lend</line>
<line>To doe these poore Queenes service.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>All Queens.</speaker>
<line>Oh helpe now</line>
<line>Our Cause cries for your knee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>If you grant not</line>
<line>My Sister her petition in that force,</line>
<line>With that Celerity, and nature which</line>
<line>Shee makes it in: from henceforth ile not dare</line>
<line>To aske you any thing, nor be so hardy</line>
<line>Ever to take a Husband.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Pray stand up.</line>
<line>I am entreating of my selfe to doe</line>
<line>That which you kneele to have me; Pyrithous</line>
<line>Leade on the Bride; get you and pray the Gods</line>
<line>For successe, and returne, omit not any thing</line>
<line>In the pretended Celebration: Queenes</line>
<line>Follow your Soldier (as before) hence you</line>
<line>And at the banckes of Anly meete us with</line>
<line>The forces you can raise, where we shall finde</line>
<line>The moytie of a number, for a busines,</line>
<line>More bigger look't; since that our Theame is haste</line>
<line>I stamp this kisse upon thy currant lippe,</line>
<line>Sweete keepe it as my Token; Set you forward</line>
<line>For I will see you gone.</line> 
<stagedir>[Exeunt towards the Temple.]</stagedir>
<line>Farewell my beauteous Sister: Pyrithous</line>
<line>Keepe the feast full, bate not an howre on't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pirithous.</speaker>
<line>Sir</line>
<line>Ile follow you at heeles; The Feasts solempnity</line>
<line>Shall want till your returne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Cosen I charge you</line>
<line>Boudge not from Athens; We shall be returning</line>
<line>Ere you can end this Feast; of which I pray you</line>
<line>Make no abatement; once more farewell all.</line>
<line> o'th (world.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.  Qu.</speaker>
<line>If not above him, for</line>
<line>Thou being but mortall makest affections bend</line>
<line>To Godlike honours; they themselves some say</line>
<line>Grone under such a Mastry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>As we are men</line>
<line>Thus should we doe, being sensually subdude</line>
<line>We loose our humane tytle; good cheere Ladies.</line> 
<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>
<line>Now turne we towards your Comforts.</line> 
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene ii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 2. Enter Palamon, and Arcite.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Deere Palamon, deerer in love then Blood</line>
<line>And our prime Cosen, yet unhardned in</line>
<line>The Crimes of nature; Let us leave the Citty</line>
<line>Thebs, and the temptings in't, before we further</line>
<line>Sully our glosse of youth,</line>
<line>And here to keepe in abstinence we shame</line>
<line>As in Incontinence; for not to swim</line>
<line>I'th aide o'th Current, were almost to sincke,</line>
<line>At least to frustrate striving, and to follow</line>
<line>The common Streame, twold bring us to an Edy</line>
<line>Where we should turne or drowne; if labour through,</line>
<line>Our gaine but life, and weakenes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Your advice</line>
<line>Is cride up with example; what strange ruins</line>
<line>Since first we went to Schoole, may we perceive</line>
<line>Walking in Thebs? Skars, and bare weedes</line>
<line>The gaine o'th Martialist, who did propound</line>
<line>To his bold ends, honour, and golden Ingots,</line>
<line>Which though he won, he had not, and now flurted</line>
<line>By peace for whom he fought, who then shall offer</line>
<line>To Marsis so scornd Altar? I doe bleede</line>
<line>When such I meete, and with great Iuno would</line>
<line>Resume her ancient fit of Ielouzie</line>
<line>To get the Soldier worke, that peace might purge</line>
<line>For her repletion, and retaine anew</line>
<line>Her charitable heart now hard, and harsher</line>
<line>Then strife, or war could be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Are you not out?</line>
<line>Meete you no ruine, but the Soldier in</line>
<line>The Cranckes, and turnes of Thebs? you did begin</line>
<line>As if you met decaies of many kindes:</line>
<line>Perceive you none, that doe arowse your pitty</line>
<line>But th' un-considerd Soldier?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes, I pitty</line>
<line>Decaies where ere I finde them, but such most</line>
<line>That sweating in an honourable Toyle</line>
<line>Are paide with yce to coole 'em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Tis not this</line>
<line>I did begin to speake of: This is vertue</line>
<line>Of no respect in Thebs, I spake of Thebs</line>
<line>How dangerous if we will keepe our Honours,</line>
<line>It is for our resyding, where every evill</line>
<line>Hath a good cullor; where eve'ry seeming good's</line>
<line>A certaine evill, where not to be ev'n Iumpe</line>
<line>As they are, here were to be strangers, and</line>
<line>Such things to be meere Monsters.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Tis in our power,</line>
<line>(Vnlesse we feare that Apes can Tutor's) to</line>
<line>Be Masters of our manners: what neede I</line>
<line>Affect anothers gate, which is not catching</line>
<line>Where there is faith, or to be fond upon</line>
<line>Anothers way of speech, when by mine owne</line>
<line>I may be reasonably conceiv'd; sav'd too,</line>
<line>Speaking it truly; why am I bound</line>
<line>By any generous bond to follow him</line>
<line>Followes his Taylor, haply so long untill</line>
<line>The follow'd, make pursuit? or let me know,</line>
<line>Why mine owne Barber is unblest, with him</line>
<line>My poore Chinne too, for tis not Cizard iust</line>
<line>To such a Favorites glasse: What Cannon is there</line>
<line>That does command my Rapier from my hip</line>
<line>To dangle't in my hand, or to go tip toe</line>
<line>Before the streete be foule? Either I am</line>
<line>The fore-horse in the Teame, or I am none</line>
<line>That draw i'th sequent trace: these poore sleight sores,</line>
<line>Neede not a plantin; That which tips my bosome</line>
<line>Almost to'th heart's,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Our Vncle Creon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>He,</line>
<line>A most unbounded Tyrant, whose successes</line>
<line>Makes heaven unfeard, and villany assured</line>
<line>Beyond its power: there's nothing, almost puts</line>
<line>Faith in a feavour, and deifies alone</line>
<line>Voluble chance, who onely attributes</line>
<line>The faculties of other Instruments</line>
<line>To his owne Nerves and act; Commands men service,</line>
<line>And what they winne in't, boot and glory on;</line>
<line>That feares not to do harm; good, dares not; Let</line>
<line>The blood of mine that's sibbe to him, be suckt</line>
<line>From me with Leeches, Let them breake and fall</line>
<line>Off me with that corruption.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Cleere spirited Cozen</line>
<line>Lets leave his Court, that we may nothing share,</line>
<line>Of his lowd infamy: for our milke,</line>
<line>Will relish of the pasture, and we must</line>
<line>Be vile, or disobedient, not his kinesmen</line>
<line>In blood, unlesse in quality.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Nothing truer:</line>
<line>I thinke the Ecchoes of his shames have dea'ft</line>
<line>The eares of heav'nly Iustice: widdows cryes</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Valerius.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Val.</speaker>
<line>The King cals for you; yet be leaden footed</line>
<line>Till his great rage be off him. Phebus when</line>
<line>He broke his whipstocke and exclaimd against</line>
<line>The Horses of the Sun, but whisperd too</line>
<line>The lowdenesse of his Fury.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Small windes shake him,</line>
<line>But whats the matter?</line>
<line>Ruine to Thebs, who is at hand to seale</line>
<line>The promise of his wrath.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Let him approach;</line>
<line>But that we feare the Gods in him, he brings not</line>
<line>A jot of terrour to us; Yet what man</line>
<line>Thirds his owne worth (the case is each of ours)</line>
<line>When that his actions dregd, with minde assurd</line>
<line>Tis bad he goes about.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Leave that unreasond.</line>
<line>Our services stand now for Thebs, not Creon,</line>
<line>Yet to be neutrall to him, were dishonour;</line>
<line>Rebellious to oppose: therefore we must</line>
<line>With him stand to the mercy of our Fate,</line>
<line>Who hath bounded our last minute.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>So we must;</line>
<line>Ist sed this warres afoote? or shall it be</line>
<line>On faile of some condition.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Val.</speaker>
<line>Tis in motion</line>
<line>The intelligence of state came in the instant</line>
<line>With the defier.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Lets to the king, who, were he</line>
<line>A quarter carrier of that honour, which</line>
<line>His Enemy come in, the blood we venture</line>
<line>Should be as for our health, which were not spent,</line>
<line>Rather laide out for purchase: but alas</line>
<line>Our hands advanc'd before our hearts, what will</line>
<line>The fall o'th stroke doe damage?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arci.</speaker>
<line>Let th' event,</line>
<line>That never erring Arbitratour, tell us</line>
<line>When we know all our selves, and let us follow</line>
<line>The becking of our chance.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iii</scenetitle>


<scenetitle>Scaena 3. Enter Pirithous, Hipolita, Emilia.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>No further.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Sir farewell; repeat my wishes</line>
<line>To our great Lord, of whose succes I dare not</line>
<line>Make any timerous question, yet I wish him</line>
<line>Exces, and overflow of power, and't might be</line>
<line>To dure ill-dealing fortune; speede to him,</line>
<line>Store never hurtes good Gouernours.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>Though I know</line>
<line>His Ocean needes not my poore drops, yet they</line>
<line>Must yeild their tribute there: My precious Maide,</line>
<line>Those best affections, that the heavens infuse</line>
<line>In their best temperd peices, keepe enthroand</line>
<line>In your deare heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Thanckes Sir; Remember me</line>
<line>To our all royall Brother, for whose speede</line>
<line>The great Bellona ile sollicite; and</line>
<line>Since in our terrene State petitions are not</line>
<line>Without giftes understood: Ile offer to her</line>
<line>What I shall be advised she likes, our hearts</line>
<line>Are in his Army, in his Tent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>In's bosome:</line>
<line>We have bin Soldiers, and wee cannot weepe</line>
<line>When our Friends don their helmes, or put to sea,</line>
<line>Or tell of Babes broachd on the Launce, or women</line>
<line>That have sod their Infants in (and after eate them)</line>
<line>The brine, they wept at killing 'em; Then if</line>
<line>You stay to see of us such Spincsters, we</line>
<line>Should hold you here for ever.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>Peace be to you</line>
<line>As I pursue this war, which shall be then</line>
<line>Beyond further requiring.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit Pir.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>How his longing</line>
<line>Followes his Friend; since his depart, his sportes</line>
<line>Though craving seriousnes, and skill, past slightly</line>
<line>His careles execution, where nor gaine</line>
<line>Made him regard, or losse consider, but</line>
<line>Playing ore busines in his hand, another</line>
<line>Directing in his head, his minde, nurse equall</line>
<line>To these so diffring Twyns; have you observ'd him,</line>
<line>Since our great Lord departed?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>With much labour:</line>
<line>And I did love him fort, they two have Cabind</line>
<line>In many as dangerous, as poore a Corner,</line>
<line>Perill and want contending, they have swift</line>
<line>Torrents whose roring tyranny and power</line>
<line>I'th least of these was dreadfull, and they have</line>
<line>Fought out together, where Deaths-selfe was lodgd,</line>
<line>Yet fate hath brought them off: Their knot of love</line>
<line>Tide, weau'd, intangled, with so true, so long,</line>
<line>And with a finger of so deepe a cunning</line>
<line>May be outworne, never undone. I thinke</line>
<line>Theseus cannot be umpire to himselfe</line>
<line>Cleaving his conscience into twaine, and doing</line>
<line>Each side like Iustice, which he loves best.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Doubtlesse</line>
<line>There is a best, and reason has no manners</line>
<line>To say it is not you: I was acquainted</line>
<line>Once with a time, when I enjoyd a Play-fellow;</line>
<line>You were at wars, when she the grave enrichd,</line>
<line>Who made too proud the Bed, tooke leave o'th Moone</line>
<line>(Which then lookt pale at parting) when our count</line>
<line>Was each a eleven.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Twas Flauia.,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Yes</line>
<line>You talke of Pirithous and Theseus love;</line>
<line>Theirs has more ground, is more maturely seasond,</line>
<line>More buckled with strong Iudgement, and their needes</line>
<line>The one of th' other may be said to water <stagedir>[ 2. Hearses ready]</stagedir></line>
<stagedir>[ with Palamon:]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ and Arcite:]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[the 3.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Queenes.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ Theseus: and]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ his Lordes]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ready.]</stagedir>
<line>Their intertangled rootes of love, but I</line>
<line>And shee (I sigh and spoke of) were things innocent,</line>
<line>Lou'd for we did, and like the Elements</line>
<line>That know not what, nor why, yet doe effect</line>
<line>Rare issues by their operance; our soules</line>
<line>Did so to one another; what she lik'd,</line>
<line>Was then of me approov'd, what not condemd</line>
<line>No more arraignement, the flowre that I would plucke</line>
<line>And put betweene my breasts, oh (then but beginning</line>
<line>To swell about the blossome) she would long</line>
<line>Till shee had such another, and commit it</line>
<line>To the like innocent Cradle, where Phenix like</line>
<line>They dide in perfume: on my head no toy</line>
<line>But was her patterne, her affections (pretty</line>
<line>Though happely, her careles, were, I followed</line>
<line>For my most serious decking, had mine eare</line>
<line>Stolne some new aire, or at adventure humd on</line>
<line>From musicall Coynadge; why it was a note</line>
<line>Whereon her spirits would sojourne (rather dwell on)</line>
<line>And sing it in her slumbers; This rehearsall</line>
<line>(Which fury-innocent wots well) comes in</line>
<line>Like old importments bastard, has this end,</line>
<line>That the true love tweene Mayde, and mayde, may be</line>
<line>More then in sex individuall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Y'are out of breath</line>
<line>And this high speeded-pace, is but to say</line>
<line>That you shall never (like the Maide Flavina)</line>
<line>Love any that's calld Man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I am sure I shall not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Now alacke weake Sister,</line>
<line>I must no more beleeve thee in this point</line>
<line>(Though, in't I know thou dost beleeve thy selfe,)</line>
<line>Then I will trust a sickely appetite,</line>
<line>That loathes even as it longs, but sure my Sister</line>
<line>If I were ripe for your perswasion, you</line>
<line>Have saide enough to shake me from the Arme</line>
<line>Of the all noble Theseus, for whose fortunes,</line>
<line>I will now in, and kneele with great assurance,</line>
<line>That we, more then his Pirothous, possesse</line>
<line>The high throne in his heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I am not against your faith,</line>
<line>Yet I continew mine.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir> 
<stagedir>[Cornets.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iv</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 4. A Battaile strooke within: Then a Retrait: Florish.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>To thee no starre be darke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>Both heaven and earth</line>
<line>Friend thee for ever.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>All the good that may</line>
<line>Be wishd upon thy head, I cry Amen too't.</line>
<line>And in their time chastice: goe and finde out</line>
<line>The bones of your dead Lords, and honour them</line>
<line>With treble Ceremonie, rather then a gap</line>
<line>Should be in their deere rights, we would suppl'it.</line>
<line>But those we will depute, which shall invest</line>
<line>You in your dignities, and even each thing</line>
<line>Our hast does leave imperfect; So adiew</line>
<line>And heavens good eyes looke on you. What are those?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt Queenes.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Herald.</speaker>
<line>Men of great quality, as may be judgd</line>
<line>By their appointment; Some of Thebs have told's</line>
<line>They are Sisters children, Nephewes to the King.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>By'th Helme of Mars, I saw them in the war,</line>
<line>Like to a paire of Lions, smeard with prey,</line>
<line>Make lanes in troopes agast. I fixt my note</line>
<line>Constantly on them; for they were a marke</line>
<line>Worth a god's view: what prisoner was't that told me</line>
<line>When I enquired their names?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Herald.</speaker>
<line>We leave, they'r called</line>
<line>Arcite and Palamon,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Tis right, those, those</line>
<line>They are not dead?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>Nor in a state of life, had they bin taken </line>
<stagedir>[3. Hearses ready.]</stagedir>
<line>When their last hurts were given, twas possible</line>
<line>They might have bin recovered; Yet they breathe</line>
<line>And haue the name of men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Then like men use 'em</line>
<line>The very lees of such (millions of rates)</line>
<line>Exceede the wine of others, all our Surgions</line>
<line>Convent in their behoofe, our richest balmes</line>
<line>Rather then niggard wast, their lives concerne us,</line>
<line>Much more then Thebs is worth, rather then have 'em</line>
<line>Freed of this plight, and in their morning state</line>
<line>(Sound and at liberty) I would 'em dead,</line>
<line>But forty thousand fold, we had rather have 'em</line>
<line>Prisoners to us, then death; Beare 'em speedily</line>
<line>From our kinde aire, to them unkinde, and minister</line>
<line>What man to man may doe for our sake more,</line>
<line>Since I have knowne frights, fury, friends, beheastes,</line>
<line>Loves, provocations, zeale, a mistris Taske,</line>
<line>Desire of liberty, a feavour, madnes,</line>
<line>Hath set a marke which nature could not reach too</line>
<line>Without some imposition, sicknes in will</line>
<line>Or wrastling strength in reason, for our Love</line>
<line>And great Appollos mercy, all our best,</line>
<line>Their best skill tender. Leade into the Citty,</line>
<line>Where having bound things scatterd, we will post</line>
<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>
<line>To Athens for our Army.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Musicke.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene v</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 5. Enter the Queenes with the Hearses of their</scenetitle>
<stagedir>[Knightes, in a Funerall Solempnity, &amp;c.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<line>Vrnes, and odours, bring away,</line>
<line>Vapours, sighes, darken the day;</line>
<line>Our dole more deadly lookes than dying</line>
<line>Balmes, and Gummes, and heavy cheeres,</line>
<line>Sacred vials fill'd with teares,</line>
<line>And clamors through the wild ayre flying.</line>
<line>Come all sad, and solempne Showes,</line>
<line>That are quick-eyd pleasures foes;</line>
<line>We convent nought else but woes. We convent, &amp;c.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Qu.</speaker>
<line>And this to yours.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Qu.</speaker>
<line>Yours this way: Heavens lend</line>
<line>A thousand differing waies, to one sure end.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. Qu.</speaker>
<line>This world's a Citty full of straying Streetes,</line>
<line>And Death's the market place, where each one meetes.</line>
</speech> 

<stagedir>[Exeunt severally.]</stagedir>

</scene>  

</act>

<act>
<acttitle>Act II</acttitle>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene i</scenetitle>

<stagedir>Scaena 1. Enter Iailor, and Wooer.</stagedir>

<speech>
<line>Keepe, though it be for great ones, yet they seldome</line>
<line>Come; Before one Salmon, you shall take a number</line>
<line>Of Minnowes: I am given out to be better lyn'd</line>
<line>Then it can appeare, to me report is a true</line>
<line>Speaker: I would I were really, that I am</line>
<line>Deliverd to be: Marry, what I have (be it what</line>
<line>It will) I will assure upon my daughter at</line>
<line>The day of my death.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Sir I demaund no more then your owne offer,</line>
<line>And I will estate your Daughter in what I</line>
<line>Have promised,</line>
<stagedir>[Enter Daughter.]</stagedir>
<line>When that shall be seene, I tender my consent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I have Sir; here shee comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iailor.</speaker>
<line>Your Friend and I have chanced to name</line>
<line>You here, upon the old busines: But no more of that.</line>
<line>Now, so soone as the Court hurry is over, we will</line>
<line>Have an end of it: I'th meane time looke tenderly</line>
<line>To the two Prisoners. I can tell you they are princes.</line>
<line>Doe thinke they have patience to make any adversity</line>
<line>Asham'd; the prison it selfe is proud of 'em; and</line>
<line>They have all the world in their Chamber.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iailor.</speaker>
<line>They are fam'd to be a paire of absolute men.</line>
<line> (doers.</line>

<line>Mervaile how they would have lookd had they beene</line>
<line>Victors, that with such a constant Nobility, enforce</line>
<line>A freedome out of Bondage, making misery their</line>
<line>Mirth, and affliction, a toy to jest at.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iailor.</speaker>
<line>Doe they so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daug.</speaker>
<line>It seemes to me they have no more sence of their</line>
<line>Captivity, then I of ruling Athens: they eate</line>
<line>Well, looke merrily, discourse of many things,</line>
<line>But nothing of their owne restraint, and disasters:</line>
<line>Yet sometime a devided sigh, martyrd as twer</line>
<line>I'th deliverance, will breake from one of them.</line>
<line>When the other presently gives it so sweete a rebuke,</line>
<line>That I could wish my selfe a Sigh to be so chid,</line>
<line>Or at least a Sigher to be comforted.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I never saw 'em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iailor.</speaker>
<line>The Duke himselfe came privately in the night,</line>
<stagedir>[Enter Palamon, and Arcite, above.]</stagedir>
<line>And so did they, what the reason of it is, I</line>
<line>Know not: Looke yonder they are; that's</line>
<line>Arcite lookes out.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>No Sir, no, that's Palamon: Arcite is the</line>
<line>Lower of the twaine; you may perceive a part</line>
<line>Of him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iai.</speaker>
<line>Goe too, leave your pointing; they would not</line>
<line>Make us their object; out of their sight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>It is a holliday to looke on them: Lord, the</line>
<line>Diffrence of men.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene ii</scenetitle>


<scenetitle>Scaena 2. Enter Palamon, and Arcite in prison.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>How doe you Noble Cosen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>How doe you Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Why strong inough to laugh at misery,</line>
<line>And beare the chance of warre yet, we are prisoners</line>
<line>I feare for ever Cosen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>I beleeve it,</line>
<line>And to that destiny have patiently</line>
<line>Laide up my houre to come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Oh Cosen Arcite,</line>
<line>Where is Thebs now? where is our noble Country?</line>
<line>Where are our friends, and kindreds? never more</line>
<line>Must we behold those comforts, never see</line>
<line>The hardy youthes strive for the Games of honour</line>
<line>(Hung with the painted favours of their Ladies)</line>
<line>Like tall Ships under saile: then start amongst 'em</line>
<line>And as an Eastwind leave 'em all behinde us,</line>
<line>Like lazy Clowdes, whilst Palamon and Arcite,</line>
<line>Even in the wagging of a wanton leg</line>
<line>Out-stript the peoples praises, won the Garlands,</line>
<line>Ere they have time to wish 'em ours. O never</line>
<line>Shall we two exercise, like Twyns of honour,</line>
<line>Our Armes againe, and feele our fyry horses</line>
<line>Like proud Seas under us, our good Swords, now</line>
<line>(Better the red-eyd god of war nev'r were)</line>
<line>Ravishd our sides, like age must run to rust,</line>
<line>And decke the Temples of those gods that hate us,</line>
<line>These hands shall never draw 'em out like lightning</line>
<line>To blast whole Armies more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>No Palamon,</line>
<line>Those hopes are Prisoners with us, here we are</line>
<line>And here the graces of our youthes must wither</line>
<line>Like a too-timely Spring; here age must finde us,</line>
<line>And which is heaviest (Palamon) unmarried,</line>
<line>The sweete embraces of a loving wife</line>
<line>Loden with kisses, armd with thousand Cupids</line>
<line>Shall never claspe our neckes, no issue know us,</line>
<line>No figures of our selves shall we ev'r see,</line>
<line>To glad our age, and like young Eagles teach 'em</line>
<line>Boldly to gaze against bright armes, and say</line>
<line>Remember what your fathers were, and conquer.</line>
<line>The faire-eyd Maides, shall weepe our Banishments,</line>
<line>And in their Songs, curse ever-blinded fortune</line>
<line>Till shee for shame see what a wrong she has done</line>
<line>To youth and nature; This is all our world;</line>
<line>We shall know nothing here but one another,</line>
<line>Heare nothing but the Clocke that tels our woes.</line>
<line>The Vine shall grow, but we shall never see it:</line>
<line>Sommer shall come, and with her all delights;</line>
<line>But dead-cold winter must inhabite here still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Tis too true Arcite. To our Theban houndes,</line>
<line>That shooke the aged Forrest with their ecchoes,</line>
<line>No more now must we halloa, no more shake</line>
<line>Our pointed Iavelyns, whilst the angry Swine</line>
<line>Flyes like a parthian quiver from our rages,</line>
<line>Strucke with our well-steeld Darts: All valiant uses,</line>
<line>(The foode, and nourishment of noble mindes,)</line>
<line>In us two here shall perish; we shall die</line>
<line>(Which is the curse of honour) lastly,</line>
<line>Children of greife, and Ignorance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Yet Cosen,</line>
<line>Even from the bottom of these miseries</line>
<line>From all that fortune can inflict upon us,</line>
<line>I see two comforts rysing, two meere blessings,</line>
<line>If the gods please, to hold here a brave patience,</line>
<line>And the enjoying of our greefes together.</line>
<line>Whilst Palamon is with me, let me perish</line>
<line>If I thinke this our prison.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pala.</speaker>
<line>Certeinly,</line>
<line>Tis a maine goodnes Cosen, that our fortunes</line>
<line>Were twyn'd together; tis most true, two soules</line>
<line>Put in two noble Bodies, let 'em suffer</line>
<line>The gaule of hazard, so they grow together,</line>
<line>Will never sincke, they must not, say they could,</line>
<line>A willing man dies sleeping, and all's done.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Shall we make worthy uses of this place</line>
<line>That all men hate so much?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>How gentle Cosen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Let's thinke this prison, holy sanctuary,</line>
<line>To keepe us from corruption of worse men,</line>
<line>We are young and yet desire the waies of honour,</line>
<line>That liberty and common Conversation</line>
<line>The poyson of pure spirits; might like women</line>
<line>Wooe us to wander from. What worthy blessing</line>
<line>Can be but our Imaginations</line>
<line>May make it ours? And heere being thus together,</line>
<line>We are an endles mine to one another;</line>
<line>We are one anothers wife, ever begetting</line>
<line>New birthes of love; we are father, friends, acquaintance,</line>
<line>We are in one another, Families,</line>
<line>I am your heire, and you are mine: This place</line>
<line>Is our Inheritance: no hard Oppressour</line>
<line>Dare take this from us; here with a little patience</line>
<line>We shall live long, and loving: No surfeits seeke us:</line>
<line>The hand of war hurts none here, nor the Seas</line>
<line>Swallow their youth: were we at liberty,</line>
<line>A wife might part us lawfully, or busines,</line>
<line>Quarrels consume us, Envy of ill men</line>
<line>Crave our acquaintance, I might sicken Cosen,</line>
<line>Where you should never know it, and so perish</line>
<line>Without your noble hand to close mine eies,</line>
<line>Or praiers to the gods; a thousand chaunces</line>
<line>Were we from hence, would seaver us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>You have made me</line>
<line>(I thanke you Cosen Arcite) almost wanton</line>
<line>With my Captivity: what a misery</line>
<line>It is to live abroade? and every where:</line>
<line>Tis like a Beast me thinkes: I finde the Court here,</line>
<line>I am sure a more content, and all those pleasures</line>
<line>That wooe the wils of men to vanity,</line>
<line>I see through now, and am sufficient</line>
<line>To tell the world, tis but a gaudy shaddow,</line>
<line>That old Time, as he passes by takes with him,</line>
<line>What had we bin old in the Court of Creon,</line>
<line>Where sin is Iustice, lust, and ignorance,</line>
<line>The vertues of the great ones: Cosen Arcite,</line>
<line>Had not the loving gods found this place for us</line>
<line>We had died as they doe, ill old men, unwept,</line>
<line>And had their Epitaphes, the peoples Curses,</line>
<line>Shall I say more?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I would heare you still.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Ye shall.</line>
<line>Is there record of any two that lov'd</line>
<line>Better then we doe Arcite?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Sure there cannot.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I doe not thinke it possible our friendship</line>
<line>Should ever leave us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Till our deathes it cannot</line>
<line> <stagedir>[Enter Emilia and her woman.]</stagedir>

</line>
<line>And after death our spirits shall be led</line>
<line>To those that love eternally. Speake on Sir.</line>
<line>This garden has a world of pleasure in't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>What Flowre is this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>Tis calld Narcissus Madam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>That was a faire Boy certaine, but a foole,</line>
<line>To love himselfe, were there not maides enough?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Pray forward.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Or were they all hard hearted?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>They could not be to one so faire.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Thou wouldst not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>I thinke I should not, Madam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>That's a good wench:</line>
<line>But take heede to your kindnes though.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>Why Madam?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Men are mad things.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Will ye goe forward Cosen?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Ile have a gowne full of 'em and of these,</line>
<line>This is pretty colour, wilt not doe</line>
<line>Rarely upon a Skirt wench?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>Deinty Madam.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Cosen, Cosen, how doe you Sir? Why Palamon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Never till now I was in prison Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Why whats the matter Man?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Behold, and wonder.</line>
<line>By heaven shee is a Goddesse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Ha.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Doe reverence.</line>
<line>She is a Goddesse Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Of all Flowres,</line>
<line>Me thinkes a Rose is best.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>Why gentle Madam?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>It is the very Embleme of a Maide.</line>
<line>For when the west wind courts her gently</line>
<line>How modestly she blowes, and paints the Sun,</line>
<line>Shee lockes her beauties in her bud againe,</line>
<line>And leaves him to base briers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>Yet good Madam,</line>
<line>Sometimes her modesty will blow so far</line>
<line>She fals for't: a Mayde</line>
<line>If shee have any honour, would be loth</line>
<line>To take example by her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Thou art wanton.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>She is wondrous faire.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>She is all the beauty extant.</line>
<line>I am wondrous merry hearted, I could laugh now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>I could lie downe I am sure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>And take one with you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wom.</speaker>
<line>That's as we bargaine Madam,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Well, agree then.</line>
<line> <stagedir>[Exeunt Emilia and woman.]</stagedir>

</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>What thinke you of this beauty?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Tis a rare one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Is't but a rare one?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Yes a matchles beauty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Might not a man well lose himselfe and love her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I cannot tell what you have done, I have,</line>
<line>Beshrew mine eyes for't, now I feele my Shackles.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>You love her then?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Who would not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>And desire her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Before my liberty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I saw her first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>That's nothing</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>But it shall be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I saw her too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes, but you must not love her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I will not as you doe; to worship her;</line>
<line>As she is heavenly, and a blessed Goddes;</line>
<line>(I love her as a woman, to enjoy her)</line>
<line>So both may love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>You shall not love at all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Not love at all.</line>
<line>Who shall deny me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I that first saw her; I that tooke possession</line>
<line>First with mine eye of all those beauties</line>
<line>In her reveald to mankinde: if thou lou'st her,</line>
<line>Or entertain'st a hope to blast my wishes,</line>
<line>Thou art a Traytour Arcite and a fellow</line>
<line>False as thy Title to her: friendship, blood</line>
<line>And all the tyes betweene us I disclaime</line>
<line>If thou once thinke upon her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Yes I love her,</line>
<line>And if the lives of all my name lay on it,</line>
<line>I must doe so, I love her with my soule,</line>
<line>If that will lose ye, farewell Palamon,</line>
<line>I say againe, I love, and in loving her maintaine</line>
<line>I am as worthy, and as free a lover</line>
<line>And have as just a title to her beauty</line>
<line>As any Palamon or any living</line>
<line>That is a mans Sonne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Have I cald thee friend?</line>
<line>Part of your blood, part of your soule? you have told me</line>
<line>That I was Palamon, and you were Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Am not I liable to those affections,</line>
<line>Those joyes, greifes, angers, feares, my friend shall suffer?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Ye may be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Why then would you deale so cunningly,</line>
<line>So strangely, so vnlike a noble kinesman</line>
<line>To love alone? speake truely, doe you thinke me</line>
<line>Vnworthy of her sight?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>No; but unjust,</line>
<line>If thou pursue that sight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Because an other</line>
<line>First sees the Enemy, shall I stand still</line>
<line>And let mine honour downe, and never charge?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes, if he be but one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>But say that one</line>
<line>Had rather combat me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Let that one say so,</line>
<line>And use thy freedome; els if thou pursuest her,</line>
<line>Be as that cursed man that hates his Country,</line>
<line>A branded villaine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You are mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I must be.</line>
<line>Till thou art worthy, Arcite, it concernes me,</line>
<line>And in this madnes, if I hazard thee</line>
<line>And take thy life, I deale but truely.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Fie Sir.</line>
<line>You play the Childe extreamely: I will love her,</line>
<line>I must, I ought to doe so, and I dare,</line>
<line>And all this justly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>O that now, that now</line>
<line>Thy false-selfe and thy friend, had but this fortune</line>
<line>To be one howre at liberty, and graspe</line>
<line>Thou art baser in it then a Cutpurse;</line>
<line>Put but thy head out of this window more,</line>
<line>And as I have a soule, Ile naile thy life too't.</line>
<line>And leape the garden, when I see her next</line>
<stagedir>[Enter Keeper.]</stagedir>
<line>And pitch between her armes to anger thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>No more; the keeper's comming; I shall live</line>
<line>To knocke thy braines out with my Shackles.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Doe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
<line>By your leave Gentlemen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pala.</speaker>
<line>Now honest keeper?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
<line>Lord Arcite, you must presently to'th Duke;</line>
<line>The cause I know not yet.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I am ready keeper.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
<line>Prince Palamon, I must awhile bereave you</line>
<line>Of your faire Cosens Company.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt Arcite, and Keeper.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>And me too,</line>
<line>Even when you please of life; why is he sent for?</line>
<line>It may be he shall marry her, he's goodly,</line>
<line>And like enough the Duke hath taken notice</line>
<line>Both of his blood and body: But his falsehood,</line>
<line>Why should a friend be treacherous? If that</line>
<line>Get him a wife so noble, and so faire;</line>
<line>Let honest men ne're love againe. Once more</line>
<line>I would but see this faire One: Blessed Garden,</line>
<line>And fruite, and flowers more blessed that still blossom</line>
<line>As her bright eies shine on ye. Would I were</line>
<line>For all the fortune of my life hereafter</line>
<line>Yon little Tree, yon blooming Apricocke;</line>
<line>How I would spread, and fling my wanton armes</line>
<line>In at her window; I would bring her fruite</line>
<line>Fit for the Gods to feed on: youth and pleasure</line>
<line>Still as she tasted should be doubled on her,</line>
<line>And if she be not heavenly I would make her</line>
<line>So neere the Gods in nature, they should feare her.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Keeper.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
<line>Banishd: Prince Pirithous</line>
<line>Obtained his liberty; but never more</line>
<line>Vpon his oth and life must he set foote</line>
<line>Vpon this Kingdome.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Hees a blessed man,</line>
<line>He shall see Thebs againe, and call to Armes</line>
<line>The bold yong men, that when he bids 'em charge,</line>
<line>Fall on like fire: Arcite shall have a Fortune,</line>
<line>If he dare make himselfe a worthy Lover,</line>
<line>Yet in the Feild to strike a battle for her;</line>
<line>And if he lose her then, he's a cold Coward;</line>
<line>How bravely may he beare himselfe to win her</line>
<line>If he be noble Arcite; thousand waies.</line>
<line>Were I at liberty, I would doe things</line>
<line>Of such a vertuous greatnes, that this Lady,</line>
<line>This blushing virgine should take manhood to her</line>
<line>And seeke to ravish me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
<line>My Lord for you</line>
<line>I have this charge too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>To discharge my life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Devils take 'em</line>
<line>That are so envious to me; pre'thee kill me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keep.</speaker>
<line>And hang for't afterward.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>By this good light</line>
<line>Had I a sword I would kill thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keep.</speaker>
<line>Why my Lord?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keep.</speaker>
<line>Indeede you must my Lord..</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>May I see the garden?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keep.</speaker>
<line>Noe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Then I am resolud, I will not goe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Doe good keeper.</line>
<line>Ile shake 'em so, ye shall not sleepe,</line>
<line>Ile make ye a new Morrisse, must I goe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Keep.</speaker>
<line>There is no remedy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Farewell kinde window.</line>
<line>May rude winde never hurt thee. O my Lady</line>
<line>If ever thou hast felt what sorrow was,</line>
<line>Dreame how I suffer. Come; now bury me.</line>
</speech> 

<stagedir>[Exeunt Palamon, and Keeper.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 3. Enter Arcite.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Banishd the kingdome? tis a benefit,</line>
<line>A mercy I must thanke 'em for, but banishd</line>
<line>The free enjoying of that face I die for,</line>
<line>Oh twas a studdied punishment, a death</line>
<line>Beyond Imagination: Such a vengeance</line>
<line>That were I old and wicked, all my sins</line>
<line>Could never plucke upon me. Palamon;</line>
<line>Thou ha'st the Start now, thou shalt stay and see</line>
<line>Her bright eyes breake each morning gainst thy window,</line>
<line>And let in life to thee; thou shalt feede</line>
<line>Vpon the sweetenes of a noble beauty,</line>
<line>That nature nev'r exceeded, nor nev'r shall:</line>
<line>Good gods? what happines has Palamon?</line>
<line>Twenty to one, hee'le come to speake to her,</line>
<line>And if she be as gentle, as she's faire,</line>
<line>I know she's his, he has a Tongue will tame</line>
<line>I know mine owne, is but a heape of ruins,</line>
<line>And no redresse there, if I goe, he has her.</line>
<line>I am resolu'd an other shape shall make me,</line>
<line>Or end my fortunes. Either way, I am happy:</line>
<line>Ile see her, and be neere her, or no more.</line>
</speech>  

<stagedir>[Enter .4. Country people, &amp; one with a garlond before them.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>And Ile be there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>And I.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Why then have with ye Boyes; Tis but a chiding,</line>
<line>Let the plough play to day, ile tick'lt out</line>
<line>Of the Iades tailes to morrow.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker><line>I am sure</line>
<line>To have my wife as jealous as a Turkey:</line>
<line>But that's all one, ile goe through, let her mumble.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Clap her aboard to morrow night, and stoa her,</line>
<line>And all's made up againe.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line> I, doe but put a feskue in her fist, and you shall see her</line>
<line>Take a new lesson out, and be a good wench.</line>
<line>Doe we all hold, against the Maying?</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Hold? what should aile us?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Arcus will be there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>And Sennois.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Hee'l eate a hornebooke ere he faile: goe too, the matter's</line>




</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Shall we be lusty.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>All the Boyes in Athens blow wind i'th breech on's,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>O pardon me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Weele see the sports, then every man to's Tackle: and</line>
<line>Sweete Companions lets rehearse by any meanes, before</line>
<line>The Ladies see us, and doe sweetly, and God knows what</line>
<line>May come on't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Whither? why, what a question's that?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Yes, tis a question, to me that know not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>To the Games my Friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Where were you bred you know it not?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Not farre Sir,</line>
<line>Are there such Games to day?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker>
<line>Yes marry are there:</line>
<line>And such as you neuer saw; The Duke himselfe</line>
<line>Will be in person there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>What pastimes are they?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Wrastling, and Running; Tis a pretty Fellow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Thou wilt not goe along.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Not yet Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Well Sir</line>
<line>Take your owne time, come Boyes</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker>
<line>My minde misgives me</line>
<line>This fellow has a veng'ance tricke o'th hip,</line>
<line>Marke how his Bodi's made for't</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Ile be hangd though</line>
<line>If he dare venture, hang him plumb porredge,</line>
<line>I durst not wish for. Well, I could have wrestled,</line>
<line>The best men calld it excellent, and run</line>
<line>Swifter, then winde upon a feild of Corne</line>
<line>(Curling the wealthy eares) never flew: Ile venture,</line>
<line>And in some poore disguize be there, who knowes</line>
<line>Whether my browes may not be girt with garlands?</line>
<line>And happines preferre me to a place,</line>
<line>Where I may ever dwell in sight of her.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[ Exit Arcite]</stagedir>
</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iv</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 4. Enter Iailors Daughter alone.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<line>My Father the meane Keeper of his Prison,</line>
<line>And he a Prince; To marry him is hopelesse;</line>
<line>To be his whore, is witles; Out upon't;</line>
<line>What pushes are we wenches driven to</line>
<line>When fifteene once has found us? First I saw him,</line>
<line>I (seeing) thought he was a goodly man;</line>
<line>He has as much to please a woman in him,</line>
<line>(If he please to bestow it so) as ever</line>
<line>These eyes yet lookt on; Next, I pittied him,</line>
<line>And so would any young wench o'my Conscience</line>
<line>That ever dream'd, or vow'd her Maydenhead</line>
<line>To a yong hansom Man; Then I lov'd him,</line>
<line>(Extreamely lov'd him) infinitely lov'd him;</line>
<line>And yet he had a Cosen, faire as he too.</line>
<line>But in my heart was Palamon, and there</line>
<line>Lord, what a coyle he keepes? To heare him</line>
<line>Sing in an evening, what a heaven it is?</line>
<line>And yet his Songs are sad-ones; Fairer spoken,</line>
<line>Was never Gentleman. When I come in</line>
<line>To bring him water in a morning, first</line>
<line>He bowes his noble body, then salutes me, thus:</line>
<line>Faire, gentle Mayde, good morrow, may thy goodnes,</line>
<line>Get thee a happy husband; Once he kist me,</line>
<line>I lov'd my lips the better ten daies after,</line>
<line>Would he would doe so ev'ry day; He greives much,</line>
<line>And me as much to see his misery.</line>
<line>What should I doe, to make him know I love him,</line>
<line>For I would faine enjoy him? Say I ventur'd</line>
<line>To set him free? what saies the law then? Thus much</line>
<line>For Law, or kindred: I will doe it,</line>
<line>And this night, or to morrow he shall love me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene v</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 4. Enter Theseus, Hipolita, Pirithous,</scenetitle>
<stagedir>[Emilia: Arcite with a Garland, &amp;c.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[ This short florish]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ of Cornets]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ and]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Showtes within.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You have done worthily; I have not seene</line>
<line>Since Hercules, a man of tougher synewes;</line>
<line>What ere you are, you run the best, and wrastle,</line>
<line>That these times can allow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>I am proud to please you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>What Countrie bred you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>This; but far off, Prince.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Are you a Gentleman?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>My father said so;</line>
<line>And to those gentle uses gave me life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Are you his heire?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>His yongest Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Your Father</line>
<line>Sure is a happy Sire then: what prooves you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>A little of all noble Quallities:</line>
<line>I could have kept a Hawke, and well have holloa'd</line>
<line>To a deepe crie of Dogges; I dare not praise</line>
<line>My feat in horsemanship; yet they that knew me</line>
<line>Would say it was my best peece: last, and greatest,</line>
<line>I would be thought a Souldier.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You are perfect.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pirith.</speaker>
<line>Vpon my soule, a proper man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emilia.</speaker>
<line>He is so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>How doe you like him Ladie?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>I admire him,</line>
<line>I have not seene so yong a man, so noble</line>
<line>(If he say true,) of his sort.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Beleeve,</line>
<line>His mother was a wondrous handsome woman,</line>
<line>His face me thinkes, goes that way.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hyp.</speaker>
<line>But his Body</line>
<line>And firie minde, illustrate a brave Father.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Marke how his vertue, like a hidden Sun</line>
<line>Breakes through his baser garments.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hyp.</speaker>
<line>Hee's well got sure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>What made you seeke this place Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Noble Theseus.</line>
<line>To purchase name, and doe my ablest service</line>
<line>To such a well-found wonder, as thy worth,</line>
<line>For onely in thy Court, of all the world</line>
<line>Dwells faire-eyd honor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>All his words are worthy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Sir, we are much endebted to your travell,</line>
<line>Nor shall you loose your wish: Perithous</line>
<line>Dispose of this faire Gentleman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Perith.</speaker>
<line>Thankes Theseus.</line>
<line>What ere you are y'ar mine, and I shall give you</line>
<line>To a most noble service, to this Lady,</line>
<line>This bright yong Virgin; pray observe her goodnesse;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Sir, y'ar a noble Giver: dearest Bewtie,</line>
<line>Thus let me seale my vowd faith: when your Servant</line>
<line>(Your most unworthie Creature) but offends you,</line>
<line>Command him die, he shall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>That were too cruell.</line>
<line>If you deserve well Sir; I shall soone see't:</line>
<line>You are a horseman, I must needs intreat you</line>
<line>This after noone to ride, but tis a rough one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I like him better (Prince) I shall not then</line>
<line>Freeze in my Saddle.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Sweet, you must be readie,</line>
<line>And you Emilia, and you (Friend) and all</line>
<line>To morrow by the Sun, to doe observance</line>
<line>To flowry May, in Dians wood: waite well Sir</line>
<line>Vpon your Mistris: Emely, I hope</line>
<line>He shall not goe a foote.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>That were a shame Sir,</line>
<line>While I have horses: take your choice, and what</line>
<line>You want at any time, let me but know it;</line>
<line>If you serve faithfully, I dare assure you</line>
<line>You'l finde a loving Mistris.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>If I doe not,</line>
<line>Let me finde that my Father ever hated,</line>
<line>Disgrace, and blowes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Go leade the way; you have won it:</line>
<line>It shall be so; you shall receave all dues</line>
<line>Fit for the honour you have won; Twer wrong else,</line>
<line>Sister, beshrew my heart, you have a Servant,</line>
<line>That if I were a woman, would be Master,</line>
<line>But you are wise.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line> I hope too wise for that Sir.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt omnes.]</stagedir>
</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene vi</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 6. Enter Iaylors Daughter alone.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Daughter.</speaker>
<line>Let all the Dukes, and all the divells rore,</line>
<line>He is at liberty: I have venturd for him,</line>
<line>And out I have brought him to a little wood</line>
<line>A mile hence, I have sent him, where a Cedar</line>
<line>Higher than all the rest, spreads like a plane</line>
<line>Fast by a Brooke, and there he shall keepe close,</line>
<line>Till I provide him Fyles, and foode, for yet</line>
<line>His yron bracelets are not off. O Love</line>
<line>What a stout hearted child thou art! My Father</line>
<line>Durst better have indur'd cold yron, than done it:</line>
<line>I love him, beyond love, and beyond reason,</line>
<line>Or wit, or safetie: I have made him know it</line>
<line>I care not, I am desperate, If the law</line>
<line>Finde me, and then condemne me for't; some wenches,</line>
<line>Some honest harted Maides, will sing my Dirge.</line>
<line>And tell to memory, my death was noble,</line>
<line>Dying almost a Martyr: That way he takes,</line>
<line>I purpose is my way too: Sure he cannot</line>
<line>Be so unmanly, as to leave me here,</line>
<line>If he doe, Maides will not so easily</line>
<line>Trust men againe: And yet he has not thank'd me</line>
<line>For what I have done: no not so much as kist me,</line>
<line>And that (me thinkes) is not so well; nor scarcely</line>
<line>Could I perswade him to become a Freeman,</line>
<line>He made such scruples of the wrong he did</line>
<line>To me, and to my Father. Yet I hope</line>
<line>When he considers more, this love of mine</line>
<line>Will take more root within him: Let him doe</line>
<line>What he will with me, so he use me kindly,</line>
<line>For use me so he shall, or ile proclaime him</line>
<line>And to his face, no-man: Ile presently</line>
<line>Provide him necessaries, and packe my cloathes up,</line>
<line>And where there is a path of ground Ile venture</line>
<line>So hee be with me; By him, like a shadow</line>
<line>Ile ever dwell; within this houre the whoobub</line>
<line>Will be all ore the prison: I am then</line>
<line>Kissing the man they looke for: farewell Father;</line>
<line>Get many more such prisoners, and such daughters,</line>
<line>And shortly you may keepe your selfe. Now to him.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[ Cornets in]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[sundry places.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[ Noise and]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ hallowing as]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[people a Maying.]</stagedir>

</scene>  

</act>

<act>
<acttitle>Act III</acttitle>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene i</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 1. Enter Arcite alone.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>The Duke has lost Hypolita; each tooke</line>
<line>A severall land. This is a solemne Right</line>
<line>They owe bloomd May, and the Athenians pay it</line>
<line>To'th heart of Ceremony: O Queene Emilia</line>
<line>Fresher then May, sweeter</line>
<line>Then hir gold Buttons on the bowes, or all</line>
<line>Th' enamelld knackes o'th Meade, or garden, yea</line>
<line>(We challenge too) the bancke of any Nymph</line>
<line>That makes the streame seeme flowers; thou o Iewell</line>
<line>O'th wood, o'th world, hast likewise blest a pace</line>
<line>With thy sole presence, in thy rumination</line>
<line>That I poore man might eftsoones come betweene</line>
<line>And chop on some cold thought, thrice blessed chance</line>
<line>To drop on such a Mistris, expectation</line>
<line>Most giltlesse on't: tell me O Lady Fortune</line>
<line>(Next after Emely my Soveraigne) how far</line>
<line>I may be prowd. She takes strong note of me,</line>
<line>Hath made me neere her; and this beuteous Morne</line>
<line>(The prim'st of all the yeare) presents me with</line>
<line>A brace of horses, two such Steeds might well</line>
<line>Be by a paire of Kings backt, in a Field</line>
<line>That their crownes titles tride: Alas, alas</line>
<line>Poore Cosen Palamon, poore prisoner, thou</line>
<line>So little dream'st upon my fortune, that</line>
<line>Thou thinkst thy selfe, the happier thing, to be</line>
<line>So neare Emilia, me thou deem'st at Thebs,</line>
<line>And therein wretched, although free; But if</line>
<line>Thou knew'st my Mistris breathd on me, and that</line>
<line>I ear'd her language, livde in her eye; O Coz</line>
<line>What passion would enclose thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Palamon.</speaker>
<line>Traytor kinseman,</line>
<line>Thou shouldst perceive my passion, if these signes</line>
<line>Of prisonment were off me, and this hand</line>
<line>But owner of a Sword: By all othes in one</line>
<line>I, and the iustice of my love would make thee</line>
<line>A confest Traytor, o thou most perfidious</line>
<line>That ever gently lookd the voydes of honour.</line>
<line>That eu'r bore gentle Token; falsest Cosen</line>
<line>That ever blood made kin, call'st thou hir thine?</line>
<line>Ile prove it in my Shackles, with these hands,</line>
<line>Void of appointment, that thou ly'st, and art</line>
<line>A very theefe in love, a Chaffy Lord</line>
<line>Nor worth the name of villaine: had I a Sword</line>
<line>And these house clogges away.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Deere Cosin Palamon,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Cosoner Arcite, give me language, such</line>
<line>As thou hast shewd me feate.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Not finding in</line>
<line>The circuit of my breast, any grosse stuffe</line>
<line>To forme me like your blazon, holds me to</line>
<line>This gentlenesse of answer; tis your passion</line>
<line>That thus mistakes, the which to you being enemy,</line>
<line>Cannot to me be kind: honor, and honestie</line>
<line>I cherish, and depend on, how so ev'r</line>
<line>You skip them in me, and with them faire Coz</line>
<line>Ile maintaine my proceedings; pray be pleas'd</line>
<line>To shew in generous termes, your griefes, since that</line>
<line>Your question's with your equall, who professes</line>
<line>To cleare his owne way, with the minde and Sword</line>
<line>Of a true Gentleman.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>That thou durst Arcite.</line>
<line>Against th' advice of feare: sure of another</line>
<line>You would not heare me doubted, but your silence</line>
<line>Should breake out, though i'th Sanctuary.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>I have seene you move in such a place, which well</line>
<line>Might justifie your manhood, you were calld</line>
<line>Men loose when they encline to trecherie,</line>
<line>And then they fight like compelld Beares, would fly</line>
<line>Were they not tyde.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Kinsman, you might as well</line>
<line>Speake this, and act it in your Glasse, as to</line>
<line>His eare, which now disdaines you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Come up to me,</line>
<line>Quit me of these cold Gyves, give me a Sword</line>
<line>Though it be rustie, and the charity</line>
<line>Of one meale lend me; Come before me then</line>
<line>A good Sword in thy hand, and doe but say</line>
<line>That Emily is thine, I will forgive</line>
<line>The trespasse thou hast done me, yea my life</line>
<line>If then thou carry't, and brave soules in shades</line>
<line>That have dyde manly, which will seeke of me</line>
<line>Some newes from earth, they shall get none but this</line>
<line>That thou art brave, and noble.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Be content,</line>
<line>Againe betake you to your hawthorne house,</line>
<line>With counsaile of the night, I will be here</line>
<line>With wholesome viands; these impediments</line>
<line>Will I file off, you shall have garments, and</line>
<line>Perfumes to kill the smell o'th prison, after</line>
<line>When you shall stretch your selfe, and say but Arcite</line>
<line>I am in plight, there shall be at your choyce</line>
<line>Both Sword, and Armour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Oh you heavens, dares any</line>
<line>So noble beare a guilty busines! none</line>
<line>But onely Arcite, therefore none but Arcite</line>
<line>In this kinde is so bold.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Sweete Palamon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I doe embrace you, and your offer, for</line>
<line>Your offer doo't I onely, Sir your person</line>
<line>Without hipocrisy I may not wish</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Winde hornes of Cornets.</speaker>

<line>More then my Swords edge ont.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You heare the Hornes;</line>
<line>Enter your Musicke least this match between's</line>
<line>Be crost, er met, give me your hand, farewell.</line>
<line>Ile bring you every needfull thing: I pray you</line>
<line>Take comfort and be strong.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Pray hold your promise;</line>
<line>And doe the deede with a bent brow, most certaine</line>
<line>You love me not, be rough with me, and powre</line>
<line>This oile out of your language; by this ayre</line>
<line>I could for each word, give a Cuffe: my stomach</line>
<line>Not reconcild by reason,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Plainely spoken,</line>
<line>Yet pardon me hard language, when I spur</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Winde hornes.</speaker>

<line>My horse, I chide him not; content, and anger</line>
<line>In me have but one face. Harke Sir, they call</line>
<line>The scatterd to the Banket; you must guesse</line>
<line>I have an office there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Sir your attendance</line>
<line>Cannot please heaven, and I know your office</line>
<line>Vnjustly is atcheev'd.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>If a good title,</line>
<line>I am perswaded this question sicke between's,</line>
<line>By bleeding must be cur'd. I am a Suitour,</line>
<line>That to your Sword you will bequeath this plea,</line>
<line>And talke of it no more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>But this one word:</line>
<line>You are going now to gaze upon my Mistris,</line>
<line>For note you, mine she is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Nay then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Nay pray you,</line>
<line>You talke of feeding me to breed me strength</line>
<line>You are going now to looke upon a Sun</line>
<line>That strengthens what it lookes on, there</line>
<line>You have a vantage ore me, but enjoy't till</line>
<line>I may enforce my remedy. Farewell.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene ii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 2. Enter Iaylors daughter alone.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>He has mistooke; the Beake I meant, is gone</line>
<line>After his fancy, Tis now welnigh morning,</line>
<line>No matter, would it were perpetuall night,</line>
<line>And darkenes Lord o'th world, Harke tis a woolfe:</line>
<line>In me hath greife slaine feare, and but for one thing</line>
<line>I care for nothing, and that's Palamon.</line>
<line>I wreake not if the wolves would jaw me, so</line>
<line>He had this File; what if I hallowd for him?</line>
<line>I cannot hallow: if I whoop'd; what then?</line>
<line>If he not answeard, I should call a wolfe,</line>
<line>And doe him but that service. I have heard</line>
<line>Strange howles this live-long night, why may't not be</line>
<line>They have made prey of him? he has no weapons,</line>
<line>He cannot run, the Iengling of his Gives</line>
<line>Might call fell things to listen, who have in them</line>
<line>A sence to know a man unarmd, and can</line>
<line>Smell where resistance is. Ile set it downe</line>
<line>He's torne to peeces, they howld many together</line>
<line>And then they feed on him: So much for that,</line>
<line>Be bold to ring the Bell; how stand I then?</line>
<line>All's char'd when he is gone, No, no I lye,</line>
<line>My Father's to be hang'd for his escape,</line>
<line>My selfe to beg, if I prizd life so much</line>
<line>As to deny my act, but that I would not,</line>
<line>Should I try death by dussons. I am mop't,</line>
<line>Foode tooke I none these two daies.</line>
<line>Sipt some water. I have not closd mine eyes</line>
<line>Save when my lids scowrd off their brine; alas</line>
<line>Dissolue my life, Let not my sence unsettle</line>
<line>Least I should drowne, or stab, or hang my selfe.</line>
<line>O state of Nature, faile together in me,</line>
<line>Since thy best props are warpt: So which way now?</line>
<line>The best way is, the next way to a grave:</line>
<line>Each errant step beside is torment. Loe</line>
<line>Save what I faile in: But the point is this</line>
<line>An end, and that is all.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 3. Enter Arcite, with Meate, Wine, and Files.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>The same: I have brought you foode and files,</line>
<line>Come forth and feare not, here's no Theseus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Nor none so honest Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>That's no matter,</line>
<line>Wee'l argue that hereafter: Come take courage,</line>
<line>You shall not dye thus beastly, here Sir drinke</line>
<line>I know you are faint, then ile talke further with you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Arcite, thou mightst now poyson me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I might.</line>
<line>But I must feare you first: Sit downe, and good now</line>
<line>No more of these vaine parlies; let us not</line>
<line>Having our ancient reputation with us</line>
<line>Make talke for Fooles, and Cowards, To your health, &amp;c.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Doe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Pray sit downe then, and let me entreate you</line>
<line>By all the honesty and honour in you,</line>
<line>No mention of this woman, t'will disturbe us,</line>
<line>We shall have time enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Well Sir, Ile pledge you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Drinke a good hearty draught, it breeds good (blood man.</line>
<line>Doe you not feele it thaw you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Stay, Ile tell you after a draught or two more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I am glad you have so good a stomach.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I am gladder I have so good meate too't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>How tasts your vittails? your hunger needs no sawce (I see,</line>
<line>But if it did, yours is too tart: sweete Cosen: what is this?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Venison.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Tis a lusty meate:</line>
<line>Giue me more wine; here Arcite to the wenches</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>After you Cuz.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>She lov'd a black-haird man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>She did so; well Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>And I have heard some call him Arcite, and</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Out with't faith.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>She met him in an Arbour:</line>
<line>What did she there Cuz? play o'th virginals?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Something she did Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Made her groane a moneth for't; or 2. or 3. or 10.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>The Marshals Sister,</line>
<line>Had her share too, as I remember Cosen,</line>
<line>Else there be tales abroade, you'l pledge her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>A pretty broune wench t'is. There was a time</line>
<line>When yong men went a hunting, and a wood,</line>
<line>Away with this straind mirth; I say againe</line>
<line>That sigh was breathd for Emily; base Cosen,</line>
<line>Dar'st thou breake first?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You are wide.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>By heaven and earth, ther's nothing in thee honest.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Then Ile leave you: you are a Beast now:</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>As thou makst me, Traytour.</line>
<line> perfumes:</line>

<line>That that shall quiet all,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>A Sword and Armour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Feare me not; you are now too fowle; farewell.</line>
<line>Get off your Trinkets, you shall want nought;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Sirha:</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Ile heare no more.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>If he keepe touch, he dies for't.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iv</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 4. Enter Iaylors daughter.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>I am very cold, and all the Stars are out too,</line>
<line>The little Stars, and all, that looke like aglets:</line>
<line>The Sun has seene my Folly: Palamon;</line>
<line>Alas no; hees in heaven; where am I now?</line>
<line>Yonder's the sea, and ther's a Ship; how't tumbles</line>
<line>And ther's a Rocke lies watching under water;</line>
<line>Now, now, it beates upon it; now, now, now,</line>
<line>Ther's a leak sprung, a sound one, how they cry?</line>
<line>Vpon her before the winde, you'l loose all els:</line>
<line>Vp with a course or two, and take about Boyes.</line>
<line>Good night, good night, y'ar gone; I am very hungry,</line>
<line>Would I could finde a fine Frog; he would tell me</line>
<line>Newes from all parts o'th world, then would I make</line>
<line>A Carecke of a Cockle shell, and sayle</line>
<line>By east and North East to the King of Pigmes,</line>
<line>For he tels fortunes rarely. Now my Father</line>
<line>Twenty to one is trust up in a trice</line>
<line>To morrow morning, Ile say never a word.</line>
<stagedir>[Sing.]</stagedir>
<line>For ile cut my greene coat, a foote above my knee,</line>
<line>And ile clip my yellow lockes; an inch below mine eie.</line>
<line>hey, nonny, nonny, nonny,</line>
<line>He's buy me a white Cut, forth for to ride</line>
<line>And ile goe seeke him, throw the world that is so wide</line>
<line>hey, nonny, nonny, nonny.</line>
<line>O for a pricke now like a Nightingale, to put my breast</line>
<line>Against. I shall sleepe like a Top else.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene v</scenetitle>

<stagedir>Scaena 6. Enter a Schoole master .4. Countrymen: and [Baum .2. or 3 wenches, with a Taborer.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker>
<line>And sweetly we will doe it Master Gerrold.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Draw up the Company, Where's the Taborour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Why Timothy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Tab.</speaker>
<line>Here my mad boyes, have at ye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>But I say where's their women?</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Here's Friz and Maudline.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>And litle Luce with the white legs, and bouncing (Barbery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker>
<line>And freckeled Nel; that never faild her Master.</line>
<line>And now and then a fauour, and a friske.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Nel.</speaker>
<line>Let us alone Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Wher's the rest o'th Musicke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Dispersd as you commanded.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Couple then</line>
<line>And see what's wanting; wher's the Bavian?</line>
<line>My friend, carry your taile without offence</line>
<line>Or scandall to the Ladies; and be sure</line>
<line>You tumble with audacity, and manhood,</line>
<line>And when you barke doe it with judgement.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bau.</speaker>
<line>Yes Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Quo usque tandem. Here is a woman wanting</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>We may goe whistle: all the fat's i'th fire.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>We have,</line>
<line>As learned Authours utter, washd a Tile,</line>
<line>We have beene fatuus, and laboured vainely.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>This is that scornefull peece, that scurvy hilding</line>
<line>That gave her promise faithfully, she would be here,</line>
<line>Cicely the Sempsters daughter:</line>
<line>The next gloves that I give her shall be dog skin;</line>
<line>Nay and she faile me once, you can tell Arcas</line>
<line>She swore by wine, and bread, she would not breake.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>An Eele and woman,</line>
<line>A learned Poet sayes: unles by'th taile</line>
<line>And with thy teeth thou hold, will either faile,</line>
<line>In manners this was false position</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1.</speaker>
<line>A fire ill take her; do's she flinch now?</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>What</line>
<line>Shall we determine Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Nothing,</line>
<line>Our busines is become a nullity</line>
<line>Yea, and a woefull, and a pittious nullity.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>4.</speaker>
<line>Now when the credite of our Towne lay on it,</line>
<line>Now to be frampall, now to pisse o'th nettle,</line>
<line>Goe thy waies, ile remember thee, ile fit thee,</line>
<line> <stagedir>[Enter Iaylors daughter.]</stagedir>

</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daughter.</speaker>
<line>The George alow, came from the South, from</line>
<line>The coast of Barbary a.</line>
<line>And there he met with brave gallants of war</line>
<line>By one, by two, by three, a</line>
<line>Well haild, well haild, you jolly gallants,</line>
<line>And whither now are you bound a [ Chaire and]</line>
<stagedir>[stooles out.]</stagedir>
<line>O let me have your company till come to the sound a</line>
<line>There was three fooles, fell out about an howlet</line>
<line>The one sed it was an owle</line>
<line>The other, he sed nay,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>And are you mad good woman?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>I would be sorry else,</line>
<line>Give me your hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Why?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>I can tell your fortune.</line>
<line>You are a foole: tell ten, I have pozd him: Buz</line>
<line>Friend you must eate no white bread, if you doe</line>
<line>Your teeth will bleede extreamely, shall we dance ho?</line>
<line>I know you, y'ar a Tinker: Sirha Tinker</line>
<line>Stop no more holes, but what you should.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Dij boni. A Tinker Damzell?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daug.</speaker>
<line>Or a Conjurer: raise me a devill now, and let him (play</line>
<line>Strike up, and leade her in.</line>

</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2.</speaker>
<line>Come Lasse, lets trip it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Ile leade. [ (Winde Hornes:]</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3.</speaker>
<line>Doe, doe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Perswasively, and cunningly: away boyes,</line>
<stagedir>[Ex. all but Schoolemaster.]</stagedir>
<line>I heare the hornes: give me some</line>
<line>Meditation, and marke your Cue;</line>
<line>Pallas inspire me.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Thes. Pir. Hip. Emil. Arcite: and traine.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>This way the Stag tooke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Stay, and edifie.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>What have we here?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Some Countrey sport, upon my life Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Well Sir, goe forward, we will edifie.</line>
<line>Ladies sit downe, wee'l stay it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>Thou doughtie Duke all haile: all haile sweet (Ladies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>This is a cold beginning.</line>
<line>That ruder Tongues distinguish villager.</line>
<line>And to say veritie, and not to fable;</line>
<line>We are a merry rout, or else a rable</line>
<line>Or company, or by a figure, Choris</line>
<line>That fore thy dignitie will dance a Morris.</line>
<line>And I that am the rectifier of all</line>
<line>By title Pedagogus, that let fall</line>
<line>The Birch upon the Breeches of the small ones,</line>
<line>And humble with a Ferula the tall ones,</line>
<line>Doe here present this Machine, or this frame,</line>
<line>And daintie Duke, whose doughtie dismall fame</line>
<line>From Dis to Dedalus, from post to pillar</line>
<line>Is blowne abroad; helpe me thy poore well willer,</line>
<line>And with thy twinckling eyes, looke right and straight</line>
<line>Vpon this mighty Morr = of mickle waight</line>
<line>Is = now comes in, which being glewd together</line>
<line>Makes Morris, and the cause that we came hether.</line>
<line>The body of our sport of no small study</line>
<line>I first appeare, though rude, and raw, and muddy,</line>
<line>To speake before thy noble grace, this tenner:</line>
<line>At whose great feete I offer up my penner.</line>
<line>The next the Lord of May, and Lady bright,</line>
<line>The Chambermaid, and Servingman by night</line>
<line>That seeke out silent hanging: Then mine Host</line>
<line>And his fat Spowse, that welcomes to their cost</line>
<line>The gauled Traveller, and with a beckning</line>
<line>Informes the Tapster to inflame the reckning:</line>
<line>Then the beast eating Clowne, and next the foole,</line>
<line>The Bavian with long tayle, and eke long toole,</line>
<line>Cum multis alijs that make a dance,</line>
<line>Say I, and all shall presently advance.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line> I, I by any meanes, deere Domine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Produce.</line>
<stagedir>[Musicke Dance.]</stagedir>
<line>Intrate filij, Come forth, and foot it, [ Knocke for]</line>
<line>[ Schoole. Enter]</line>
<stagedir>[The Dance.]</stagedir>
<line>Ladies, if we have beene merry</line>
<line>And have pleasd thee with a derry,</line>
<line>And a derry, and a downe</line>
<line>Say the Schoolemaster's no Clowne:</line>
<line>Duke, if we have pleasd three too</line>
<line>And have done as good Boyes should doe,</line>
<line>Give us but a tree or twaine</line>
<line>For a Maypole, and againe</line>
<line>Ere another yeare run out,</line>
<line>Wee'l make thee laugh and all this rout.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Take 20. Domine; how does my sweet heart.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Never so pleasd Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Twas an excellent dance, and for a preface</line>
<line>I never heard a better.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Schoolemaster, I thanke you, One see 'em all rewarded.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Sch.</speaker>
<line>May the Stag thou huntst stand long,</line>
<line>And thy dogs be swift and strong:</line>
<line>May they kill him without lets,</line>
</speech>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene vi</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>About this houre my Cosen gave his faith</line>
<line>To visit me againe, and with him bring</line>
<line>Two Swords, and two good Armors; if he faile</line>
<line>He's neither man, nor Souldier; when he left me</line>
<line>I did not thinke a weeke could have restord</line>
<line>My lost strength to me, I was growne so low,</line>
<line>And Crest-falne with my wants: I thanke thee Arcite,</line>
<line>Thou art yet a faire Foe; and I feele my selfe</line>
<line>With this refreshing, able once againe</line>
<line>To out dure danger: To delay it longer</line>
<line>And not a Souldier: Therefore this blest morning</line>
<line>Shall be the last; and that Sword he refuses,</line>
<line>If it but hold, I kill him with; tis Iustice:</line>
<line>So love, and Fortune for me: O good morrow.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Arcite with Armors and Swords.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Good morrow noble kinesman,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I have put you</line>
<line>To too much paines Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>That too much faire Cosen,</line>
<line>Is but a debt to honour, and my duty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Would you were so in all Sir; I could wish ye</line>
<line>As kinde a kinsman, as you force me finde</line>
<line>A beneficiall foe, that my embraces</line>
<line>Might thanke ye, not my blowes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I shall thinke either</line>
<line>Well done, a noble recompence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Then I shall quit you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Defy me in these faire termes, and you show</line>
<line>More then a Mistris to me, no more anger</line>
<line>As you love any thing that's honourable;</line>
<line>We were not bred to talke man, when we are arm'd</line>
<line>And both upon our guards, then let our fury</line>
<line>Like meeting of two tides, fly strongly from us,</line>
<line>And then to whom the birthright of this Beauty</line>
<line>Truely pertaines (without obbraidings, scornes,</line>
<line>Dispisings of our persons, and such powtings</line>
<line>Fitter for Girles and Schooleboyes) will be seene</line>
<line>And quickly, yours, or mine: wilt please you arme Sir,</line>
<line>Or if you feele your selfe not fitting yet</line>
<line>And furnishd with your old strength, ile stay Cosen</line>
<line>And ev'ry day discourse you into health,</line>
<line>As I am spard, your person I am friends with,</line>
<line>And I could wish I had not saide I lov'd her</line>
<line>Though I had dide; But loving such a Lady</line>
<line>And justifying my Love, I must not fly from't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal. Arcite</speaker>
<line>, thou art so brave an enemy</line>
<line>That no man but thy Cosen's fit to kill thee,</line>
<line>I am well, and lusty, choose your Armes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Choose you Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou exceede in all, or do'st thou doe it</line>
<line>To make me spare thee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>If you thinke so Cosen,</line>
<line>You are deceived, for as I am a Soldier.</line>
<line>I will not spare you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>That's well said.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You'l finde it</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Then as I am an honest man and love,</line>
<line>With all the justice of affection</line>
<line>Ile pay thee soundly: This ile take.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>That's mine then,</line>
<line>Ile arme you first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Do: pray thee tell me Cosen,</line>
<line>Where gotst thou this good Armour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Tis the Dukes,</line>
<line>And to say true, I stole it; doe I pinch you?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Noe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Is't not too heavie?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I have worne a lighter,</line>
<line>But I shall make it serve.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Ile buckl't close.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>By any meanes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You care not for a Grand guard?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>No, no, wee'l use no horses, I perceave</line>
<line>You would be faine be at that Fight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I am indifferent.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Faith so am I: good Cosen, thrust the buckle</line>
<line>Through far enough.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I warrant you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>My Caske now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Will you fight bare-armd?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>We shall be the nimbler.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Thanke you Arcite.</line>
<line>How doe I looke, am I falne much away?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Faith very little; love has usd you kindly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Ile warrant thee, Ile strike home.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Doe, and spare not;</line>
<line>Ile give you cause sweet Cosen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Now to you Sir,</line>
<line>Me thinkes this Armor's very like that, Arcite,</line>
<line>Thou wor'st that day the 3. Kings fell, but lighter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>That was a very good one, and that day</line>
<line>I well remember, you outdid me Cosen,</line>
<line>I never saw such valour: when you chargd</line>
<line>Vpon the left wing of the Enemie,</line>
<line>I spurd hard to come up, and under me</line>
<line>I had a right good horse.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>You had indeede</line>
<line>A bright Bay I remember.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Yes but all</line>
<line>Was vainely labour'd in me, you outwent me,</line>
<line>Nor could my wishes reach you; yet a little</line>
<line>I did by imitation.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>More by vertue,</line>
<line>You are modest Cosen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>When I saw you charge first,</line>
<line>Me thought I heard a dreadfull clap of Thunder</line>
<line>Breake from the Troope.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>But still before that flew</line>
<line>The lightning of your valour: Stay a little,</line>
<line>Is not this peece too streight?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>No, no, tis well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I would have nothing hurt thee but my Sword,</line>
<line>A bruise would be dishonour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Now I am perfect.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Stand off then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Take my Sword, I hold it better.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I thanke ye: No, keepe it, your life lyes on it,</line>
<line>Here's one, if it but hold, I aske no more.</line>
<line>For all my hopes: My Cause and honour guard me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>And me my love: Is there ought else to say?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[ They bow severall]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ wayes:]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ then advance]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[and stand.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>This onely, and no more: Thou art mine Aunts Son.</line>
<line>And that blood we desire to shed is mutuall,</line>
<line>In me, thine, and in thee, mine: My Sword</line>
<line>Is in my hand, and if thou killst me</line>
<line>The gods, and I forgive thee; If there be</line>
<line>A place prepar'd for those that sleepe in honour,</line>
<line>I wish his wearie soule, that falls may win it:</line>
<line>Fight bravely Cosen, give me thy noble hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Here Palamon: This hand shall never more</line>
<line>Come neare thee with such friendship.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>I commend thee.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>If I fall, curse me, and say I was a coward,</line>
<line>For none but such, dare die in these just Tryalls.</line>
<line>Once more farewell my Cosen,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line> Farewell Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Fight.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Hornes within: they stand.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Loe Cosen, loe, our Folly has undon us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Why?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>This is the Duke, a hunting as I told you,</line>
<line>If we be found, we are wretched, O retire</line>
<line>For honours sake, and safely presently</line>
<line>Into your Bush agen; Sir we shall finde</line>
<line>Too many howres to dye in, gentle Cosen:</line>
<line>If you be seene you perish instantly</line>
<line>For breaking prison, and I, if you reveale me,</line>
<line>For my contempt; Then all the world will scorne us,</line>
<line>And say we had a noble difference,</line>
<line>But base disposers of it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>No, no, Cosen</line>
<line>I will no more be hidden, not put off</line>
<line>This great adventure to a second Tryall:</line>
<line>I know your cunning, and I know your cause,</line>
<line>He that faints now, shame take him, put thy selfe</line>
<line>Vpon thy present guard.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>You are not mad?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Or I will make th' advantage of this howre</line>
<line>Mine owne, and what to come shall threaten me,</line>
<line>I feare lesse then my fortune: know weake Cosen</line>
<line>I love Emilia, and in that ile bury</line>
<line>Thee, and all crosses else.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Then come, what can come</line>
<line>Thou shalt know Palamon, I dare as well</line>
<line>Die, as discourse, or sleepe: Onely this feares me,</line>
<line>The law will have the honour of our ends.</line>
<line>Have at thy life.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Looke to thine owne well Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Fight againe. Hornes.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Enter Theseus, Hipolita, Emilia, Perithous and traine.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Theseus.</speaker>
<line>What ignorant and mad malicious Traitors,</line>
<line>Are you? That gainst the tenor of my Lawes</line>
<line>Are making Battaile, thus like Knights appointed,</line>
<line>Without my leave, and Officers of Armes?</line>
<line>By Castor both shall dye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Hold thy word Theseus,</line>
<line>We are certainly both Traitors, both despisers</line>
<line>Of thee, and of thy goodnesse: I am Palamon</line>
<line>That cannot love thee, he that broke thy Prison,</line>
<line>Thinke well, what that deserves; and this is Arcite</line>
<line>A bolder Traytor never trod thy ground</line>
<line>A Falser neu'r seem'd friend: This is the man</line>
<line>Was begd and banish'd, this is he contemnes thee</line>
<line>And what thou dar'st doe; and in this disguise</line>
<line>Against this owne Edict followes thy Sister,</line>
<line>That fortunate bright Star, the faire Emilia</line>
<line>Whose servant, (if there be a right in seeing,</line>
<line>And first bequeathing of the soule to) justly</line>
<line>I am, and which is more, dares thinke her his.</line>
<line>This treacherie like a most trusty Lover,</line>
<line>I call'd him now to answer; if thou bee'st</line>
<line>As thou art spoken, great and vertuous,</line>
<line>The true descider of all injuries,</line>
<line>Say, Fight againe, and thou shalt see me Theseus</line>
<line>Doe such a Iustice, thou thy selfe wilt envie,</line>
<line>Then take my life, Ile wooe thee too't.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>O heaven,</line>
<line>What more then man is this!</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>I have sworne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>We seeke not</line>
<line>Thy breath of mercy Theseus, Tis to me</line>
<line>A thing as soone to dye, as thee to say it,</line>
<line>And no more mov'd: where this man calls me Traitor,</line>
<line>Let me say thus much; if in love be Treason,</line>
<line>In service of so excellent a Beutie,</line>
<line>As I love most, and in that faith will perish,</line>
<line>As I have brought my life here to confirme it,</line>
<line>As I have serv'd her truest, worthiest,</line>
<line>As I dare kill this Cosen, that denies it,</line>
<line>So let me be most Traitor, and ye please me:</line>
<line>For scorning thy Edict Duke, aske that Lady</line>
<line>Why she is faire, and why her eyes command me</line>
<line>Stay here to love her; and if she say Traytor,</line>
<line>I am a villaine fit to lye unburied.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Thou shalt have pitty of us both, o Theseus,</line>
<line>If unto neither thou shew mercy, stop,</line>
<line>(As thou art just) thy noble eare against us,</line>
<line>As thou art valiant; for thy Cosens soule</line>
<line>Whose 12. strong labours crowne his memory,</line>
<line>Lets die together, at one instant Duke,</line>
<line>Onely a little let him fall before me,</line>
<line>That I may tell my Soule he shall not have her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>I grant your wish, for to say true, your Cosen</line>
<line>Has ten times more offended, for I gave him</line>
<line>More mercy then you found, Sir, your offenses</line>
<line>Being no more then his: None here speake for 'em</line>
<line>For ere the Sun set, both shall sleepe for ever.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hipol.</speaker>
<line>Alas the pitty, now or never Sister</line>
<line>Speake not to be denide; That face of yours</line>
<line>Will beare the curses else of after ages</line>
<line>For these lost Cosens.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>In my face deare Sister</line>
<line>I finde no anger to 'em; nor no ruyn,</line>
<line>The misadventure of their owne eyes kill 'em;</line>
<line>Yet that I will be woman, and have pitty,</line>
<line>My knees shall grow to'th ground but Ile get mercie.</line>
<line>Helpe me deare Sister, in a deede so vertuous,</line>
<line>The powers of all women will be with us,</line>
<line>Most royall Brother.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hipol.</speaker>
<line>Sir by our tye of Marriage.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>By your owne spotlesse honour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>By that faith,</line>
<line>That faire hand, and that honest heart you gave me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>By that you would have pitty in another,</line>
<line>By your owne vertues infinite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>By valour,</line>
<line>By all the chaste nights I have ever pleasd you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>These are strange Conjurings.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Nay then Ile in too: By all our friendship Sir, by all (our dangers,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>By that you would have trembled to deny</line>
<line>A blushing Maide.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>By your owne eyes: By strength</line>
<line>In which you swore I went beyond all women,</line>
<line>Almost all men, and yet I yeelded Theseus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>To crowne all this; By your most noble soule</line>
<line>Which cannot want due mercie, I beg first.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Next heare my prayers.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Last let me intreate Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>For mercy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Mercy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Mercy on these Princes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Ye make my faith reele: Say I felt</line>
<line>Compassion to 'em both, how would you place it?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Vpon their lives: But with their banishments.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You are a right woman, Sister; you have pitty,</line>
<line>But want the vnderstanding where to use it.</line>
<line>If you desire their lives, invent a way</line>
<line>Safer then banishment: Can these two live</line>
<line>And have the agony of love about 'em,</line>
<line>And not kill one another? Every day</line>
<line>They'ld fight about you; howrely bring your honour</line>
<line>In publique question with their Swords; Be wise then</line>
<line>And here forget 'em; it concernes your credit,</line>
<line>And my oth equally: I have said they die,</line>
<line>Better they fall by'th law, then one another.</line>
<line>Bow not my honor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>O my noble Brother,</line>
<line>That oth was rashly made, and in your anger,</line>
<line>Your reason will not hold it, if such vowes</line>
<line>Stand for expresse will, all the world must perish.</line>
<line>Beside, I have another oth, gainst yours</line>
<line>Of more authority, I am sure more love,</line>
<line>Not made in passion neither, but good heede.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>What is it Sister?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Vrge it home brave Lady.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>That you would nev'r deny me any thing</line>
<line>Fit for my modest suit, and your free granting:</line>
<line>I tye you to your word now, if ye fall in't,</line>
<line>Thinke how you maime your honour;</line>
<line>(For now I am set a begging Sir, I am deafe</line>
<line>To all but your compassion) how their lives</line>
<line>Might breed the ruine of my name; Opinion,</line>
<line>Shall any thing that loves me perish for me?</line>
<line>That were a cruell wisedome, doe men proyne</line>
<line>The goodly Mothers that have groand for these,</line>
<line>And all the longing Maides that ever lov'd,</line>
<line>If your vow stand, shall curse me and my Beauty,</line>
<line>And in their funerall songs, for these two Cosens</line>
<line>Despise my crueltie, and cry woe worth me,</line>
<line>Till I am nothing but the scorne of women;</line>
<line>For heavens sake save their lives, and banish 'em.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>On what conditions?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Sweare 'em never more</line>
<line>To make me their Contention, or to know me,</line>
<line>To tread upon thy Dukedome, and to be</line>
<line>Before I take this oth, forget I love her?</line>
<line>O all ye gods dispise me then: Thy Banishment</line>
<line>I not mislike, so we may fairely carry</line>
<line>Our Swords, and cause along: else never trifle,</line>
<line>But take our lives Duke, I must love and will,</line>
<line>And for that love, must and dare kill this Cosen</line>
<line>On any peece the earth has.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Will you Arcite</line>
<line>Take these conditions?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>He's a villaine then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>These are men.</line>
<line>I never shall enjoy her, yet ile preserve</line>
<line>The honour of affection, and dye for her,</line>
<line>Make death a Devill.</line>
<line>Content to take th' other to your husband?</line>
<line>They cannot both enjoy you; They are Princes</line>
<line>As goodly as your owne eyes, and as noble</line>
<line>As ever fame yet spoke of; looke upon 'em,</line>
<line>And if you can love, end this difference,</line>
<line>I give consent, are you content too Princes?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Both.</speaker>
<line>With all our soules.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>He that she refuses</line>
<line>Must dye then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Both.</speaker>
<line>Any death thou canst invent Duke.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>If I fall from that mouth, I fall with favour,</line>
<line>And Lovers yet unborne shall blesse my ashes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>If she refuse me, yet my grave will wed me,</line>
<line>And Souldiers sing my Epitaph.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Make choice then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I cannot Sir, they are both too excellent</line>
<line>For me, a hayre shall never fall of these men.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>What will become of 'em?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Thus I ordaine it,</line>
<line>And by mine honor, once againe it stands,</line>
<line>Or both shall dye. You shall both to your Countrey,</line>
<line>And each within this moneth accompanied</line>
<line>With three faire Knights, appeare againe in this place,</line>
<line>In which Ile plant a Pyramid; and whether</line>
<line>Before us that are here, can force his Cosen</line>
<line>By fayre and knightly strength to touch the Pillar,</line>
<line>He shall enjoy her: the other loose his head,</line>
<line>And all his friends; Nor shall he grudge to fall,</line>
<line>Nor thinke he dies with interest in this Lady:</line>
<line>Will this content yee?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Yes: here Cosen Arcite</line>
<line>I am friends againe, till that howre.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I embrace ye.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Are you content Sister?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Yes, I must Sir,</line>
<line>Els both miscarry.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Come shake hands againe then,</line>
<line>And take heede, as you are Gentlemen, this Quarrell</line>
<line>Sleepe till the howre prefixt, and hold your course.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>We dare not faile thee Theseus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Come, Ile give ye</line>
<line>Now usage like to Princes, and to Friends:</line>
<line>When ye returne, who wins, Ile settle heere,</line>
<line>Who looses, yet Ile weepe upon his Beere.</line>
</speech>
 
<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

</act>

<act>
<acttitle>Act IV</acttitle>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene i</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 1. Enter Iailor, and his friend.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Iailor.</speaker>
<line>Heare you no more, was nothing saide of me</line>
<line>Concerning the escape of Palamon?</line>
<line>Good Sir remember.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Nothing that I heard,</line>
<line>For I came home before the busines</line>
<line>Was fully ended: Yet I might perceive</line>
<line>Ere I departed, a great likelihood</line>
<line>Of both their pardons: For Hipolita,</line>
<line>And faire-eyd Emilie, upon their knees</line>
<line>Begd with such hansom pitty, that the Duke</line>
<line>Me thought stood staggering, whether he should follow</line>
<line>His rash oth, or the sweet compassion</line>
<line>Of those two Ladies; and to second them,</line>
<line>That truely noble Prince Perithous</line>
<line>Halfe his owne heart, set in too, that I hope</line>
<line>All shall be well: Neither heard I one question</line>
<line>Of your name, or his scape.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter 2. Friend.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Pray heaven it hold so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Be of good comfort man; I bring you newes,</line>
<line>Good newes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>They are welcome,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Palamon has cleerd you,</line>
<line>And got your pardon, and discoverd</line>
<line>Not to be held ungratefull to her goodnes,</line>
<line>Has given a summe of money to her Marriage,</line>
<line>A large one ile assure you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Ye are a good man</line>
<line>And ever bring good newes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>How was it ended?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Why, as it should be; they that nev'r begd</line>
<line>But they prevaild, had their suites fairely granted,</line>
<line>The prisoners have their lives.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>I knew t'would be so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>I hope they are good.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>They are honourable,</line>
<line>How good they'l prove, I know not.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Wooer.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>T'will be knowne.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>Alas Sir, wher's your Daughter?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Why doe you aske?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>O Sir when did you see her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>How he lookes?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>This morning.</line>
<line> (she sleepe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>I doe not thinke she was very well, for now</line>
<line>You make me minde her, but this very day</line>
<line>I ask'd her questions, and she answered me</line>
<line>So farre from what she was, so childishly.</line>
<line>So sillily, as if she were a foole,</line>
<line>An Inocent, and I was very angry.</line>
<line>But what of her Sir?</line>
<line>As by an other that lesse loves her:</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Well Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Not right?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Not well?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>No Sir not well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>Tis too true, she is mad.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>It cannot be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>Beleeve you'l finde it so.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>I halfe suspected</line>
<line>What you told me: the gods comfort her:</line>
<line>Either this was her love to Palamon,</line>
<line>Or feare of my miscarrying on his scape,</line>
<line>Or both.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>Tis likely.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>But why all this haste Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>Ile tell you quickly. As I late was angling</line>
<line>In the great Lake that lies behind the Pallace,</line>
<line>From the far shore, thicke set with reedes, and Sedges,</line>
<line>As patiently I was attending sport,</line>
<line>I heard a voyce, a shrill one, and attentive</line>
<line>I gave my eare, when I might well perceive</line>
<line>T'was one that sung, and by the smallnesse of it</line>
<line>A boy or woman. I then left my angle</line>
<line>To his owne skill, came neere, but yet perceivd not</line>
<line>Who made the sound; the rushes, and the Reeds</line>
<line>Had so encompast it: I laide me downe</line>
<line>And listned to the words she song, for then</line>
<line>Through a small glade cut by the Fisher men,</line>
<line>I saw it was your Daughter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Pray goe on Sir?</line>
<line>Is gone to'th wood to gather Mulberies,</line>
<line>Ile finde him out to morrow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Pretty soule.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>His shackles will betray him, hee'l be taken,</line>
<line>And what shall I doe then? Ile bring a beavy,</line>
<line>A hundred blacke eyd Maides, that love as I doe</line>
<line>With Chaplets on their heads of Daffadillies,</line>
<line>With cherry-lips, and cheekes of Damaske Roses,</line>
<line>And all wee'l daunce an Antique fore the Duke,</line>
<line>And beg his pardon; Then she talk'd of you Sir;</line>
<line>That you must loose your head to morrow morning,</line>
<line>And she must gather flowers to bury you,</line>
<line>And see the house made handsome, then she sung</line>
<line>Nothing but Willow, willow, willow, and betweene</line>
<line>Ever was, Palamon, faire Palamon,</line>
<line>And Palamon, was a tall yong man. The place</line>
<line>Was knee deepe where she sat; her careles Tresses,</line>
<line>A wreake of bull-rush rounded; about her stucke</line>
<line>Thousand fresh water flowers of severall cullors.</line>
<line>That me thought she appeard like the faire Nimph</line>
<line>That feedes the lake with waters, or as Iris</line>
<line>Newly dropt downe from heaven; Rings she made</line>
<line>Of rushes that grew by, and to 'em spoke</line>
<line>The prettiest posies: Thus our true love's tide,</line>
<line>This you may loose, not me, and many a one:</line>
<line>And then she wept, and sung againe, and sigh'd,</line>
<line>And with the same breath smil'd, and kist her hand.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Alas what pitty it is?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I made in to her.</line>
<line>She saw me, and straight sought the flood, I sav'd her,</line>
<line>And set her safe to land: when presently</line>
<line>She slipt away, and to the Citty made,</line>
<line>With such a cry, and swiftnes, that beleeve me</line>
<line>Shee left me farre behinde her; three, or foure,</line>
<line>I saw from farre off crosse her, one of 'em</line>
<line>I knew to be your brother, where she staid,</line>
<line>And fell, scarce to be got away: I left them with her.</line>
<stagedir>[Enter Brother, Daughter, and others.]</stagedir>
<line>And hether came to tell you: Here they are.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>May you never more enjoy the light, &amp;c.</line>
<line>Is not this a fine Song?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>O a very fine one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>I can sing twenty more.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>I thinke you can,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Yes truely can I, I can sing the Broome,</line>
<line>And Bony Robin. Are not you a tailour?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>Yes,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Wher's my wedding Gowne?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>Ile bring it to morrow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Doe, very rarely, I must be abroad else</line>
<line>To call the Maides, and pay the Minstrels</line>
<line>For I must loose my Maydenhead by cocklight</line>
<line>Twill never thrive else.</line>
<line>O faire, oh sweete, &amp;c.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Singes.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>You must ev'n take it patiently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Tis true,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Yes wench we know him.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Is't not a fine yong Gentleman?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Tis, Love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>By no meane crosse her, she is then distemperd</line>
<line>For worse then now she showes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Yes, he's a fine man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>O, is he so? you have a Sister.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>But she shall never have him, tell her so,</line>
<line>For a tricke that I know, y'had best looke to her,</line>
<line>For if she see him once, she's gone, she's done,</line>
<line>And undon in an howre. All the young Maydes</line>
<line>Of our Towne are in love with him, but I laugh at'em</line>
<line>And let 'em all alone, Is't not a wise course?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>There is at least two hundred now with child (by him,</line>
<line>Close as a Cockle; and all these must be Boyes,</line>
<line>He has the tricke on't, and at ten yeares old</line>
<line>They must be all gelt for Musitians,</line>
<line>And sing the wars of Theseus.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>This is strange.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>As ever you heard, but say nothing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
<line>As twenty to dispatch, hee'l tickl't up</line>
<line>In two howres, if his hand be in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>She's lost</line>
<line>Past all cure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>Heaven forbid man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Come hither, you are a wise man.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Do's she know him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>No, would she did.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>You are master of a Ship?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Wher's your Compasse?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Heere.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Set it too'th North.</line>
<line>Let me alone; Come waygh my hearts, cheerely.</line>
<line>Whistle Master?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>Lets get her in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>Vp to the top Boy.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Bro.</speaker>
<line>Wher's the Pilot?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. Fr.</speaker>
<line>Heere,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>What ken'st thou?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. Fr.</speaker>
<line>A faire wood.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Beare for it master: take about:</line>
<stagedir>[Singes.]</stagedir>
<line>When Cinthia with her borrowed light, &amp;c.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene ii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 2. Enter Emilia alone, with 2. Pictures.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<line>And end their strife: Two such yong hansom men</line>
<line>Shall never fall for me, their weeping Mothers,</line>
<line>Following the dead cold ashes of their Sonnes</line>
<line>Shall never curse my cruelty: Good heaven,</line>
<line>What a sweet face has Arcite? If wise nature</line>
<line>With all her best endowments, all those beuties</line>
<line>She sowes into the birthes of noble bodies,</line>
<line>Were here a mortall woman, and had in her</line>
<line>The coy denialls of yong Maydes, yet doubtles,</line>
<line>She would run mad for this man: what an eye?</line>
<line>Of what a fyry sparkle, and quick sweetnes,</line>
<line>Has this yong Prince? Here Love himselfe sits smyling,</line>
<line>Iust such another wanton Ganimead,</line>
<line>Set Love a fire with, and enforcd the god</line>
<line>Snatch up the goodly Boy, and set him by him</line>
<line>A shining constellation: What a brow,</line>
<line>Of what a spacious Majesty he carries?</line>
<line>Arch'd like the great eyd Iuno's, but far sweeter,</line>
<line>Smoother then Pelops Shoulder? Fame and honour</line>
<line>Me thinks from hence, as from a Promontory</line>
<line>Pointed in heaven, should clap their wings, and sing</line>
<line>To all the under world, the Loves, and Fights</line>
<line>Of gods, and such men neere 'em. Palamon,</line>
<line>Is but his foyle, to him, a meere dull shadow,</line>
<line>Hee's swarth, and meagre, of an eye as heavy</line>
<line>As if he had lost his mother; a still temper,</line>
<line>No stirring in him, no alacrity,</line>
<line>Of all this sprightly sharpenes, not a smile;</line>
<line>Yet these that we count errours may become him:</line>
<line>Narcissus was a sad Boy, but a heavenly:</line>
<line>Oh who can finde the bent of womans fancy?</line>
<line>I am a Foole, my reason is lost in me,</line>
<line>I have no choice, and I have ly'd so lewdly</line>
<line>That women ought to beate me. On my knees</line>
<line>I aske thy pardon: Palamon, thou art alone,</line>
<line>And only beutifull, and these the eyes,</line>
<line>These the bright lamps of beauty, that command</line>
<line>And threaten Love, and what yong Mayd dare crosse 'em</line>
<line>What a bold gravity, and yet inviting</line>
<line>Has this browne manly face? O Love, this only</line>
<line>From this howre is Complexion: Lye there Arcite,</line>
<line>Thou art a changling to him, a meere Gipsey.</line>
<line>And this the noble Bodie: I am sotted,</line>
<line>Vtterly lost: My Virgins faith has fled me.</line>
<line>For if my brother but even now had ask'd me</line>
<line>Whether I lov'd, I had run mad for Arcite,</line>
<line>Now if my Sister; More for Palamon,</line>
<line>Stand both together: Now, come aske me Brother,</line>
<line>Alas, I know not: aske me now sweet Sister,</line>
<line>I may goe looke; What a meere child is Fancie,</line>
<line>That having two faire gawdes of equall sweetnesse,</line>
<line>Cannot distinguish, but must crie for both.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Emil. and Gent.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>How now Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Gent.</speaker>
<line>From the Noble Duke your Brother</line>
<line>Madam, I bring you newes: The Knights are come.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>To end the quarrell?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Gent.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Would I might end first:</line>
<line>What sinnes have I committed, chast Diana,</line>
<line>That my unspotted youth must now be soyld</line>
<line>With blood of Princes? and my Chastitie</line>
<line>Be made the Altar, where the lives of Lovers,</line>
<line>Two greater, and two better never yet</line>
<line>Made mothers joy, must be the sacrifice</line>
<line>To my unhappy Beautie?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Theseus, Hipolita, Perithous and attendants.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Theseus.</speaker>
<line>Bring 'em in quickly,</line>
<line>By any meanes, I long to see 'em.</line>
<line>Your two contending Lovers are return'd,</line>
<line>And with them their faire Knights: Now my faire Sister,</line>
<line>You must love one of them.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I had rather both,</line>
<line>So neither for my sake should fall untimely</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Messengers. Curtis.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Who saw 'em</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>I a while.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Gent.</speaker>
<line>And I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>From whence come you Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>From the Knights.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Pray speake</line>
<line>You that have seene them, what they are.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>I will Sir.</line>
<line>And truly what I thinke: Six braver spirits</line>
<line>Then these they have brought, (if we judge by the outside)</line>
<line>I never saw, nor read of. He that stands</line>
<line>In the first place with Arcite, by his seeming</line>
<line>Should be a stout man, by his face a Prince,</line>
<line>(His very lookes so say him) his complexion,</line>
<line>Nearer a browne, than blacke; sterne, and yet noble,</line>
<line>Which shewes him hardy, fearelesse, proud of dangers:</line>
<line>The circles of his eyes show faire within him,</line>
<line>And as a heated Lyon, so he lookes;</line>
<line>His haire hangs long behind him, blacke and shining</line>
<line>Like Ravens wings: his shoulders broad, and strong,</line>
<line>Armd long and round, and on his Thigh a Sword</line>
<line>Hung by a curious Bauldricke; when he frownes</line>
<line>To seale his will with, better o'my conscience</line>
<line>Was never Souldiers friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Thou ha'st well describde him,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Yet a great deale short</line>
<line>Me thinkes, of him that's first with Palamon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Pray speake him friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>I ghesse he is a Prince too,</line>
<line>And if it may be, greater; for his show</line>
<line>Has all the ornament of honour in't:</line>
<line>Hee's somewhat bigger, then the Knight he spoke of,</line>
<line>But of a face far sweeter; His complexion</line>
<line>Is (as a ripe grape) ruddy: he has felt</line>
<line>Without doubt what he fights for, and so apter</line>
<line>To make this cause his owne: In's face appeares</line>
<line>All the faire hopes of what he undertakes,</line>
<line>And when he's angry, then a setled valour</line>
<line>(Not tainted with extreames) runs through his body,</line>
<line>And guides his arme to brave things: Feare he cannot,</line>
<line>He shewes no such soft temper, his head's yellow,</line>
<line>Hard hayr'd, and curld, thicke twind like Ivy tops,</line>
<line>Not to undoe with thunder; In his face</line>
<line>The liverie of the warlike Maide appeares,</line>
<line>Pure red, and white, for yet no beard has blest him.</line>
<line>And in his rowling eyes, sits victory,</line>
<line>As if she ever ment to corect his valour:</line>
<line>His Nose stands high, a Character of honour.</line>
<line>His red lips, after fights, are fit for Ladies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Must these men die too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>When he speakes, his tongue</line>
<line>Sounds like a Trumpet; All his lyneaments</line>
<line>Are as a man would wish 'em, strong, and cleane,</line>
<line>He weares a well-steeld Axe, the staffe of gold,</line>
<line>His age some five and twenty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>Ther's another,</line>
<line>A little man, but of a tough soule, seeming</line>
<line>As great as any: fairer promises</line>
<line>In such a Body, yet I never look'd on.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>O, he that's freckle fac'd?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>The same my Lord,</line>
<line>Are they not sweet ones?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Yes they are well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>Me thinkes,</line>
<line>Being so few, and well disposd, they show</line>
<line>Great, and fine art in nature, he's white hair'd,</line>
<line>Not wanton white, but such a manly colour</line>
<line>Next to an aborne, tough, and nimble set,</line>
<line>Which showes an active soule; his armes are brawny</line>
<line>Linde with strong sinewes: To the shoulder peece,</line>
<line>Gently they swell, like women new conceav'd,</line>
<line>Which speakes him prone to labour, never fainting</line>
<line>Vnder the waight of Armes; stout harted, still,</line>
<line>But when he stirs, a Tiger; he's gray eyd,</line>
<line>Which yeelds compassion where he conquers: sharpe</line>
<line>To spy advantages, and where he finds 'em,</line>
<line>He's swift to make 'em his: He do's no wrongs,</line>
<line>Nor takes none; he's round fac'd, and when he smiles</line>
<line>He showes a Lover, when he frownes, a Souldier:</line>
<line>About his head he weares the winners oke,</line>
<line>And in it stucke the favour of his Lady:</line>
<line>His age, some six and thirtie. In his hand</line>
<line>He beares a charging Staffe, embost with silver.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Are they all thus?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>They are all the sonnes of honour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Now as I have a soule I long to see 'em.</line>
<line>Lady you shall see men fight now.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>I wish it,</line>
<line>But not the cause my Lord; They would show</line>
<line>Bravely about the Titles of two Kingdomes;</line>
<line>Tis pitty Love should be so tyrannous:</line>
<line>O my soft harted Sister, what thinke you?</line>
<line>Weepe not, till they weepe blood; Wench it must be.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You have steel'd 'em with your Beautie: honord (Friend,</line>
<line>Fitting the persons that must use it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Yes Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Come, Ile goe visit 'em: I cannot stay,</line>
<line>Their fame has fir'd me so; Till they appeare,</line>
<line>Good Friend be royall.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>There shall want no bravery.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emilia.</speaker>
<line>Poore wench goe weepe, for whosoever wins,</line>
<line>Looses a noble Cosen, for thy sins. <stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir></line>
</speech>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 3. Enter Iailor, Wooer, Doctor.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>She is continually in a harmelesse distemper, sleepes</line>
<line>Little, altogether without appetite, save often drinking,</line>
<line>Dreaming of another world, and a better; and what</line>
<line>Broken peece of matter so'ere she's about, the name</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Palamon</speaker>
<line>lardes it, that she farces ev'ry busines</line>
<stagedir>[Enter Daughter.]</stagedir>
<line>Withall, fyts it to every question; Looke where</line>
<line>Shee comes, you shall perceive her behaviour.</line>
<line>Giraldo, Emilias Schoolemaster; he's as</line>
<line>Fantasticall too, as ever he may goe upon's legs,</line>
<line>For in the next world will Dido see Palamon, and</line>
<line>Then will she be out of love with Eneas.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>What stuff's here? pore soule.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Ioy.</speaker>
<line>Ev'n thus all day long.</line>
<line>Or no ferry: then if it be your chance to come where</line>
<line>The blessed spirits, as ther's a sight now; we maids</line>
<line>That have our Lyvers, perish'd, crakt to peeces with</line>
<line>Love, we shall come there, and doe nothing all day long</line>
<line>But picke flowers with Proserpine, then will I make</line>
<line>Palamon a Nosegay, then let him marke me, = then.</line>
<line>Thother place, such burning, frying, boyling, hissing,</line>
<line>Howling, chattring, cursing, oh they have shrowd</line>
<line>Measure, take heede; if one be mad, or hang or</line>
<line>Drowne themselves, thither they goe, Iupiter blesse</line>
<line>Vs, and there shall we be put in a Caldron of</line>
<line>Lead, and Vsurers grease, amongst a whole million of</line>
<line>Cutpurses, and there boyle like a Gamon of Bacon</line>
<line>That will never be enough.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>How her braine coynes?</line>
<stagedir>[Sings.]</stagedir>
<line>I will be true, my stars, my fate, &amp;c.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit. Daugh.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>What thinke you of her Sir?</line>
<line> (minister to.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>Vnderstand you, she ever affected any man, ere</line>
<line>She beheld Palamon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iay.</speaker>
<line>I was once Sir, in great hope, she had fixd her</line>
<line>Liking on this gentleman my friend.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Woo.</speaker>
<line>I did thinke so too, and would account I had a (great</line>
<line>Pen-worth on't, to give halfe my state, that both</line>
<line>She and I at this present, stood unfainedly on the</line>
<line>Same tearmes.</line>
<line>Execute their preordaind faculties, but they are</line>
<line>Now in a most extravagant vagary. This you</line>
<line>Must doe, Confine her to a place, where the light</line>
<line>May rather seeme to steale in, then be permitted; take</line>
<line>Vpon you (yong Sir her friend) the name of</line>
<line>Palamon, say you come to eate with her, and to</line>
<line>Commune of Love; this will catch her attention, for</line>
<line>This her minde beates upon; other objects that are</line>
<line>Inserted tweene her minde and eye, become the prankes</line>
<line>And friskins of her madnes; Sing to her, such greene</line>
<line>Songs of Love, as she sayes Palamon hath sung in</line>
<line>Prison; Come to her, stucke in as sweet flowers, as the</line>
<line>Season is mistres of, and thereto make an addition of</line>
<line>Som other compounded odours, which are grateful to the</line>
<line>Sence: all this shall become Palamon, for Palamon can</line>
<line>Sing, and Palamon is sweet, and ev'ry good thing, desire</line>
<line>To eate with her, crave her, drinke to her, and still</line>
<line>Among, intermingle your petition of grace and acceptance</line>
<line>Into her favour: Learne what Maides have beene her</line>
<line>Companions, and play-pheeres, and let them repaire to</line>
<line>Her with Palamon in their mouthes, and appeare with</line>
<line>Tokens, as if they suggested for him, It is a falsehood</line>
<line>She is in, which is with falsehoods to be combated.</line>
<line>This may bring her to eate, to sleepe, and reduce what's</line>
<line>Now out of square in her, into their former law, and</line>
<line>Regiment; I have seene it approved, how many times</line>
<line>I know not, but to make the number more, I have</line>
<line>Great hope in this. I will betweene the passages of</line>
<line>This project, come in with my applyance: Let us</line>
</speech>

</scene> 

</act>

<act>
<acttitle>Act V</acttitle>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene i</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 1. Enter Thesius, Perithous, Hipolita, attendants.</scenetitle>

<speech>
<line>Tender their holy prayers: Let the Temples</line>
<line>Burne bright with sacred fires, and the Altars</line>
<line>In hallowed clouds commend their swelling Incense</line>
<line>To those above us: Let no due be wanting,</line>
<stagedir>[Florish of Cornets.]</stagedir>
<line>They have a noble worke in hand, will honour</line>
<line>The very powers that love 'em.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Palamon and Arcite, and their Knights.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Sir they enter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You valiant and strong harted Enemies</line>
<line>You royall German foes, that this day come</line>
<line>To blow that nearenesse out that flames betweene ye;</line>
<line>Lay by your anger for an houre, and dove-like</line>
<line>Before the holy Altars of your helpers</line>
<line>(The all feard gods) bow downe your stubborne bodies,</line>
<line>Your ire is more than mortall; So your helpe be,</line>
<line>And as the gods regard ye, fight with Iustice,</line>
<line>Ile leave you to your prayers, and betwixt ye</line>
<line>I part my wishes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Honour crowne the worthiest.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit Theseus, and his traine.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>The glasse is running now that cannot finish</line>
<line>Till one of us expire: Thinke you but thus,</line>
<line>That were there ought in me which strove to show</line>
<line>Mine enemy in this businesse, wer't one eye</line>
<line>Against another: Arme opprest by Arme:</line>
<line>I would destroy th 'offender, Coz, I would</line>
<line>Though parcell of my selfe: Then from this gather</line>
<line>How I should tender you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>I am in labour</line>
<line>To push your name, your auncient love, our kindred</line>
<line>Out of my memory; and i'th selfe same place</line>
<line>To seate something I would confound: So hoyst we</line>
<line>The sayles, that must these vessells port even where</line>
<line>The heavenly Lymiter pleases.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>You speake well;</line>
<line>Before I turne, Let me embrace thee Cosen</line>
<line>This I shall never doe agen.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>One farewell.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Why let it be so: Farewell Coz.</line>
<line> <stagedir>[Exeunt Palamon and his Knights.]</stagedir>

</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Farewell Sir;</line>
<line>Knights, Kinsemen, Lovers, yea my Sacrifices</line>
<line>True worshippers of Mars, whose spirit in you</line>
<line>Expells the seedes of feare, and th' apprehension</line>
<line>Which still is farther off it, Goe with me</line>
<line>Before the god of our profession: There</line>
<line>Require of him the hearts of Lyons, and</line>
<line>The breath of Tigers, yea the fearcenesse too,</line>
<line>Yea the speed also, to goe on, I meane:</line>
<line>Else wish we to be Snayles; you know my prize</line>
<line>Must be drag'd out of blood, force and great feate</line>
<line>Must put my Garland on, where she stickes</line>
<line>The Queene of Flowers: our intercession then</line>
<line>Must be to him that makes the Campe, a Cestron</line>
<line>Brymd with the blood of men: give me your aide</line>
<line>And bend your spirits towards him.</line>
<stagedir>[They kneele.]</stagedir>
<line>Thou mighty one, that with thy power hast turnd</line>
<line>Greene Neptune into purple.</line>
<line>Comets prewarne, whose havocke in vaste Feild</line>
<line>Vnearthed skulls proclaime, whose breath blowes downe,</line>
<line>The teeming Ceres foyzon, who dost plucke</line>
<line>With hand armenypotent from forth blew clowdes,</line>
<line>The masond Turrets, that both mak'st, and break'st</line>
<line>The stony girthes of Citties: me thy puple,</line>
<line>Yongest follower of thy Drom, instruct this day</line>
<line>With military skill, that to thy lawde</line>
<line>I may advance my Streamer, and by thee,</line>
<line>Be stil'd the Lord o'th day, give me great Mars</line>
<line>Some token of thy pleasure.</line>
<stagedir>[ Here they fall on their faces as formerly, and there is heard]</stagedir>
<line>Shaker of ore-rank States, thou grand decider</line>
<line>Of dustie, and old tytles, that healst with blood</line>
<line>The earth when it is sicke, and curst the world</line>
<line>O'th pluresie of people; I doe take</line>
<line>Thy signes auspiciously, and in thy name</line>
<line>To my designe; march boldly, let us goe.</line>
<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>
<line>To daie extinct; our argument is love,</line>
<line>Which if the goddesse of it grant, she gives</line>
<line>Victory too, then blend your spirits with mine,</line>
<line>You, whose free noblenesse doe make my cause</line>
<line>Your personall hazard; to the goddesse Venus</line>
<line>Commend we our proceeding, and implore</line>
<line>Her power unto our partie.</line>
<stagedir>[Here they kneele as formerly.]</stagedir>
<line>Haile Soveraigne Queene of secrets, who hast power</line>
<line>To call the feircest Tyrant from his rage;</line>
<line>And weepe unto a Girle; that ha'st the might</line>
<line>Even with an ey-glance, to choke Marsis Drom</line>
<line>And turne th' allarme to whispers, that canst make</line>
<line>A Criple florish with his Crutch, and cure him</line>
<line>Before Apollo; that may'st force the King</line>
<line>To be his subjects vassaile, and induce</line>
<line>Stale gravitie to daunce, the pould Bachelour</line>
<line>Whose youth like wanton Boyes through Bonfyres</line>
<line>Have skipt thy flame, at seaventy, thou canst catch</line>
<line>And make him to the scorne of his hoarse throate</line>
<line>Abuse yong laies of love; what godlike power</line>
<line>Hast thou not power upon? To Phaebus thou</line>
<line>Add'st flames, hotter then his the heavenly fyres</line>
<line>Did scortch his mortall Son, thine him; the huntresse</line>
<line>All moyst and cold, some say began to throw</line>
<line>Her Bow away, and sigh: take to thy grace</line>
<line>Me thy vowd Souldier, who doe beare thy yoke</line>
<line>As t'wer a wreath of Roses, yet is heavier</line>
<line>Then Lead it selfe, stings more than Nettles;</line>
<line>I have never beene foule mouthd against thy law,</line>
<line>Nev'r reveald secret, for I knew none; would not</line>
<line>Had I kend all that were; I never practised</line>
<line>Vpon mans wife, nor would the Libells reade</line>
<line>Of liberall wits: I never at great feastes</line>
<line>Sought to betray a Beautie, but have blush'd</line>
<line>At simpring Sirs that did: I have beene harsh</line>
<line>To large Confessors, and have hotly ask'd them</line>
<line>If they had Mothers, I had one, a woman,</line>
<line>And women t'wer they wrong'd. I knew a man</line>
<line>Of eightie winters, this I told them, who</line>
<line>A Lasse of foureteene brided; twas thy power</line>
<line>To put life into dust, the aged Crampe</line>
<line>Had screw'd his square foote round,</line>
<line>The Gout had knit his fingers into knots,</line>
<line>Torturing Convulsions from his globie eyes,</line>
<line>Had almost drawne their spheeres, that what was life</line>
<line>In him seem'd torture: this Anatomie</line>
<line>Had by his yong faire pheare a Boy, and I</line>
<line>Beleev'd it was his, for she swore it was,</line>
<line>And who would not beleeve her? briefe I am</line>
<line>To those that prate and have done; no Companion</line>
<line>To those that boast and have not; a defyer</line>
<line>To those that would and cannot; a Rejoycer,</line>
<line>Yea him I doe not love, that tells close offices</line>
<line>The fowlest way, nor names concealements in</line>
<line>The boldest language, such a one I am,</line>
<line>And vow that lover never yet made sigh</line>
<line>Truer then I. O then most soft sweet goddesse</line>
<line>Give me the victory of this question, which</line>
<line>Is true loves merit, and blesse me with a signe</line>
<line>Of thy great pleasure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>O thou that from eleven, to ninetie raign'st</line>
<line>In mortall bosomes, whose chase is this world</line>
<line>And we in heards thy game; I give thee thankes</line>
<line>For this faire Token, which being layd unto</line>
<line>Mine innocent true heart, armes in assurance</line>
<stagedir>[They bow.]</stagedir>
<line>My body to this businesse: Let us rise</line>
<line>And bow before the goddesse: Time comes on.</line>
<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Still Musicke of Records.]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[ Enter Emilia in white, her haire about her shoulders, a wheaten]</stagedir>
<line>Sweet, solitary, white as chaste, and pure</line>
<line>As windefand Snow, who to thy femall knights</line>
<line>Alow'st no more blood than will make a blush,</line>
<line>Which is their orders robe. I heere thy Priest</line>
<line>Am humbled fore thine Altar, O vouchsafe</line>
<line>With that thy rare greene eye, which never yet</line>
<line>Beheld thing maculate, looke on thy virgin,</line>
<line>And sacred silver Mistris, lend thine eare</line>
<line>(Which nev'r heard scurrill terme, into whose port</line>
<line>Ne're entred wanton sound,) to my petition</line>
<line>Seasond with holy feare; This is my last</line>
<line>Of vestall office, I am bride habited,</line>
<line>But mayden harted, a husband I have pointed,</line>
<line>But doe not know him out of two, I should</line>
<line>Choose one, and pray for his successe, but I</line>
<line>Am guiltlesse of election of mine eyes,</line>
<line>Were I to loose one, they are equall precious,</line>
<line>I could doombe neither, that which perish'd should</line>
<line>Goe too't unsentenc'd: Therefore most modest Queene,</line>
<line>He of the two Pretenders, that best loves me</line>
<line>And has the truest title in't, Let him</line>
<line>Take off my wheaten Gerland, or else grant</line>
<line>The fyle and qualitie I hold, I may</line>
<line>Continue in thy Band.</line>
<line>See what our Generall of Ebbs and Flowes</line>
<line>Out from the bowells of her holy Altar</line>
<line>With sacred act advances: But one Rose,</line>
<line>If well inspird, this Battaile shal confound</line>
<line>Both these brave Knights, and I a virgin flowre</line>
<line>Must grow alone unpluck'd.</line>
<line>The flowre is falne, the Tree descends: O Mistris</line>
<line>Thou here dischargest me, I shall be gather'd,</line>
<line>I thinke so, but I know not thine owne will;</line>
<line>Vnclaspe thy Misterie: I hope she's pleas'd,</line>
<line>Her Signes were gratious.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[They curtsey and Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene ii</scenetitle>

<speech>
<line>Would eate, and when I would kisse her: I told her</line>
<line>Presently, and kist her twice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>Twas well done; twentie times had bin far better,</line>
<line>For there the cure lies mainely.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Then she told me</line>
<line>She would watch with me to night, for well she knew</line>
<line>What houre my fit would take me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>Let her doe so,</line>
<line>And when your fit comes, fit her home,</line>
<line>And presently.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>She would have me sing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>You did so?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doct.</speaker>
<line>Twas very ill done then,</line>
<line>You should observe her ev'ry way.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Alas</line>
<line>I have no voice Sir, to confirme her that way.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>That's all one, if yee make a noyse,</line>
<line>If she intreate againe, doe any thing,</line>
<line>Lye with her if she aske you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Hoa there Doctor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Yes in the waie of cure.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>But first by your leave</line>
<line>I'th way of honestie.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>That's but a nicenesse,</line>
<line>Nev'r cast your child away for honestie;</line>
<line>Cure her first this way, then if shee will be honest,</line>
<line>She has the path before her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Thanke yee Doctor.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Pray bring her in</line>
<line>And let's see how shee is.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>I will, and tell her</line>
<line>Her Palamon staies for her: But Doctor,</line>
<line>Me thinkes you are i'th wrong still.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit Iaylor.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Why, doe you thinke she is not honest Sir?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>How old is she?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>She's eighteene.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>She may be,</line>
<line>But that's all one, tis nothing to our purpose,</line>
<line>What ere her Father saies, if you perceave</line>
<line>Her moode inclining that way that I spoke of</line>
<line>Videlicet, the way of flesh, you have me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Yet very well Sir.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Please her appetite</line>
<line>And doe it home, it cures her ipso facto,</line>
<line>The mellencholly humour that infects her,</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I am of your minde Doctor.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Iaylor, Daughter, Maide.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Docter.</speaker>
<line>You'l finde it so; she comes, pray honour her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daughter.</speaker>
<line>I thanke him for his gentle patience,</line>
<line>He's a kind Gentleman, and I am much bound to him,</line>
<line>Did you nev'r see the horse he gave me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>How doe you like him?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>He's a very faire one.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>You never saw him dance?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>I have often.</line>
<line>He daunces very finely, very comely,</line>
<line>And for a Iigge, come cut and long taile to him,</line>
<line>He turnes ye like a Top.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>That's fine indeede.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Hee'l dance the Morris twenty mile an houre,</line>
<line>And that will founder the best hobby-horse</line>
<line>(If I have any skill) in all the parish,</line>
<line>And gallops to the turne of Light a' love,</line>
<line>What thinke you of this horse?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Having these vertues</line>
<line>I thinke he might be broght to play at Tennis.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Alas that's nothing.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Can he write and reade too.</line>
<line>Must rise betime that cozens him; you know</line>
<line>The Chestnut Mare the Duke has?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Very well.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>She is horribly in love with him, poore beast,</line>
<line>But he is like his master coy and scornefull.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>What dowry has she?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Some two hundred Bottles,</line>
<line>And twenty strike of Oates, but hee'l ne're have her;</line>
<line>He lispes in's neighing able to entice</line>
<line>A Millars Mare,</line>
<line>Hee'l be the death of her.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>What stuffe she utters?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Make curtsie, here your love comes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Pretty soule</line>
<line>How doe ye? that's a fine maide, ther's a curtsie.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Yours to command ith way of honestie;</line>
<line>How far is't now to'th end o'th world my Masters?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Why a daies Iorney wench.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Will you goe with me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>What shall we doe there wench?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Why play at stoole ball,</line>
<line>What is there else to doe?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I am content</line>
<line>If we shall keepe our wedding there.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Tis true</line>
<line>For there I will assure you, we shall finde</line>
<line>Some blind Priest for the purpose, that will venture</line>
<line>To marry us, for here they are nice, and foolish;</line>
<line>Besides my father must be hang'd to morrow</line>
<line>And that would be a blot i'th businesse</line>
<line>Are not you Palamon?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Doe not you know me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>That's all one, I will have you.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Will you surely?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Yes by this faire hand will I.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Wee'l to bed then.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Ev'n when you will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>O Sir, you would faine be nibling.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Why doe you rub my kisse off?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Tis a sweet one,</line>
<line>And will perfume me finely against the wedding.</line>
<line>Is not this your Cosen Arcite?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Yes sweet heart,</line>
<line>And I am glad my Cosen Palamon</line>
<line>Has made so faire a choice.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Doe you thinke hee'l have me?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Yes without doubt.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>Doe you thinke so too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Yes.</line>
<line>Now he's at liberty: Alas poore Chicken</line>
<line>He was kept downe with hard meate, and ill lodging</line>
<line>But ile kisse him up againe.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter a Messenger.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Are they i'th Field?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>They are</line>
<line>You beare a charge there too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Ile away straight</line>
<line>I must ev'n leave you here.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Docter.</speaker>
<line>Nay wee'l goe with you,</line>
<line>I will not loose the Fight.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>How did you like her?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
<line>Ile warrant you within these 3. or 4. daies</line>
<line>Ile make her right againe. You must not from her</line>
<line>But still preserve her in this way.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I will.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doc.</speaker>
<line>Lets get her in.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Come sweete wee'l goe to dinner</line>
<line>And then weele play at Cardes.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>And shall we kisse too?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>A hundred times</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>And twenty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line> I and twenty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>And then wee'l sleepe together.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Doc.</speaker>
<line>Take her offer.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>Yes marry will we.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line>But you shall not hurt me.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Wooer.</speaker>
<line>I will not sweete.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Daugh.</speaker>
<line> If you doe (Love) ile cry.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Florish. Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iii</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 3. Enter Theseus, Hipolita, Emilia, Perithous: and</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Ile no step further.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Per.</speaker>
<line>Will you loose this sight?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I had rather see a wren hawke at a fly</line>
<line>Then this decision ev'ry; blow that falls</line>
<line>Threats a brave life, each stroake laments</line>
<line>The place whereon it fals, and sounds more like</line>
<line>A Bell, then blade: I will stay here,</line>
<line>It is enough my hearing shall be punishd,</line>
<line>With what shall happen, gainst the which there is</line>
<line>No deaffing, but to heare; not taint mine eye</line>
<line>With dread sights, it may shun.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>Sir, my good Lord</line>
<line>Your Sister will no further.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Oh she must.</line>
<line>She shall see deeds of honour in their kinde,</line>
<line>Which sometime show well pencild. Nature now</line>
<line>Shall make, and act the Story, the beleife</line>
<line>Both seald with eye, and eare; you must be present,</line>
<line>You are the victours meede, the price, and garlond</line>
<line>To crowne the Questions title.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Pardon me,</line>
<line>If I were there, I'ld winke</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>You must be there;</line>
<line>This Tryall is as t'wer i'th night, and you</line>
<line>The onely star to shine.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I am extinct,</line>
<line>There is but envy in that light, which showes</line>
<line>The one the other: darkenes which ever was</line>
<line>The dam of horrour, who do's stand accurst</line>
<line>Of many mortall Millions, may even now</line>
<line>By casting her blacke mantle over both</line>
<line>That neither could finde other, get her selfe</line>
<line>Some part of a good name, and many a murther</line>
<line>Set off wherto she's guilty.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>You must goe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>In faith I will not.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Why the knights must kindle</line>
<line>Their valour at your eye: know of this war</line>
<line>You are the Treasure, and must needes be by</line>
<line>To give the Service pay.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Sir pardon me,</line>
<line>The tytle of a kingdome may be tride</line>
<line>Out of it selfe.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Well, well then, at your pleasure,</line>
<line>Those that remaine with you, could wish their office</line>
<line>To any of their Enemies.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Farewell Sister,</line>
<line>I am like to know your husband fore your selfe</line>
<line>By some small start of time, he whom the gods</line>
<line>Doe of the two know best, I pray them he</line>
<line>Be made your Lot.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt Theseus, Hipolita, Perithous, &amp;c.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Arcite is gently visagd; yet his eye</line>
<line>Is like an Engyn bent, or a sharpe weapon</line>
<line>In a soft sheath; mercy, and manly courage</line>
<line>Are bedfellowes in his visage: Palamon</line>
<line>Has a most menacing aspect, his brow</line>
<line>Is grav'd, and seemes to bury what it frownes on,</line>
<line>Yet sometime tis not so, but alters to</line>
<line>The quallity of his thoughts; long time his eye</line>
<line>Will dwell upon his object. Mellencholly</line>
<line>Becomes him nobly; So do's Arcites mirth,</line>
<line>But Palamons sadnes is a kinde of mirth,</line>
<line>So mingled, as if mirth did make him sad,</line>
<line>And sadnes, merry; those darker humours that</line>
<line>Sticke misbecomingly on others, on them</line>
<line>Live in faire dwelling.</line>
<stagedir>[Cornets. Trompets sound as to a charge.]</stagedir>
<line>Harke how yon spurs to spirit doe incite</line>
<line>The Princes to their proofe, Arcite may win me,</line>
<line>And yet may Palamon wound Arcite to</line>
<line>The spoyling of his figure. O what pitty</line>
<line>Enough for such a chance; if I were by</line>
<line>I might doe hurt, for they would glance their eies</line>
<line>Toward my Seat, and in that motion might</line>
<line>Omit a ward, or forfeit an offence</line>
<line>Which crav'd that very time: it is much better</line>
<line>Then minister to such harme, what is the chance?</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Servant.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Ser.</speaker>
<line>The Crie's a Palamon.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Then he has won: Twas ever likely,</line>
<line>He lookd all grace and successe, and he is</line>
<line>Doubtlesse the prim'st of men: I pre'thee run</line>
<line>And tell me how it goes.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Showt, and Cornets: Crying a Palamon.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Ser.</speaker>
<line>Still Palamon.</line>
<line>Palamons on the left, why so, I know not,</line>
<line>I had no end in't; else chance would have it so.</line>
<stagedir>[Another cry, and showt within, and Cornets.]</stagedir>
<line>On the sinister side, the heart lyes; Palamon</line>
<line>Had the best boding chance: This burst of clamour</line>
<line>Is sure th' end o'th Combat.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Servant.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Ser.</speaker>
<line>They saide that Palamon had Arcites body</line>
<line>Within an inch o'th Pyramid, that the cry</line>
<line>Was generall a Palamon: But anon,</line>
<line>Th 'Assistants made a brave redemption, and</line>
<line>The two bold Tytlers, at this instant are</line>
<line>Hand to hand at it.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Were they metamorphisd</line>
<line>Both into one; oh why? there were no woman</line>
<line>Worth so composd a Man: their single share,</line>
<line>Their noblenes peculier to them, gives</line>
<line>The prejudice of disparity values shortnes</line>
<stagedir>[Cornets. Cry within, Arcite, Arcite.]</stagedir>
<line>To any Lady breathing = More exulting?</line>
<line>Palamon still?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Ser.</speaker>
<line>Nay, now the sound is Arcite.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>I pre'thee lay attention to the Cry.</line>
<stagedir>[Cornets. A great showt and cry, Arcite, victory.]</stagedir>
<line>Set both thine eares to'th busines.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Ser.</speaker>
<line>The cry is</line>
<line>Arcite, and victory, harke Arcite, victory,</line>
<line>The Combats consummation is proclaim'd</line>
<line>By the wind Instruments.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Halfe sights saw</line>
<line>That Arcite was no babe: god's lyd, his richnes</line>
<line>And costlines of spirit look't through him, it could</line>
<line>No more be hid in him, then fire in flax,</line>
<line>Then humble banckes can goe to law with waters,</line>
<line>That drift windes, force to raging: I did thinke</line>
<line>Good Palamon would miscarry, yet I knew not</line>
<line>Why I did thinke so; Our reasons are not prophets</line>
<line>When oft our fancies are: They are comming off:</line>
<line>Alas poore Palamon.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Cornets.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Lo, where our Sister is in expectation,</line>
<line>Yet quaking, and unsetled: Fairest Emily,</line>
<line>The gods by their divine arbitrament</line>
<line>Have given you this Knight, he is a good one</line>
<line>As ever strooke at head: Give me your hands;</line>
<line>Receive you her, you him, be plighted with</line>
<line>A love that growes, as you decay;</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arcite.</speaker>
<line>Emily,</line>
<line>To buy you, I have lost what's deerest to me,</line>
<line>Save what is bought, and yet I purchase cheapely,</line>
<line>As I doe rate your value.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>O loved Sister,</line>
<line>He speakes now of as brave a Knight as ere</line>
<line>Did spur a noble Steed: Surely the gods</line>
<line>Would have him die a Batchelour, least his race</line>
<line>Should shew i'th world too godlike: His behaviour</line>
<line>So charmd me, that me thought Alcides was</line>
<line>To him a sow of lead: if I could praise</line>
<line>Each part of him to'th all; I have spoke, your Arcite</line>
<line>Did not loose by't; For he that was thus good</line>
<line>Encountred yet his Better, I have heard</line>
<line>Two emulous Philomels, beate the eare o'th night</line>
<line>With their contentious throates, now one the higher,</line>
<line>Anon the other, then againe the first,</line>
<line>And by and by out breasted, that the sence</line>
<line>Could not be judge betweene 'em: So it far'd</line>
<line>Good space betweene these kinesmen; till heavens did</line>
<line>Make hardly one the winner: weare the Girlond</line>
<line>With joy that you have won: For the subdude,</line>
<line>Give them our present Iustice, since I know</line>
<line>Their lives but pinch 'em; Let it here be done:</line>
<line>The Sceane's not for our seeing, goe we hence,</line>
<line>Right joyfull, with some sorrow. Arme your prize,</line>
<line>I know you will not loose her: Hipolita</line>
<line>I see one eye of yours conceives a teare</line>
<line>The which it will deliver.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Emil.</speaker>
<line>Is this wynning?</line>
<line>Oh all you heavenly powers where is your mercy?</line>
<line>But that your wils have saide it must be so,</line>
<line>And charge me live to comfort this unfriended,</line>
<line>This miserable Prince, that cuts away</line>
<line>A life more worthy from him, then all women;</line>
<line>I should, and would die too.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Hip.</speaker>
<line>Infinite pitty</line>
<line>That fowre such eies should be so fixd on one</line>
<line>That two must needes be blinde fort.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>So it is.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt.]</stagedir>

</scene>

<scene>
<scenetitle>Scene iv</scenetitle>

<scenetitle>Scaena 4. Enter Palamon and his Knightes pyniond: Iaylor,</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>Palamon.</speaker>
<line>Speech prefix not in Q</line>
<line>Ther's many a man alive, that hath out liv'd</line>
<line>The love o'th people, yea i'th selfesame state</line>
<line>Stands many a Father with his childe; some comfort</line>
<line>We have by so considering: we expire</line>
<line>And not without mens pitty. To live still,</line>
<line>Have their good wishes, we prevent</line>
<line>The loathsome misery of age, beguile,</line>
<line>The Gowt and Rheume, that in lag howres attend</line>
<line>For grey approachers; we come towards the gods</line>
<line>Yong, and unwrapper'd not, halting under Crymes</line>
<line>Many and stale: that sure shall please the gods</line>
<line>Sooner than such, to give us Nectar with 'em,</line>
<line>For we are more cleare Spirits. My deare kinsemen.</line>
<line>Whose lives (for this poore comfort) are laid downe,</line>
<line>You have sould 'em too too cheape.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. K.</speaker>
<line>What ending could be</line>
<line>Of more content? ore us the victors have</line>
<line>Fortune, whose title is as momentary,</line>
<line>As to us death is certaine: A graine of honour</line>
<line>They not o're-weigh us.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. K.</speaker>
<line>Let us bid farewell;</line>
<line>And with our patience, anger tottring Fortune,</line>
<line>Who at her certain'st reeles.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>3. K.</speaker>
<line>Come? who begins?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Ev'n he that led you to this Banket, shall</line>
<line>Taste to you all: ah ha my Friend, my Friend,</line>
<line>Your gentle daughter gave me freedome once;</line>
<line>You'l see't done now for ever: pray how do'es she?</line>
<line>I heard she was not well; her kind of ill</line>
<line>Gave me some sorrow.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>Sir she's well restor'd,</line>
<line>And to be marryed shortly.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>By my short life</line>
<line>I am most glad on't; Tis the latest thing</line>
<line>I shall be glad of, pre'thee tell her so:</line>
<line>Commend me to her, and to peece her portion</line>
<line>Tender her this.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. K.</speaker>
<line>Nay lets be offerers all.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>2. K.</speaker>
<line>Is it a maide?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Verily I thinke so,</line>
<line>A right good creature, more to me deserving</line>
<line>Then I can quight or speake of.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>All  K.</speaker>
<line>Commend us to her.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[They give their purses.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Iaylor.</speaker>
<line>The gods requight you all,</line>
<line>And make her thankefull.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Adiew; and let my life be now as short,</line>
<line>As my leave taking.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Lies on the Blocke.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>1. K.</speaker>
<line>Leade couragious Cosin.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>1. 2. K.</speaker>
<line>Wee'l follow cheerefully.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[ A great noise within crying, run, save hold:]</stagedir>
<stagedir>[Enter in hast a Messenger.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Mess.</speaker>
<line>Hold, hold, O hold, hold, hold.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter Pirithous in haste.]</stagedir>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>Hold hoa: It is a cursed hast you made</line>
<line>If you have done so quickly: noble Palamon,</line>
<line>The gods will shew their glory in a life</line>
<line>That thou art yet to leade.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Can that be,</line>
<line>When Venus I have said is false? How doe things fare?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>Arise great Sir, and give the tydings eare</line>
<line>That are most early sweet, and bitter.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>What</line>
<line>Hath wakt us from our dreame?</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pir.</speaker>
<line>List then: your Cosen</line>
<line>Mounted upon a Steed that Emily</line>
<line>Did first bestow on him, a blacke one, owing</line>
<line>Not a hayre worth of white, which some will say</line>
<line>Weakens his price, and many will not buy</line>
<line>His goodnesse with this note: Which superstition</line>
<line>Heere findes allowance: On this horse is Arcite</line>
<line>Trotting the stones of Athens, which the Calkins</line>
<line>Did rather tell, then trample; for the horse</line>
<line>Would make his length a mile, if't pleas'd his Rider</line>
<line>To put pride in him: as he thus went counting</line>
<line>The flinty pavement, dancing as t'wer to'th Musicke</line>
<line>His owne hoofes made; (for as they say from iron</line>
<line>Came Musickes origen) what envious Flint,</line>
<line>Cold as old Saturne, and like him possest</line>
<line>With fire malevolent, darted a Sparke</line>
<line>Or what feirce sulphur else, to this end made,</line>
<line>I comment not; the hot horse, hot as fire</line>
<line>Tooke Toy at this, and fell to what disorder</line>
<line>His power could give his will, bounds, comes on end,</line>
<line>Forgets schoole dooing, being therein traind,</line>
<line>And of kind mannadge, pig-like he whines</line>
<line>At the sharpe Rowell, which he freats at rather</line>
<line>Then any jot obaies; seekes all foule meanes</line>
<line>Of boystrous and rough Iadrie, to dis-seate</line>
<line>His Lord, that kept it bravely: when nought serv'd,</line>
<line> When neither Curb would cracke, girth breake nor diffring (plunges</line>
<line>He kept him tweene his legges, on his hind hoofes</line>
<line>on end he stands</line>
<line>That Arcites leggs being higher then his head</line>
<line>Seem'd with strange art to hang: His victors wreath</line>
<line>Even then fell off his head: and presently</line>
<line>Backeward the Iade comes ore, and his full poyze</line>
<line>Becomes the Riders loade: yet is he living,</line>
<line>But such a vessell tis, that floates but for</line>
<line>The surge that next approaches: he much desires</line>
<line>To have some speech with you: Loe he appeares.</line>
<line>The gods are mightie Arcite, if thy heart,</line>
<line>Thy worthie, manly heart be yet unbroken:</line>
<line>Give me thy last words, I am Palamon,</line>
<line>One that yet loves thee dying.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Arc.</speaker>
<line>Take Emilia</line>
<line>And with her, all the worlds joy: Reach thy hand,</line>
<line>Farewell: I have told my last houre; I was false,</line>
<line>Yet never treacherous: Forgive me Cosen:</line>
<line>One kisse from faire Emilia: Tis done:</line>
<line>Take her: I die.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>Thy brave soule seeke Elizium.</line>
<line>Thou art a right good man, and while I live,</line>
<line>This day I give to teares.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>And I to honour.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>In this place first you fought: ev'n very here</line>
<line>I sundred you, acknowledge to the gods</line>
<line>Our thankes that you are living:</line>
<line>His part is playd, and though it were too short</line>
<line>He did it well: your day is lengthned, and,</line>
<line>The blissefull dew of heaven do's arowze you.</line>
<line>The powerfull Venus, well hath grac'd her Altar,</line>
<line>And given you your love: Our Master Mars</line>
<line>Hast vouch'd his Oracle, and to Arcite gave</line>
<line>The grace of the Contention: So the Deities</line>
<line>Have shewd due justice: Beare this hence.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Pal.</speaker>
<line>O Cosen,</line>
<line>That we should things desire, which doe cost us</line>
<line>The losse of our desire; That nought could buy</line>
<line>Deare love, but losse of deare love.</line>
</speech>

<speech>
<speaker>Thes.</speaker>
<line>Never Fortune</line>
<line>Did play a subtler Game: The conquerd triumphes,</line>
<line>The victor has the Losse: yet in the passage,</line>
<line>The gods have beene most equall: Palamon,</line>
<line>Your kinesman hath confest the right o'th Lady</line>
<line>Did lye in you, for you first saw her, and</line>
<line>Even then proclaimd your fancie: He restord her</line>
<line>As your stolne Iewell, and desir'd your spirit</line>
<line>To send him hence forgiven; The gods my justice</line>
<line>Take from my hand, and they themselves become</line>
<line>The Executioners: Leade your Lady off;</line>
<line>And call your Lovers from the stage of death,</line>
<line>Whom I adopt my Frinds. A day or two</line>
<line>Let us looke sadly, and give grace unto</line>
<line>The Funerall of Arcite, in whose end</line>
<line>The visages of Bridegroomes weele put on</line>
<line>And smile with Palamon; for whom an houre,</line>
<line>But one houre since, I was as dearely sorry,</line>
<line>As glad of Arcite: and am now as glad,</line>
<line>As for him sorry. O you heavenly Charmers,</line>
<line>What things you make of us? For what we lacke</line>
<line>We laugh, for what we have, are sorry still,</line>
<line>Are children in some kind. Let us be thankefull</line>
<line>For that which is, and with you leave dispute</line>
<line>That are above our question: Let's goe off,</line>
<line>And beare us like the time.</line>
</speech> 

<stagedir>[Florish. Exeunt.]</stagedir>
</scene>

<epilogue>
<scenetitle>[Epilogue]</scenetitle>

<speech>
<speaker>EPILOGVE.</speaker>
<line>I would now aske ye how ye like the Play,</line>
<line>But as it is with Schoole Boyes, cannot say,</line>
<line>I am cruell fearefull: pray yet stay a while,</line>
<line>And let me looke upon ye: No man smile?</line>
<line>Then it goes hard I see; He that has</line>
<line>Lov'd a yong hansome wench then, show his face:</line>
<line>Tis strange if none be heere, and if he will</line>
<line>Against his Conscience let him hisse, and kill</line>
<line>Our Market: Tis in vaine, I see to stay yee,</line>
<line>Have at the worst can come, then; Now what say ye?</line>
<line>And yet mistake me not: I am not bold</line>
<line>We have no such cause. If the tale we have told</line>
<line>(For tis no other) any way content ye)</line>
<line>(For to that honest purpose it was ment ye)</line>
<line>We have our end; and ye shall have ere long</line>
<line>I dare say many a better, to prolong</line>
<line>Your old loves to us: we, and all our might,</line>
<line>Rest at your service, Gentlemen, good night.</line>
</speech>

<stagedir>[Florish.]</stagedir>

</epilogue>
</act>

<finis>
<finistitle>FINIS.</finistitle>
</finis>

<authordetails>
<author>PlayShakespeare.com</author>
<authorurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</authorurl>
<copyright>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>2.0</version>
<license>GFDL License 1.3</license>
<licenseurl>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</licenseurl>
<termsurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com/about-us</termsurl>
</authordetails>

</play>