<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<frontmatter>

<readeraddress>
<title>To the Reader.</title>
<body>
<line>This Figure, that thou here &#383;ee&#383;t put,</line>
<line offset="1">It was for gentle Shake&#383;peare cut:</line>
<line>Wherein the Grauer had a &#383;trife</line>
<line offset="1">with Nature, to out-doo the life:</line>
<line>O, could he but haue drawne his wit</line>
<line offset="1">As well in bra&#383;&#383;e, as he hath hit</line>
<line>His face, the Print would then &#383;urpa&#383;&#383;e</line>
<line offset="1">All, that vvas euer vvrit in bra&#383;&#383;e.</line>
<line>But, &#383;ince he cannot, Reader, looke</line>
<line offset="1">Not on his Pi&#392;ture, but his Booke.</line>
<author>B.I.</author>
</body>
</readeraddress>

<frontispiece>
<toptitle>
<author>
<line>M<smallcap>r</smallcap>. WILLIAM</line>
<line>SHAKESPEARES</line>
</author>
<title>
<line>COMEDIES,</line>
<line>HISTORIES, &amp;</line>
<line>TRAGEDIES.</line>
</title>
<subtitle>Publi&#383;hed according to the True Originall Copies.</subtitle>
</toptitle>
<engraving>
<image />
<illustrator>
	<name>Martin Droeshout</name>
	<role>Sculpsit</role>
	<location>London</location>
</illustrator>
</engraving>
<place>LONDON</place>
<printer>Printed by I&#383;aac Iaggard, and Ed. Blount. <year>1623</year>.</printer>
</frontispiece>

<dedication>
<flourish />
<title>TO THE MOST NOBLE<lb/>And<lb/>INCOMPARABLE PAIRE<lb/>OF BRETHREN.</title>
<subtitle>William<lb/>
Earle of Pembroke,&amp;c. Lord Chamberlaine to the<lb/>
<nameref>Kings mo&#383;t Excellent Maie&#383;ty.</nameref><lb/>
AND<lb/>
Philip<lb/>
Earle of Montgomery,&amp;c. Gentleman of his Maie&#383;ties<lb/>
Bed-Chamber. Both Knights of the mo&#383;t Noble Order<lb/>
of the Garter, and our &#383;ingular good<lb/>
LORDS.<lb/>
</subtitle>
<salutation>Right Honourable,</salutation>
<line><dropcap type="floral">W</dropcap>hil&#383;t we &#383;tudie to be thankful in our particular, for the many favors we have receiued from your L.L. we are falne vpon the ill fortune, to mingle two the mo&#383;t diuer&#383;e things that can bee, feare, and ra&#383;hne&#383;&#383;e; ra&#383;hne&#383;&#383;e in the enterprize, and feare of the &#383;ucce&#383;&#383;e. For, when we valew the places your H.H. &#383;u&#383;taine, we cannot but know their dignity greater, then to de&#383;cend to the reading of these trifles: and, while we name them trifles, we haue depriu'd our &#383;elves of the defence of our Dedication. But &#383;ince your L.L. have beene pleas'd to thinke the&#383;e trifles &#383;ome-thing, heeretofore; and have pro&#383;equuted both them, and their Authour liuing, with so much fauour: we hope, that (they out-living him, and he not having the fate, common with &#383;ome, to be exequutor to his owne writings) you will u&#383;e the like indulgence toward them, you have done unto their parent. There is a great difference, vvhether any Booke choo&#383;e his Patrones, or finde them: This hath done both. For, &#383;o much were your L.L. likings of the &#383;euerall parts, vvhen they were acted, as before they vvre published, the Volume ask'd to be yours. We haue but collected them, and done an office to the dead, to procure his Orphanes, Guardians; vvithout ambition either of &#383;elfe-profit, or fame: onely to keepe the memory of &#383;o worthy a Friend, &amp; Fellow alive, as was our <nameref>SHAKESPEARE</nameref>, by humble offer of his playes, to your most noble patronage. Wherein, as we have iu&#383;tly ob&#383;erved, no man to come neere your L.L. but vvith a kind of religious addre&#383;&#383;e; it hath bin the height of our care, who are the Pre&#383;enters, to make the pre&#383;ent worthy of your H.H. by the perfection. But, there we mu&#383;t al&#383;o craue our abilities to be con&#383;iderd, my Lords. We cannot go beyond our owne powers. Country hands reach foorth milke, creame, fruites, or what they have : and many Nations (we have heard) that had not gummes &amp; incen&#383;e, obtained their reque&#383;ts with a leauened Cake. It was no fault to approach their Gods, by what meanes they could: And the mo&#383;t, though meane&#383;t, of thins are made more precious, when they are dedicated to Temples. In that name therefore, we mo&#383;t humbly con&#383;ecrate to your H.H. the&#383;e remaines of your &#383;ervant Shakespeare; that what delight is in them, may be euer your L.L. the reputation his, &amp; the faults ours, if any be committed, by a payre &#383;o carefull to &#383;hew their gratitude both to the liuing, and the dead, as is</line>
<closing>Your Lord&#383;hippes mo&#383;t bounden,</closing>
<author>JOHN HEMINGE.<lb/>
HENRY CONDELL.</author>
</dedication>

<preface>
<flourish />
<salutation>To the great Variety of Readers.</salutation>
<line><dropcap type="floral">F</dropcap>rom the most able, to him that can but spell: There you are number'd. We had rather you were weighd. Especially, when the fate of all Bookes depends upon your capacities : and not of your heads alone, but of your purses. Well ! It is now publique, &amp; you wil stand for your priviledges wee know : to read, and censure. Do so, but buy it first. That doth best commend a Booke, the Stationer saies. Then, how odde soever your braines be, or your wisedomes, make your licence the same, and spare not. Judge your six-pen'orth, your shillings worth, your five shillings worth at a time, or higher, so you rise to the just rates, and welcome. But, whatever you do, Buy. Censure will not drive a Trade, or make the Jacke go. And though you be a Magistrate of wit, and sit on the Stage at Black-Friers, or the Cock-pit, to arraigne Playes dailie, know, these Playes have had their triall alreadie, and stood out all Appeales ; and do now come forth quitted rather by a Decree of Court, then any purchas'd Letters of commendation.</line>
<line>It had bene a thing, we confesse, worthie to have bene wished, that the Author himselfe had liv'd to have set forth, and overseen his owne writings ; But since it hath bin ordain'd otherwise, and he by death departed from that right, we pray you do not envie his Friends, the office of their care, and paine, to have collected &amp; publish'd them; and so to have publish'd them, as where (before) you were abus'd with diverse stolne, and surreptitious copies, maimed, and deformed by the frauds and stealthes of injurious impostors, that expos'd them : even those, are now offer'd to your view cur'd, and perfect of their limbes; and all the rest, absolute in their numbers, as he conceived the'. Who, as he was a happie imitator of Nature, was a most gentle expresser of it. His mind and hand went together: And what he thought, he uttered with that easinesse, that wee have scarse received from him a blot in his papers. But it is not our province, who onely gather his works, and give them you, to praise him. It is yours that reade him. And there we hope, to your divers capacities, you will finde enough, both to draw, and hold you : for his wit can no more lie hid, then it could be lost. Reade him, therefore; and againe, and againe : And if then you doe not like him, surely you are in some manifest danger, not to understand him. And so we leave you to other of his Friends, whom if you need, can bee your guides : if you neede them not, you can leade your selves, and others. And such Readers we wish him.</line>
<author>John Heminge.<lb/>
Henrie Condell.</author>
</preface>

<eulogy author="johnson">
<flourish />
<title>To the memory of my beloued,<lb/>
The AVTHOR</title>
<subtitle>Mr. William Shakespeare<lb/>
And<lb/>
what he hath left vs.</subtitle>

<body>
<line><dropcap type="floral">T</dropcap>o draw no envy <nameref>(Shake&#383;peare)</nameref> on thy name,</line>
<line offset="2">Am I thus ample to thy Booke, and Fame;</line>
<line>While I confesse thy writings to be such,</line>
<line offset="2">As neither Man, nor Muse, can praise too much.</line>
<line>'Tis true, and all men's suffrage. But these wayes</line>
<line offset="2">Were not the paths I meant unto thy praise;</line>
<line>For seeliest Ignorance on these may light,</line>
<line offset="2">Which, when it sounds at best, but eccho's right;</line>
<line>Or blinde Affection, which doth ne're advance</line>
<line offset="2">The truth, but gropes, and urgeth all by chance;</line>
<line>Or crafty Malice, might pretend this praise,</line>
<line offset="2">And thine to ruine, where it seem'd to raise.</line>
<line>These are, as some infamous Baud, or Whore,</line>
<line offset="2">Should praise a Matron. What could hurt her more?</line>
<line>But thou art proofe against them, and indeed</line>
<line offset="2">Above th' ill fortune of them, or the need.</line>
<line>I, therefore will begin. Soule of the Age !</line>
<line offset="2">The applause ! delight ! the wonder of our Stage !</line>
<line>My <nameref>Shakespeare</nameref>, rise; I will not lodge thee by</line>
<line offset="2"><nameref>Chaucer</nameref>, or <nameref>Spenser</nameref>, or bid <nameref>Beaumont</nameref> lye</line>
<line>A little further, to make thee a roome :</line>
<line offset="2">Thou art a Moniment, without a tombe,</line>
<line>And art alive still, while thy Booke doth live,</line>
<line offset="2">And we have wits to read, and praise to give.</line>
<line>That I not mixe thee so, my braine excuses ;</line>
<line offset="2">I meane with great, but disproportion'd Muses :</line>
<line>For, if I thought my judgement were of yeeres,</line>
<line offset="2">I should commit thee surely with thy peeres,</line>
<line>And tell, how farre thou dist our Lily out-shine,</line>
<line offset="2">Or sporting <nameref>Kid</nameref> or <nameref>Marlowes</nameref> mighty line.</line>
<line>And though thou hadst small Latine, and lesse Greeke,</line>
<line offset="2">From thence to honour thee, I would not seeke</line>
<line>For names; but call forth thund'ring <nameref>schilus</nameref>,</line>
<line offset="2"><nameref>Euripides</nameref>, and <nameref>Sophocles</nameref> to vs,</line>
<line><nameref>Paccuvius</nameref>, <nameref>Accius</nameref>, him of <nameref>Cordoua</nameref> dead,</line>
<line offset="2">To life againe, to heare thy Buskin tread,</line>
<line>And shake a stage : Or, when thy sockes were on,</line>
<line offset="2">Leave thee alone, for the comparison</line>
<line>Of all, that insolent Greece, or haughtie Rome</line>
<line offset="2">Sent forth, or since did from their ashes come.</line>
<line>Triumph, my Britaine, thou hast one to showe,</line>
<line offset="2">To whom all scenes of Europe homage owe.</line>
<line>He was not of an age, but for all time !</line>
<line offset="2">And all the Muses still were in their prime,</line>
<line>When like Apollo he came forth to warme</line>
<line offset="2">Our eares, or like a Mercury to charme !</line>
<line>Nature her selfe was proud of his designes,</line>
<line offset="2">And joy'd to weare the dressing of his lines !</line>
<line>Which were so richly spun, and woven so fit,</line>
<line offset="2">As, since, she will vouchsafe no other Wit.</line>
<line>The merry Greeke, tart Aristophanes,</line>
<line offset="2">Neat Terence, witty Plautus, now not</line>
<line>please;But antiquated, and deserted lye</line>
<line offset="2">As they were not of Natures family.</line>
<line>Yet must I not give Nature all: Thy Art,</line>
<line offset="2">My gentle Shakespeare, must enjoy a part;</line>
<line>For though the Poets matter, Nature be,</line>
<line offset="2">His Art doth give the fashion. And, that he,</line>
<line>Who casts to write a living line, must sweat,</line>
<line offset="2">(Such as thine are) and strike the second heat</line>
<line>Upon the Muses anvile : turne the same,</line>
<line offset="2">(And himselfe with it) that he thinkes to frame;</line>
<line>Or for the lawrell, he may gaine a scorne,</line>
<line offset="2">For a good Poet's made, as well as borne.</line>
<line>And such wert thou. Looke how the fathers face</line>
<line offset="2">Lives in his issue, even so, the race</line>
<line>Of Shakespeares minde, and manners brightly shines</line>
<line offset="2">In his well toned, and true-filed lines :</line>
<line>In each of which, he seemes to shake a Lance,</line>
<line offset="2">As brandish't at the eyes of Ignorance.</line>
<line>Sweet swan of Avon! what a fight it were</line>
<line offset="2">To see thee in our waters yet appeare,</line>
<line>And make those flights upon the bankes of Thames,</line>
<line offset="2">That so did take Eliza, and our James !</line>
<line>But stay, I see thee in the Hemisphere</line>
<line offset="2">Advanc'd, and made a Constellation there !</line>
<line>Shine forth, thou Starre of Poets, and with rage,</line>
<line offset="2">Or influence, chide, or cheere the drooping Stage;</line>
<line>Which, since thy flight fro' hence, hath mourn'd like night,</line>
<line offset="2">And despaires day, but for thy Volumes light.</line>
</body>
<author>Ben: Ionson</author>
</eulogy>

<eulogy author="holland">
<flourish />
<title>Vpon the Lines and Life of the Famous</title>
<subtitle>Scenicke Poet, Master W I L L I A M<lb/>
S H A K E S P E A R E</subtitle>
<body>
<line><dropcap type="floral">T</dropcap>hose hands, which you so clapt, go now, and wring</line>
<line>You Britaines brave; for done are Shakespeares dayes :</line>
<line>His dayes are done, that made the dainty Playes,</line>
<line>Which made the Globe of heav'n and earth to ring.</line>
<line>Dry'de is that veine, dry'd is the Thespian Spring,</line>
<line>Turn'd all to teares, and Phoebus clouds his rayes :</line>
<line>That corp's, that coffin now besticke those bayes,</line>
<line>Which crown'd him Poet first, then Poets King.</line>
<line>If Tragedies might any Prologue have,</line>
<line>All those he made, would scarse make a one to this :</line>
<line>Where Fame, now that he gone is to the grave</line>
<line>(Deaths publique tyring-house) the Nuncius is,</line>
<line offset="2">For though his line of life went soone about,</line>
<line offset="2">The life yet of his lines shall never out.</line>
</body>
<author>HVGH HOLLAND.</author>
</eulogy>

<eulogy author="digges">
<flourish />
<title>TO THE MEMORIE</title>
<subtitle>of the deceased Authour Maister<lb/>
W. Shakespeare.</subtitle>
<body>
<line><dropcap type="floral">S</dropcap>hake-speare, at length thy pious fellowes give</line>
<line>The world thy Workes : thy Workes, by which, out-live</line>
<line>Thy Tombe, thy name must when that stone is rent,</line>
<line>And Time dissolves thy Stratford Moniment,</line>
<line>Here we alive shall view thee still. This Booke,</line>
<line>When Brasse and Marble fade, shall make thee looke</line>
<line>Fresh to all Ages: when Posteritie</line>
<line>Shall loath what's new, thinke all is prodegie</line>
<line>That is not Shake-speares; ev'ry Line, each Verse</line>
<line>Here shall revive, redeeme thee from thy Herse.</line>
<line>Nor Fire, nor cankring Age, as Naso said,</line>
<line>Of his, thy wit-fraught Booke shall once invade.</line>
<line>Nor shall I e're beleeve, or thinke thee dead.</line>
<line>(Though mist) untill our bankrout Stage be sped</line>
<line>(Imposible) with some new straine t'out-do</line>
<line>Passions of Juliet, and her Romeo ;</line>
<line>Or till I heare a Scene more nobly take,</line>
<line>Then when thy half-Sword parlying Romans spake.</line>
<line>Till these, till any of thy Volumes rest</line>
<line>Shall with more fire, more feeling be exprest,</line>
<line>Be sure, our Shake-speare, thou canst never dye,</line>
<line>But crown'd with Lawrell, live eternally.</line>
</body>
<author>L. Digges.</author>
</eulogy>

<eulogy author="mabbe">
<subtitle>To the memorie of M.W.Shakes-speare.</subtitle>
<body>
<line><dropcap type="floral">W</dropcap>EE wondred (Shake-speare) that thou went'st so soone</line>
<line>From the Worlds-Stage, to the Graves-Tyring-roome.</line>
<line>Wee thought thee dead, but this thy printed worth,</line>
<line>Tels thy Spectators, that thou went'st but forth</line>
<line>To enter with applause. An Actors Art,</line>
<line>Can dye, and live, to acte a second part.</line>
<line>That's but an Exit of Mortalitie;</line>
<line>This, a Re-entrance to a Plaudite.</line>
</body>
<author>I. M.</author>
</eulogy>


<companyactors>
<title>The Workes of William Shakespeare,</title>
<subtitle>containing all his Comedies, Histories, and<lb/>
Tragedies: Truely set forth, according to their first<lb/>
O R I G I N A L L.</subtitle>

<subtitle>The Names of the Principall Actors<lb/>
in all these Playes.</subtitle>
<body>
<actorname>William Shakespeare.</actorname>
<actorname>Richard Burbadge.</actorname>
<actorname>John Hemmings.</actorname>
<actorname>Augustine Phillips.</actorname>
<actorname>William Kempt.</actorname>
<actorname>Thomas Poope.</actorname>
<actorname>George Bryan.</actorname>
<actorname>Henry Condell.</actorname>
<actorname>William Slye.</actorname>
<actorname>Richard Cowly.</actorname>
<actorname>John Lowine.</actorname>
<actorname>Samuell Crosse.</actorname>
<actorname>Alexander Cooke.</actorname>
<actorname>Samuel Gilburne.</actorname>
<actorname>Robert Armin.</actorname>
<actorname>William Ostler.</actorname>
<actorname>Nathan Field.</actorname>
<actorname>John Underwood.</actorname>
<actorname>Nicholas Tooley.</actorname>
<actorname>William Ecclestone.</actorname>
<actorname>Joseph Taylor.</actorname>
<actorname>Robert Benfield.</actorname>
<actorname>Robert Goughe.</actorname>
<actorname>Richard Robinson.</actorname>
<actorname>John Shancke.</actorname>
<actorname>John Rice.</actorname>
</body>
</companyactors>

<toc>
<flourish />
<title>A CATALOGVE</title>
<subtitle>of the &#383;euerall Comedies, Hi&#383;tories, and Tra-<lb/>gedies contained in this Volume.</subtitle>

<toclist>
<genre type="comedies">
<genretitle>COMEDIES.</genretitle>
<playname foliopage="Folio 1." order="first"><dropcap type="floral">T</dropcap>He Tempe&#383;t.</playname>
<playname foliopage="20" order="second">The two Gentlemen of Verona.</playname>
<playname foliopage="38">The Merry Wiues of Wind&#383;or.</playname>
<playname foliopage="61">Mea&#383;ure for Mea&#383;ure.</playname>
<playname foliopage="85">The Comedy of Errours.</playname>
<playname foliopage="101">Much adoo about Nothing</playname>
<playname foliopage="122">Loves Labour lost.</playname>
<playname foliopage="145">Midsommer Nights Dreame.</playname>
<playname foliopage="163">The Merchant of Venice.</playname>
<playname foliopage="185">As you Like it.</playname>
<playname foliopage="208">The Taming of the Shrew.</playname>
<playname foliopage="230">All is well, that Ends well.</playname>
<playname foliopage="255">Twelfe-Night, or what you will.</playname>
<playname foliopage="304">The Winters Tale.</playname>
</genre>

<genre type="histories">
<genretitle>HISTORIES.</genretitle>
<playname foliopage="Fol. 1.">The Life and Death of King John.</playname>
<playname foliopage="23">The Life &#38; death of Richard the &#383;econd.</playname>
<playname foliopage="46">The Fir&#383;t part of King Henry the fourth.</playname>
<playname foliopage="74">The Second part of K. Henry the fourth.</playname>
<playname foliopage="69">The Life of King Henry the Fift.</playname>
<playname foliopage="96">The Fir&#383;t part of King Henry the Sixt.</playname>
<playname foliopage="120">The Second part of King Hen. the Sixt.</playname>
<playname foliopage="147">The Third part of King Henry the Sixt.</playname>
<playname foliopage="173">The Life &#38; Death of Richard the Third</playname>
<playname foliopage="205">The Life of King Henry the Eight.</playname>
</genre>

<genre type="tragedies">
<genretitle>TRAGEDIES.</genretitle>
<playname foliopage="Fol. 1.">The Tragedy of Coriolanus.</playname>
<playname foliopage="31">Titus Andronicus.</playname>
<playname foliopage="53">Romeo and Juliet.</playname>
<playname foliopage="80">Timon of Athens.</playname>
<playname foliopage="109">The Life and death of Julius Ca&#383;ar.</playname>
<playname foliopage="131">The Tragedy of Macbeth.</playname>
<playname foliopage="152">The Tragedy of Hamlet.</playname>
<playname foliopage="283">King Lear.</playname>
<playname foliopage="310">Othello, the Moore of Venice.</playname>
<playname foliopage="346">Anthony and Cleopater.</playname>
<playname foliopage="369">Cymbeline King of Britaine.</playname>
</genre>
</toclist>

</toc>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2016 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>1.0</version>
<license>GFDL License 1.3</license>
<licenseurl>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</licenseurl>
<termsurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com/license</termsurl>
</sourcedetails>

</frontmatter>
