<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<poem unique="funeral-elegy">
<title short="A Funeral Elegy">A Funeral Elegy for Master William Peter</title>
<playwright>by W.S.</playwright>

<poemintro>
<dedication>
<line>TO MASTER JOHN PETER</line>
<line>of Bowhay in Devon, Esquire.</line>
<line>The love I bore to your brother, and will do to his memory, hath crav'd from me this last duty of a friend; I am herein but a second to the privilege of Truth, who can warrant more in his behalf than I undertook to deliver.Exercise in this kind I will little affect, and am less addicted to, but there must be miracle in that labor which, to witness my remembrance to this departed gentleman, I would not willingly undergo.  Yet whatsoever is here done, is done to him, and to him only. For whom and whose sake I will not forget to remember any friendly respects to you, or to any of those that have lov'd him for himself, and himself for his deserts. </line>
<dedauthor>W. S.</dedauthor>
</dedication>
</poemintro>

<poembody>

<subtitle>A FUNERAL ELEGY</subtitle>

<stanza>
<line>Since Time, and his predestinated end,</line>
<line>Abridg'd the circuit of his hopeful days,</line>
<line>Whiles both his Youth and Virtue did intend</line>
<line>The good endeavors of deserving praise,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>What memorable monument can last</line>
<line>Whereon to build his never-blemish'd name</line>
<line>But his own worth, wherein his life was grac'd-</line>
<line>Sith as [that] ever he maintain'd the same?</line>
<line>Oblivion in the darkest day to come,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>When sin shall tread on merit in the dust,</line>
<line>Cannot rase out the lamentable tomb</line>
<line>Of his short-liv'd deserts; but still they must,</line>
<line>Even in the hearts and memories of men,</line>
<line>Claim fit Respect, that they, in every limb</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Rememb'ring what he was, with comfort then</line>
<line>May pattern out one truly good, by him.</line>
<line>For he was truly good, if honest care</line>
<line>Of harmless conversation may commend</line>
<line>A life free from such stains as follies are,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Ill recompensed only in his end.</line>
<line>Nor can the tongue of him who lov'd him least</line>
<line>(If there can be minority of love</line>
<line>To one superlative above the rest</line>
<line>Of many men in steady faith) reprove</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>His constant temper, in the equal weight</line>
<line>Of thankfulness and kindness: Truth doth leave</line>
<line>Sufficient proof, he was in every right</line>
<line>As kind to give, as thankful to receive.</line>
<line>The curious eye of a quick-brain'd survey</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Could scantly find a mote amidst the sun</line>
<line>Of his too-short'ned days, or make a prey</line>
<line>Of any faulty errors he had done-</line>
<line>Not that he was above the spleenful sense</line>
<line>And spite of malice, but for that he had</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Warrant enough in his own innocence</line>
<line>Against the sting of some in nature bad.</line>
<line>Yet who is he so absolutely blest</line>
<line>That lives encompass'd in a mortal frame,</line>
<line>Sometime in reputation not oppress'd</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>By some in nothing famous but defame?</line>
<line>Such in the By-path and the Ridgeway lurk</line>
<line>That leads to ruin, in a smooth pretense</line>
<line>Of what they do to be a special work</line>
<line>Of singleness, not tending to offense;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whose very virtues are, not to detract</line>
<line>Whiles hope remains of gain (base fee of slaves),</line>
<line>Despising chiefly men in fortunes wrack'd-</line>
<line>But death to such gives unrememb'red graves.</line>
<line>Now therein liv'd he happy, if to be</line>
<line>Free from detraction happiness it be.</line>
<line>His younger years gave comfortable hope</line>
<line>To hope for comfort in his riper youth,</line>
<line>Which, harvest-like, did yield again the crop</line>
<line>Of Education, better'd in his truth.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Those noble twins of heaven-infused races,</line>
<line>Learning and Wit, refined in their kind</line>
<line>Did jointly both, in their peculiar graces,</line>
<line>Enrich the curious temple of his mind;</line>
<line>Indeed a temple, in whose precious white</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Sat Reason by Religion oversway'd,</line>
<line>Teaching his other senses, with delight,</line>
<line>How Piety and Zeal should be obey'd-</line>
<line>Not fruitlessly in prodigal expense</line>
<line>Wasting his best of time, but so content</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>With Reason's golden Mean to make defense</line>
<line>Against the assault of youth's encouragement;</line>
<line>As not the tide of this surrounding age</line>
<line>(When now his father's death had freed his will)</line>
<line>Could make him subject to the drunken rage</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Of such whose only glory is their ill.</line>
<line>He from the happy knowledge of the wise</line>
<line>Draws virtue to reprove secured fools</line>
<line>And shuns the glad sleights of ensnaring vice</line>
<line>To spend his spring of days in sacred schools.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Here gave he diet to the sick desires</line>
<line>That day by day assault the weaker man,</line>
<line>And with fit moderation still retires</line>
<line>From what doth batter virtue now and then.</line>
<line>But that I not intend in full discourse</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>To progress out his life, I could display</line>
<line>A good man in each part exact and force</line>
<line>The common voice to warrant what I say.</line>
<line>For if his fate and heaven had decreed</line>
<line>That full of days he might have liv'd to see</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>The grave in peace, the times that should succeed</line>
<line>Had been best-speaking witnesses with me;</line>
<line>Whose conversation so untouch'd did move</line>
<line>Respect most in itself, as who would scan</line>
<line>His honesty and worth, by them might prove</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>He was a kind, true, perfect gentleman-</line>
<line>Not in the outside of disgraceful folly,</line>
<line>Courting opinion with unfit disguise,</line>
<line>Affecting fashions, nor addicted wholly</line>
<line>To unbeseeming blushless vanities,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>But suiting so his habit and desire</line>
<line>As that his Virtue was his best Attire.</line>
<line>Not in the waste of many idle words</line>
<line>Car'd he to be heard talk, nor in the float</line>
<line>Of fond conceit, such as this age affords,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>By vain discourse upon himself to dote;</line>
<line>For his becoming silence gave such grace</line>
<line>To his judicious parts, as what he spake</line>
<line>Seem'd rather answers which the wise embrace</line>
<line>Than busy questions such as talkers make.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>And though his qualities might well deserve</line>
<line>Just commendation, yet his furnish'd mind</line>
<line>Such harmony of goodness did preserve</line>
<line>As nature never built in better kind;</line>
<line>Knowing the best, and therefore not presuming</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>In knowing, but for that it was the best,</line>
<line>Ever within himself free choice resuming</line>
<line>Of true perfection, in a perfect breast;</line>
<line>So that his mind and body made an inn,</line>
<line>The one to lodge the other, both like fram'd</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For fair conditions, guests that soonest win</line>
<line>Applause; in generality, well fam'd,</line>
<line>If trim behavior, gestures mild, discreet</line>
<line>Endeavors, modest speech, beseeming mirth,</line>
<line>True friendship, active grace, persuasion sweet,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Delightful love innated from his birth,</line>
<line>Acquaintance unfamiliar, carriage just,</line>
<line>Offenseless resolution, wish'd sobriety,</line>
<line>Clean-temper'd moderation, steady trust,</line>
<line>Unburthen'd conscience, unfeign'd piety;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>If these, or all of these, knit fast in one</line>
<line>Can merit praise, then justly may we say,</line>
<line>Not any from this frailer stage is gone</line>
<line>Whose name is like to live a longer day-</line>
<line>Though not in eminent courts or places great</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For popular concourse, yet in that soil</line>
<line>Where he enjoy'd his birth, life, death, and seat</line>
<line>Which now sits mourning his untimely spoil.</line>
<line>And as much glory is it to be good</line>
<line>For private persons, in their private home,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>As those descended from illustrious blood</line>
<line>In public view of greatness, whence they come.</line>
<line>Though I, rewarded with some sadder taste</line>
<line>Of knowing shame, by feeling it have prov'd</line>
<line>My country's thankless misconstruction cast</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Upon my name and credit, both unlov'd</line>
<line>By some whose fortunes, sunk into the wane</line>
<line>Of plenty and desert, have strove to win</line>
<line>Justice by wrong, and sifted to embane</line>
<line>My reputation with a witless sin;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Yet time, the father of unblushing truth,</line>
<line>May one day lay ope malice which hath cross'd it,</line>
<line>And right the hopes of my endangered youth,</line>
<line>Purchasing credit in the place I lost it.</line>
<line>Even in which place the subject of the verse</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>(Unhappy matter of a mourning style</line>
<line>Which now that subject's merits doth rehearse)</line>
<line>Had education and new being; while</line>
<line>By fair demeanor he had won repute</line>
<line>Amongst the all of all that lived there,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For that his actions did so wholly suit</line>
<line>With worthiness, still memorable here.</line>
<line>The many hours till the day of doom</line>
<line>Will not consume his life and hapless end,</line>
<line>For should he lie obscur'd without a tomb,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Time would to time his honesty commend;</line>
<line>Whiles parents to their children will make known,</line>
<line>And they to their posterity impart,</line>
<line>How such a man was sadly overthrown</line>
<line>By a hand guided by a cruel heart,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whereof as many as shall hear that sadness</line>
<line>Will blame the one's hard fate, the other's madness;</line>
<line>Whiles such as do recount that tale of woe,</line>
<line>Told by remembrance of the wisest heads,</line>
<line>Will in the end conclude the matter so,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>As they will all go weeping to their beds.</line>
<line>For when the world lies winter'd in the storms</line>
<line>Of fearful consummation, and lays down</line>
<line>Th' unsteady change of his fantastic forms,</line>
<line>Expecting ever to be overthrown;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>When the proud height of much affected sin</line>
<line>Shall ripen to a head, and in that pride</line>
<line>End in the miseries it did begin</line>
<line>And fall amidst the glory of his tide;</line>
<line>Then in a book where every work is writ</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Shall this man's actions be reveal'd, to show</line>
<line>The gainful fruit of well-employed wit,</line>
<line>Which paid to heaven the debt that it did owe.</line>
<line>Here shall be reckon'd up the constant faith,</line>
<line>Never untrue, where once he love profess'd;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Which is a miracle in men, one saith,</line>
<line>Long sought though rarely found, and he is best</line>
<line>Who can make friendship, in those times of change,</line>
<line>Admired more for being firm than strange.</line>
<line>When those weak houses of our brittle flesh</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Shall ruin'd be by death, our grace and strength,</line>
<line>Youth, memory and shape that made us fresh</line>
<line>Cast down, and utterly decay'd at length;</line>
<line>When all shall turn to dust from whence we came</line>
<line>And we low-level'd in a narrow grave,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>What can we leave behind us but a name,</line>
<line>Which, by a life well led, may honor have?</line>
<line>Such honor, O thou youth untimely lost,</line>
<line>Thou didst deserve and hast; for though thy soul</line>
<line>Hath took her flight to a diviner coast,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Yet here on earth thy fame lives ever whole,</line>
<line>In every heart seal'd up, in every tongue</line>
<line>Fit matter to discourse, no day prevented</line>
<line>That pities not thy sad and sudden wrong,</line>
<line>Of all alike beloved and lamented.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>And I here to thy memorable worth,</line>
<line>In this last act of friendship, sacrifice</line>
<line>My love to thee, which I could not set forth</line>
<line>In any other habit of disguise.</line>
<line>Although I could not learn, whiles yet thou wert,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>To speak the language of a servile breath,</line>
<line>My truth stole from my tongue into my heart,</line>
<line>Which shall not thence be sund'red, but in death.</line>
<line>And I confess my love was too remiss</line>
<line>That had not made thee know how much I priz'd thee,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>But that mine error was, as yet it is,</line>
<line>To think love best in silence: for I siz'd thee</line>
<line>By what I would have been, not only ready</line>
<line>In telling I was thine, but being so,</line>
<line>By some effect to show it.He is steady</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Who seems less than he is in open show.</line>
<line>Since then I still reserv'd to try the worst</line>
<line>Which hardest fate and time thus can lay on me.</line>
<line>T' enlarge my thoughts was hindered at first,</line>
<line>While thou hadst life; I took this task upon me,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>To register with mine unhappy pen</line>
<line>Such duties as it owes to thy desert,</line>
<line>And set thee as a president to men,</line>
<line>And limn thee to the world but as thou wert-</line>
<line>Not hir'd, as heaven can witness in my soul,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>By vain conceit, to please such ones as know it,</line>
<line>Nor servile to be lik'd, free from control,</line>
<line>Which, pain to many men, I do not owe it.</line>
<line>But here I trust I have discharged now</line>
<line>(Fair lovely branch too soon cut off) to thee,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>My constant and irrefragable vow,</line>
<line>As, had it chanc'd, thou mightst have done to me-</line>
<line>But that no merit strong enough of mine</line>
<line>Had yielded store to thy well-abled quill</line>
<line>Whereby t'enroll my name, as this of thine,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>How s'ere enriched by thy plenteous skill.</line>
<line>Here, then, I offer up to memory</line>
<line>The value of my talent, precious man,</line>
<line>Whereby if thou live to posterity,</line>
<line>Though't be not as I would, 'tis as I can:</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>In minds from whence endeavor doth proceed,</line>
<line>A ready will is taken for the deed.</line>
<line>Yet ere I take my longest last farewell</line>
<line>From thee, fair mark of sorrow, let me frame</line>
<line>Some ampler work of thank, wherein to tell</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>What more thou didst deserve than in thy name,</line>
<line>And free thee from the scandal of such senses</line>
<line>As in the rancor of unhappy spleen</line>
<line>Measure thy course of life, with false pretenses</line>
<line>Comparing by thy death what thou hast been.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>So in his mischiefs is the world accurs'd:</line>
<line>It picks out matter to inform the worst.</line>
<line>The willful blindness that hoodwinks the eyes</line>
<line>Of men enwrapped in an earthy veil</line>
<line>Makes them most ignorantly exercise</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>And yield to humor when it doth assail,</line>
<line>Whereby the candle and the body's light</line>
<line>Darkens the inward eyesight of the mind,</line>
<line>Presuming still it sees, even in the night</line>
<line>Of that same ignorance which makes them blind.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Hence conster they with corrupt commentaries,</line>
<line>Proceeding from a nature as corrupt,</line>
<line>The text of malice, which so often varies</line>
<line>As 'tis by seeming reason underpropp'd.</line>
<line>O, whither tends the lamentable spite</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Of this world's teenful apprehension,</line>
<line>Which understands all things amiss, whose light</line>
<line>Shines not amidst the dark of their dissension?</line>
<line>True 'tis, this man, whiles yet he was a man,</line>
<line>Sooth'd not the current of besotted fashion,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Nor could disgest, as some loose mimics can,</line>
<line>An empty sound of overweening passion,</line>
<line>So much to be made servant to the base</line>
<line>And sensual aptness of disunion'd vices,</line>
<line>To purchase commendation by disgrace,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whereto the world and heat of sin entices.</line>
<line>But in a safer contemplation,</line>
<line>Secure in what he knew, he ever chose</line>
<line>The ready way to commendation,</line>
<line>By shunning all invitements strange, of those</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whose illness is, the necessary praise</line>
<line>Must wait upon their actions; only rare</line>
<line>In being rare in shame (which strives to raise</line>
<line>Their name by doing what they do not care),</line>
<line>As if the free commission of their ill</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Were even as boundless as their prompt desires;</line>
<line>Only like lords, like subjects to their will,</line>
<line>Which their fond dotage ever more admires.</line>
<line>He was not so: but in a serious awe,</line>
<line>Ruling the little ordered commonwealth</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Of his own self, with honor to the law</line>
<line>That gave peace to his bread, bread to his health;</line>
<line>Which ever he maintain'd in sweet content</line>
<line>And pleasurable rest, wherein he joy'd</line>
<line>A monarchy of comfort's government,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Never until his last to be destroy'd.</line>
<line>For in the Vineyard of heaven-favored learning</line>
<line>Where he was double-honor'd in degree,</line>
<line>His observation and discreet discerning</line>
<line>Had taught him in both fortunes to be free;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whence now retir'd home, to a home indeed</line>
<line>The home of his condition and estate,</line>
<line>He well provided 'gainst the hand of need,</line>
<line>Whence young men sometime grow unfortunate;</line>
<line>His disposition, by the bonds of unity,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>So fast'ned to his reason that it strove</line>
<line>With understanding's grave immunity</line>
<line>To purchase from all hearts a steady love;</line>
<line>Wherein not any one thing comprehends</line>
<line>Proportionable note of what he was,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Than that he was so constant to his friends</line>
<line>As he would no occasion overpass</line>
<line>Which might make known his unaffected care,</line>
<line>In all respects of trial, to unlock</line>
<line>His bosom and his store, which did declare</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>That Christ was his, and he was Friendship's Rock:</line>
<line>A Rock of Friendship figured in his name,</line>
<line>Fore-shewing what he was, and what should be,</line>
<line>Most true presage; and he discharg'd the same</line>
<line>In every act of perfect amity-</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Though in the complemental phrase of words</line>
<line>He never was addicted to the vain</line>
<line>Of boast, such as the common breath affords;</line>
<line>He was in use most fast, in tongue most plain,</line>
<line>Nor amongst all those virtues that forever</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Adorn'd his reputation will be found</line>
<line>One greater than his Faith, which did persever,</line>
<line>Where once it was protested, alway sound.</line>
<line>Hence sprung the deadly fuel that reviv'd</line>
<line>The rage which wrought his end, for had he been</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Slacker in love, he had been longer liv'd</line>
<line>And not oppress'd by wrath's unhappy sin-</line>
<line>By wrath's unhappy sin, which unadvis'd</line>
<line>Gave death for free good will, and wounds for love.</line>
<line>Pity it was that blood had not been priz'd</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>At higher rate, and reason set above</line>
<line>Most unjust choler, which untimely Drew</line>
<line>Destruction on itself; and most unjust,</line>
<line>Robb'd virtue of a follower so true</line>
<line>As time can boast of, both for love and trust:</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>So henceforth all (great glory to his blood)</line>
<line>Shall be but seconds to him, being good.</line>
<line>The wicked end their honor with their sin</line>
<line>In death, which only then the good begin.</line>
<line>Lo, here a lesson by experience taught</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For men whose pure simplicity hath drawn</line>
<line>Their trust to be betray'd by being caught</line>
<line>Within the snares of making truth a pawn;</line>
<line>Whiles it, not doubting whereinto it enters,</line>
<line>Without true proof and knowledge of a friend,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Sincere in singleness of heart, adventers</line>
<line>To give fit cause, ere love begin to end:</line>
<line>His unfeign'd friendship where it least was sought,</line>
<line>Him to a fatal timeless ruin brought;</line>
<line>Whereby the life that purity adorn'd</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>With real merit, by this sudden end</line>
<line>Is in the mouth of some in manner scorn'd,</line>
<line>Made questionable, for they do intend,</line>
<line>According to the tenor of the saw</line>
<line>Mistook, if not observ'd (writ long ago</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>When men were only led by Reason's law),</line>
<line>That "Such as is the end, the life proves so."</line>
<line>Thus he, who to the universal lapse</line>
<line>Gave sweet redemption, off'ring up his blood</line>
<line>To conquer death by death, and loose the traps</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Of hell, even in the triumph that it stood:</line>
<line>He thus, for that his guiltless life was spilt</line>
<line>By death, which was made subject to the curse,</line>
<line>Might in like manner be reprov'd of guilt</line>
<line>In his pure life, for that his end was worse.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>But O far be it, our unholy lips</line>
<line>Should so profane the deity above</line>
<line>As thereby to ordain revenging whips</line>
<line>Against the day of Judgment and of Love.</line>
<line>The hand that lends us honor in our days</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>May shorten when it please, and justly take</line>
<line>Our honor from us many sundry ways,</line>
<line>As best becomes that wisdom did us make.</line>
<line>The second brother, who was next begot</line>
<line>Of all that ever were begotten yet,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Was by a hand in vengeance rude and hot</line>
<line>Sent innocent to be in heaven set-</line>
<line>Whose fame the angels in melodious choirs</line>
<line>Still witness to the world.Then why should he,</line>
<line>Well-profited in excellent desires,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Be more rebuk'd, who had like destiny?</line>
<line>Those saints before the everlasting throne</line>
<line>Who sit with crowns of glory on their heads,</line>
<line>Wash'd white in blood, from earth hence have not gone</line>
<line>All to their joys in quiet on their beds,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>But tasted of the sour-bitter scourge</line>
<line>Of torture and affliction ere they gained</line>
<line>Those blessings which their sufferance did urge,</line>
<line>Whereby the grace fore-promis'd they attained.</line>
<line>Let then the false suggestions of the froward,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Building large castles in the empty air,</line>
<line>By suppositions fond and thoughts untoward</line>
<line>(Issues of discontent and sick despair)</line>
<line>Rebound gross arguments upon their heart</line>
<line>That may disprove their malice, and confound</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Uncivil loose opinions which insert</line>
<line>Their souls into the roll that doth unsound</line>
<line>Betraying policies, and show their brains,</line>
<line>Unto their shame, ridiculous; whose scope</line>
<line>Is envy, whose endeavors fruitless pains,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>In nothing surely prosperous, but hope-</line>
<line>And that same hope, so lame, so unprevailing,</line>
<line>It buries self-conceit in weak opinion;</line>
<line>Which being cross'd, gives matter of bewailing</line>
<line>Their vain designs, on whom want hath dominion.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Such, and of such condition, may devise</line>
<line>Which way to wound with defamation's spirit</line>
<line>(Close-lurking whisper's hidden forgeries)</line>
<line>His taintless goodness, his desertful merit.</line>
<line>But whiles the minds of men can judge sincerely,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Upon assured knowledge, his repute</line>
<line>And estimation shall be rumor'd clearly</line>
<line>In equal worth--time shall to time renew 't.</line>
<line>The Grave-that in his ever-empty womb</line>
<line>Forever closes up the unrespected</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Who, when they die, die all-shall not entomb</line>
<line>His pleading best perfections as neglected.</line>
<line>They to his notice in succeeding years</line>
<line>Shall speak for him when he shall lie below;</line>
<line>When nothing but his memory appears</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Of what he was, then shall his virtues grow.</line>
<line>His being but a private man in rank</line>
<line>(And yet not rank'd beneath a gentleman)</line>
<line>Shall not abridge the commendable thank</line>
<line>Which wise posterity shall give him then;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For Nature, and his therein happy Fate.</line>
<line>Ordain'd that by his quality of mind</line>
<line>T' ennoble that best part, although his state</line>
<line>Were to a lower blessedness confin'd.</line>
<line>Blood, pomp, state, honor, glory and command,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Without fit ornaments of disposition,</line>
<line>Are in themselves but heathenish and [profaned],</line>
<line>And much more peaceful is a mean condition</line>
<line>Which, underneath the roof of safe content,</line>
<line>Feeds on the bread of rest, and takes delight</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>To look upon the labors it hath spent</line>
<line>For its own sustenance, both day and night;</line>
<line>Whiles others, plotting which way to be great,</line>
<line>How to augment their portion and ambition,</line>
<line>Do toil their giddy brains, and ever sweat</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For popular applause and power's commission.</line>
<line>But one in honors, like a seeled dove</line>
<line>Whose inward eyes are dimm'd with dignity,</line>
<line>Does think most safety doth remain above,</line>
<line>And seeks to be secure by mounting high:</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Whence, when he falls, who did erewhile aspire,</line>
<line>Falls deeper down, for that he climbed higher.</line>
<line>Now men who in a lower region live</line>
<line>Exempt from danger of authority</line>
<line>Have fittest times in Reason's rules to thrive,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Not vex'd with envy of priority,</line>
<line>And those are much more noble in the mind</line>
<line>Than many that have nobleness by kind.</line>
<line>Birth, blood, and ancestors, are none of ours,</line>
<line>Nor can we make a proper challenge to them,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>But virtues and perfections in our powers</line>
<line>Proceed most truly from us, if we do them.</line>
<line>Respective titles or a gracious style,</line>
<line>With all what men in eminence possess,</line>
<line>Are, without ornaments to praise them, vile:</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>The beauty of the mind is nobleness.</line>
<line>And such as have that beauty, well deserve</line>
<line>Eternal characters, that after death</line>
<line>Remembrance of their worth we may preserve,</line>
<line>So that their glory die not with their breath.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Else what avails it in a goodly strife</line>
<line>Upon this face of earth here to contend,</line>
<line>The good t'exceed the wicked in their life,</line>
<line>Should both be like obscured in their end?</line>
<line>Until which end, there is none rightly can</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Be termed happy, since the happiness</line>
<line>Depends upon the goodness of the man,</line>
<line>Which afterwards his praises will express.</line>
<line>Look hither then, you that enjoy the youth</line>
<line>Of your best days, and see how unexpected</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Death can betray your jollity to ruth</line>
<line>When death you think is least to be respected!</line>
<line>The person of this model here set out</line>
<line>Had all that youth and happy days could give him,</line>
<line>Yet could not all-encompass him about</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Against th'assault of death, who to relieve him</line>
<line>Strook home but to the frail and mortal parts</line>
<line>Of his humanity, but could not touch</line>
<line>His flourishing and fair long-liv'd deserts,</line>
<line>Above fate's reach, his singleness was such-</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>So that he dies but once, but doubly lives,</line>
<line>Once in his proper self, then in his name;</line>
<line>Predestinated Time, who all deprives,</line>
<line>Could never yet deprive him of the same.</line>
<line>And had the Genius which attended on him</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Been possibilited to keep him safe</line>
<line>Against the rigor that hath overgone him,</line>
<line>He had been to the public use a staff,</line>
<line>Leading by his example in the path</line>
<line>Which guides to doing well, wherein so few</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>The proneness of this age to error hath</line>
<line>Informed rightly in the courses true.</line>
<line>As then the loss of one, whose inclination</line>
<line>Strove to win love in general, is sad,</line>
<line>So specially his friends, in soft compassion</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Do feel the greatest loss they could have had.</line>
<line>Amongst them all, she who those nine of years</line>
<line>Liv'd fellow to his counsels and his bed</line>
<line>Hath the most share in loss:for I in hers</line>
<line>Feel what distemperature this chance hath bred.</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>The chaste embracements of conjugal love,</line>
<line>Who in a mutual harmony consent,</line>
<line>Are so impatient of a strange remove</line>
<line>As meager death itself seems to lament,</line>
<line>And weep upon those cheeks which nature fram'd</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>To be delightful orbs in whom the force</line>
<line>Of lively sweetness plays, so that asham'd</line>
<line>Death often pities his unkind divorce.</line>
<line>Such was the separation here constrain'd</line>
<line>(Well-worthy to be termed a rudeness rather),</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>For in his life his love was so unfeign'd</line>
<line>As he was both an husband and a father-</line>
<line>The one in firm affection and the other</line>
<line>In careful providence, which ever strove</line>
<line>With joint assistance to grace one another</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>With every helpful furtherance of love.</line>
<line>But since the sum of all that can be said</line>
<line>Can be but said that "He was good" (which wholly</line>
<line>Includes all excellence can be display'd</line>
<line>In praise of virtue and reproach of folly).</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>His due deserts, this sentence on him gives,</line>
<line>"He died in life, yet in his death he lives."</line>
<line>Now runs the method of this doleful song</line>
<line>In accents brief to thee, O thou deceas'd!</line>
<line>To whom those pains do only all belong</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>As witnesses I did not love thee least.</line>
<line>For could my worthless brain find out but how</line>
<line>To raise thee from the sepulcher of dust,</line>
<line>Undoubtedly thou shouldst have partage now</line>
<line>Of life with me, and heaven be counted just</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>If to a supplicating soul it would</line>
<line>Give life anew, by giving life again</line>
<line>Where life is miss'd; whereby discomfort should</line>
<line>Right his old griefs, and former joys retain</line>
<line>Which now with thee are leap'd into thy tomb</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>And buried in that hollow vault of woe,</line>
<line>Expecting yet a more severer doom</line>
<line>Than time's strict flinty hand will let 'em know.</line>
<line>And now if I have level'd mine account</line>
<line>And reckon'd up in a true measured score</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Those perfect graces which were ever wont</line>
<line>To wait on thee alive, I ask no more</line>
<line>(But shall hereafter in a poor content</line>
<line>Immure those imputations I sustain,</line>
<line>Learning my days of youth so to prevent</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>As not to be cast down by them again)-</line>
<line>Only those hopes which fate denies to grant</line>
<line>In full possession to a captive heart</line>
<line>Who, if it were in plenty, still would want</line>
<line>Before it may enjoy his better part;</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>From which detain'd, and banish'd in th' exile</line>
<line>Of dim misfortune, has none other prop</line>
<line>Whereon to lean and rest itself the while</line>
<line>But the weak comfort of the hapless, Hope.</line>
<line>And Hope must in despite of fearful change</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Play in the strongest closet of my breast,</line>
<line>Although perhaps I ignorantly range</line>
<line>And court opinion in my deep'st unrest.</line>
<line>But whether doth the stream of my mischance</line>
<line>Drive me beyond myself, fast friend, soon lost,</line>
</stanza>

<stanza>
<line>Long may thy worthiness thy name advance</line>
<line>Amongst the virtuous and deserving most,</line>
<line>Who herein hast forever happy prov'd:</line>
<line>In life thou liv'dst, in death thou died'st belov'd.</line>
</stanza>

<finistitle>FINIS.</finistitle>

</poembody>

<sourcedetails>
<source>PlayShakespeare.com</source>
<sourceurl>http://www.playshakespeare.com</sourceurl>
<copyright>2005-2013 by PlayShakespeare.com</copyright>
<version>3.3</version>
<license>This document is strictly copyrighted and may not be copied, altered, or distributed.</license>
</sourcedetails>

</poem>