<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="plays.xsl"?>

<PLAY>
<TITLE>King Leir: The true Chronical History of King Leir and his three daughters, Gonorill, Ragan and Cordella</TITLE>
<TITLESHORT>King Leir</TITLESHORT>
<PLAYWRIGHT>Unknown</PLAYWRIGHT>

<PERSONAE>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">King Leir, King of Britain Brittany.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Skalliger, Perillus, King Leir's counsellors.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">The Gallian King, King of France, husband of Cordella.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Mumford, the Gallian King's attendant.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">The King of Cornwall, husband of Gonorill.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Morgan, King of Cambria, husband of Ragan.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Servant to the King of Cornwall.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Servant to the King of Cambria.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Messenger &#91;or Murtherer&#93;, in the service of Gonorill.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Ambassador from Gallia to Britain.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">First Mariner.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Second Mariner.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Captain of the Watch.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">First Watchman.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Second Watchman.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">First British Captain.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Second British Captain.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">The mayor of a British town.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Gonorill, eldest daughter of King Leir, wife of the king of Cornwall.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Ragan, second daughter of King Leir, wife of the king of Cambria.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Cordella, youngest daughter of King Leir, wife of the Gallian king.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA short="XXX.">Nobles at Leir's court; nobles of Gallia; attendants on the king of Cornwall; nobles of the prince of Cambria; Gallian soldiers; soldiers of Cornwall and Cambria.</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Actus I</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene I</SCENETITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter King Leir and Nobles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus to our grief the obsequies performed</LINE>
<LINE>Of our (too late) deceased and dearest queen,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose soul I hope, possessed of heavenly joys,</LINE>
<LINE>Doth ride in triumph amongst the cherubins;</LINE>
<LINE>Let us request your grave advice, my lords,</LINE>
<LINE>For the disposing of our princely daughters,</LINE>
<LINE>For whom our care is specially employed,</LINE>
<LINE>As nature bindeth to advance their states,</LINE>
<LINE>In royal marriage with some princely mates:</LINE>
<LINE>For wanting now their mother's good advice,</LINE>
<LINE>Under whose government they have received</LINE>
<LINE>A perfect pattern of a virtuous life:</LINE>
<LINE>Left as it were a ship without a stern,</LINE>
<LINE>Or silly sheep without a pastor's care:</LINE>
<LINE>Although ourselves do dearly tender them,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet are we ignorant of their affairs:</LINE>
<LINE>For fathers best do know to govern sons;</LINE>
<LINE>But daughters' steps the mother's counsel turns.</LINE>
<LINE>A son we want for to succeed our crown,</LINE>
<LINE>And course of time hath cancelled the date</LINE>
<LINE>Of further issue from our withered loins:</LINE>
<LINE>One foot already hangeth in the grave,</LINE>
<LINE>And age hath made deep furrows in my face:</LINE>
<LINE>The world of me, I of the world am weary,</LINE>
<LINE>And I would fain resign these earthly cares,</LINE>
<LINE>And think upon the welfare of my soul:</LINE>
<LINE>Which by no better means may be effected,</LINE>
<LINE>Than by resigning up the crown from me,</LINE>
<LINE>In equal dowry to my daughters three.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A worthy care, my liege, which well declares,</LINE>
<LINE>The zeal you bare unto our quondam queen:</LINE>
<LINE>And since your grace hath licensed me to speak,</LINE>
<LINE>I censure thus; your majesty knowing well,</LINE>
<LINE>What several suitors your princely daughters have,</LINE>
<LINE>To make them each a jointure more or less,</LINE>
<LINE>As is their worth, to them that love profess.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more, nor less, but even all alike,</LINE>
<LINE>My zeal is fixed, all fashioned in one mould:</LINE>
<LINE>Wherefore unpartial shall my censure be,</LINE>
<LINE>Both old and young shall have alike from me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>NOBLEMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My gracious lord, I heartily do wish,</LINE>
<LINE>That god had lent you an heir indubitate,</LINE>
<LINE>Which might have sat upon your royal throne,</LINE>
<LINE>When fates should loose the prison of your life,</LINE>
<LINE>By whose succession all this doubt might cease;</LINE>
<LINE>And as by you, by him we might have peace.</LINE>
<LINE>But after-wishes ever come too late,</LINE>
<LINE>And nothing can revoke the course of fate:</LINE>
<LINE>Wherefore, my liege, my censure deems it best,</LINE>
<LINE>To match them with some of your neighbour kings,</LINE>
<LINE>Bordering within the bounds of Albion,</LINE>
<LINE>By whose united friendship, this our state</LINE>
<LINE>May be protected against all foreign hate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Herein, my lords, your wishes sort with mine,</LINE>
<LINE>And mine (I hope) do sort with heavenly powers:</LINE>
<LINE>For at this instant two near neighbouring kings</LINE>
<LINE>Of Cornwall and of Cambria, motion love</LINE>
<LINE>To my two daughters, Gonorill and Ragan.</LINE>
<LINE>My youngest daughter, fair Cordella, vows</LINE>
<LINE>No liking to a monarch, unless love allows.</LINE>
<LINE>She is solicited by divers peers;</LINE>
<LINE>But none of them her partial fancy hears.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, if my policy may her beguile,</LINE>
<LINE>I will match her to some king within this isle,</LINE>
<LINE>And so establish such a perfect peace,</LINE>
<LINE>As fortune's force shall never prevail to cease.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Of us and ours, your gracious care, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Deserves an everlasting memory,</LINE>
<LINE>To be enrolled in chronicles of fame,</LINE>
<LINE>By never-dying perpetuity:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet to become so provident a prince,</LINE>
<LINE>Lose not the title of a loving father:</LINE>
<LINE>Do not force love, where fancy cannot dwell,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest streams being stopped, above the banks do swell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am resolved, and even now my mind</LINE>
<LINE>Doth meditate a sudden strategem,</LINE>
<LINE>To try which of my daughters loves me best:</LINE>
<LINE>Which till I know, I cannot be in rest.</LINE>
<LINE>This granted, when they jointly shall contend,</LINE>
<LINE>Each to exceed the other in their love:</LINE>
<LINE>Then at the vantage will I take Cordella,</LINE>
<LINE>Even as she doth protest she loves me best,</LINE>
<LINE>I will say, then, daughter, grant me one request,</LINE>
<LINE>To show thou lovest me as thy sisters do,</LINE>
<LINE>Accept a husband, whom myself will woo.</LINE>
<LINE>Although (poor soul) her senses will be mute:</LINE>
<LINE>Then will I triumph in my policy,</LINE>
<LINE>And match her with a king of Brittany.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will to them before, and bewray your secrecy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus fathers think their children to beguile,</LINE>
<LINE>And oftentimes themselves do first repent,</LINE>
<LINE>When heavenly powers do frustrate their intent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene II</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Gonorill and Ragan.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I marvel, Ragan, how you can endure</LINE>
<LINE>To see that proud pert peat, our youngest sister,</LINE>
<LINE>So slightly to account of us, her elders,</LINE>
<LINE>As if we were no better than herself!</LINE>
<LINE>We cannot have a quaint device so soon,</LINE>
<LINE>Or new-made fashion, of our choice invention;</LINE>
<LINE>But if she like it, she will have the same,</LINE>
<LINE>Or study newer to exceed us both.</LINE>
<LINE>Besides, she is so nice and so demure;</LINE>
<LINE>So sober, courteous, modest, and precise,</LINE>
<LINE>That all the court hath work enough to do,</LINE>
<LINE>To talk how she exceedeth me and you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What should I do? would it were in my power,</LINE>
<LINE>To find a cure for this contagious ill:</LINE>
<LINE>Some desperate medicine must be soon applied,</LINE>
<LINE>To dim the glory of her mounting fame;</LINE>
<LINE>Else ere it be long, she will have both prick and praise,</LINE>
<LINE>And we must be set by for working days.</LINE>
<LINE>Do you not see what several choice of suitors</LINE>
<LINE>She daily hath, and of the best degree?</LINE>
<LINE>Say, amongst all, she hap to fancy one,</LINE>
<LINE>And have a husband whenas we have none:</LINE>
<LINE>Why then, by right, to her we must give place,</LINE>
<LINE>Though it be never so much to our disgrace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my virginity, rather than</LINE>
<LINE>She shall have a husband before me,</LINE>
<LINE>I will marry one or other in his shirt:</LINE>
<LINE>And yet I have made half a grant already</LINE>
<LINE>Of my good-will unto the king of Cornwall.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Swear not so deeply, sister, here cometh my lord Skalliger:</LINE>
<LINE>Something his hasty coming doth import.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Skalliger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet princesses, I am glad I met you here so luckily,</LINE>
<LINE>Having good news which doth concern you both,</LINE>
<LINE>And craveth speedy expedition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For god's sake tell us what it is, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>I am with child until you utter it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, to save your longing, this it is:</LINE>
<LINE>Your father in great secrecy today,</LINE>
<LINE>Told me, he means to marry you out of hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the noble prince of Cambria;</LINE>
<LINE>You, madam, to the king of Cornwall's grace:</LINE>
<LINE>Your younger sister he would fain bestow</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the rich king of Hibernia:</LINE>
<LINE>But that he doubts, she hardly will consent;</LINE>
<LINE>For hitherto she never could fancy him.</LINE>
<LINE>If she do yield, why then, between you three,</LINE>
<LINE>He will divide his kingdom for your dowries.</LINE>
<LINE>But yet there is a further mystery,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, so you will conceal, I will disclose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whatever thou speakest to us, kind Skalliger,</LINE>
<LINE>Think that thou speakest it only to thyself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He earnestly desireth for to know,</LINE>
<LINE>Which of you three do bear most love to him,</LINE>
<LINE>And on your loves he so extremely dotes,</LINE>
<LINE>As never any did, I think, before.</LINE>
<LINE>As presently doth mean to send for you,</LINE>
<LINE>To be resolved of this tormenting doubt:</LINE>
<LINE>And look, whose answer pleaseth him the best,</LINE>
<LINE>They shall have most unto their marriages.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O that I had some pleasing mermaid's voice,</LINE>
<LINE>For to enchant his senseless senses with!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For he supposeth that Cordella will</LINE>
<LINE>Striving to go beyond you in her love,</LINE>
<LINE>Promise to do whatever he desires:</LINE>
<LINE>Then will he straight enjoin her for his sake,</LINE>
<LINE>The hibernian king in marriage for to take.</LINE>
<LINE>This is the sum of all I have to say;</LINE>
<LINE>Which being done, I humbly take my leave,</LINE>
<LINE>Not doubting but your wisdoms will foresee</LINE>
<LINE>What course will best unto your good agree.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, gentle Skalliger, thy kindness undeserved</LINE>
<LINE>Shall not be unrequited if we live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Skalliger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now have we fit occasion offered us,</LINE>
<LINE>To be revenged upon her unperceived.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, our revenge we will inflict on her</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be accounted piety in us:</LINE>
<LINE>I will so flatter with my doting father,</LINE>
<LINE>As he was never so flattered in his life.</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, I will say, that if it be his pleasure,</LINE>
<LINE>To match me to a beggar, I will yield:</LINE>
<LINE>For why, I know whatever I do say,</LINE>
<LINE>He means to match me with the Cornwall king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will say the like: for I am well assured,</LINE>
<LINE>Whatever I say to please the old man's mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Who dotes, as if he were a child again,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall enjoy the noble Cambrian prince:</LINE>
<LINE>Only, to feed his humour, will suffice,</LINE>
<LINE>To say, I am content with anyone</LINE>
<LINE>Whom he will appoint me; this will please him more,</LINE>
<LINE>Than ever Apollo's music pleased Jove.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I smile to think, in what a woeful plight</LINE>
<LINE>Cordella will be, when we answer thus:</LINE>
<LINE>For she will rather die, than give consent</LINE>
<LINE>To join in marriage with the Irish king:</LINE>
<LINE>So will our father think, she loveth him not,</LINE>
<LINE>Because she will not grant to his desire,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we will aggravate in such bitter terms,</LINE>
<LINE>That he will soon convert his love to hate:</LINE>
<LINE>For he, you know, is always in extremes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not all the world could lay a better plot,</LINE>
<LINE>I long till it be put in practice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene III</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leir and Perillus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Perillus, go seek my daughters,</LINE>
<LINE>Will them immediately come and speak with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will, my gracious lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, what a combat feels my panting heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Betwixt children's love, and care of common weal!</LINE>
<LINE>How dear my daughters are unto my soul,</LINE>
<LINE>None knows, but he, that knows my thoughts and secret deeds.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, little do they know the dear regard,</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein I hold their future state to come:</LINE>
<LINE>When they securely sleep on beds of down,</LINE>
<LINE>These aged eyes do watch for their behalf:</LINE>
<LINE>While they like wantons sport in youthful toys,</LINE>
<LINE>This throbbing heart is pierced with dire annoys.</LINE>
<LINE>As doth the sun exceed the smallest star;</LINE>
<LINE>So much the father's love exceeds the child's.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet my complaints are causeless: for the world</LINE>
<LINE>Affords not children more conformable:</LINE>
<LINE>And yet, methinks, my mind presageth still</LINE>
<LINE>I know not what; and yet I fear some ill.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Perillus with the three daughters.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Well, here my daughters come: I have found out</LINE>
<LINE>A present means to rid me of this doubt.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our royal lord and father, in all duty,</LINE>
<LINE>We come to know the tenour of your will,</LINE>
<LINE>Why you so hastily have sent for us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dear Gonorill, kind Ragan, sweet Cordella,</LINE>
<LINE>Ye flourishing branches of a kingly stock,</LINE>
<LINE>Sprung from a tree that once did flourish green,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose blossoms now are nipped with winter's frost,</LINE>
<LINE>And pale grim death doth wait upon my steps,</LINE>
<LINE>And summons me unto his next assizes.</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore, dear daughters, as ye tender the safety</LINE>
<LINE>Of him that was the cause of your first being,</LINE>
<LINE>Resolve a doubt which much molests my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Which of you three to me would prove most kind;</LINE>
<LINE>Which loves me most, and which at my request</LINE>
<LINE>Will soonest yield unto their father's hest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope, my gracious father makes no doubt</LINE>
<LINE>Of any of his daughters' love to him:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet for my part, to show my zeal to you,</LINE>
<LINE>Which cannot be in windy words rehearsed,</LINE>
<LINE>I prize my love to you at such a rate,</LINE>
<LINE>I think my life inferior to my love.</LINE>
<LINE>Should you enjoin me for to tie a millstone</LINE>
<LINE>About my neck, and leap into the sea,</LINE>
<LINE>At your command I willingly would do it:</LINE>
<LINE>Yea, for to do you good, I would ascend</LINE>
<LINE>The highest turret in all brittany,</LINE>
<LINE>And from the top leap headlong to the ground:</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, more should you appoint me for to marry</LINE>
<LINE>The meanest vassal in the spacious world,</LINE>
<LINE>Without reply I would accomplish it:</LINE>
<LINE>In brief, command whatever you desire,</LINE>
<LINE>And if I fail no favour I require.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, how my words revive my dying soul!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, how I do abhor this flattery!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But what saith Ragan to her father's will?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, that my simple utterance could suffice,</LINE>
<LINE>To tell the true intention of my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Which burns in zeal of duty to your grace,</LINE>
<LINE>And never can be quenched, but by desire</LINE>
<LINE>To show the same in outward forwardness.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, that there were some other maid that durst</LINE>
<LINE>But make a challenge of her love with me;</LINE>
<LINE>I would make her soon confess she never loved</LINE>
<LINE>Her father half so well as I do you.</LINE>
<LINE>Ay then, my deeds should prove in plainer case,</LINE>
<LINE>How much my zeal aboundeth to your grace:</LINE>
<LINE>But for them all, let this one mean suffice,</LINE>
<LINE>To ratify my love before your eyes:</LINE>
<LINE>I have right noble suitors to my love,</LINE>
<LINE>No worse than kings, and haply I love one:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, would you have me make my choice anew,</LINE>
<LINE>would bridle fancy, and be ruled by you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did never Philomel sing so sweet a note.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did never flatterer tell so false a tale.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak now, Cordella, make my joys at full,</LINE>
<LINE>And drop down nectar from thy honey lips.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot paint my duty forth in words</LINE>
<LINE>I hope my deeds shall make report for me:</LINE>
<LINE>But look what love the child doth owe the father,</LINE>
<LINE>The same to you I bear, my gracious lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is an answer answerless indeed:</LINE>
<LINE>Were you my daughter, I should scarcely brook it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou not blush, proud peacock as thou art,</LINE>
<LINE>To make our father such a slight reply?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why how now, minion, are you grown so proud?</LINE>
<LINE>Doth our dear love make you thus peremptory?</LINE>
<LINE>What, is your love become so small to us,</LINE>
<LINE>As that you scorn to tell us what it is?</LINE>
<LINE>Do you love us, as every child doth love</LINE>
<LINE>Their father? true indeed, as some,</LINE>
<LINE>Who by disobedience short their father's days,</LINE>
<LINE>And so would you; some are so father-sick,</LINE>
<LINE>That they make means to rid them from the world;</LINE>
<LINE>And so would you: some are indifferent,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether their aged parents live or die;</LINE>
<LINE>And so are you. but, didst thou know, proud girl,</LINE>
<LINE>What care I had to foster thee to this,</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, then thou wouldst say as thy sisters do:</LINE>
<LINE>Our life is less, than love we owe to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dear father, do not so mistake my words</LINE>
<LINE>Nor my plain meaning be misconstrued;</LINE>
<LINE>My tongue was never used to flattery.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You were not best say I flatter: if you do,</LINE>
<LINE>My deeds shall show, I flatter not with you.</LINE>
<LINE>I love my father better than thou canst.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The praise were great, spoke from another's mouth:</LINE>
<LINE>But it should seem your neighbours dwell far off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, here is one, that will confirm as much</LINE>
<LINE>As she hath said, both for myself and her.</LINE>
<LINE>I say, thou dost not wish my father's good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dear father. ---</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, bastard imp, no issue of King Leir,</LINE>
<LINE>I will not hear thee speak one tittle more.</LINE>
<LINE>Call not me father, if thou love thy life,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor these thy sisters once presume to name:</LINE>
<LINE>Look for no help henceforth from me nor mine;</LINE>
<LINE>Shift as thou wilt, and trust unto thyself:</LINE>
<LINE>My kingdom will I equally divide</LINE>
<LINE>Betwixt thy two sisters to their royal dower,</LINE>
<LINE>And will bestow them worthy their deserts:</LINE>
<LINE>This done, because thou shalt not have the hope,</LINE>
<LINE>To have a child's part in the time to come,</LINE>
<LINE>I presently will dispossess myself,</LINE>
<LINE>And set up these upon my princely throne.</LINE>
<LINE>Gonorill. I ever thought that pride would have a fall.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Plain dealing, sister: your beauty is so sheen,</LINE>
<LINE>You need no dowry, to make you be a queen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Leir, Gonorill, Ragan.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now whither, poor forsaken, shall I go,</LINE>
<LINE>When mine own sisters triumph in my woe?</LINE>
<LINE>But unto him which doth protect the just,</LINE>
<LINE>In him will poor Cordella put her trust.</LINE>
<LINE>These hands shall labour, for to get my spending;</LINE>
<LINE>And so I will live until my days have ending.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, how I grieve, to see my lord thus fond,</LINE>
<LINE>To dote so much upon vain flattering words.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, if he but with good advice had weighed,</LINE>
<LINE>The hidden tenour of her humble speech,</LINE>
<LINE>Reason to rage should not have given place,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor poor Cordella suffer such disgrace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act II</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene I</SCENETITLE>

<LINE>Enter the Gallian king with Mumford and three nobles more.</LINE>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dissuade me not, my lords, I am resolved,</LINE>
<LINE>This next fair wind to sail for Brittany,</LINE>
<LINE>In some disguise, to see if flying fame</LINE>
<LINE>Be not too prodigal in the wondrous praise</LINE>
<LINE>Of these three nymphs, the daughters of King Leir.</LINE>
<LINE>If present view do answer absent praise,</LINE>
<LINE>And eyes allow of what our ears have heard,</LINE>
<LINE>And Venus stand auspicious to my vows,</LINE>
<LINE>And fortune favour what I take in hand;</LINE>
<LINE>I will return seized of as rich a prize</LINE>
<LINE>As Jason, when he won the golden fleece.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heavens grant you may; the match were full of honour,</LINE>
<LINE>And well beseeming the young Gallian king.</LINE>
<LINE>I would your grace would favour me so much,</LINE>
<LINE>As make me partner of your pilgrimage.</LINE>
<LINE>I long to see the gallant British dames,</LINE>
<LINE>And feed mine eyes upon their rare perfections:</LINE>
<LINE>For till I know the contrary, I will say,</LINE>
<LINE>Our dames in France are far more fair than they.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lord Mumford, you have saved me a labour,</LINE>
<LINE>In offering that which I did mean to ask:</LINE>
<LINE>And I most willingly accept your company.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet first I will enjoin you to observe</LINE>
<LINE>Some few conditions which I shall propose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So that you do not tie mine eyes for looking</LINE>
<LINE>After the amorous glances of fair dames:</LINE>
<LINE>So that you do not tie my tongue from speaking,</LINE>
<LINE>My lips from kissing when occasion serves,</LINE>
<LINE>My hands from congees, and my knees to bow</LINE>
<LINE>To gallant girls; which were a task more hard,</LINE>
<LINE>Than flesh and blood is able to endure:</LINE>
<LINE>Command what else you please, I rest content.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To bind thee from a thing thou canst not leave,</LINE>
<LINE>Were but a means to make thee seek it more:</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore speak, look, kiss, salute for me;</LINE>
<LINE>In these myself am like to second thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Now hear thy task. I charge thee from the time</LINE>
<LINE>The first we set sail for the British shore,</LINE>
<LINE>To use no words of dignity to me,</LINE>
<LINE>But in the friendliest manner that thou canst,</LINE>
<LINE>Make use of me as thy companion:</LINE>
<LINE>For we will go disguised in palmers' weeds,</LINE>
<LINE>That no man shall mistrust us what we are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If that be all, I will fit your turn, I warrant you. I am</LINE>
<LINE>some kin to the Blunts, and I think, the bluntest of all my kindred;</LINE>
<LINE>therefore if I be too blunt with you, thank yourself for praying me to be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy pleasant company will make the way seem short.</LINE>
<LINE>It resteth now, that in my absence hence,</LINE>
<LINE>I do commit the government to you</LINE>
<LINE>My trusty lords and faithful counsellors.</LINE>
<LINE>Time cutteth off the rest I have to say:</LINE>
<LINE>The wind blows fair, and I must needs away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>NOBLES.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heavens send your voyage to as good effect,</LINE>
<LINE>As we your land do purpose to protect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene II</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the king of Cornwall and his man booted and spurred, a riding wand and letter in his hand.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But how far distant are we from the court?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Some twenty miles, my lord, or thereabouts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It seemeth to me twenty thousand miles:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet hope I to be there within this hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then are you like to ride alone for me.</LINE>
<LINE>I think, my lord is weary of his life. <STAGEDIR>to
himself.</STAGEDIR>
</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet Gonorill, I long to see thy face,</LINE>
<LINE>Which hast so kindly gratified my love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the King of Cambria booted and spurred, and his
man with a wand and a letter.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get a fresh horse: for by my soul I swear, </LINE>
<STAGEDIR>looks at the letter.</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I am past patience, longer to forbear</LINE>
<LINE>The wished sight of my beloved mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>Dear Ragan, stay and comfort of my life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now what in god's name doth my lord intend?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>to himself.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>He thinks he never shall come at his journey's end.</LINE>
<LINE>I would he had old Daedalus' waxen wings,</LINE>
<LINE>That he might fly, so I might stay behind:</LINE>
<LINE>For ere we get to Troynovant, I see,</LINE>
<LINE>He quite will tire himself, his horse and me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Cornwall and Cambria look one upon another and start to
see each other there</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brother of Cambria, we greet you well,</LINE>
<LINE>As one whom here we little did expect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brother of Cornwall, met in happy time:</LINE>
<LINE>I thought as much to have met with the souldan of Persia,</LINE>
<LINE>As to have met you in this place, my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>No doubt, it is about some great affairs,</LINE>
<LINE>That makes you here so slenderly accompanied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To say the truth, my lord, it is no less,</LINE>
<LINE>And for your part some hasty wind of chance</LINE>
<LINE>Hath blown you hither thus upon the sudden.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, to break off further circumstances,</LINE>
<LINE>For at this time I cannot brook delays:</LINE>
<LINE>Tell you your reason, I will tell you mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In faith, content, and therefore to be brief;</LINE>
<LINE>For I am sure my haste is as great as yours:</LINE>
<LINE>I am sent for, to come unto King Leir,</LINE>
<LINE>Who by these present letters promiseth</LINE>
<LINE>His eldest daughter, lovely Gonorill,</LINE>
<LINE>To me in marriage, and for present dowry,</LINE>
<LINE>The moiety of half his regiment.</LINE>
<LINE>The lady's love I long ago possessed:</LINE>
<LINE>But until now I never had the father's.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You tell me wonders, yet I will relate</LINE>
<LINE>Strange news, and henceforth we must brothers call;</LINE>
<LINE>Witness these lines: his honourable age,</LINE>
<LINE>Being weary of the troubles of his crown,</LINE>
<LINE>His princely daughter Ragan will bestow</LINE>
<LINE>On me in marriage, with half his seignories,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom I would gladly have accepted of,</LINE>
<LINE>With the third part, her complements are such.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I have one half, and you have the other,</LINE>
<LINE>Then between us we must needs have the whole.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The hole! how mean you that? 'sblood, I hope,</LINE>
<LINE>We shall have two holes between us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, the whole kingdom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, that is very true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then is left for his third daughter's dowry,</LINE>
<LINE>Lovely Cordella, whom the world admires?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is very strange, I know not what to think,</LINE>
<LINE>Unless they mean to make a nun of her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were pity such rare beauty should be hid</LINE>
<LINE>Within the compass of a cloister's wall:</LINE>
<LINE>But howsoever, if Leir's words prove true,</LINE>
<LINE>It will be good, my lord, for me and you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then let us haste, all danger to prevent,</LINE>
<LINE>For fear delays do alter his intent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene III </SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Gonorill and Ragan.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sister, when did you see Cordella last,</LINE>
<LINE>That pretty piece, that thinks none good enough</LINE>
<LINE>To speak to her, because, sir-reverence,</LINE>
<LINE>She hath a little beauty extraordinary?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Since time my father warned her from his presence,</LINE>
<LINE>I never saw her, that I can remember.</LINE>
<LINE>God give her joy of her surpassing beauty;</LINE>
<LINE>I think, her dowry will be small enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have incensed my father so against her,</LINE>
<LINE>As he will never be reclaimed again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I was not much behind to do the like.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, sister, what moves you to bear her such good-will?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In truth, I think, the same that moveth you;</LINE>
<LINE>Because she doth surpass us both in beauty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beshrew your fingers, how right you can guess:</LINE>
<LINE>I tell you true, it cuts me to the heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But we will keep her low enough, I warrant,</LINE>
<LINE>And clip her wings for mounting up too high.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who ever hath her, shall have a rich marriage of her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She were right fit to make a parson's wife:</LINE>
<LINE>For they, men say, do love fair women well,</LINE>
<LINE>And many times do marry them with nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With nothing! marry god forbid: why, are there any such?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I mean, no money.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cry you mercy, I mistook you much:</LINE>
<LINE>And she is far too stately for the church;</LINE>
<LINE>She will lay her husband's benefice on her back,</LINE>
<LINE>Even in one gown, if she may have her will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In faith, poor soul, I pity her a little.</LINE>
<LINE>Would she were less fair, or more fortunate.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, I think long until I see my Morgan,</LINE>
<LINE>The gallant prince of Cambria, here arrive.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so do I, until the Cornwall king</LINE>
<LINE>Present himself, to consummate my joys.</LINE>
<LINE>Peace, here cometh my father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leir, Perillus, and others.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cease, good my lords, and sue not to reverse</LINE>
<LINE>Our censure, which is now irrevocable.</LINE>
<LINE>We have dispatched letters of contract</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the kings of Cambria and of Cornwall;</LINE>
<LINE>Our hand and seal will justify no less:</LINE>
<LINE>Then do not so dishonour me, my lords</LINE>
<LINE>As to make shipwreck of our kingly word.</LINE>
<LINE>I am as kind as is the pelican,</LINE>
<LINE>That kills itself, to save her young ones' lives:</LINE>
<LINE>And yet as jealous as the princely eagle,</LINE>
<LINE>That kills her young ones, if they do but dazzle</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the radiant splendour of the sun.</LINE>
<LINE>Within this two days I expect their coming.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter kings of Cornwall and Cambria.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>But in good time, they are arrived already.</LINE>
<LINE>This haste of yours, my lords, doth testify</LINE>
<LINE>The fervent love you bear unto my daughters:</LINE>
<LINE>And think yourselves as welcome to King Leir,</LINE>
<LINE>As ever Priam's children were to him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My gracious lord, and father too, I hope,</LINE>
<LINE>Pardon, for that I made no greater haste:</LINE>
<LINE>But were my horse as swift as were my will,</LINE>
<LINE>I long ere this had seen your majesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No other excuse of absence can I frame,</LINE>
<LINE>Than what my brother hath informed your grace:</LINE>
<LINE>Or our undeserved welcome, we do vow,</LINE>
<LINE>Perpetually to rest at your command.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But you, sweet love, illustrious Gonorill,</LINE>
<LINE>The regent, and the sovereign of my soul,</LINE>
<LINE>Is Cornwall welcome to your excellency?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As welcome, as Leander was to hero,</LINE>
<LINE>Or brave Aeneas to the Carthage queen:</LINE>
<LINE>So and more welcome is your grace to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, may my fortune prove no worse then his,</LINE>
<LINE>Since heavens do know, my fancy is as much.</LINE>
<LINE>Dear Ragan, say, if welcome unto thee,</LINE>
<LINE>All welcomes else will little comfort me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As gold is welcome to the covetous eye,</LINE>
<LINE>As sleep is welcome to the traveller,</LINE>
<LINE>As is fresh water to sea-beaten men,</LINE>
<LINE>Or moistened showers unto the parched ground,</LINE>
<LINE>Or anything more welcomer than this,</LINE>
<LINE>So and more welcome lovely Morgan is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What resteth then, but that we consummate,</LINE>
<LINE>The celebration of these nuptial rites?</LINE>
<LINE>My kingdom I do equally divide.</LINE>
<LINE>Princes draw lots, and take your chance as falls.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Then they draw lots.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>These I resign as freely unto you,</LINE>
<LINE>As erst by true succession they were mine.</LINE>
<LINE>And here I do freely dispossess myself,</LINE>
<LINE>And make you two my true adopted heirs:</LINE>
<LINE>Myself will sojourn with my son of Cornwall,</LINE>
<LINE>And take me to my prayers and my beads.</LINE>
<LINE>I know, my daughter Ragan will be sorry,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I do not spend my days with her:</LINE>
<LINE>Would I were able to be with both at once;</LINE>
<LINE>They are the kindest girls in Christendom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been silent all this while, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>To see if any worthier than myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Would once have spoke in poor Cordella's cause:</LINE>
<LINE>But love or fear ties silence to their tongues.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, hear me speak for her, my gracious lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose deeds have not deserved this ruthless doom,</LINE>
<LINE>As thus to disinherit her of all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Urge this no more, and if thou love thy life:</LINE>
<LINE>I say, she is no daughter, that doth scorn</LINE>
<LINE>To tell her father how she loveth him.</LINE>
<LINE>Whoever speaketh hereof to me again,</LINE>
<LINE>I will esteem him for my mortal foe.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, let us in, to celebrate with joy,</LINE>
<LINE>The happy nuptials of these lovely pairs.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt omnes, manes Perillus.</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Perillus. Ah, who so blind, as they that will not see</LINE>
<LINE>The near approach of their own misery?</LINE>
<LINE>Poor lady, I extremely pity her:</LINE>
<LINE>And whilst I live, each drop of my heart blood,</LINE>
<LINE>Will I strain forth, to do her any good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene IV</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Gallian king and Mumford, desguised like pilgrims.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, how do you brook this British air?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'My lord,' I told you of this foolish humour,</LINE>
<LINE>And bound you to the contrary, you know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon me for once, my lord; I did forget.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'My lord' again? then let us have nothing else,</LINE>
<LINE>And so be taken for spies, and then it is well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Swounds, I could bite my tongue in two for anger:</LINE>
<LINE>For god's sake name yourself some proper name.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call me Tresillus; I'll call thee Denapoll.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Might I be made the monarch of the world,</LINE>
<LINE>I could not hit upon these names, I swear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then call me Will, I will call thee Jack.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, be it so, for I have well deserved to be called Jack.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand close; for here a British lady cometh:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Cordella</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>A fairer creature never mine eyes beheld.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is a day of joy unto my sisters,</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein they both are married unto kings;</LINE>
<LINE>And I, by birth, as worthy as themselves,</LINE>
<LINE>Am turned into the world, to seek my fortune.</LINE>
<LINE>How may I blame the fickle queen of chance,</LINE>
<LINE>That maketh me a pattern of her power?</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, poor weak maid, whose imbecility</LINE>
<LINE>Is far unable to endure these brunts.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, father Leir, how dost thou wrong thy child,</LINE>
<LINE>Who always was obedient to thy will!</LINE>
<LINE>But why accuse I fortune and my father?</LINE>
<LINE>No, no, it is the pleasure of my God:</LINE>
<LINE>And I do willingly embrace the rod.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is no goddess; for she doth complain</LINE>
<LINE>On fortune, and the unkindness of her father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These costly robes ill-fitting my estate</LINE>
<LINE>I will exchange for other meaner habits.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now if I had a kingdom in my hands,</LINE>
<LINE>I would exchange it for a milkmaid's smock and petticoat,</LINE>
<LINE>That she and I might shift our clothes together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will betake me to my thread and needle,</LINE>
<LINE>And earn my living with my fingers' ends.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O brave! god willing, thou shalt have my custom,</LINE>
<LINE>By sweet saint Denis, here I sadly swear,</LINE>
<LINE>For all the shirts and night-gear that I wear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will profess and vow a maiden's life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then I protest thou shalt not have my custom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I can forbear no longer for to speak:</LINE>
<LINE>For if I do, I think my heart will break.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Sblood, will, I hope you are not in love with my sempster.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am in such a labyrinth of love,</LINE>
<LINE>As that I know not which way to get out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You will never get out, unless you first get in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee jack, cross not my passions.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee will, to her, and try her patience.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou fairest creature, whatsoever thou art,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever any mortal eyes beheld,</LINE>
<LINE>Vouchsafe to me, who have overheard thy woes,</LINE>
<LINE>To show the cause of these thy sad laments.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah pilgrims, what avails to show the cause,</LINE>
<LINE>When there is no means to find a remedy?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To utter grief, doth ease a heart overcharged.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To touch a sore, doth aggravate the pain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The silly mouse, by virtue of her teeth,</LINE>
<LINE>Released the princely lion from the net.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kind palmer, which so much desirest to hear</LINE>
<LINE>The tragic tale of my unhappy youth:</LINE>
<LINE>Know this in brief, I am the hapless daughter</LINE>
<LINE>Of Leir, sometimes king of Brittany.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, who debars his honourable age,</LINE>
<LINE>From being still the king of Brittany?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None, but himself hath dispossessed himself,</LINE>
<LINE>And given all his kingdom to the kings</LINE>
<LINE>Of Cornwall and of Cambria, with my sisters.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath he given nothing to your lovely self?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He loved me not, and therefore gave me nothing,</LINE>
<LINE>Only because I could not flatter him:</LINE>
<LINE>And in this day of triumph to my sisters,</LINE>
<LINE>Doth fortune triumph in my overthrow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet lady, say there should come a king,</LINE>
<LINE>As good as either of your sisters' husbands,</LINE>
<LINE>To crave your love, would you accept of him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, do not mock with those in misery,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor do not think, though fortune have the power,</LINE>
<LINE>To spoil mine honour, and debase my state,</LINE>
<LINE>That she hath any interest in my mind:</LINE>
<LINE>For if the greatest monarch on the earth,</LINE>
<LINE>Should sue to me in this extremity,</LINE>
<LINE>Except my heart could love, and heart could like,</LINE>
<LINE>Better than any that I ever saw,</LINE>
<LINE>His great estate no more should move my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Than mountains move by blast of every wind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think not, sweet nymph, 'tis holy palmers' guise,</LINE>
<LINE>To grieved souls fresh torments to devise:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore in witness of my true intent,</LINE>
<LINE>Let heaven and earth bear record of my words:</LINE>
<LINE>There is a young and lusty Gallian king,</LINE>
<LINE>So like to me, as I am to myself,</LINE>
<LINE>That earnestly doth crave to have thy love,</LINE>
<LINE>And join with thee in Hymen's sacred bonds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The like to thee did ne'er these eyes behold;</LINE>
<LINE>Oh live to add new torments to my grief:</LINE>
<LINE>Why didst thou thus entrap me unawares?</LINE>
<LINE>Ah palmer, my estate doth not befit</LINE>
<LINE>A kingly marriage as the case now stands.</LINE>
<LINE>Whilom whenas I lived in honour's height,</LINE>
<LINE>A prince perhaps might postulate my love:</LINE>
<LINE>Now misery, dishonour and disgrace,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath light on me, and quite reversed the case.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy king will hold thee wise, if thou surcease</LINE>
<LINE>The suit, whereas no dowry will ensue.</LINE>
<LINE>Then be advised, palmer, what to do:</LINE>
<LINE>Cease for thy king, seek for thyself to woo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your birth's too high for any, but a king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My mind is low enough to love a palmer,</LINE>
<LINE>Rather than any king upon the earth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, but you never can endure their life,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is so straight and full of penury.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O yes, I can, and happy if I might:</LINE>
<LINE>I will hold thy palmer's staff within my hand,</LINE>
<LINE>And think it is the sceptre of a queen.</LINE>
<LINE>Sometime I will set thy bonnet on my head,</LINE>
<LINE>And think I wear a rich imperial crown.</LINE>
<LINE>Sometime I will help thee in thy holy prayers,</LINE>
<LINE>And think I am with thee in paradise.</LINE>
<LINE>Thus I will mock fortune as she mocketh me,</LINE>
<LINE>And never will lovely choice repent:</LINE>
<LINE>For, having thee, I shall have all content.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were sin to hold her longer in suspense,</LINE>
<LINE>Since that my soul hath vowed she shall be mine.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, dear Cordella, cordial to my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>I am no palmer, as I seem to be,</LINE>
<LINE>But hither come in this unknown disguise,</LINE>
<LINE>To view the admired beauty of those eyes.</LINE>
<LINE>I am the king of Gallia, gentle maid,</LINE>
<LINE>Although thus slenderly accompanied,</LINE>
<LINE>And yet thy vassal by imperious love,</LINE>
<LINE>And sworn to serve thee everlastingly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whatever you be, of high or low descent,</LINE>
<LINE>All's one to me, I do request but this:</LINE>
<LINE>That as I am, you will accept of me,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will have you whatsoever you be:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet well I know, you come of royal race,</LINE>
<LINE>I see such sparks of honour in your face.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have palmer's weeds such power to win fair ladies?</LINE>
<LINE>Faith, then I hope the next that falls is mine:</LINE>
<LINE>Upon condition I no worse might speed,</LINE>
<LINE>I would forever wear a palmer's weed.</LINE>
<LINE>I like an honest and plain dealing wench,</LINE>
<LINE>That swears, without exceptions, I will have you.</LINE>
<LINE>These foppets, that know not whether to love a man or no,</LINE>
<LINE>except they first go ask their mother's leave,</LINE>
<LINE>by this hand, I hate them ten times worse than poison.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What resteth then our happiness to procure?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, go to church, to make the matter sure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be so because the world shall say,</LINE>
<LINE>King Leir's three daughters were wedded in one day:</LINE>
<LINE>The celebration of this happy chance,</LINE>
<LINE>We will defer, until we come to France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I like the wooing, that is not long a-doing.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, for her sake, I know what I know:</LINE>
<LINE>I will never marry whilst I live,</LINE>
<LINE>Except I have one of these British ladies,</LINE>
<LINE>My humour is alienated from the maids of France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>
</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act III</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene I</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Perillus, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The king hath dispossessed himself of all,</LINE>
<LINE>Those to advance, which scarce will give him thanks:</LINE>
<LINE>His youngest daughter he hath turned away,</LINE>
<LINE>And no man knows what is become of her.</LINE>
<LINE>He sojourns now in Cornwall with the eldest,</LINE>
<LINE>Who flattered him, until she did obtain</LINE>
<LINE>That at his hands, which now she doth possess:</LINE>
<LINE>And now she sees he hath no more to give,</LINE>
<LINE>It grieves her heart to see her father live.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, whom should man trust in this wicked age,</LINE>
<LINE>When children thus against their parents rage?</LINE>
<LINE>But he, the mirror of mild patience,</LINE>
<LINE>Puts up all wrongs, and never gives reply:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet shames she not in most opprobrious sort,</LINE>
<LINE>To call him fool and dotard to his face,</LINE>
<LINE>And sets her parasites of purpose oft,</LINE>
<LINE>In scoffing wise to offer him disgrace.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh iron age! O times! O monstrous, vile,</LINE>
<LINE>When parents are contemned of the child!</LINE>
<LINE>His pension she hath half restrained from him,</LINE>
<LINE>And will, ere long, the other half, I fear:</LINE>
<LINE>For she thinks nothing is bestowed in vain,</LINE>
<LINE>But that which doth her father's life maintain.</LINE>
<LINE>Trust not alliance; but trust strangers rather,</LINE>
<LINE>Since daughters prove disloyal to the father.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, I will counsel him the best I can:</LINE>
<LINE>Would I were able to redress his wrong.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet what I can, unto my utmost power,</LINE>
<LINE>He shall be sure of to the latest hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act III</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene II</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Gonorill and Skalliger.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee, Skalliger, tell me what thou thinkest:</LINE>
<LINE>Could any woman of our dignity</LINE>
<LINE>Endure such quips and peremptory taunts,</LINE>
<LINE>As I do daily from my doting father?</LINE>
<LINE>Doth it not suffice that I him keep of alms,</LINE>
<LINE>Who is not able for to keep himself?</LINE>
<LINE>But as if he were our better, he should think</LINE>
<LINE>To check and snap me up at every word.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot make me a new fashioned gown,</LINE>
<LINE>And set it forth with more than common cost;</LINE>
<LINE>But his old doting doltish withered wit,</LINE>
<LINE>Is sure to give a senseless check for it.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot make a banquet extraordinary,</LINE>
<LINE>To grace myself and spread my name abroad,</LINE>
<LINE>But he, old fool, is captious by and by,</LINE>
<LINE>And saith, the cost would well suffice for twice.</LINE>
<LINE>Judge then, I pray, what reason is it, that I</LINE>
<LINE>Should stand alone charged with his vain expense,</LINE>
<LINE>And that my sister Ragan should go free,</LINE>
<LINE>To whom he gave as much as unto me?</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, Skalliger, tell me, if thou know,</LINE>
<LINE>By any means to rid me of this woe.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your many favours still bestowed on me,</LINE>
<LINE>Bind me in duty to advise your grace,</LINE>
<LINE>How you may soonest remedy this ill.</LINE>
<LINE>The large allowance which he hath from you,</LINE>
<LINE>Is that which makes him so forget himself:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore abridge it half, and you shall see,</LINE>
<LINE>That having less, he will more thankful be:</LINE>
<LINE>For why, abundance maketh us forget</LINE>
<LINE>The fountains whence the benefits do spring.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, Skalliger, for thy kind advice herein,</LINE>
<LINE>I will not be ungrateful, if I live:</LINE>
<LINE>I have restrained half his portion already,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will presently restrain the other,</LINE>
<LINE>That having no means to relieve himself,</LINE>
<LINE>He may go seek elsewhere for better help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SKALLIGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, viperous woman, shame to all thy sex:</LINE>
<LINE>The heavens, no doubt, will punish thee for this;</LINE>
<LINE>And me, a villain, that to curry favour,</LINE>
<LINE>Have given the daughter counsel against the father.</LINE>
<LINE>But us the world doth this experience give,</LINE>
<LINE>That he that cannot flatter cannot live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene III</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter king of Cornwall, Leir, Perillus, and nobles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Father, what aileth you to be so sad?</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks, you frolic not as you were wont.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The nearer we do grow unto our graves,</LINE>
<LINE>The less we do delight in worldly joys.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But if a man can frame himself to mirth,</LINE>
<LINE>It is a mean for to prolong his life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then welcome sorrow, Leir's only friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Who doth desire his troubled days had end.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Comfort yourself, father, here comes your daughter,</LINE>
<LINE>Who much will grieve, I know, to see you sad.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But more doth grieve, I fear, to see me live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Gonorill</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My Gonorill, you come in wished time,</LINE>
<LINE>To put your father from these pensive dumps.</LINE>
<LINE>In faith I fear that all things go not well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, do you fear, that I have angered him?</LINE>
<LINE>Hath he complained of me unto my lord?</LINE>
<LINE>I will provide him a piece of bread and cheese;</LINE>
<LINE>For in a time he will practise nothing else,</LINE>
<LINE>Than carry tales from one unto another.</LINE>
<LINE>It is all his practice for to kindle strife,</LINE>
<LINE>Betwixt you, my lord, and me your loving wife:</LINE>
<LINE>But I will take an order, if I can,</LINE>
<LINE>To cease the effect, where first the cause began.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet, be not angry in a partial cause,</LINE>
<LINE>He never complained of thee in all his life.</LINE>
<LINE>Father, you must not weigh a woman's words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, not I: poor soul, she breeds young bones,</LINE>
<LINE>And that is it makes her so touchy sure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, breeds young bones already! you will make</LINE>
<LINE>An honest woman of me then, belike.</LINE>
<LINE>O vile old wretch! who ever heard the like,</LINE>
<LINE>That seeketh thus his own child to defame?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot stay to hear this discord sound.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For anyone that loves your company,</LINE>
<LINE>You may go pack, and seek some other place,</LINE>
<LINE>To sow the seed of discord and disgrace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus, say or do the best that ever I can,</LINE>
<LINE>It is wrested straight into another sense.</LINE>
<LINE>This punishment my heavy sins deserve,</LINE>
<LINE>And more than this ten thousand thousand times:</LINE>
<LINE>Else aged Leir them could never find</LINE>
<LINE>Cruel to him, to whom he hath been kind.</LINE>
<LINE>Why do I over-live myself, to see</LINE>
<LINE>The course of nature quite reversed in me?</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, gentle death, if ever any wight</LINE>
<LINE>Did wish thy presence with a perfect zeal:</LINE>
<LINE>Then come, I pray thee, even with all my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And end my sorrows with thy fatal dart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>He weeps</STAGEDIR>


<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, do not so disconsolate yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor dew your aged cheeks with wasting tears.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What man art thou that takest any pity</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the worthless state of old Leir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One, who doth bear as great a share of grief,</LINE>
<LINE>As if it were my dearest father's case.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>ah, good my friend, how ill art thou advised,</LINE>
<LINE>For to consort with miserable men:</LINE>
<LINE>Go learn to flatter, where thou mayest in time</LINE>
<LINE>Get favour amongst the mighty, and so climb:</LINE>
<LINE>For now I am so poor and full of want,</LINE>
<LINE>As that I never can recompense thy love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is got by flattery doth not long endure;</LINE>
<LINE>And men in favour live not most secure.</LINE>
<LINE>My conscience tells me, if I should forsake you,</LINE>
<LINE>I were the hatefullest execrement on the earth:</LINE>
<LINE>Which well do know, in course of former time,</LINE>
<LINE>How good my lord hath been to me and mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did I ere raise thee higher than the rest</LINE>
<LINE>Of all thy ancestors which were before?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I never did seek it; but by your good grace,</LINE>
<LINE>I still enjoyed my own with quietness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did I ere give thee living, to increase</LINE>
<LINE>The due revenues which thy father left?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had enough, my lord, and having that,</LINE>
<LINE>What should you need to give me any more?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, did I ever dispossess myself,</LINE>
<LINE>And give thee half my kingdom in good-will?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, my lord, there were no reason, why</LINE>
<LINE>You should have such a thought, to give it me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>nay, if thou talk of reason, then be mute;</LINE>
<LINE>For with good reason I can thee confute.</LINE>
<LINE>If they, which first by nature's sacred law,</LINE>
<LINE>Do owe to me the tribute of their lives;</LINE>
<LINE>If they to whom I always have been kind,</LINE>
<LINE>And bountiful beyond comparison;</LINE>
<LINE>If they, for whom I have undone myself,</LINE>
<LINE>And brought my age unto this extreme want,</LINE>
<LINE>Do now reject, contemn, despise, abhor me,</LINE>
<LINE>What reason moveth thee to sorrow for me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where reason fails, let tears confirm my love,</LINE>
<LINE>And speak how much your passions do me move.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, good my lord, condemn not all for one:</LINE>
<LINE>You have two daughters left, to whom I know</LINE>
<LINE>You shall be welcome, if you please to go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, how thy words add sorrow to my soul,</LINE>
<LINE>To think of my unkindness to Cordella!</LINE>
<LINE>Whom causeless I did dispossess of all,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the unkind suggestions of her sisters:</LINE>
<LINE>And for her sake, I think this heavy doom</LINE>
<LINE>Is fallen on me, and not without desert:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet unto Ragan was I always kind,</LINE>
<LINE>And gave to her the half of all I had:</LINE>
<LINE>It may be, if I should to her repair,</LINE>
<LINE>She would be kinder, and entreat me fair.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No doubt she would, and practise ere it be long,</LINE>
<LINE>By force of arms for to redress your wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, since thou dost advise me for to go,</LINE>
<LINE>I am resolved to try the worst of woe. </LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene IV</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Ragan, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How may I bless the hour of my nativity,</LINE>
<LINE>Which bodeth unto me such happy stars!</LINE>
<LINE>How may I thank kind fortune, that vouchsafes</LINE>
<LINE>To all my actions, such desired event!</LINE>
<LINE>I rule the king of cambria as I please:</LINE>
<LINE>The states are all obedient to my will;</LINE>
<LINE>And look whatever I say, it shall be so;</LINE>
<LINE>Not anyone, that dareth answer no.</LINE>
<LINE>My eldest sister lives in royal state,</LINE>
<LINE>And wanteth nothing fitting her degree:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet hath she such a cooling card withal,</LINE>
<LINE>As that her honey savoureth much of gall.</LINE>
<LINE>My father with her is quarter-master still,</LINE>
<LINE>And many times restrains her of her will:</LINE>
<LINE>But if he were with me, and served me so,</LINE>
<LINE>I would send him packing somewhere else to go.</LINE>
<LINE>I would entertain him with such slender cost,</LINE>
<LINE>That he should quickly wish to change his host.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene V</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Cornwall, Gonorill, and attendants.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, Gonorill, what dire unhappy chance</LINE>
<LINE>Hath sequestered thy father from our presence,</LINE>
<LINE>That no report can yet be heard of him?</LINE>
<LINE>Some great unkindness hath been offered him,</LINE>
<LINE>Exceeding far the bounds of patience:</LINE>
<LINE>Else all the world shall never me persuade,</LINE>
<LINE>He would forsake us without notice made.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, my lord, whom doth it touch so near,</LINE>
<LINE>Or who hath interest in this grief, but I,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom sorrow had brought to her longest home,</LINE>
<LINE>But that I know his qualities so well?</LINE>
<LINE>I know, he is but stolen upon my sister</LINE>
<LINE>At unawares, to see her how she fares,</LINE>
<LINE>And spend a little time with her, to note</LINE>
<LINE>How all things go, and how she likes her choice:</LINE>
<LINE>And when occasion serves, he will steal from her,</LINE>
<LINE>And unawares return to us again.</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore, my lord, be frolic, and resolve</LINE>
<LINE>To see my father here again ere long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope so too; but yet to be more sure,</LINE>
<LINE>I will send a post immediately to know</LINE>
<LINE>Whether he be arrived there or no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I will intercept the messenger,</LINE>
<LINE>And temper him before he doth depart</LINE>
<LINE>With sweet persuasions, and with sound rewards,</LINE>
<LINE>That his report shall ratify my speech,</LINE>
<LINE>And make my lord cease further to inquire.</LINE>
<LINE>If he be not gone to my sister's court,</LINE>
<LINE>As sure my mind presageth that he is,</LINE>
<LINE>Fall sick, and as common passenger,</LINE>
<LINE>Be dead and buried: would god it were so well;</LINE>
<LINE>For then there were no more to do, but this,</LINE>
<LINE>He went away, and none knows where he is.</LINE>
<LINE>But say he be in Cambria with the king,</LINE>
<LINE>And there exclaim against me, as he will:</LINE>
<LINE>I know he is as welcome to my sister,</LINE>
<LINE>As water is into a broken ship.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, after him I will send such thunderclaps</LINE>
<LINE>Of slander, scandal, and invented tales,</LINE>
<LINE>That all the blame shall be removed from me,</LINE>
<LINE>And unperceived rebound upon himself.</LINE>
<LINE>Thus with one nail another I will expel,</LINE>
<LINE>And make the world judge, that I us'd him well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the messenger that should go to Cambria, with a letter.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My honest friend, whither away so fast?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To Cambria, madam, with letters from the King.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To whom?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Unto your father, if he be there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me see them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>She opens them.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I hope your grace will stand</LINE>
<LINE>Between me and my neck-verse, if I be</LINE>
<LINE>Called in question, for opening the king's letters.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was I that opened them, it was not thou.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but you need not care: and so must I,</LINE>
<LINE>A handsome man, be quickly trussed up,</LINE>
<LINE>And when a man is hanged, all the world cannot save him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He that hangs thee, were better hang his father,</LINE>
<LINE>Or that but hurts thee in the least degree.</LINE>
<LINE>I tell thee, we make great account of thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am overjoyed, I surfeit of sweet words:</LINE>
<LINE>Kind queen, had I a hundred lives, I would</LINE>
<LINE>Spend ninety-nine of them for you, for that word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but thou wouldst keep one life still,</LINE>
<LINE>And that is as many as thou art like to have.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That one life is not too dear for my good
queen; this sword, this buckler, this head, this heart,
these hands, arms, legs, tripes, bowels, and all the members
else whatsoever, are at your dispose; use me, trust me,
command me: if I fail in anything, tie me to a dung-cart,
and make a scavenger's horse of me, and whip me, so long as
I have any skin on my back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In token of further employment, take that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flings him a purse.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A strong bond, a firm obligation, good
in law, good in law: if I keep not the condition, let my
neck be the forfeiture of my negligence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I like thee well, thou hast a good tongue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And as bad a tongue if it be set on it, as
any oysterwife at Billingsgate hath: why, I have made many
of my neighbours forsake their houses with railing upon
them, and go dwell elsewhere; and so by my means houses have
been good cheap in our parish: my tongue being well whetted
with choler, is more sharp than a razor of Palermo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, thou art a fit man for my purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Commend me not, sweet queen, before you try me. as my deserts are, so do think of me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well said, then this is thy trial: instead
of carrying the king's letters to my father, carry thou
these letters to my sister, which contain matter quite
contrary to the other: there shall she be given to
understand, that my father hath detracted her, given out
slanderous speeches against her; that he hath most
intolerably abused me, set my lord and me at variance, and
made mutinies amongst the commons.</LINE>
<LINE>These things (although it be not so)</LINE>
<LINE>Yet thou must affirm them to be true,</LINE>
<LINE>With oaths and protestations as will serve</LINE>
<LINE>To drive my sister out of love with him,</LINE>
<LINE>And cause my will accomplished to be.</LINE>
<LINE>This do, thou winnest my favour for ever,</LINE>
<LINE>And makest a high way of preferment to thee</LINE>
<LINE>And all thy friends.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It sufficeth, conceit it is already done:</LINE>
<LINE>I will so tongue-whip him, that I will</LINE>
<LINE>Leave him as bare of credit, as a poulter</LINE>
<LINE>Leaves a cony, when she pulls off his skin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet there is a further matter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thirst to hear it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If my sister thinketh convenient, as my
letters importeth, to make him away, hast thou the heart to
effect it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Few words are best in so small a matter:</LINE>
<LINE>These are but trifles. By this book I will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>kisses the paper</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>About it presently, I long till it be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fly, I fly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act IV</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene I</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Cordella, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been over-negligent to-day,</LINE>
<LINE>In going to the temple of my God,</LINE>
<LINE>To render thanks for all his benefits,</LINE>
<LINE>Which he miraculously hath bestowed on me,</LINE>
<LINE>In raising me out of my mean estate,</LINE>
<LINE>Whenas I was devoid of worldly friends,</LINE>
<LINE>And placing me in such a sweet content,</LINE>
<LINE>As far exceeds the reach of my deserts.</LINE>
<LINE>My kingly husband, mirror of his time,</LINE>
<LINE>For zeal, for justice, kindness, and for care</LINE>
<LINE>To God, his subjects, me, and common weal,</LINE>
<LINE>By his appointment was ordained for me.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot wish the thing that I do want;</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot want the thing but I may have,</LINE>
<LINE>Save only this which I shall never obtain,</LINE>
<LINE>My father's love, oh this I never shall gain.</LINE>
<LINE>I would abstain from any nutriment,</LINE>
<LINE>And pine my body to the very bones:</LINE>
<LINE>Barefoot I would on pilgrimage set forth</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the furthest quarters of the earth,</LINE>
<LINE>And all my lifetime would I sackcloth wear,</LINE>
<LINE>And mourning-wise pour dust upon my head:</LINE>
<LINE>So he but to forgive me once would please,</LINE>
<LINE>That his gray hairs might go to heaven in peace.</LINE>
<LINE>And yet I know not how I him offended,</LINE>
<LINE>Or wherein justly I have deserved blame.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, sisters! you are much to blame in this,</LINE>
<LINE>It was not he, but you that did me wrong:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet God forgive both him, and you, and me;</LINE>
<LINE>Even as I do in perfit charity.</LINE>
<LINE>I will to church, and pray unto my Saviour,</LINE>
<LINE>That ere I die, I may obtain his favour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene II</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leir and Perillus, faintly.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Rest on me, my lord, and stay yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>The way seems tedious to your aged limbs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, rest on me, kind friend, and stay thyself,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art as old as I, but more kind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, good my lord, it ill befits, that I</LINE>
<LINE>Should lean upon the person of a King.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But it fits worse, that I should bring thee forth,</LINE>
<LINE>That had no cause to come along with me,</LINE>
<LINE>Through these uncouth paths, and tireful ways,</LINE>
<LINE>And never ease thy fainting limbs a whit.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast left all, ay, all to come with me,</LINE>
<LINE>And I, for all, have naught to guerdon thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cease, good my lord, to aggravate my woes,</LINE>
<LINE>With these kind words, which cuts my heart in two,</LINE>
<LINE>To think your will should want the power to do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cease, good Perillus, for to call me lord,</LINE>
<LINE>And think me but the shadow of myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That honourable title will I give,</LINE>
<LINE>Unto my lord, so long as I do live.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, be of comfort; for I see the place</LINE>
<LINE>Whereas your daughter keeps her residence.</LINE>
<LINE>And lo, in happy time the Cambrian prince</LINE>
<LINE>Is here arrived, to gratify our coming.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the prince of Cambria, Ragan, and nobles. Look upon them, and whisper together</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Were I best speak, or sit me down and die?</LINE>
<LINE>I am ashamed to tell this heavy tale.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then let me tell it, if you please, my lord:</LINE>
<LINE>It is shame for them that were the cause thereof.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What two old men are those that seem so sad?</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks, I should remember well their looks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I mistake not, sure it is my father:</LINE>
<LINE>I must dissemble kindness now of force.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>She runs to him, and kneels down, saying:</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Father, I bid you welcome, full of grief,</LINE>
<LINE>To see your grace used thus unworthily,</LINE>
<LINE>And ill befitting for your reverend age,</LINE>
<LINE>To come on foot a journey so endurable.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, what disaster chance hath been the cause,</LINE>
<LINE>To make your cheeks so hollow, spare and lean?</LINE>
<LINE>He cannot speak for weeping: for god's love, come.</LINE>
<LINE>Let us refresh him with some needful things,</LINE>
<LINE>And at more leisure we may better know,</LINE>
<LINE>Whence springs the ground of this unlooked-for woe.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, father, ere we any further talk,</LINE>
<LINE>You shall refresh you after this weary walk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt, manet Ragan</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Comes he to me with finger in the eye,</LINE>
<LINE>To tell a tale against my sister here?</LINE>
<LINE>Whom I do know, he greatly hath abused:</LINE>
<LINE>And now like a contentious crafty wretch,</LINE>
<LINE>He first begins for to complain himself,</LINE>
<LINE>Whenas himself is in the greatest fault?</LINE>
<LINE>I will not be partial in my sister's cause;</LINE>
<LINE>Nor yet believe his doting vain reports;</LINE>
<LINE>Who for a trifle (safely) I dare say,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon a spleen is stolen thence away:</LINE>
<LINE>And here (forsooth) he hopeth to have harbour,</LINE>
<LINE>And to be moaned and made on like a child:</LINE>
<LINE>But ere it be long, his coming he shall curse,</LINE>
<LINE>And truly say, he came from bad to worse:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet will I make fair wheather, to procure</LINE>
<LINE>Convenient means, and then I will strike it sure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene III</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Messenger, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now happily I am arrived here,</LINE>
<LINE>Before the stately palace of the Cambrian king:</LINE>
<LINE>If Leir be here safe-seated, and in rest,</LINE>
<LINE>To rouse him from it I will do my best.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Ragan</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Now bags of gold, your virtue is, no doubt</LINE>
<LINE>To make me in my message bold and stout.</LINE>
<LINE>The king of heaven preserve your Majesty.</LINE>
<LINE>And send your highness everlasting reign.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, good my friend; but what imports thy message?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kind greetings from the Cornwall queen:</LINE>
<LINE>The residue these letters will declare.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>She opens the letters</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How fares our royal sister?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did leave her, at my parting, in good health.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>She reads the letters, frowns and stamps</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>See how her colour comes and goes again</LINE>
<LINE>Now red as scarlet, now as pale as ash:</LINE>
<LINE>See how she knits her brow, and bites her lips,</LINE>
<LINE>And stamps, and makes a dumb show of disdain,</LINE>
<LINE>Mixed with revenge, and violent extremes.</LINE>
<LINE>Here will be more work and more crowns for me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, poor soul, and hath he used her thus?</LINE>
<LINE>And is he now come hither, with intent</LINE>
<LINE>To set divorce betwixt my lord and me?</LINE>
<LINE>Doth he give out, that he doth hear report,</LINE>
<LINE>That I do rule my husband as I list,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore means to alter so the case,</LINE>
<LINE>That I shall know my lord to be my head?</LINE>
<LINE>Well, it were best for him to take good heed,</LINE>
<LINE>Or I will make him hop without a head,</LINE>
<LINE>For his presumption, dottard that he is.</LINE>
<LINE>In Cornwall he hath made such mutinies,</LINE>
<LINE>First, setting of the king against the queen;</LINE>
<LINE>Then stirring up the commons against the king;</LINE>
<LINE>That had he there continued any longer,</LINE>
<LINE>He had been called in question for his fact.</LINE>
<LINE>So upon that occasion thence he fled,</LINE>
<LINE>And comes thus slyly stealing unto us;</LINE>
<LINE>And now already since his coming hither,</LINE>
<LINE>My lord and he are grown in such a league,</LINE>
<LINE>That I can have no conference with his grace:</LINE>
<LINE>I fear, he doth already intimate</LINE>
<LINE>Some forged cavillations against my state:</LINE>
<LINE>It is therefore best to cut him off in time,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest slanderous rumours once abroad dispersed,</LINE>
<LINE>It is to late for them to be reversed.</LINE>
<LINE>Friend, as the tenour of these letters shows,</LINE>
<LINE>My sister puts great confidence in thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She never yet committed trust to me,</LINE>
<LINE>But that, I hope, she found me always faithful:</LINE>
<LINE>So will I be to any friend of hers,</LINE>
<LINE>That hath occasion to employ my help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hast thou the heart to act a stratagem,</LINE>
<LINE>And give a stab or two, if need require?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have a heart compact of adamant,</LINE>
<LINE>Which never knew what melting pity meant.</LINE>
<LINE>I weigh no more the murdering of a man,</LINE>
<LINE>Than I respect the cracking of a flea,</LINE>
<LINE>When I do catch her biting on my skin.</LINE>
<LINE>If you will have your husband or your father,</LINE>
<LINE>Or both of them sent to another world,</LINE>
<LINE>Do but command me do it, it shall be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is enough, we make no doubt of thee:</LINE>
<LINE>Meet us tomorrow here, at nine o'clock:</LINE>
<LINE>Meanwhile, farewell, and drink that for my sake.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, this is it will make me do the deed:</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, had I every day such customers,</LINE>
<LINE>This were the gainfullest trade in Christendom!</LINE>
<LINE>A purse of gold given for a paltry stab.</LINE>
<LINE>Why, here's a wench that longs to have a stab.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, I could give it her, and never hurt her neither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene IV</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Gallian king, and Cordella.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When will these clouds of sorrow once disperse,</LINE>
<LINE>And smiling joy triumph upon thy brow?</LINE>
<LINE>When will this</LINE>
<LINE>Scene of sadness have an end,</LINE>
<LINE>And pleasant acts ensue, to move delight?</LINE>
<LINE>When will my lovely queen cease to lament,</LINE>
<LINE>And take some comfort to her grieved thoughts?</LINE>
<LINE>If of thyself thou deign'st to have no care,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet pity me, whom thy grief makes despair.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, grieve not you, my lord, you have no cause;</LINE>
<LINE>Let not my passions move your mind a whit:</LINE>
<LINE>For I am bound by nature to lament</LINE>
<LINE>For his ill will, that life to me first lent.</LINE>
<LINE>If so the stock be dried with disdain,</LINE>
<LINE>Withered and sere the branch must needs remain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But thou art now graft in another stock;</LINE>
<LINE>I am the stock, and thou the lovely branch:</LINE>
<LINE>And from my root continual sap shall flow,</LINE>
<LINE>To make thee flourish with perpetual spring.</LINE>
<LINE>Forget thy father and thy kindred now,</LINE>
<LINE>Since they forsake thee like inhuman beasts,</LINE>
<LINE>Think they are dead, since all their kindness dies,</LINE>
<LINE>And bury them, where black oblivion lies.</LINE>
<LINE>Think not thou art the daughter of old Leir,</LINE>
<LINE>Who did unkindly disinherit thee:</LINE>
<LINE>But think thou art the noble Gallian queen,</LINE>
<LINE>And wise to him that dearly loveth thee:</LINE>
<LINE>Embrace the joys that present with thee dwell,</LINE>
<LINE>Let sorrow pack and hide herself in hell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not that I miss my country or my kin,</LINE>
<LINE>My old acquaintance or my ancient friends,</LINE>
<LINE>Doth any whit distemperate my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Knowing you, which are more dear to me,</LINE>
<LINE>Than country, kin, and all things else can be.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet pardon me, my gracious lord, in this:</LINE>
<LINE>For what can stop the course of Nature's power?</LINE>
<LINE>As easy is it for four-footed beasts,</LINE>
<LINE>To stay themselves upon the liquid air,</LINE>
<LINE>And mount aloft into the element,</LINE>
<LINE>And overstrip the feathered fowls in flight:</LINE>
<LINE>As easy is it for the slimy fish,</LINE>
<LINE>To live and thrive without the help of water:</LINE>
<LINE>As easy is it for the blackamoor,</LINE>
<LINE>To wash the tawny colour from his skin,</LINE>
<LINE>Which all oppose against the course of nature,</LINE>
<LINE>As I am able to forget my father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mirror of virtue, Phoenix of our age!</LINE>
<LINE>Too kind a daughter for an unkind father,</LINE>
<LINE>Be of good comfort; for I will dispatch</LINE>
<LINE>Ambassadors immediately for Britain,</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the king of Cornwall's court, whereas</LINE>
<LINE>Your father keepeth now his residence,</LINE>
<LINE>And in the kindest manner him entreat,</LINE>
<LINE>That setting former grievances apart,</LINE>
<LINE>He will be pleased to come and visit us.</LINE>
<LINE>If no entreaty will suffice the turn,</LINE>
<LINE>I will offer him the half of all my crown:</LINE>
<LINE>If that moves not, we will furnish out a fleet,</LINE>
<LINE>And sail to Cornwall for to visit him;</LINE>
<LINE>And there you shall be firmly reconciled</LINE>
<LINE>In perfit love, as erst you were before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where tongue cannot sufficient thanks afford,</LINE>
<LINE>The king of heaven remunerate my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only be blithe and frolic, sweet, with me;</LINE> 
<LINE>This and much more I will do to comfort thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene V</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Messenger, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is a world to see now I am flush,</LINE>
<LINE>How many friends I purchase everywhere!</LINE>
<LINE>How many seeks to creep into my favour,</LINE>
<LINE>And kiss their hands, and bend their knees to me!</LINE>
<LINE>No more, here comes the queen, now shall I know her mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And hope for to derive more crowns from her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Ragan</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My friend, I see thou mindest thy promise well,</LINE>
<LINE>And art before me here, methinks, today.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a poor man, and it like your grace;</LINE>
<LINE>But yet I always love to keep my word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, keep thy word with me, and thou shalt see,</LINE>
<LINE>That of a poor man I will make thee rich.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I long to hear it, it might have been dispatched,</LINE>
<LINE>If you had told me of it yesternight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is a thing of right strange consequence,</LINE>
<LINE>And well I cannot utter it in words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is more strange, that I am not by this</LINE>
<LINE>Beside myself, with longing for to hear it.</LINE>
<LINE>Were it to meet the devil in his den,</LINE>
<LINE>And try a bout with him for a scratched face,</LINE>
<LINE>I would undertake it, if you would but bid me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, good my friend, that I should have thee do,</LINE>
<LINE>Is such a thing, as I do shame to speak;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet it must needs be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will speak it for thee, queen: shall I kill thy father?</LINE>
<LINE>I know it is that, and if it be so, say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, that is enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And yet that is not all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou must kill that old man that came with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here are two hands, for each of them is one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And for each hand here is a recompense.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Gives him two purses</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, that I had ten hands by miracle!</LINE>
<LINE>I could tear ten in pieces with my teeth,</LINE>
<LINE>So in my mouth you'ld put a purse of gold.</LINE>
<LINE>But in what manner must it be effected?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tomorrow morning ere the break of day,</LINE>
<LINE>I by a wile will send them to the thicket,</LINE>
<LINE>That is about some two miles from the court,</LINE>
<LINE>And promise them to meet them there myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I must have private conference,</LINE>
<LINE>About some news I have received from Cornwall.</LINE>
<LINE>This is enough, I know, they will not fail,</LINE>
<LINE>And then be ready for to play thy part:</LINE>
<LINE>Which done, thou mayest right easily escape,</LINE>
<LINE>And no man once mistrust thee for the fact:</LINE>
<LINE>But yet, before thou prosecute the act,</LINE>
<LINE>Show him the letter, which my sister sent,</LINE>
<LINE>There let him read his own indictment first,</LINE>
<LINE>And then proceed to execution:</LINE>
<LINE>But see thou faint not; for they will speak fair.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Could he speak words as pleasing as the pipe</LINE>
<LINE>Of Mercury, which charmed the hundred eyes</LINE>
<LINE>Of watchful Argos, and enforced him sleep:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet here are words so pleasing to my thoughts,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To the purse:</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>As quite shall take away the sound of his.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>About it then, and when thou hast dispatched,</LINE>
<LINE>I will find a means to send thee after him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VI</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Cornwall and Gonorill.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wonder that the messenger doth stay,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom we dispatched for Cambria so long since:</LINE>
<LINE>If that his answer do not please us well,</LINE>
<LINE>And he do shew good reason for delay,</LINE>
<LINE>I will teach him how to dally with his king,</LINE>
<LINE>And to detain us in such long suspense.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, I think the reason may be this:</LINE>
<LINE>My father means to come along with him;</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore it is his pleasure he shall stay,</LINE>
<LINE>For to attend upon him on the way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It may be so, and therefore till I know</LINE>
<LINE>The truth thereof, I will suspend my judgment.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Servant</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SERVANT.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An' it like your grace, there is an ambassador</LINE>
<LINE>Arrived from Gallia, and craves admittance to your majesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>From Gallia? what should his message</LINE>
<LINE>Hither import? is not your father haply</LINE>
<LINE>Gone thither? well, whatsoever it be,</LINE>
<LINE>Bid him come in, he shall have audience.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Ambassador</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What news from Gallia? speak ambassador.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The noble king and queen of Gallia first salutes,</LINE>
<LINE>By me, their honourable father, my lord Leir:</LINE>
<LINE>Next, they commend them kindly to your graces,</LINE>
<LINE>As those whose welfare they entirely wish.</LINE>
<LINE>Letters I have to deliver to my lord Leir,</LINE>
<LINE>And presents too, if I might speak with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you might speak with him? why, do you think,</LINE>
<LINE>We are afraid that you should speak with him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon me, madam; for I think not so,</LINE>
<LINE>But say so only, because he is not here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, my friend, upon some urgent cause,</LINE>
<LINE>He is at this time absent from the court:</LINE>
<LINE>But if a day or two you here repose,</LINE>
<LINE>It is very likely you shall have him here,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else have certain notice where he is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are not we worthy to receive your message?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had in charge to do it to himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It may be then it will not be done in
haste. <STAGEDIR>to herself</STAGEDIR>
How doth my sister brook the air of France?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Exceeding well, and never sick one hour,</LINE>
<LINE>Since first she set her foot upon the shore.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am the more sorry.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope, not so, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Didst thou not say, that she was ever sick,</LINE>
<LINE>Since the first hour that she arrived there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, madam, I said quite contrary.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then I mistook thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then she is merry, if she have her health.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh no, her grief exceeds, until the time,</LINE>
<LINE>That she be reconciled unto her father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God continue it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, her health.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen to that: but god release her grief,</LINE>
<LINE>And send her father in a better mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Than to continue always so unkind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will be a mediator in her cause,</LINE>
<LINE>And seek all means to expiate his wrath.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I hope your grace will do the like.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Should I be a mean to exasperate his wrath</LINE>
<LINE>Against my sister, whom I love so dear? no, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To expiate or mitigate his wrath:</LINE>
<LINE>For he hath misconceived without a cause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, ay, what else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is pity it should be so, would it were otherwise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were great pity it should be otherwise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Than how, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Than that they should be reconciled again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shows you bear an honourable mind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shows thy understanding to be blind,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>speaks to herself</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And that thou hadst need of an interpreter:</LINE>
<LINE>Well, I will know thy message ere it be long,</LINE>
<LINE>And find a mean to cross it, if I can.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come in, my friend, and frolic in our court,</LINE>
<LINE>Till certain notice of my father come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VII</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leir and Perillus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, you are up today before your hour,</LINE>
<LINE>It is news to you to be abroad so rathe.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is news indeed, I am so extreme heavy,</LINE>
<LINE>That I can scarcely keep my eyelids open.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so am I, but I impute the cause</LINE>
<LINE>To rising sooner than we use to do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hither my daughter means to come disguised:</LINE>
<LINE>I will sit me down, and read until she come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>pulls out a book and sits down</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She will not be long, I warrant you, my lord:</LINE>
<LINE>But say, a couple of these they call good fellows,</LINE>
<LINE>Should step out of a hedge, and set upon us,</LINE>
<LINE>We were in good case for to answer them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were not for us to stand upon our hands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear, we scant should stand upon our legs.</LINE>
<LINE>But how should we do to defend ourselves?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even pray to god, to bless us from their hands:</LINE>
<LINE>For fervent prayer much ill hap withstands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will sit and pray with you for company;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet was I never so heavy in my life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They both fall asleep</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter the Messenger (murderer), with two daggers in hand</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Were it not a mad jest, if two or
three of my profession should meet me, and lay me down in a
ditch, and play rob thief with me, and perforce take my gold
away from me, whilst I act this stratagem, and by this means
the graybeards should escape? faith, when I were at liberty
again, I would make no more to do, but go to the next tree,
and there hang myself.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Sees them, and begins</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>But stay, methinks my youths are here already,</LINE>
<LINE>And with pure zeal have prayed themselves asleep.</LINE>
<LINE>I think, they know to what intent they came,</LINE>
<LINE>And are provided for another world.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>He takes their books away</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Now could I stab them bravely, while they sleep,</LINE>
<LINE>And in a manner put them to no pain;</LINE>
<LINE>And doing so, I showed them mighty friendship:</LINE>
<LINE>For fear of death is worse than death itself.</LINE>
<LINE>But that my sweet queen willed me for to show</LINE>
<LINE>This letter to them, ere I did the deed.</LINE>
<LINE>Mass, they begin to stir: I will stand aside;</LINE>
<LINE>So shall I come upon them unawares.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They wake and rise</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I marvel that my daughter stays so long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear, we did mistake the place, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God grant we do not miscarry in the place:</LINE>
<LINE>I had a short nap, but so full of dread,</LINE>
<LINE>As much amazeth me to think thereof.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not, my lord, dreams are but fantasies,</LINE>
<LINE>And slight imaginations of the brain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Persuade him so; but I will make him and you</LINE>
<LINE>Confess, that dreams do often prove too true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray, my lord, what was the effect of it?</LINE>
<LINE>I may go near to guess what it portends.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Leave that to me, I will expound the dream.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methought, my daughters, Gonorill and Ragan,</LINE>
<LINE>Stood both before me with such grim aspects,</LINE>
<LINE>Each brandishing a falchion in their hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Ready to lop a limb off where it fell,</LINE>
<LINE>And in their other hands a naked poniard,</LINE>
<LINE>Wherewith they stabbed me in a hundred places,</LINE>
<LINE>And to their thinking left me there for dead:</LINE>
<LINE>But then my youngest daughter, fair Cordella,</LINE>
<LINE>Came with a box of balsam in her hand,</LINE>
<LINE>And poured it into my bleeding wounds,</LINE>
<LINE>By whose good means I was recovered well,</LINE>
<LINE>In perfect health, as erst I was before:</LINE>
<LINE>And with the fear of this I did awake,</LINE>
<LINE>And yet for fear my feeble joints do quake.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will make you quake for something presently.</LINE>
<LINE>Stand, stand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They reel</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We do, my friend, although with much ado.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Deliver, deliver.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Deliver us, good lord, from such as he.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You should have prayed before, while it was time,</LINE>
<LINE>And then perhaps, you might have escaped my hands:</LINE>
<LINE>But you, like faithful watch-men, fell asleep,</LINE>
<LINE>The whilst I came and took your halberds from you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Shows their books</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>And now you want your weapons of defense,</LINE>
<LINE>How have you any hope to be delivered?</LINE>
<LINE>This comes, because you have no better stay,</LINE>
<LINE>But fall asleep, when you should watch and pray.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My friend, thou seemest to be a proper man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Sblood, how the old slave claws me by the elbow?</LINE>
<LINE>He thinks, belike, to escape by scraping thus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And it may be, are in some need of money.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That to be false, behold my evidence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Shows his purses</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If that I have will do thee any good,</LINE>
<LINE>I give it thee, even with a right good will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Messenger takes it</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, take mine too, and wish with all my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>To do thee pleasure, it were twice as much.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>The messenger takes his, and weighs both in his hands</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll none of them, they are too light for me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>
<STAGEDIR>Puts them in his pocket</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why then farewell: and if thou have occasion</LINE>
<LINE>In anything, to use me to the queen,</LINE>
<LINE>It is like enough that I can pleasure thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They proffer to go</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear, do your hear, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>If I had occasion to use you to the queen,</LINE>
<LINE>Would you do one thing for me I should ask?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, anything that lies within my power.</LINE>
<LINE>Here is my hand upon it, so farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>proffers to go</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear you sir, hear you? pray, a word with you.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks, a comely honest ancient man</LINE>
<LINE>Should not dissemble with one for a vantage.</LINE>
<LINE>I know, when I shall come to try this gear,</LINE>
<LINE>You will recant from all that you have said.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mistrust not him, but try him when thou wilt:</LINE>
<LINE>He is her father, therefore may do much.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know he is, and therefore mean to try him:</LINE>
<LINE>You are his friend too, I must try you both.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BOTH.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee do, prithee do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>proffer to go out</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay graybeards then, and prove men of your words:</LINE>
<LINE>The queen hath tied me by a solemn oath,</LINE>
<LINE>Here in this place to see you both dispatched:</LINE>
<LINE>Now for the safeguard of my conscience,</LINE>
<LINE>Do me the pleasure for to kill yourselves:</LINE>
<LINE>So shall you save me labour for to do it,</LINE>
<LINE>And prove yourselves true old men of your words.</LINE>
<LINE>And here I vow in sight of all the world,</LINE>
<LINE>I never will trouble you whilst I live again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Affright us not with terror, good my friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor strike such fear into our aged hearts.</LINE>
<LINE>Play not the cat, which dallieth with the mouse;</LINE>
<LINE>And on a sudden maketh her a prey:</LINE>
<LINE>But if thou art marked for the man of death</LINE>
<LINE>To me and to my Damion, tell me plain,</LINE>
<LINE>That we may be prepared for the stroke,</LINE>
<LINE>And make ourselves fit for the world to come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am the last of any mortal race,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever your eyes are likely to behold,</LINE>
<LINE>And hither sent of purpose to this place,</LINE>
<LINE>To give a final period to your days,</LINE>
<LINE>Which are so wicked, and have lived so long,</LINE>
<LINE>That your own children seek to short your life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Camest thou from France, of purpose to do this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>From France? Zounds, do I look like a
Frenchman? sure I have.not mine own face on; somebody hath
changed faces with me, and I know not of it: but I am sure,
my apparel is all English. Sirra, what meanest thou to ask
that question? I could spoil the fashion of this face for
anger. A French face!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Because my daughter, whom I have offended,</LINE>
<LINE>And at whose hands I have deserved as ill,</LINE>
<LINE>As ever any father did of child,</LINE>
<LINE>Is Queen of France, no thanks at all to me,</LINE>
<LINE>But unto god, who my injustice see.</LINE>
<LINE>If it be so, that she doth seek revenge,</LINE>
<LINE>As with good reason she may justly do,</LINE>
<LINE>I will most willingly resign my life,</LINE>
<LINE>A sacrifice to mitigate her ire:</LINE>
<LINE>I never will entreat thee to forgive,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I am unworthy for to live.</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore speak soon, and I will soon make speed;</LINE>
<LINE>Whether Cordella willed thee do this deed?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As I am a perfect gentleman, thou speakest French to me:</LINE>
<LINE>I never heard Cordella's name before,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor never was in France in all my life:</LINE>
<LINE>I never knew thou hadst a daughter there,</LINE>
<LINE>To whom thou didst prove so unkind a churl:</LINE>
<LINE>But thy own tongue declares that thou hast been</LINE>
<LINE>A vile old wretch, and full of heinous sin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, no, my friend, thou art deceived much:</LINE>
<LINE>For her except, whom I confess I wronged,</LINE>
<LINE>Through doting frenzy, and over-jealous love.</LINE>
<LINE>There lives not any under heaven's bright eye,</LINE>
<LINE>That can convict me of impiety.</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore sure thou dost mistake the mark:</LINE>
<LINE>For I am in true peace with all the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are the fitter for the king of heaven:</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore, for to rid thee of suspense,</LINE>
<LINE>Know thou, the Queens of Cambria and Cornwall,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy own two daughters, Gonorill and Ragan,</LINE>
<LINE>Appointed me to massacre thee here.</LINE>
<LINE>Why wouldst thou then persuade me, that thou art</LINE>
<LINE>In charity with all the world? but now</LINE>
<LINE>When thy own issue hold thee in such hate,</LINE>
<LINE>That they have hired me to abridge thy fate,</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, fie upon such vile dissembling breath,</LINE>
<LINE>That would deceive, even at the point of death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Am I awake, or is it but a dream?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear nothing, man, thou art but in a dream,</LINE>
<LINE>And thou shalt never wake until doomsday,</LINE>
<LINE>By then, I hope, thou wilt have slept enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet, gentle friend, grant one thing ere I die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will grant you anything, except your lives.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, but assure me by some certain token,</LINE>
<LINE>That my two daughters hired thee to this deed:</LINE>
<LINE>If I were once resolved of that, then I</LINE>
<LINE>Would wish no longer life, but crave to die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That to be true, in sight of heaven I swear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Swear not by heaven, for fear of punishment:</LINE>
<LINE>The heavens are guiltless of such heinous acts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I swear by earth, the mother of us all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Swear not by earth; for she abhors to bear</LINE>
<LINE>Such bastards, as are murderers of her sons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why then, by hell, and all the devils I swear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Swear not by hell; for that stands gaping wide,</LINE>
<LINE>To swallow thee, and if thou do this deed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Thunder and lightning</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would that word were in his belly again,</LINE>
<LINE>It hath frighted me even to the very heart:</LINE>
<LINE>This old man is some strong magician:</LINE>
<LINE>His words have turned my mind from this exploit.</LINE>
<LINE>Then neither heaven, earth, nor hell be witness;</LINE>
<LINE>But let this paper witness for them all.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Shows Gonorill's letter</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Shall I relent, or shall I prosecute?</LINE>
<LINE>Shall I resolve or were I best recant?</LINE>
<LINE>I will not crack my credit with two queens,</LINE>
<LINE>To whom I have already passed my word.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, but my conscience for this act doth tell,</LINE>
<LINE>I get heaven's hate, earth's scorn, and pains of hell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They bless themselves</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh just Jehovah, whose almighty power</LINE>
<LINE>Doth govern all things in this spacious world,</LINE>
<LINE>How canst thou suffer such outrageous acts</LINE>
<LINE>To be committed without just revenge?</LINE>
<LINE>O viperous generation and accursed,</LINE>
<LINE>To seek his blood, whose blood did make them first!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, my true friend in all extremity,</LINE>
<LINE>Let us submit us to the will of god:</LINE>
<LINE>Things past all sense, let us not seek to know;</LINE>
<LINE>It is god's will, and therefore must be so.</LINE>
<LINE>My friend, I am prepared for the stroke:</LINE>
<LINE>Strike when thou wilt, and I forgive thee here,</LINE>
<LINE>Even from the very bottom of my heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I am not prepared for to strike.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, Perillus, even the truest friend,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever lived in adversity:</LINE>
<LINE>The latest kindness I will request of thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Is that thou go unto my daughter Cordella,</LINE>
<LINE>And carry her her father's latest blessing:</LINE>
<LINE>Withal desire her, that she will forgive me;</LINE>
<LINE>For I have wronged her without any cause.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, lord, receive me, for I come to thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And die, I hope, in perfect charity.</LINE>
<LINE>Dispatch, I pray thee, I have lived too long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but you are unwise, to send an errand</LINE>
<LINE>By him that never meaneth to deliver it:</LINE>
<LINE>Why, he must go along with you to heaven:</LINE>
<LINE>It were not good you should go all alone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No doubt, he shall, when by the course of nature,</LINE>
<LINE>He must surrender up his due to death:</LINE>
<LINE>But that time shall not come till god permit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, presently, to bear you company.</LINE>
<LINE>I have a passport for him in my pocket,</LINE>
<LINE>Already sealed, and he must needs ride post.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Shows a bag of money</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The letter which I read, imports not so,</LINE>
<LINE>It only toucheth me; no word of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but the queen commands it must be so,</LINE>
<LINE>And I am paid for him, as well as you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I, who have borne you company in life,</LINE>
<LINE>Most willingly will bear a share in death.</LINE>
<LINE>It skilleth not for me, my friend, a whit,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor for a hundred such as thou and I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, but it doth, sir, by your leave;
your good days are past:though it be no matter for you, it
is a matter for me, proper men are not so rife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, but beware, how thou dost lay thy hand</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the high anointed of the Lord:</LINE>
<LINE>O, be advised ere thou dost begin:</LINE>
<LINE>Dispatch me straight, but meddle not with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Friend, thy commission is to deal with me,</LINE>
<LINE>And I am he that hath deserved all:</LINE>
<LINE>The plot was laid to take away my life:</LINE>
<LINE>And here it is, I do entreat thee take it:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet for my sake, and as thou art a man,</LINE>
<LINE>Spare this my friend, that hither with me came:</LINE>
<LINE>I brought him forth, whereas he had not been,</LINE>
<LINE>But for good-will to bear me company.</LINE>
<LINE>He left his friends, his country and his goods,</LINE>
<LINE>And came with me in most extremity.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, if he should miscarry here and die,</LINE>
<LINE>Who is the cause of it, but only I?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why that am I, let that never trouble thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O no, 'tis I. O, had I now to give thee</LINE>
<LINE>The monarchy of all the spacious world</LINE>
<LINE>To save his life, I would bestow it on thee:</LINE>
<LINE>But I have nothing but these tears and prayers,</LINE>
<LINE>And the submission of a bended knee.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>kneels</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>O, if all this to mercy move thy mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Spare him, in heaven thou shalt like mercy find.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am as hard to be moved as another, and yet methinks the</LINE>
<LINE>Strength of their persuasions stirs me a little.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My friend, if fear of the almighty power</LINE>
<LINE>Have power to move thee, we have said enough:</LINE>
<LINE>But if thy mind be moveable with gold,</LINE>
<LINE>We have not presently to give it thee:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet to thyself thou mayest do greater good,</LINE>
<LINE>To keep thy hands still undefiled from blood:</LINE>
<LINE>For do but well consider with thyself,</LINE>
<LINE>When thou hast finished this outrageous act,</LINE>
<LINE>What horror still will haunt thee for the deed:</LINE>
<LINE>Think this again, that they which would incense</LINE>
<LINE>Thee for to be the butcher of their father,</LINE>
<LINE>When it is done, for fear it should be known,</LINE>
<LINE>Would make a means to rid thee from the world:</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, then art thou forever tied in chains</LINE>
<LINE>Of everlasting torments to endure,</LINE>
<LINE>Even in the hottest hole of grisly hell,</LINE>
<LINE>Such pains, as never mortal tongue can tell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>It thunders, he quakes and lets fall the dagger next to Perillus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, heavens be thanked, he will spare my friend.</LINE>
<LINE>Now when thou wilt come make an end of me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>He lets fall the other dagger.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, happy fight! he means to save my lord.</LINE>
<LINE>The king of heaven continue this good mind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why stayest thou to do execution?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am as willful as you for your life</LINE>
<LINE>I will not do it, now you do entreat me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, now I see thou hast some spark of grace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSENGER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beshrew you for it, you have put it in me:</LINE>
<LINE>The parlousest old men, that ever I heard.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, to be flat, I will not meddle with you:</LINE>
<LINE>Here I found you, and here I will leave you:</LINE>
<LINE>If any ask you why the case so stands?</LINE>
<LINE>Say that your tongues were better than your hands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit. Dresse</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell. If ever we together meet,</LINE>
<LINE>It shall go hard, but I will thee regreet.</LINE>
<LINE>Courage, my lord, the worst is overpast;</LINE>
<LINE>Let us give thanks to God, and hie us hence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art deceived; for I am past the best,</LINE>
<LINE>And know not whither for to go from hence:</LINE>
<LINE>Death had been better welcome unto me,</LINE>
<LINE>Than longer life to add more misery.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were not good to return from whence we came,</LINE>
<LINE>Unto your daughter Ragan back again.</LINE>
<LINE>Now let us go to France, unto Cordella,</LINE>
<LINE>Your youngest daughter, doubtless she will succour you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, how can I persuade myself of that,</LINE>
<LINE>Since the other two are quite devoid of love;</LINE>
<LINE>To whom I was so kind, as that my gifts,</LINE>
<LINE>Might make them love, if it were nothing else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No worldly gifts, but grace from God on high,</LINE>
<LINE>Doth nourish virtue and true charity.</LINE>
<LINE>Remember well what words Cordella spake,</LINE>
<LINE>What time you asked her, how she loved your grace,</LINE>
<LINE>She said, her love unto you was as much,</LINE>
<LINE>As ought a child to bear unto her father.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But she did find, my love was not to her,</LINE>
<LINE>As should a father bear unto a child.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That makes her love not to be any less,</LINE>
<LINE>If she do love you as a child should do:</LINE>
<LINE>You have tried two, try one more for my sake,</LINE>
<LINE>I will never entreat you further trial make.</LINE>
<LINE>Remember well the dream you had of late,</LINE>
<LINE>And think what comfort it foretells to us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, truest friend, that ever man possessed,</LINE>
<LINE>I know thou counsellest all things for the best:</LINE>
<LINE>If this third daughter play a kinder part,</LINE>
<LINE>It comes of God, and not of my desert.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VIII</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Gallian Ambassador, solus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is of late news come unto the court,</LINE>
<LINE>That old lord Leir remains in Cambria:</LINE>
<LINE>I will hie me thither presently, to impart</LINE>
<LINE>My letters and my message unto him.</LINE>
<LINE>I never was less welcome to a place</LINE>
<LINE>In all my lifetime, than I have been hither,</LINE>
<LINE>Especially unto the stately queen,</LINE>
<LINE>Who would not cast one gracious look on me,</LINE>
<LINE>But still with lowering and suspicious eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Would take exceptions at each word I spake,</LINE>
<LINE>And fain she would have undermined me,</LINE>
<LINE>To know what my ambassage did import:</LINE>
<LINE>But she is like to hop without her hope,</LINE>
<LINE>Though, by report, shall have it in all things else.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, I will post away for Cambria:</LINE>
<LINE>Within these few days I hope to be there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT>
<ACTTITLE>Act V</ACTTITLE>
<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene I</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the king and queen of Gallia, and Mumford.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By this, our father understands our mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And our kind greetings sent to him of late:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore my mind presageth ere it be long,</LINE>
<LINE>We shall receive from Britain happy news.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I fear, my sister will dissuade his mind;</LINE>
<LINE>For she to me hath always been unkind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not, my love, since that we know the worst,</LINE>
<LINE>The last means helps, if that we miss the first:</LINE>
<LINE>If he will not come to Gallia unto us,</LINE>
<LINE>Then we will sail to Britain unto him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, if I once see Britain again, I have
sworn, I will never come home without my wench, and I will
not be forsworn, I will rather never come home while I
live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you sure, Mumford, she is a maid still?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I will not swear she is a maid, but she
goes for one: I will take her at all adventures, if I can
get her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, that is well put in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well put in? Nay, it was ill put in; for had
it been as well put in, as ever I put in, in my days, I
would have made her follow me to France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, you would have been so kind, as take
her with you, or else, were I as she, I would have been so
loving, as I would stay behind you: Yet I must confess, you
are a very proper man, and able to make a wench do more than
she would do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I have a pair of slops for the nonce,</LINE>
<LINE>Will hold all your mocks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, we see you have a handsome hose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and of the newest fashion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>More bobs, more: put them in still, they
will serve instead of bombast, yet put not in too many, lest
the seams crack, and they fly out amongst you again: You
must not think to outface me so easily in my mistress'
quarrel, who if I see once again, ten team of horses shall
not draw me away, till I have full and whole possession.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but one team and a cart will serve the turn.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not only for him, but also for his wench.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, you are two to one, I will give you over:</LINE>
<LINE>And since I see you so pleasantly disposed,</LINE>
<LINE>Which indeed is but seldom seen, I will claim</LINE>
<LINE>A promise of you, which you shall not deny me:</LINE>
<LINE>For promise is debt, and by this hand you promised it me.</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore you owe it me, and you shall pay it me,</LINE>
<LINE>Or I will sue you upon an action of unkindness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, lord Mumford, what promise did I make thee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, nothing but this,</LINE>
<LINE>That the next fair weather, which is very now,</LINE>
<LINE>You would go in progress down to the seaside,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is very near.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, in this motion I will join with thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And be a mediator to my queen.</LINE>
<LINE>Prithee, my love, let this match go forward,</LINE>
<LINE>My mind foretells, it will be a lucky voyage.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Entreaty needs not, where you may command,</LINE>
<LINE>So you be pleased, I am right well content;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, as the sea I much desire to see;</LINE>
<LINE>So am I most unwilling to be seen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will go disguised, all unknown to any.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Howsoever you make one, I will make another.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I the third: oh, I am over-joyed!</LINE>
<LINE>See what love is, which getteth with a word,</LINE>
<LINE>What all the world besides could never obtain!</LINE>
<LINE>But what disguises shall we have, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith thus: my queen and I will be disguised,</LINE>
<LINE>Like a plain country couple, and you shall be Roger,</LINE>
<LINE>Our man, and wait upon us: or if you will,</LINE>
<LINE>You shall go first, and we will wait on you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were more than time; this device is excellent.</LINE>
<LINE>Come let us about it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene II</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Cambria and Ragan with nobles.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What strange mischance or unexpected hap</LINE>
<LINE>Hath thus deprived us of our father's presence?</LINE>
<LINE>Can no man tell us what is become of him,</LINE>
<LINE>With whom we did converse not two days since?</LINE>
<LINE>My lords, let everywhere light horse be sent,</LINE>
<LINE>And scour about through all our regiment.</LINE>
<LINE>Dispatch a post immediately to Cornwall,</LINE>
<LINE>To see if any news be of him there;</LINE>
<LINE>Myself will make a strict enquiry here,</LINE>
<LINE>And all about our cities near at hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Till certain news of his abode be brought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All sorrow is but counterfeit to mine,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose lips are almost sealed up with grief:</LINE>
<LINE>Mine is the substance, whilst they do but seem</LINE>
<LINE>To weep the loss, which tears cannot redeem.</LINE>
<LINE>O, never was heard so strange a misadventure,</LINE>
<LINE>A thing so far beyond the reach of sense,</LINE>
<LINE>Since no man's reason in the cause can enter.</LINE>
<LINE>What hath removed my father thus from hence?</LINE>
<LINE>O, I do fear some charm or invocation</LINE>
<LINE>Of wicked spirits, or infernal fiends,</LINE>
<LINE>Stirred by Cordella, moves this innovation,</LINE>
<LINE>And brings my father timeless to his end.</LINE>
<LINE>But might I know, that the detested witch</LINE>
<LINE>Were certain cause of this uncertain ill,</LINE>
<LINE>Myself to France would go in some disguise,</LINE>
<LINE>And with these nails scratch out her hateful eyes:</LINE>
<LINE>For since I am deprived of my father,</LINE>
<LINE>I loath my life, and wish my death the rather.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The heavens are just, and hate impiety,</LINE>
<LINE>And will, no doubt, reveal such heinous crimes:</LINE>
<LINE>Censure not any, till you know the right:</LINE>
<LINE>Let him be judge, that bringeth truth to light.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, but my grief, like to a swelling tide,</LINE>
<LINE>Exceeds the bounds of common patience:</LINE>
<LINE>Nor can I moderate my tongue so much,</LINE>
<LINE>To conceal them, whom I hold in suspect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This matter shall be sifted: if it be she,</LINE>
<LINE>A thousand Frances shall not harbour her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All happiness unto the Cambrian king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome, my friend, from whence is thy Ambassage?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I came from Gallia, unto Cornwall sent,</LINE>
<LINE>With letters to your honourable father,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom there not finding, as I did expect,</LINE>
<LINE>I was directed hither to repair.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Frenchman, what is thy message to my father?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My letters, madam, will import the same,</LINE>
<LINE>Which my commission is for to deliver.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In his absence you may trust us with your letters.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must perform my charge in such a manner,</LINE>
<LINE>As I have strict commandment from the king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is good packing betwixt your king and you:</LINE>
<LINE>You need not hither come to ask for him,</LINE>
<LINE>You know where he is better than ourselves.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I hope not far off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath the young murderess, your outrageous queen,</LINE>
<LINE>No means to colour her detested deeds,</LINE>
<LINE>In finishing my guiltless father's days,</LINE>
<LINE>Because he gave her nothing to her dower</LINE>
<LINE>But by the colour of a feigned Ambassage,</LINE>
<LINE>To send him letters hither to our court?</LINE>
<LINE>Go carry them to them that sent them hither,</LINE>
<LINE>And bid them keep their scrolls unto themselves:</LINE>
<LINE>They cannot blind us with such slight excuse,</LINE>
<LINE>To smother up so monstrous vile abuse.</LINE>
<LINE>And were it not, it is against law of arms,</LINE>
<LINE>To offer violence to a messenger,</LINE>
<LINE>We would inflict such torments on thyself,</LINE>
<LINE>As should enforce thee to reveal the truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, your threats no whit appal my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>I know my conscience guiltless of this act;</LINE>
<LINE>My king and queen, I dare be sworn, are free</LINE>
<LINE>From any thought of such impiety:</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore, madam, you have done them wrong,</LINE>
<LINE>And ill-beseeming with a sister's love,</LINE>
<LINE>Who in mere duty tender him as much,</LINE>
<LINE>As ever you respected him for dower.</LINE>
<LINE>The king your husband will not say as much.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will suspend my judgment for a time,</LINE>
<LINE>Till more appearance give us further light:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet to be plain, your coming doth enforce</LINE>
<LINE>A great suspicion to our doubtful mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And that you do resemble, to be brief,</LINE>
<LINE>Him that first robs, and then cries, 'Stop the thief.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray God some near you have not done the like.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence, saucy mate, reply no more to us;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>She strikes him</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>For law of arms shall not protect thy tongue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AMBASSADOR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never was I offered such discourtesy;</LINE>
<LINE>God and my king, I trust, ere it be long,</LINE>
<LINE>Will find a mean to remedy this wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Amb.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How shall I live, to suffer this disgrace,</LINE>
<LINE>At every base and vulgar peasant's hands?</LINE>
<LINE>It ill befitteth my imperial state,</LINE>
<LINE>To be thus used, and no man take my part.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>She weeps</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What should I do? infringe the law of arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Were to my everlasting obloquy:</LINE>
<LINE>But I will take revenge upon his master,</LINE>
<LINE>Which sent him hither, to delude us thus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, if you put up this, be sure, ere long,</LINE>
<LINE>Now that my father thus is made away,</LINE>
<LINE>She will come and claim a third part of your crown,</LINE>
<LINE>As due unto her by inheritance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I will prove her title to be nought</LINE>
<LINE>But shame, and the reward of parricide,</LINE>
<LINE>And make her an example to the world,</LINE>
<LINE>For after-ages to admire her penance.</LINE>
<LINE>This will I do, as I am Cambria's king,</LINE>
<LINE>Or lose my life, to prosecute revenge.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, first let us learn what news is of our father,</LINE>
<LINE>And then proceed, as best occasion fits.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene III</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Leir, Perillus, and two mariners in sea-gowns and sea-caps.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My honest friends, we are ashamed to show</LINE>
<LINE>The great extremity of our present state,</LINE>
<LINE>In that at this time we are brought so low,</LINE>
<LINE>That we want money for to pay our passage.</LINE>
<LINE>The truth is so, we met with some good fellows,</LINE>
<LINE>A little before we came aboard your ship,</LINE>
<LINE>Which stripped us quite of all the coin we had,</LINE>
<LINE>And left us not a penny in our purses:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet wanting money, we will use the mean,</LINE>
<LINE>To see you satisfied to the uttermost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is a good gown, it would become me passing well, I should be fine in it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Look on Leir</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is a good cloak, I marvel how I should look in it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Look on Perillus.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, had we others to supply their room,</LINE>
<LINE>Though never so mean, you willingly should have them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear, sir? you look like an
honest man; I will not stand to do you a pleasure: here is a
good strong motley gabardine, cost me fourteen good
shillings at billingsgate, give me your gown for it, and
your cap for mine, and I will forgive your passage.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With all my heart, and twenty thanks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Lear and he changeth</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear, sir? you shall have
a better match than he, because you are my friend: here is a
good sheep's russet sea-gown, will bide more stress, I
warrant you, than two of his, yet for you seem to be an
honest gentleman, I am content to change it for your cloak,
and ask you nothing for your passage more. </LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Pulls off Perillus' cloak</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My own I willingly would change with thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And think myself indebted to thy kindness:</LINE>
<LINE>But would my friend might keep his garment still.</LINE>
<LINE>My friend, I will give thee this new doublet, if thou wilt</LINE>
<LINE>Restore his gown unto him back again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, if I do, would I might never eat
powdered beef and mustard more, nor drink can of good liquor
whilst I live. My friend, you have small reason to seek to
hinder me of my bargain: but the best is, a bargain's a
bargain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<STAGEDIR>To Perillus</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Kind friend, it is much better as it is.</LINE>
<LINE>For by this means we may escape unknown,</LINE>
<LINE>Till time and opportunity do fit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark, hark, they are laying their heads together,</LINE>
<LINE>They'll repent them of their bargain anon,</LINE>
<LINE>'Twere best for us to go while we are well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST MARINER.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God be with you, sir, for your passage back again,</LINE>
<LINE>I will use you as unreasonable as another.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know thou wilt; but we hope to bring ready money.</LINE>
<LINE>With us, when we come back again.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Mariners</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>Were ever men in this extremity,</LINE>
<LINE>In a strange country, and devoid of friends,</LINE>
<LINE>And not a penny for to help ourselves?</LINE>
<LINE>Kind friend, what thinkest thou will become of us?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be of good cheer, my lord, I have a doublet</LINE>
<LINE>Will yield us money enough to serve our turns,</LINE>
<LINE>Until we come unto your daughter's court:</LINE>
<LINE>And then, I hope, we shall find friends enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, kind Perillus, that is it I fear,</LINE>
<LINE>And makes me faint, or ever I come there.</LINE>
<LINE>Can kindness spring out of ingratitude?</LINE>
<LINE>Or love be reaped, where hatred hath been sown?</LINE>
<LINE>Can henbane join in league with Mithridate?</LINE>
<LINE>Or sugar grow in wormwood's bitter stalk?</LINE>
<LINE>It cannot be, they are too opposite:</LINE>
<LINE>And so am I to any kindness here.</LINE>
<LINE>I have thrown wormwood on the sugared youth,</LINE>
<LINE>And like to henbane poisoned the fount,</LINE>
<LINE>Whence flowed the Mithridate of a child's good will:</LINE>
<LINE>I, like an envious thorn, have pricked the heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And turned sweet grapes, to sour unrelished sloes:</LINE>
<LINE>The causeless ire of my respectless breast,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath soured the sweet milk of dame nature's paps:</LINE>
<LINE>My bitter words have galled her honey thoughts,</LINE>
<LINE>And weeds of rancour choked the flower of grace.</LINE>
<LINE>Then what remainder is of any hope,</LINE>
<LINE>But all our fortunes will go quite aslope?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not, my lord, the perfect good indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>Can never be corrupted by the bad:</LINE>
<LINE>A new fresh vessel still retains the taste</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore, though you name yourself the thorn,</LINE>
<LINE>The weed, the gall, the henbane and the wormwood;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet she will continue in her former state,</LINE>
<LINE>The honey, milk, grape, sugar, Mithridate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou pleasing orator unto me in woe,</LINE>
<LINE>Cease to beguile me with thy hopeful speeches:</LINE>
<LINE>O join with me, and think of nought but crosses,</LINE>
<LINE>And then we will one lament another's losses.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, say the worst, the worst can be but death,</LINE>
<LINE>And death is better than for to despair:</LINE>
<LINE>Then hazard death, which may convert to life;</LINE>
<LINE>Banish despair, which brings a thousand deaths.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Overcome with thy strong arguments, I yield,</LINE>
<LINE>To be directed by thee, as thou wilt:</LINE>
<LINE>As thou yieldest comfort to my crazed thoughts,</LINE>
<LINE>Would I could yield the like unto thy body,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is full weak, I know, and ill apaid,</LINE>
<LINE>For want of fresh meat and due sustenance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alack, my lord, my heart doth bleed, to think</LINE>
<LINE>That you should be in such extremity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, let us go, and see what god will send;</LINE>
<LINE>When all means fail, he is the surest friend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene IV</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Gallian king and queen, and Mumford with a basket, disguised like country folk.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This tedious journey all on foot, sweet love,</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot be pleasing to your tender joints,</LINE>
<LINE>Which never were used to these toilsome walks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I never in my life took more delight</LINE>
<LINE>In any journey, than I do in this:</LINE>
<LINE>It did me good, whenas we happed to light</LINE>
<LINE>Amongst the merry crew of country folk,</LINE>
<LINE>To see what industry and pains they took,</LINE>
<LINE>To win them commendations amongst their friends.</LINE>
<LINE>Lord, how they labour to bestir themselves,</LINE>
<LINE>And in their quirks to go beyond the moon,</LINE>
<LINE>And so take on them with such antic fits,</LINE>
<LINE>That one would think they were beside their wits!</LINE>
<LINE>Come away, Roger, with your basket.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Soft, dame, here comes a couple of old youths,</LINE>
<LINE>I must needs make myself fat with jesting at them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, prithee do not, they do seem to be</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Lear and Perillus very faintly</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Men much overcome with grief and misery.</LINE>
<LINE>Let's stand aside, and hearken what they say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, my Perillus, now I see we both</LINE>
<LINE>Shall end our days in this unfruitful soil.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, I do faint for want of sustenance:</LINE>
<LINE>And thou, I know, in little better case.</LINE>
<LINE>No gentle tree affords one taste of fruit,</LINE>
<LINE>To comfort us, until we meet with men:</LINE>
<LINE>No lucky path conducts our luckless steps</LINE>
<LINE>Unto a place where any comfort dwells.</LINE>
<LINE>Sweet rest betide unto our happy souls;</LINE>
<LINE>For here I see our bodies must have end.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, my dear lord, how doth my heart lament,</LINE>
<LINE>To see you brought to this extremity!</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, if you love me, as you do profess,</LINE>
<LINE>Or ever thought well of me in my life;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>He strips up his arm</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Feed on this flesh, whose veins are not so dry,</LINE>
<LINE>But there is virtue left to comfort you.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh, feed on this, if this will do you good,</LINE>
<LINE>I will smile for joy, to see you suck my blood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am no cannibal, that I should delight</LINE>
<LINE>To slake my hungry jaws with human flesh:</LINE>
<LINE>I am no devil, or ten times worse than so,</LINE>
<LINE>To suck the blood of such a peerless friend.</LINE>
<LINE>O, do not think that I respect my life</LINE>
<LINE>So dearly, as I do thy loyal love.</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, Britain, I shall never see thee more,</LINE>
<LINE>That hast unkindly banished thy king:</LINE>
<LINE>And yet not thou dost make me to complain,</LINE>
<LINE>But they which were more near to me than thou.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What do I hear? this lamentable voice,</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks, ere now I oftentimes have heard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, Gonorill, was half my kingdom's gift</LINE>
<LINE>The cause that thou didst seek to have my life?</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, cruel Ragan, did I give thee all,</LINE>
<LINE>And all could not suffice without my blood?</LINE>
<LINE>Ah, poor Cordella, did I give thee nought,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor never shall be able for to give?</LINE>
<LINE>O, let me warn all ages that ensueth,</LINE>
<LINE>How they trust flattery, and reject the truth.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, unkind girls, I here forgive you both,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet the just heavens will hardly do the like;</LINE>
<LINE>And only crave forgiveness at the end</LINE>
<LINE>Of good Cordella, and of thee, my friend;</LINE>
<LINE>Of God, whose majesty I have offended,</LINE>
<LINE>By my transgression many thousand ways:</LINE>
<LINE>Of her, dear heart, whom I for no occasion</LINE>
<LINE>Turned out of all, through flatterer's persuasion;</LINE>
<LINE>Of thee, kind friend, who but for me, I know,</LINE>
<LINE>Had'st never come unto this place of woe.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alack, that ever I should live to see</LINE>
<LINE>My noble father in this misery.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet love, reveal not what thou art as yet,</LINE>
<LINE>Until we know the ground of all this ill.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, but some meat, some meat: do you not see,</LINE>
<LINE>How near they are to death for want of food?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lord, which didst help thy servants at their need,</LINE>
<LINE>Or now or never send us help with speed.</LINE>
<LINE>Oh comfort, comfort! yonder is a banquet,</LINE>
<LINE>And men and women, my lord: be of good cheer;</LINE>
<LINE>For I see comfort coming very near.</LINE>
<LINE>O my lord, a banquet, and men and women!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, let kind pity mollify their hearts,</LINE>
<LINE>That they may help us in our great extremes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God save you, friends; and if this blessed banquet</LINE>
<LINE>Affordeth any food or sustenance,</LINE>
<LINE>Even for his sake that saved us all from death,</LINE>
<LINE>Vouchsafe to save us from the grip of famine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>She brings him to the table</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here father, sit and eat, here, sit and drink:</LINE>
<LINE>And would it were far better for your sakes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Perillus takes Leir by the hand to the table</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will give you thanks anon: my friend doth faint,</LINE>
<LINE>And needeth present comfort.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Leir drinks</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I warrant, he never stays to say a grace:</LINE>
<LINE>O, there is no sauce to a good stomach.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The blessed God of heaven hath thought upon us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The thanks be his, and these kind courteous folk,</LINE>
<LINE>By whose humanity we are preserved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They eat hungrily, Lear drinks</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And may that draught be unto him, as was</LINE>
<LINE>That which old Eson drank, which did renew</LINE>
<LINE>His withered age, and made him young again.</LINE>
<LINE>And may that meat be unto him, as was</LINE>
<LINE>That which Elias ate, in strength whereof</LINE>
<LINE>He walked forty days, and never fainted.</LINE>
<LINE>Shall I conceal me longer from my father?</LINE>
<LINE>Or shall I manifest myself to him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Forbear awhile, until his strength return,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest being overjoyed with seeing thee,</LINE>
<LINE>His poor weak senses should forsake their office,</LINE>
<LINE>And so our cause of joy be turned to sorrow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What cheer, my lord? how do you feel yourself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks, I never ate such savoury meat:</LINE>
<LINE>It is as pleasant as the blessed Manna,</LINE>
<LINE>That rained from heaven amongst the Israelites:</LINE>
<LINE>It hath recalled my spirits home again,</LINE>
<LINE>And made me fresh, as erst I was before.</LINE>
<LINE>But how shall we congratulate their kindness?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In faith, I know not how sufficiently;</LINE>
<LINE>But the best mean that I can think on, is this:</LINE>
<LINE>I will offer them my doublet in requital;</LINE>
<LINE>For we have nothing else to spare.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, stay, Perillus, for they shall have mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon, my lord, I swear they shall have mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Perillus offers his doublet. They will not take it.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, who would think such kindness should remain</LINE>
<LINE>Among such strange and unacquainted men:</LINE>
<LINE>And that such hate should harbour in the breast</LINE>
<LINE>Of those, which have occasion to be best?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, good old father, tell to me thy grief,</LINE>
<LINE>I will sorrow with thee, if not add relief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, good young daughter, I may call thee so;</LINE>
<LINE>For thou art like a daughter I did owe.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you not owe her still? what, is she dead?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, god forbid: but all my interest is gone,</LINE>
<LINE>By showing myself too much unnatural:</LINE>
<LINE>So have I lost the title of a father,</LINE>
<LINE>And may be called a stranger to her rather.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your title is good still; for it is always known,</LINE>
<LINE>A man may do as him list with his own.</LINE>
<LINE>But have you but one daughter then in all?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, I have more by two, than would I had.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, say not so, but rather see the end:</LINE>
<LINE>They that are bad, may have the grace to mend:</LINE>
<LINE>But how have they offended you so much?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If from the first I should relate the cause,</LINE>
<LINE>It would make a heart of adamant to weep;</LINE>
<LINE>And thou, poor soul, kind-hearted as thou art,</LINE>
<LINE>Dost weep already, ere I do begin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For god's love tell it, and when you have done,</LINE>
<LINE>I will tell the reason why I weep so soon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then know this first, I am a Briton born,</LINE>
<LINE>And had three daughters by one loving wife:</LINE>
<LINE>And though I say it, of beauty they were sped;</LINE>
<LINE>Especially the youngest of the three,</LINE>
<LINE>For her perfections hardly matched could be:</LINE>
<LINE>On these I doted with a jealous love,</LINE>
<LINE>And thought to try which of them loved me best,</LINE>
<LINE>By asking them, which would do most for me?</LINE>
<LINE>The first and second flattered me with words,</LINE>
<LINE>And vowed they loved me better than their lives:</LINE>
<LINE>The youngest said, she loved me as a child</LINE>
<LINE>Might do: her answer I esteemed most vile,</LINE>
<LINE>And presently in an outrageous mood,</LINE>
<LINE>I turned her from me to go sink or swim:</LINE>
<LINE>And all I had, even to the very clothes,</LINE>
<LINE>I gave in dowry with the other two:</LINE>
<LINE>And she that best deserved the greatest share,</LINE>
<LINE>I gave her nothing, but disgrace and care.</LINE>
<LINE>Now mark the sequel: when I had done thus,</LINE>
<LINE>I sojourned in my eldest daughter's house,</LINE>
<LINE>Where for a time I was entreated well,</LINE>
<LINE>And lived in state sufficing my content:</LINE>
<LINE>But every day her kindness did grow cold,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I with patience put up well enough,</LINE>
<LINE>And seemed not to see the things I saw:</LINE>
<LINE>But at the last she grew so far incensed</LINE>
<LINE>With moody fury, and with causeless hate,</LINE>
<LINE>That in most vile and contumelious terms,</LINE>
<LINE>She bade me pack, and harbour somewhere else.</LINE>
<LINE>Then was I fain for refuge to repair</LINE>
<LINE>Unto my other daughter for relief,</LINE>
<LINE>Who gave me pleasing and most courteous words;</LINE>
<LINE>But in her actions showed herself so sore,</LINE>
<LINE>As never any daughter did before:</LINE>
<LINE>She prayed me in a morning out betime,</LINE>
<LINE>To go to a thicket two miles from the court,</LINE>
<LINE>Pointing that there she would come talk with me:</LINE>
<LINE>There she had set a shag-haired murdering wretch,</LINE>
<LINE>To massacre my honest friend and me.</LINE>
<LINE>Then judge yourself, although my tale be brief,</LINE>
<LINE>If ever man had greater cause of grief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor never like impiety was done,</LINE>
<LINE>Since the creation of the world begun.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And now I am constrained to seek relief</LINE>
<LINE>Of her, to whom I have been so unkind;</LINE>
<LINE>Whose censure, if it do award me death,</LINE>
<LINE>I must confess she pays me but my due:</LINE>
<LINE>But if she show a loving daughter's part,</LINE>
<LINE>It comes of god and her, not my desert.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No doubt she will, I dare be sworn she will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How know you that, not knowing what she is?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Myself a father have a great way hence,</LINE>
<LINE>Used me as ill as ever you did her;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, that his reverend age I once might see,</LINE>
<LINE>I would creep along, to meet him on my knee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, no men's children are unkind but mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Condemn not all, because of others' crime:</LINE>
<LINE>But look, dear father, look, behold and see</LINE>
<LINE>Thy loving daughter speaketh unto thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>she kneels</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, stand thou up, it is my part to kneel,</LINE>
<LINE>And ask forgiveness for my former faults.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>he kneels</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, if you wish, I should enjoy my breath,</LINE>
<LINE>Dear father rise, or I receive my death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>he rises</STAGEDIR>
<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then I will rise to satisfy your mind,</LINE>
<LINE>But kneel again, till pardon be resigned.</LINE>
</SPEECH>
<STAGEDIR>he kneels</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pardon you: the word beseems not me:</LINE>
<LINE>But I do say so, for to ease your knee.</LINE>
<LINE>You gave me life, you were the cause that I</LINE>
<LINE>Am what I am, who else had never been.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But you gave life to me and to my friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose days had else had an untimely end.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You brought me up, whenas I was but young,</LINE>
<LINE>And far unable for to help myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cast thee forth, whenas thou was but young,</LINE>
<LINE>And far unable for to help thyself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God, world and nature say I do you wrong,</LINE>
<LINE>That can endure to see you kneel so long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me break off this loving controversy,</LINE>
<LINE>Which doth rejoice my very soul to see.</LINE>
<LINE>Good father, rise, she is your loving daughter,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>he rises</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And honours you with as respective duty,</LINE>
<LINE>As if you were the monarch of the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I will never rise from off my knee,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>she kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Until I have your blessing, and your pardon</LINE>
<LINE>Of all my faults committed anyway,</LINE>
<LINE>From my first birth unto this present day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The blessing, which the God of Abraham gave</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the tribe of Judah, light on thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And multiply thy days, that thou mayest see</LINE>
<LINE>Thy children's children prosper after thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy faults, which are just none that I do know,</LINE>
<LINE>God pardon on high, and I forgive below. </LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>she rises</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now is my heart at quiet, and doth leap</LINE>
<LINE>Within my breast, for joy of this good hap:</LINE>
<LINE>And now, dear father, welcome to our court,</LINE>
<LINE>And welcome, kind Perillus, unto me,</LINE>
<LINE>Mirror of virtue and true honesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, he hath been the kindest friend to me,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever man had in adversity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My tongue doth fail, to say what heart doth think,</LINE>
<LINE>I am so ravished with exceeding joy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All you have spoke: now let me speak my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And in few words much matter here conclude:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>he kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>If ever my heart do harbour any joy,</LINE>
<LINE>Or true content repose within my breast,</LINE>
<LINE>Till I have rooted out this viperous sect,</LINE>
<LINE>And repossessed my father of his crown,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me be counted for the perjuredest man,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever spake word since the world began.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>rise</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me pray too, that never prayed before;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>he kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>If ere I resalute the British earth,</LINE>
<LINE>(As, ere't be long, I do presume I shall)</LINE>
<LINE>And so return from thence without my wench,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me be gelded for my recompense.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>rise</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, let us to arms for to redress this wrong:</LINE>
<LINE>Till I am there, methinks, the time seems long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>




<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene V</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Ragan, sola.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I feel a hell of conscience in my breast,</LINE>
<LINE>Tormenting me with horror for my fact,</LINE>
<LINE>And makes me in a agony of doubt,</LINE>
<LINE>For fear the world should find my dealing out.</LINE>
<LINE>The slave whom I appointed for the act,</LINE>
<LINE>I never set eye upon the peasant since:</LINE>
<LINE>O, could I get him for to make him sure,</LINE>
<LINE>My doubts would cease, and I should rest secure.</LINE>
<LINE>But if the old men, with persuasive words,</LINE>
<LINE>Have saved their lives, and made him to relent;</LINE>
<LINE>Then are they fled unto the court of France,</LINE>
<LINE>And like a trumpet manifest my shame.</LINE>
<LINE>A shame on these white-livered slaves, say I,</LINE>
<LINE>That with fair words so soon are overcome.</LINE>
<LINE>O god, that I had been but made a man;</LINE>
<LINE>Or that my strength were equal with my will!</LINE>
<LINE>These foolish men are nothing but mere pity,</LINE>
<LINE>And melt as butter doth against the sun.</LINE>
<LINE>Why should they have pre-eminence over us,</LINE>
<LINE>Since we are creatures of more brave resolve?</LINE>
<LINE>I swear, I am quite out of charity</LINE>
<LINE>With all the heartless men in Christendom.</LINE>
<LINE>A pox upon them, when they are afraid</LINE>
<LINE>To give a stab, or slit a paltry wind-pipe,</LINE>
<LINE>Which are so easy matters to be done.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, had I thought the slave would serve me so,</LINE>
<LINE>Myself would have been executioner:</LINE>
<LINE>It is now undone, and if that it be known,</LINE>
<LINE>I will make as good shift as I can for one.</LINE>
<LINE>He that repines at me, however it stands,</LINE>
<LINE>T'were best for him to keep him from my hands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>


<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VI</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Sounds drums and trumpets: Enter the Gallian king, Leir, Mumford, and the army.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus have we brought our army to the sea,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereas our ships are ready to receive us:</LINE>
<LINE>The wind stands fair, and we in four hours' sail,</LINE>
<LINE>May easily arrive on British shore,</LINE>
<LINE>Where unexpected we may them surprise,</LINE>
<LINE>And gain a glorious victory with ease.</LINE>
<LINE>Wherefore, my loving countrymen, resolve,</LINE>
<LINE>Since truth and justice fighteth on our sides,</LINE>
<LINE>That we shall march with conquest where we go.</LINE>
<LINE>Myself will be as forward as the first,</LINE>
<LINE>And step by step march with the hardiest wight:</LINE>
<LINE>And not the meanest soldier in our camp</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be in danger, but I will second him.</LINE>
<LINE>To you, my lord, we give the whole command</LINE>
<LINE>Of all the army, next unto ourself;</LINE>
<LINE>Not doubting of you, but you will extend</LINE>
<LINE>Your wonted valour in this needful case,</LINE>
<LINE>Encouraging the rest to do the like,</LINE>
<LINE>By your approved magnanimity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My liege, 'tis needless to spur a willing horse,</LINE>
<LINE>That's apt enough to run himself to death:</LINE>
<LINE>For here I swear by that sweet saint's bright eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Which are the stars, which guide me to good hap,</LINE>
<LINE>Either to see my old lord crowned anew,</LINE>
<LINE>Or in his cause to bid the world adieu.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, good lord Mumford, it is more of your good-will,</LINE>
<LINE>Than any merit or desert in me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And now to you, my worthy countrymen,</LINE>
<LINE>Ye valiant race of Genovestan Gauls,</LINE>
<LINE>Surnamed Red-shanks, for your chivalry,</LINE>
<LINE>Because you fight up to the shanks in blood;</LINE>
<LINE>Show yourselves now to be right Gauls indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>And be so bitter on your enemies,</LINE>
<LINE>That they may say, you are as bitter as gall.</LINE>
<LINE>Gall them, brave shot, with your artillery:</LINE>
<LINE>Gall them, brave halberts, with your sharp point bills,</LINE>
<LINE>Each in their appointed place, not one, but all,</LINE>
<LINE>Fight for the credit of yourselves and Gaul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then what should more persuasion need to those,</LINE>
<LINE>That rather wish to deal, than hear of blows?</LINE>
<LINE>Let us to our ships, and if that god permit,</LINE>
<LINE>In four hours' sail, I hope we shall be there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And in five hours more, I make no doubt,</LINE>
<LINE>But we shall bring our wished desires about.</LINE> 
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>


<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VII</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Captain of the Watch, and two Watchmen.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My honest friends, it is your turn tonight,</LINE>
<LINE>To watch in this place, near about the beacon,</LINE>
<LINE>And vigilantly have regard,</LINE>
<LINE>If any fleet of ships pass hitherward:</LINE>
<LINE>Which if you do, your office is to fire</LINE>
<LINE>The beacon presently, and raise the town.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, ay, ay, fear nothing; we know our
charge, I warrant: I have been a watchman about this beacon
this thirty year, and yet I never see it stir, but stood as
quietly as might be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith neighbour, and you will follow
my advice, instead of watching the beacon, we will go to
goodmanGeniting's, and watch a pot of ale and a rasher of
bacon: and if we do not drink ourselves drunk, then so; I
warrant, the beacon will see us when we come out again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but how if somebody excuse us to the captain?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis no matter, I will prove by good reason that we watch the beacon: ass for example.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope you do not call me ass by craft, neighbour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, but for example: say here stands the pot of ale, that is the beacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, ay, it is a very good beacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, say here stands your nose, that is the fire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed I must confess, it is somewhat red.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see come marching in a dish, half a score pieces of salt bacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I understand your meaning, that is as much to say, half a score ships.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True, you conster right; presently,
like a faithful watchman, I fire the beacon, and call up the
town.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, that is as much as to say, you set your nose to the pot, and drink up the drink.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are in the right; come, let us
go fire the beacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene VIII</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the King of Gallia with a still march, Mumford and soldiers.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now march our ensigns on the British earth,</LINE>
<LINE>And we are near approaching to the town.</LINE>
<LINE>Then look about you valiant countrymen,</LINE>
<LINE>And we shall finish this exploit with ease.</LINE>
<LINE>The inhabitants of this mistrustful place</LINE>
<LINE>Are dead asleep, as men that are secure:</LINE>
<LINE>Here shall we skirmish but with naked men,</LINE>
<LINE>Devoid of sense, new-waked from a dream,</LINE>
<LINE>That know not what our coming doth pretend,</LINE>
<LINE>Till they do feel our meaning on their skins:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore assail: God and our right for us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene IX</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Alarm, with men and women half naked: Enter two Captains without doublets, with swords.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>Where are these villains that were set to watch,</LINE>
<LINE>And fire the beacon, if occasion served,</LINE>
<LINE>That thus have suffered us to be surprised,</LINE>
<LINE>And never given notice to the town?</LINE>
<LINE>We are betrayed, and quite devoid of hope,</LINE>
<LINE>By any means to fortify ourselves.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis ten to one the peasants are o'ercome</LINE>
<LINE>With drink and sleep, and so neglect their charge.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A whirl-wind carry them quick to a whirl-pool,</LINE>
<LINE>That there the slaves may drink their bellies full.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This 'tis, to have the beacon so near the ale-house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the watchmen, drunk, with each a pot</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>Out on ye, villains, whither run you now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To fire the town, and call up the beacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, sir to fire the beacon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>He drinks</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>What, with a pot of ale, you drunken rogues?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST CAPTAIN.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>You will fire the beacon, when the
town is lost: I will teach you how to tend your office
better.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Draws to stab them. Enter Mumford, Captains run away.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yield, yield, yield.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>He kicks down their pots</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Reel? no, we do not reel: You may lack a pot of ale ere you die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But in mean space, I answer, you want none.
Well there is no dealing with you, you are tall men, and
well weaponed, I would there were no worse than you in the
town.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SECOND WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A' speaks like an honest man, my choler's past already.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, neighbour, let us go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FIRST WATCHMAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, first let us see and we can stand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene X</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum, excursions. Mumford after them, and some half
naked. Enter the Gallian king, Leir, Mumford, Cordella,
Perillus and soldiers, with the chief of the town bound.</STAGEDIR>


<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not, my friends, you shall receive no hurt,</LINE>
<LINE>If you will subscribe unto your lawful king,</LINE>
<LINE>And quite revoke your fealty from Cambria,</LINE>
<LINE>And from aspiring Cornwall too, whose wives</LINE>
<LINE>Have practised treason against their father's life.</LINE>
<LINE>We come in justice of your wronged king,</LINE>
<LINE>And do intend no harm at all to you,</LINE>
<LINE>So you submit unto your lawful king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kind countrymen, it grieves me, that perforce,</LINE>
<LINE>I am constrained to use extremities.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>NOBLES.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Long have you here been looked for, good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>And wished for by a general consent:</LINE>
<LINE>And had we known your highness had arrived,</LINE>
<LINE>We had not made resistance to your grace:</LINE>
<LINE>And now, my gracious lord, you need not doubt,</LINE>
<LINE>But all the country will yield presently,</LINE>
<LINE>Which since your absence have been greatly taxed,</LINE>
<LINE>For to maintain their overswelling pride.</LINE>
<LINE>We will presently send word to all our friends;</LINE>
<LINE>When they have notice, they will come apace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, loving subjects; and thanks, worthy son,</LINE>
<LINE>Thanks, my kind daughter, thanks to you, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Who willingly adventured have your blood,</LINE>
<LINE>(Without desert) to do me so much good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Oh, say not so:</LINE>
<LINE>I have been much beholding to your grace:</LINE>
<LINE>I must confess, I have been in some skirmishes,</LINE>
<LINE>But I was never in the like to this:</LINE>
<LINE>For where I was wont to meet with armed men,</LINE>
<LINE>I was now encountered with naked women.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We that are feeble, and want use of arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Will pray to god, to shield you from all harms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The while your hands do manage ceaseless toil,</LINE>
<LINE>Our hearts shall pray, the foes may have the foil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will fast and pray, whilst you for us do fight,</LINE>
<LINE>That victory may prosecute the right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks, your words do amplify (my friends)</LINE>
<LINE>And add fresh vigour to my willing limbs:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>drum</STAGEDIR> 
<LINE>But hark, I hear the adverse drum approach.</LINE>
<LINE>God and our right, Saint Denis, and Saint George.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter Cornwall, Cambria, Gonorill, Ragan and the army</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Presumptuous king of Gauls, how darest thou</LINE>
<LINE>Presume to enter on our British shore?</LINE>
<LINE>And more than that, to take our towns perforce,</LINE>
<LINE>And draw our subjects' hearts from their true king?</LINE>
<LINE>Be sure to buy it at as dear a price,</LINE>
<LINE>As ever you bought presumption in your lives.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Over-daring Cornwall, know, we came in right,</LINE>
<LINE>And just revengement of the wronged king,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose daughters there, fell vipers as they are,</LINE>
<LINE>Have sought to murder and deprive of life:</LINE>
<LINE>But god protected him from all their spite,</LINE>
<LINE>And we are come in justice of his right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor he nor thou have any interest here,</LINE>
<LINE>But what you win and purchase with the sword.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy slanders to our noble virtuous queens,</LINE>
<LINE>We will in the battle thrust them down thy throat,</LINE>
<LINE>Except for fear of our revenging hands,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou fly to sea, as not secure on lands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>Welshman, I will so ferret you ere night for that word,</LINE>
<LINE>That you shall have no mind to crake so well this
twelvemonth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They lie, that say, we sought our father's death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is merely forged for a colour's sake,</LINE>
<LINE>To set a gloss on your invasion.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks, an old man ready for to die,</LINE>
<LINE>Should be ashamed to broach so foul a lie.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER> 
<LINE>Fie, shameless sister, so devoid of grace,</LINE>
<LINE>To call our father liar to his face.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, puritan, dissembling hypocrite,</LINE>
<LINE>Which art so good, that thou wilt prove stark naught:</LINE>
<LINE>Anon, whenas I have you in my fingers,</LINE>
<LINE>I will make you wish yourself in purgatory.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, peace thou monster, shame unto thy sex:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou fiend in likeness of a human creature.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I never heard a fouler spoken man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Out on thee, viper, scum, filthy parricide,</LINE>
<LINE>More odious to my sight than is a toad.</LINE>
<LINE>Knowest thou these letters?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>She snatches them &amp; tears them.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think you to outface me with your paltry scrolls?</LINE>
<LINE>You come to drive my husband from his right,</LINE>
<LINE>Under the colour of a forged letter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who ever heard the like impiety?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are our debtor of more patience:</LINE>
<LINE>We were more patient when we stayed for you,</LINE>
<LINE>Within the thicket two long hours and more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What hours? what thicket?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There, where you sent your servant with your letters,</LINE>
<LINE>Sealed with your hand, to send us both to heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>Where as I think, you never mean to come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RAGAN.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, you are grown a child again with age,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else your senses dote for want of sleep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PERILLUS.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed you made us rise betimes, you know,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet had a care we should sleep where you bade us stay,</LINE>
<LINE>But never wake more till the latter day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GONORILL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, peace, old fellow, thou art sleepy still.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, and if you reason till tomorrow,</LINE>
<LINE>You get no other answer at their hands.</LINE>
<LINE>It is pity two such good faces</LINE>
<LINE>Should have so little grace between them.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, let us see if their husbands with their hands,</LINE>
<LINE>Can do as much, as they do with their tongues.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, with their swords they will make your tongue unsay</LINE>
<LINE>What they have said, or else they will cut them out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To it, gallants, to it, let us not stand brawling thus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt both armies.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene XI</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Sound Alarum: excursions. Mumford must chase Cambria away: then cease. Enter Cornwall.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORNWALL.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The day is lost, our friends do all revolt,</LINE>
<LINE>And join against us with the adverse part:</LINE>
<LINE>There is no means of safety but by flight,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore I will to Cornwall with my queen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Cambria</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAMBRIA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think, there is a devil in the camp hath haunted</LINE>
<LINE>Me today: he hath so tired me, that in a manner I can fight no more.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Mumford</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Zounds, here he comes, I will take me to my horse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit. Mumford follows him to the door, and returns.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MUMFORD.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, Welshman, give thee but thy due,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast a light and nimble pair of legs:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art more in debt to them than to thy hands:</LINE>
<LINE>But if I meet thee once again today,</LINE>
<LINE>I will cut them off, and set them to a better heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

<SCENE>
<SCENETITLE>Scene XII</SCENETITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum and excursions; then sound victory. Enter Leir, Perillus, King, Cordella, and Mumford.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks be to god, your foes are overcome,</LINE>
<LINE>And you again possessed of your right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>First to the heavens, next, thanks to you, my son,</LINE>
<LINE>By whose good means I repossess the same:</LINE>
<LINE>Which if it please you to accept yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>With all my heart I will resign to you.</LINE>
<LINE>For it is yours by right, and none of mine.</LINE>
<LINE>First, have you raised, at your own charge, a power</LINE>
<LINE>Of valiant soldiers; this comes all from you;</LINE>
<LINE>Next have you ventured your own person's scathe.</LINE>
<LINE>And lastly worthy Gallia never stained,</LINE>
<LINE>My kingly title I by thee have gained.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>KING.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thank heavens, not me, my zeal to you is such,</LINE>
<LINE>Command my utmost I will never grutch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORDELLA.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He that with all kind love entreats his queen,</LINE>
<LINE>Will not be to her father unkind seen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEIR.</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ah, my Cordella, now I call to mind,</LINE>
<LINE>The modest answer, which I took unkind:</LINE>
<LINE>But now I see, I am no whit beguiled,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou lovedst me dearly, and as ought a child.</LINE>
<LINE>And thou, Perillus, partner once in woe,</LINE>
<LINE>Thee to requite, the best I can, I will do:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet all I can, ay, were it never so much,</LINE>
<LINE>Were not sufficient, thy true love is such.</LINE>
<LINE>Thanks, worthy Mumford, to thee last of all,</LINE>
<LINE>Not greeted last, because thy desert was small;</LINE>
<LINE>No, thou hast lion-like laid on today,</LINE>
<LINE>Chasing the Cornwall king and Cambria;</LINE>
<LINE>Who with my daughters, daughters did I say?</LINE>
<LINE>To save their lives, the fugitives did play.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, son and daughter, who did me advance,</LINE>
<LINE>Repose with me awhile, and then for France.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Sound drums and trumpets. Exeunt.</STAGEDIR>

</SCENE>

</ACT>

<AUTHORDETAILS>
<AUTHOR>PlayShakespeare.com</AUTHOR>
<AUTHORURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com</AUTHORURL>
<COPYRIGHT>2005-2012 by PlayShakespeare.com</COPYRIGHT>
<VERSION>1.0</VERSION>
<LICENSE>GFDL License 1.3</LICENSE>
<LICENSEURL>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</LICENSEURL>
<TERMSURL>http://www.playshakespeare.com/about-us</TERMSURL>
</AUTHORDETAILS>

</PLAY>
