<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="All&#8217;s Well That Ends Well">
<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING.">King of France</persname>
<persdescription>The King of France is ill of a fistula, and feels his age keenly when he is ill. While refusing for diplomatic reasons to fully support the Florentines in their war with Sienna, he does not stop any of his lords who wish to go to the wars of their own accord from doing so, saving the overly-young such as Bertram. He warns them about Italian women before they go. He was a great friend of Bertram&#8217;s father, and is glad to have the young man among his wards. He is half in love with his illness, convinced that he cannot be cured and refusing help once the properly-trained doctors have thrown up their arms. Still, he agrees to see Helena, and to try her cure when she offers her own life should she fail. Being cured, his spirits are more than revived, and he dances around with her. Having absolute power as both sovereign and warder over a number of young lords, he agrees to bestow any one of them that Helena chooses as her husband. He is enraged when Bertram refuses his command to accept her. He is grieved at reports of the lady&#8217;s death, but agrees to put the whole incident in the past and pretend that Bertram has never offended him. Seeing Bertram with the ring he gave to Helena, however, revives his anger, and he soon comes to believe that Bertram had her murdered. He is not best pleased by Diana&#8217;s riddles, but when all is revealed he takes quite a shine to her, and offers to let her choose any husband she wishes among his lords, thus risking starting the whole thing over again. Oddly for a king, he does not believe there is an inherent difference between people&#8217;s birth, rather that their worth is determined by their actions and moral character. He speaks the epilogue.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUKE.">Duke of Florence</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Florence is at war with Sienna. His explanations for this convince the two French Lords, and he is himself at a loss as to why his manifest right is not being fully supported by the King of France, rather than merely permitting lords to fight if they so choose. He names Bertram his master of horse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BER.">Bertram, Count of Roussillion</persname>
<persdescription>Bertram is a young lord of France, recently become Count of Roussillon by his father&#8217;s death. Being still underage, he is taken into wardship by the King, meaning among other things that the monarch may force him to marry whomsoever he chooses. He dearly wishes to go away to the Florentine wars, but is prevented from doing so by the King on the basis of his age. He is very proud of his lineage, and disdains Helena, whom he has grown up with, for her low birth. He only accepts to marry her when ordered to by the King on pain of losing his favor forever, and quickly plans to leave her. He callously sends her back to his mother, refuses to let her call him husband unless she fulfills an impossible obligation, and swears never to consummate the marriage. Arriving in Florence, he is named general of the horse, and acts valorously in the wars, gaining great renown. Egged on by Parolles, whom he listens to above all others, he attempts to seduce Diana, using flowery language in an attempt to get into her bed. When she asks him for an ancestral ring he carries, he at first refuses, but on being promised sex he immediately hands it over to her. He agrees to the two French Lords&#8217; plan to abduct Parolles to test whether he actually is no more than a braggart, and is quickly convinced, especially on hearing Parolles&#8217;s opinion of him and the letters the braggart has sent to Diana recommended that she milk Bertram for all he&#8217;s worth. Hearing of Helena&#8217;s death, he perfunctorily mourns for her and plans to return to France, where he begs the King&#8217;s pardon, swearing that he began to love Helena after she was gone. He accepts to marry Lafew&#8217;s daughter, and is confused when told that the ring he gives the old lord as a token is Helena&#8217;s, and once belonged to the King. Challenged as to his actions in Florence, he proceeds to lie again and again, slandering Diana as a whore. On Helena&#8217;s reappearance, he begs pardon, and conditionally promises to love her. He is not the most attractive of characters, but it must be remembered that he is very young.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LAF.">Lafew</persname>
<persdescription>Lafew is an old bearded lord at the court of France who is sent to fetch Bertram when the latter&#8217;s father dies and he enters his wardship. Meeting Helena at Roussillion, he is impressed by her, and later agrees to persuade the King to see her and try her doctoring. He is taken aback, nevertheless, at just how successful her ministering are, and develops rather a crush on the young lady, growing appalled when he believes that the various lords are rejecting her. He quickly sees through Parolles&#8217;s boasting and absurd apparel and refuses to have anything to do with him, and unsuccessfully attempts to warn Bertram about him. He grows convinced that all of Bertram&#8217;s bad behavior can be laid at Parolles&#8217;s door. Still, when the latter is disgraced and revealed to the whole world for what he is, Lafew accepts to keep him from the poorhouse. Helena being dead, he seeks to arrange a match between his daughter Maudlin (Madeline?) and Bertram, but he soon changes his mind on hearing the young man accused of seduction and swears he&#8217;ll have none of him. Helena&#8217;s reappearance leads him to tears, and he decides to take Parolles to his service as something of a jester.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PAR.">Parolles</persname>
<persdescription>Parolles is a loud-mouthed, dirty-minded braggart of a soldier, extremely overdressed, and able to convince the unwary that he is an extraordinary soldier, though he is in fact a great coward. The inventiveness of his excuses and lies is so great that many of those who see through him cannot find it in them to cast him aside, regarding him almost as a freak of nature and enjoying his company all the more for knowing that all he says is lies. Even Helena likes him, and engages in a witty debate on the subject of virginity with him, though in other company he will slander her character. He laces his speech with Italian phrases. He is a companion of Bertram&#8217;s, and follows him to the court. He talks far too much there, irritating Lafew, who soon sees through him. With the two French Lords, he convinces Bertram to run away to the wars, and lies to Helena about her husband&#8217;s intents. With him in Florence, he attempts to help him seduce Diana, and suggests that Diana ought to give in, as Bertram is rather rich and could easily be parted from his money. He is fully aware of what he is, but plays his role all the same, which allows the French lords to push him to swear to recover the lost drum. Captured and blindfolded by those he supposes to be the enemy, he is terrified and spills all that they want to know upon barely being asked, and slandering all those he knows. Discovering the trick, he comes to the realization that he would be better off admitting to being a fool and making his living as one, rather than pretending to be anything else, and he seeks the charity of Lafew. He testifies to Bertram&#8217;s attempts to bed Diana. Lafew ends up taking him into his service as a jester of sorts.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="STEW.">Rinaldo</persname>
<persdescription>Rinaldo is the Countess of Roussillon&#8217;s steward. Overhearing Helena speaking to herself about her love for Bertram, he feels it his duty to inform the Countess of the fact. He fails to give the Countess Helena&#8217;s letter announcing her departure to Compostella in a timely manner, leaving it impossible to overtake her. He writes to Bertram on the Countess&#8217;s behalf to reproach him for his abandonment of his wife.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CLO.">Lavatch</persname>
<persdescription>Lavatch is a poor servant of the Countess of Roussillon. He hopes to get married, though his views on women are not the most charitable. He is a funny fellow and knows it, never answering a question directly if he can get some mileage out of the answer, and twitting the Countess despite all her threats of whipping. Though she allows him his jesting, he knows well enough when her tone requires him to cease the jokes and get to work. The sight of court ladies makes him quite forget his own lady-friend back home. He is a great fan of Bertram, whose flight leaves him less merry than he was. He enjoys lording it over the disgraced Parolles.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PAGE.">Countess&#8217;s Page</persname>
<persdescription>A Page, servant to the Countess of Roussillion, is sent to find Parolles and call him to join Lafew and Bertram as they leave for court.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GENT.">Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>Gentleman Astringer is a Frenchman following the court. He agrees to present a petition to the King, though uncertain of whether he should have done.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COUNT.">Countess of Roussillion</persname>
<persdescription>The Countess of Roussillion is the widow of the recently-deceased Count. Soon after her widowing, she loses her son Bertram when he is taken into wardship by the crown. She is very fond of the daughter of the late doctor Gerard de Narbon, who she promised to bring up on the doctor&#8217;s death. She knows what it is to be in love, and slowly teases out of Helena a confession that she is in love with Bertram. She allows Helena to travel to Paris to attempt to cure the King, secretly hoping that she will be able to gain Bertram as a husband. She is horrified when she learns that Bertram has deserted Helena and disobeyed the King&#8217;s orders, and on discovering how callously he is writing to his wife she swears to disinherit him. When she hears of Helena&#8217;s death, she is grieved, but somewhat reconciled to her son, on whose behalf she begs the King for pardon. She is an honorable old lady with much care for her good name, but who is able to joke with her servant Lavatch as well as she speaks with the grandees of the court. She is convinced that Parolles is to blame for her son&#8217;s actions.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HEL.">Helena</persname>
<persdescription>Helena is the orphaned daughter of the greatest doctor of the age, Gerard de Narbon, who left her many of his recipes for cures and much of his skill. Left to the care of the dowager Countess of Roussillion, she is brought up with all accomplishments. She falls desperately in love with the young Count, Bertram, whom has little to say to her. His departure to court brings her to weeping, though she recovers enough to be able to trade witticisms on the subject of virginity with the braggart Parolles, whom she knows to be a shamelessly thorough liar but whose company she enjoys for that very reason. A determined girl who knows the ways of the world, she keenly feels the difference in rank between herself and Bertram, but decides that if she managed to cure the King of his debilitating illness, he would reward her by allowing her to choose a husband among the lords of his court. She does not realize that she has been overheard speaking to herself about her love for Bertram, and is thus not prepared when the Countess ambushes her and cajoles her into admitting her feelings. By laying her life on the line, she convinces the King to let her attempt to cure him. Succeeding, she claims her reward, but is shocked to silence when Bertram refuses her, and attempts to keep the King from forcing him into wedlock with her. Married nevertheless, she becomes almost obsequiously obedient, though pestering him for at least a farewell kiss before he leaves her. Receiving a letter like a slap in the face from Bertram, she is distraught, and horrified that he has gone to the war where he may be killed, as she thinks because of her. She sneaks away in the night, reporting that she is gone on a pilgrimage, in the hopes that the news will bring Bertram home. She tracks him down to Florence, where she hears that he is attempting to seduce a young lady she meets. Seeing an opportunity, she arranges to have the girl accept to receive Bertram at night and to get the ring from his finger. She replaces Diana in the bed that night, and in the dark Bertram does not notice the difference. Impregnated, she has thus fulfilled his conditions, and she brings Diana and her mother along with her as she returns to the French court to prove that she has done so. Having had Bertram&#8217;s lies publicly exposed before the King, she attempts to be reconciled with him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="WID.">An Old Widow of Florence</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. MAR. AND WID.">Both Mariana and Widow</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>An Old Widow runs a resting point for pilgrims on their road to Compostella. Convinced by Helena&#8217;s story that she is Bertram&#8217;s wife, though the gold helps her to this conviction, she agrees to help her with her bed-trick which will have the dual effect of allowing Helena to fulfill her husband&#8217;s requirements and saving Diana from Bertram&#8217;s importuning (and the endless nighttime serenading he engages in). She plays her part of outraged mother to the hilt, following the King of France until she finds him, and protecting her daughter. She knows very well how men go about getting into the beds of the girls they affection, and trains her daughter Diana exactly how to treat him to make the trick work.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="DIA.">Diana</persname>
<persdescription>Diana Capilet is a young lady of Florence, the daughter of the Widow innkeeper. She is being forcefully wooed by Bertram, and is not entirely indifferent to him. She is touched by Helena&#8217;s story and agrees to her plot to trick Bertram in to sleeping with her. She allows Bertram to seduce her and quickly convinces him to exchange his ancestral ring for her chastity. The experience disgusts her enough that she vows to never marry. She has the backbone to walk into the French court and accuse Bertram of dishonoring her before the King himself, not to mention speaking in riddles that put her in danger of jail to produce the most dramatic entrance possible for Helena. The King offers her a choice of lords for a husband if she so chooses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MAR.">Mariana</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. MAR. AND WID.">Both Mariana and Widow</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Mariana is a friend of the Widow and her daughter Diana, and is full of warnings against the wiles of young men. She has no taste for Parolles.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. LORD.">First French Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First French Lord is in the lineup of possible husbands for Helena, and is quite willing to marry her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. LORD.">Second French Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All French Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second French Lord is in the lineup of possible husbands for Helena. He is intimidating, though courteous.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="3. LORD.">Third French Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All French Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third French Lord (mute) is in the lineup of possible husbands for Helena.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="4. LORD.">Fourth French Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL LORDS.">All French Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fourth French Lord is in the lineup of possible husbands for Helena. He scoffs at the thought that he is too young to marry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. LORD. DUM.">First French Lord Dumaine</persname>
<persdescription>First French Lord (Captain Dumaine) in the Florentine service is a war-happy young man who thinks it a great pity that Bertram will not be able to follow himself and other lords to battle. He offers to help the younger man steal away from court. He lets Helena and the Countess know where Bertram has gone while delivering his letter to Helena, and learning of its contents is remorseful at having done so. While at first impressed by Parolles&#8217;s bragging, he soon sees through it, and helps conceive and execute the plot against him, convincing the others that they should set Parolles to fetch his drum as part of the joke. He is not altogether impressed with Bertram&#8217;s behavior concerning Helena, especially once he hears of the lady&#8217;s death. During Parolles&#8217;s interrogation he makes sure to ask what Parolles thinks of him, and is enraged at the answers, though Parolles ends up going so far that the Lord begins to admire him for sheer gall and inventiveness.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. LORD. DUM.">Second French Lord Dumaine</persname>
<persdescription>Second French Lord (the other Captain Dumaine) in the Florentine service is the brother of the First. A war-happy young man, he thinks it a great pity that Bertram will not be able to follow himself and other lords to battle. He offers to help the younger man steal away from court. He does not like to guess at what politicians are up to even when he disapproves of their actions. He attempts to excuse Bertram to Helena. He is convinced of Parolles&#8217;s lack of worth, and conceives the braggart&#8217;s abduction and interrogation in an invented language. He is astonished, overhearing Parolles speaking to himself, to consider that it is possible that Parolles is quite aware of what he is. He plays the part of the enemy general in the braggart&#8217;s interrogation, and when the trick is revealed taunts him with the fact that he will tell Lafew of this. He becomes less and less impressed by Bertram by the day, particularly in his seducing of Diana and the fact that he will be happy to hear that Helena&#8217;s dead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. SOLD. AS INTERPRETER.">First Soldier as Interpreter</persname>
<persdescription>The First Soldier as Interpreter is a French soldier who begs to be allowed to play the part of interpreter during the abduction of Parolles. He has a wonderful store of fake language to use, which matches that of the French lords to perfection. He has a great time tormenting Parolles, and mocking him once the trick is known.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. SOLD.">Second Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Soldier is part of the ambush that abducts Parolles, and is sent to let Bertram and the First French Lord Dumaine know that he has been caught and is ready to speak.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger works for Bertram, and reports on how the latter has parted from the Duke of Florence.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>
 