<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Antony and Cleopatra">

<persona>
<persname short="CLEO.">Cleopatra, Queen of Egypt</persname>
<persdescription>Cleopatra is the Queen of Egypt. Notoriously one of the most difficult characters to play in all of Shakespeare, she is deeply erotic, charismatic, theatrical, volatile, temperamental, and generally unclassifiable. She seems to seduce every man she meets, leading her to be considered both an enchantress and a whore. An emblem of Oriental decadence, she is contrasted to the puritanical Romans, especially Caesar and Octavia, and it is her drawing Antony into her net that brings about his downfall, as he "goes native" under her influence, giving Caesar a handy excuse to cast Antony as a traitor to Roman principles. She may or may not have a genuine sentimental attachment to Antony; that is a matter of interpretation. If she does not, then she is using her erotic wiles to subjugate him so as to keep herself in power. She was once the lover of Julius Caesar, whom she claims was next to nothing compared to Antony. Excellent at staging herself to awe viewers (as she clearly managed to do to Enobarbus), she nevertheless possesses several vulnerabilities, not the least of which is her awareness that she is aging, which leads her to fear that Octavia make draw Antony from her. She is afraid that her dark skin may make her less appealing, along with her wrinkles. The extent to which Antony is under her spell, however, is revealed in the tales of how she drew him into cross-dressing with her. She is also able to make him disregard a direct messenger from Rome, mocking all that the Romans could possibly have to say. She plays at being sullen to disconcert Antony, but sends endless messengers to him when he is away, and appears to be unable to focus on anything in his absence. She has fits of violent temper, and beats the messenger who announces Antony&#8217;s marriage to Octavia until he runs away and is scared to return to her presence. She sends him to find out what Octavia looks like, and manages to reassure herself that she is herself the more attractive, though the messenger&#8217;s youthful indiscretion on the matter of age does not help. When war comes between Caesar and Antony, she insists on joining in the war in person, despite being a woman, and argues for the battle at sea. In the middle of the battle, however, she takes fright and runs with all her fleet, and Antony follows. Despite this disgrace to him, she is able to apologize and remain in his good favor. When Thidias comes to convince her to switch to Caesar&#8217;s side, she speaks flatteringly of Caesar, and offers her subjection. (This may be a deception on her part, or not.) She attempts to help arm Antony before the next battle, despite not knowing how the various bits and pieces of armor fit together. When Antony is convinced that she has betrayed him during the battle, he turns on her in rage, and she runs from him, afraid for her life. She locks herself in her monument, and at Charmian&#8217;s suggestion sends him word that she has killed herself, to find out how he will take the news. When he bungles his suicide and is brought to her, she refuses to exit the monument, out of fear, but helps to lift him in. She faints at his death. She speaks kindly to Proculeius, but on being seized by the Romans enters into a rage and threatens to kill herself, if need be by starving. When Caesar comes to her, she offers her submission, including giving him a scroll containing a list of all she possesses. This list, it turns out, is incomplete. All of this is done to make Caesar believe that she wishes to live, just as he speaks kindly to her to keep her from killing herself. But knowing that Caesar intends to lead her in a Triumph, she has herself dressed in her finest robes of state, and having had asps brought her by a country fellow, she allows them to bite her, one of the breast, the other on the arm, and dies.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLOWN.">Clown</persname>
<persdescription>A Clown is one of the more curious characters. The base fellow (the term &#8220;clown&#8221; means rustic, rather than a red-nosed person in a silly wig) brings Cleopatra her asps in a basket of figs; being a country clod, he is not considered important enough to keep from approaching the Queen by the Romans. One of Shakespeare&#8217;s bumpkins who do not quite master the language, he apparently has absolutely no sense of the gravity of events and prevents things from reaching sublimity while he is on stage. Seemingly rather dense, he does not take Cleopatra&#8217;s very obvious hints that he should leave, instead continuing to make labored comical comments.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RANN.">Rannius</persname>
<persdescription>Rannius, a Roman appearing as a mute in I.ii</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SOOTH.">Lamprius, the Soothsayer</persname>
<persdescription>Lamprius, the Soothsayer is, like the best of his kind, an enigmatic character. Reading the palms of Charmian and Iras, she correctly divines their futures, though what he tells them is so oddly phrased that the actual circumstances yet to come cannot be worked out. He follows Antony to Rome, but recommends he return to Egypt, as Antony&#8217;s &#8220;better angel&#8221; becomes weak in Caesar&#8217;s presence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DIO.">Diomedes</persname>
<persdescription>Diomedes is one of Cleopatra&#8217;s followers. She sends him to Antony when she suddenly fears he may have killed himself, but he arrives too late. Having informed the dying Antony that Cleopatra is, in fact, alive, he calls for Antony&#8217;s guard to help carry him to Cleopatra&#8217;s monument.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SEL.">Seleucus</persname>
<persdescription>Seleucus is Cleopatra&#8217;s treasurer. When she gives Caesar a scroll apparently containing an inventory of all her wealth, she calls on him to witness that it is complete. He claims that he is unwilling to lie and admits that the scroll does not mention about half her wealth, leading to Cleopatra&#8217;s having a fit of temper at him. It is possible that this is all a charade organized between Seleucus and Cleopatra, as the scroll is part of her plot to make Caesar believe she intends to live.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Mardian</persname>
<persdescription>Mardian is Cleopatra&#8217;s chief eunuch. A singer, he entertains her at need. He is quite capable of joking about his gelded state, which is just as well seeing as Cleopatra and her attendants have a tendency to do so whenever he&#8217;s around. Cleopatra sends him to bring Antony the false news of her death. He is among Cleopatra&#8217;s attendants when the Romans capture her, but is not present at her death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALEX.">Alexas</persname>
<persdescription>Alexas is one of Cleopatra&#8217;s attendants, the rather long-suffering butt of Charmian and Iras&#8217;s jokes. He brings in the Soothsayer and appears to believe in him much more than the women do. He goes with Antony when he leaves Egypt, and return to report about the trip and Antony&#8217;s disposition to Cleopatra. He is later sent by Cleopatra to order the messenger to find out about Octavia. He is sent by Antony to visit King Herod, but rebels and persuades the latter to turn to Caesar. In thanks, Caesar hangs him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AMB.">Schoolmaster (Ambassador)</persname>
<persdescription>An ambassador from Antony to Caesar is in fact Antony&#8217;s Schoolmaster. His being sent either means that Antony is done for, and has few followers left, as Dolabella states, or is a calculated insult to Caesar. He presents two separate embassies, one from Antony asking to be allowed either to live in Egypt or Athens, and another from Cleopatra requesting she may remain queen and bequeath this to her heirs. When he returns to Antony with the news that Caesar has no intention of letting him survive, he sends him back again with orders to call Caesar a coward and dare him to personal combat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIL.">Silius</persname>
<persdescription>Silius is one of Antony&#8217;s soldiers, sent with Ventidius to fight the Parthians. He urges Ventidius to gain an even greater victory by following the fleeing Parthians all through their land and destroying them, but accepts Ventidius&#8217;s refusal.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAR.">Varrius</persname>
<persdescription>Varrius is one of Pompey&#8217;s followers. He brings Pompey the unwelcome news that Antony has returned from Egypt to Rome to help quell Pompey&#8217;s revolt.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MENE.">Menecrates</persname>
<persdescription>Menecrates is one of the two pirates who join cause with Pompey, helping to give him the mastery of the seas. He does not believe that Caesar and Antony will be able to patch up their differences enough to make a difference in the revolt.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MENAS.">Menas</persname>
<persdescription>Menas is one of the two pirates who join cause with Pompey, helping to give him the mastery of the seas. He is much closer to Pompey than Menecrates. He and Enobarbus have fought before, but after the agreement between Pompey and the triumvirate, they chat quite amiably. He wishes that they had fought, as he believes that Pompey is giving away his power for nothing, and does not believe that the bond between Caesar and Antony will last, since he does not think anyone would give up Cleopatra for Octavia. He offers to Pompey to cut the ropes holding the ship to the land, set sail, and massacre the triumvirate and their followers; when Pompey refuses, he swears to never follow him again. He offers Enobarbus a bed for the night in his cabin afterwards. He may join Caesar and become part of his council of war, if one of the Folio&#8217;s stage directions can be trusted.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TAUR.">Taurus</persname>
<persdescription>Taurus is Caesar&#8217;s lieutenant, and commands his land forces at Actium.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GALL.">Gallus</persname>
<persdescription>Gallus is one of Caesar&#8217;s followers, and sent along with Proculeius when the latter is sent to keep Cleopatra from committing suicide. He may be the leader of a group of soldiers who physically take possession of her person.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="THID.">Thidias</persname>
<persdescription>Thidias is one of Caesar&#8217;s servants. Caesar sends him as a messenger to Cleopatra to try and convince her to switch sides, but when Antony discovers him just as he kisses Cleopatra&#8217;s hand, he has him thoroughly whipped. The whipping is sound enough to make him cry out, which Antony mocks him for.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRO.">Proculeius</persname>
<persdescription>Proculeius is one of Caesar&#8217;s followers. Antony tells Cleopatra to trust him. Caesar sends him to keep Cleopatra from killing herself. He sweet-talks her until his soldiers (or possibly Gallus) are able to physically take possession of her. Even after this, he continues to talk to her with all courtesy, counseling against suicide and urging her to trust in Caesar&#8217;s goodness.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOL.">Dolabella</persname>
<persdescription>Dolabella is one of Caesar&#8217;s followers. He recognizes Antony&#8217;s emissary as being Antony&#8217;s schoolmaster, and is charged by Caesar to go command Antony to surrender just before news of Antony&#8217;s death is brought. He is sent to Cleopatra, who has him admit that Caesar intends to lead her in a Triumph. Of his own accord, he tells her how long she has before Caesar intends to take her away, implicitly telling her by when she has time to commit suicide.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AGR.">Agrippa</persname>
<persdescription>Agrippa is one of Caesar&#8217;s chief advisers and generals. He is the one who suggests Antony marry Octavia, though it is possible, even likely, that this was Caesar&#8217;s own idea and that Agrippa was merely charged with bringing the matter up, as a disinterested party. He is Enobarbus&#8217;s friend and drinking companion, and hears his famous description of Cleopatra on her barge. For the rest of the play he is always present at Caesar&#8217;s military councils.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAEC.">Maecenas</persname>
<persdescription>Maecenas is one of Caesar&#8217;s followers. He attempts to calm down Antony and Caesar at their first conference. A friend of Enobarbus&#8217;s, he is one of the drinking companions to whom the latter gives his famous description of Cleopatra on her barge. When Antony sends his challenge to single combat to Caesar, Maecenas interprets this as a sign that Antony is pressed to the limit, and recommends giving him no time to rest.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAN.">Canidius</persname>
<persdescription>Canidius, a lieutenant-general, is one of Antony&#8217;s followers. He is skeptical of the idea of fighting Caesar by sea, and is given command of Antony&#8217;s land forces during the naval battle of Actium. On seeing Antony&#8217;s defeat, he defects to Caesar.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PHI.">Philo</persname>
<persdescription>Philo is one of Antony&#8217;s soldiers and our introduction to the play. Though he appears only in the first scene, he sets the tone, expressing his anger and disgust at Antony&#8217;s un-Roman ways.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DEM.">Demetrius</persname>
<persdescription>Demetrius is a Roman newly arrived in Egypt. He is unaware of the change in Antony&#8217;s manner until Philo apprises him of it, and is shocked that Antony considers Caesar to be of such little importance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DEC.">Decretas</persname>
<persdescription>Decretas is one of Antony&#8217;s guards. After Antony kills himself, he takes the sword Antony used and brings it to Caesar as proof of Antony&#8217;s death, in the hopes of ingratiating himself with Caesar.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCAR.">Scarus</persname>
<persdescription>Scarus is one of Antony&#8217;s followers. He witnesses Cleopatra&#8217;s flight from the battle at Actium and curses her for it. He stays loyal to Antony, however, and Cleopatra promises him a suit of armor made of gold that was once a king&#8217;s for his valiance. He is likely the Soldier who warns Antony not to fight by sea in 3.7.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EROS.">Eros</persname>
<persdescription>Eros is one of Antony&#8217;s attendants. He brings the news of Lepidus&#8217;s arrest by Caesar to Antony and also tells Enobarbus of it. He is one of those who leads Cleopatra to Antony after the defeat at Actium, in the hopes that she can comfort him. He brings Antony his armor and helps him put it on. He tells Antony of Enobarbus&#8217;s desertion and is told to send Enobarbus&#8217;s treasure after him. Upon hearing of Cleopatra&#8217;s (supposed) death, Antony asks Eros to kill him, but Eros stabs himself instead, being unwilling to witness Antony&#8217;s death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VEN.">Ventidius</persname>
<persdescription>Ventidius is one of Antony&#8217;s generals. Antony sends him to make war on the Parthians, and he wins a great victory in which Pacorus, the son of Parthian king Orades, is killed. When his follower Silius recommends that he continue fighting further and take over the entire Parthian empire, he refuses, citing the risk of Antony&#8217;s jealousy should he achieve such a great feat. He writes to Antony announcing his victory claiming that it was done in Antony&#8217;s name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ENO.">Domitius Enobarbus</persname>
<persdescription>Enobarbus is Antony&#8217;s friend and one of his followers, essentially his aide-de-camp. Though Antony sometimes makes him be quiet, in general he gets away with speaking his mind, and he provides an ironic, sarcastic and at times downright cheeky commentary on the action. Despite this, he obeys instantly when Antony gives a command. He enjoys drinking, and like most men is under Cleopatra&#8217;s spell. At the feast on Pompey&#8217;s galley, he insists that it is not raucous enough, and brings on the song and dance. Despite his loyalty to Antony, though, there comes a time when he can no longer hide from himself that he does not approve of his leader anymore, and he defects to Caesar. When Antony sends him his belongings with friendly words and no reproaches, he begins to have second thoughts about ever having left a man so generous. He dies loudly repenting having done so.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POM.">Sextus Pompeius</persname>
<persdescription>Sextus Pompey is the son of Pompey the Great, whom Julius Caesar had defeated just before the opening of <persnameref>Julius Caesar</persnameref>. He leads a popular rebellion against the triumvirate, which is widespread enough that it forces Caesar and Antony to make a truce. He accepts a parley with the triumvirate and in the end agrees to their terms, and suggests that they feast together. When Menas suggests to him that they set sail and murder the triumvirate at table, he refuses out of honor, but wishes Menas had done so without telling him about it. Of all the rulers we see in the play, he is the only one who ever speaks of the good of the people.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LEP.">M. Aemilius Lepidus</persname>
<persdescription>Lepidus is one of the triumvirs of Rome. Disregarded by the other two, Antony and Caesar, he is either a buffoon or a decent man caught in the wrong job, depending on how he is played. He attempts to make Antony and Caesar friends again, and genuinely wishes for peace between them. Unfortunately he is caught between the two, and will end up crushed by them. He cannot hold his liquor, and when drunk is very credulous. He is unfailingly polite, and during the banquet on Pompey&#8217;s ship never refuses another glass of wine even though he knows he shouldn&#8217;t. During the confrontation with Pompey he steps in to stop the posturing and get down to business. Enobarbus and Agrippa mock his expressions of friendship to the other two leaders. Caesar disposes of him off-stage, accusing him of having collaborated with Pompey, and having him killed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAES.">Octavius Caesar</persname>
<persdescription>Octavius Caesar, history&#8217;s Augustus, is one of the triumvirs (three leaders) of Rome. He disapproves of everything Antony stands for; he himself is a puritanical, rigid man, and he cannot stomach the loss of control that Antony&#8217;s actions betoken. He calls on Antony when he needs military help against Pompey&#8217;s insurrection, and to seal the bargain gives his sister in marriage to Antony. He is extremely fond of his sister, and becomes enraged when Antony abandons her. Over the course of the play he develops from a somewhat callow youth to the ruler of the known world, preceded by guards announcing his arrival. He is not above trickery, and is ready to lie to get Cleopatra under his control. He also has Lepidus done away with on apparently spurious grounds, and does not seem overly concerned with keeping his word if it gets in his way. When going into battle against Antony, he orders that those who have deserted Antony should fight in the front line. He is ruthless, and stands in contrast to the heroic Antony, who is a leftover from another age. His age at times works against him: Antony has a tendency to refer to him as the &#8220;boy Caesar.&#8221; He is the same as the Octavius Caesar of <persnameref>Julius Caesar</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT.">Mark Antony</persname>
<persdescription>Antony is one of the triumvirs of Rome. The same as the Mark Antony of <persnameref>Julius Caesar</persnameref>, he is much older in this play, and ever-so-faintly past his prime. A survivor from an age of heroes, he does not quite fit in the new world that Caesar is creating. He is a clearly a fine specimen of a man, physically imposing and powerful, though he may be going slightly to seed. Caesar is well-advised not to meet him in single combat, as he would be severely outmatched. Generous and given to overlarge gestures, Antony inspires great love and devotion in his followers. He is the greatest soldier of the age, which is why Caesar and Lepidus need his help so much against Pompey: his name alone alters the balance of power. He is, however, almost completely under Cleopatra&#8217;s spell. Preferring to spend time with her than on official business, he refuses to hear a messenger from Rome. Discovering that his wife Fulvia has made civil war on his brother, before dying, he realizes that he can no longer stay in Egypt, and that his devotion to Cleopatra is making him risk everything, especially given Pompey&#8217;s revolt and the need the triumvirate has of him to put it down. Leaving Cleopatra, he tells her that Fulvia&#8217;s death should reassure her that he is not deserting her, but he then accepts Caesar&#8217;s offer of his sister Octavia in marriage. He asks the Soothsayer whether he should return to Egypt, and all that he is told confirms his fears. Noticing that his luck is bad compared to Caesar&#8217;s, he resolves to leave, having married Octavia only for the sake of peace, while his pleasures are in the East. At Pompey&#8217;s feast, he mocks the credulous Lepidus with his description of the crocodile. He later rages against Caesar&#8217;s belittling behavior concerning him, and agrees to send Octavia as a mediator between them, using her absence as an opportunity to return to Egypt. There he and Cleopatra enthrone themselves as Emperor and Empress of the East, paying no attention to Rome itself. This complete rejection of Rome infuriates Caesar and gives him an excellent rallying call against Antony. Despite the advice of his council, he insists on fighting Caesar at sea as Cleopatra recommends, and accepts to have her go to the war herself; but when she takes fright and flees, he follows. The sheer disgrace this brings on him, quite aside from the military defeat, breaks his spirit. He becomes aware of how far he has fallen, and turns on Cleopatra in a rage. He is reconciled to her, though. When Caesar refuses to accept his request to be allowed to live as a private citizen, he sends him back an insulting message calling for single combat between the two. Seeing Thidias having a private audience with Cleopatra and kissing her hand, he becomes enraged and has him whipped, cursing Cleopatra in fine style. He sends Thidias back with a message of defiance to Caesar, and rouses himself again, calling his captains to have a gaudy night with him. By bringing his followers to the point of tears, he is able to reaffirm their loyalty to him. Hearing that Enobarbus has deserted leaving all of his possessions behind, he sends them all after him. After his final defeat, he curses Cleopatra to her face as the cause of all his woes, but when she sends him the false news of her death he decides that he has lived long enough. He asks Eros to kill him, but the latter commits suicide rather than do so. Antony then attempts to kill himself, but does not manage it well, and is left slowly dying; like Eros, his guards refuses to give a fatal blow. Carried to the monument, he is lifted into it by Cleopatra and his women. He warns her to trust only Proculeius among the Romans, then begs to be remembered as he used to be and to be thought of as a Roman killed by a Roman. He then dies.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="IRAS.">Iras</persname>
<persdescription>Iras is Cleopatra&#8217;s second lady-in-waiting. She is somewhat more subdued a character than Charmian, but is just as able to make a dirty pun. She pushes Cleopatra to try and comfort Antony after the defeat at Actium, and later helps lift him into the monument. When Cleopatra faints at Antony&#8217;s death, she at first thinks her mistress is dead. She agrees with Cleopatra that it is better to die nobly than to be led in Triumph. After helping to dress Cleopatra in her royal robes, she dies, apparently of a broken heart, before Cleopatra can in fact commit suicide.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHAR.">Charmian</persname>
<persdescription>Charmian is Cleopatra&#8217;s main lady-in-waiting. Saucy and given to making racy jokes on every available pretext, she is also deeply loyal to her mistress. She does not take the Soothsayer seriously. She has a tendency to advise Cleopatra on how to deal with Antony, recommending that she give way to him in all things, and later suggesting the idea of telling Antony that Cleopatra&#8217;s dead. She plays along with all of Cleopatra&#8217;s theatrics, though in private suggests to her that her adoration of Antony is too great and attempts to calm her rage at the messenger. Not unlike Enobarbus with Antony, she is able to tease Cleopatra, for instance by reminding her of how much she had doted on Julius Caesar. She helps to lift Antony into the monument, and is the one Cleopatra sends to have asps brought to them. After Cleopatra&#8217;s death, she too has an asp bite her, and dies.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OCT.">Octavia</persname>
<persdescription>Octavia is Caesar&#8217;s sister. She is offered as a wife to Antony to seal a bond between him and Caesar. Cold, pious and proper, she is in every way the opposite of Cleopatra. She is deeply attached to her brother and weeps to leave him. She is horrified when Caesar and Antony fall out, feeling she&#8217;s caught in the middle. Antony allows her to go to Caesar to attempt to mediate between them, but when she arrives at Caesar&#8217;s camp she discovers that he did so as it gave him an opportunity to run off to Egypt.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUCILL.">Lucillius</persname>
<persdescription>Lucillius, a Roman appearing as a mute in I.ii</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCAR.">Scarus</persname>
<persdescription>Scarus is one of Antony&#8217;s commanders, who warns him not to fight by sea. When Antony refuses to listen, he reaffirms his opinion to Camidius, and double-checks that their land forces will not be divided. He witnesses Cleopatra&#8217;s flight from the battle at Actium and curses her for it. He stays loyal to Antony, however. He explains Caesar&#8217;s unbelievable speed of action as his having left Rome in such a way that the spies did not realize it. He is primed for battle the morning of the land fight, though he has to announce to Antony that Enobarbus has deserted them. He is overjoyed at their victory and does not care about his wounds; Cleopatra promises him an armor made of gold that was once a king&#8217;s for his valiance. He witnesses Antony&#8217;s dejection as the battle of Actium goes badly for him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 1. ATT.">Antony&#8217;s First Attendant</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ATT.">Both Antony&#8217;s Attendants</persname>
	<persname short="ALL. ANT. ATT.">All Antony&#8217;s Attendants</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s First Attendant follows him at the Egyptian court and calls to find out if there is a messenger from Sicyon. He continues to follow Antony and refuses to run away when Antony suggests that his followers should. He is brought to tears when Antony begins to clasp his followers&#8217; hands at their meal before the last battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 2. ATT.">Antony&#8217;s Second Attendant</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ATT.">Both Antony&#8217;s Attendants</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s Second Attendant confirms the presence of a messenger from Sicyon. He continues to follow Antony and refuses to run away when Antony suggests that his followers should. He is brought to tears when Antony begins to clasp his followers&#8217; hands at their meal before the last battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. CAES. MESS.">Caesar&#8217;s First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s First Messenger brings Caesar the unwelcome news that Pompey has a strong sea force, and that the people who follow him do it out of love, while they merely obey Caesar from fear.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CAES. MESS.">Caesar&#8217;s Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s Second Messenger brings the news that Menas and Menecrates have joined with Pompey, and that they have total mastery of the sea, prompting Caesar&#8217;s outburst at Antony.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. CAES. MESS.">Caesar&#8217;s Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s Third Messenger comes to tell him that Antony has advanced for battle. He is sent to have the soldiers who deserted Antony placed at the front of the troops, so that they&#8217;ll bear the brunt of the assault.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. MESS.">First Roman Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Roman Messenger attempts to deliver some news from Rome to Antony, but is brushed off.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. MESS.">Second Roman Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Roman Messenger confirms to Antony that Caesar has taken Toryne, proof of the startling speed at which he is advancing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger brings Antony the news of how his wife, Fulvia, has made war on his brother Lucius. He also admits to Antony that the Romans are beginning to turn against him, and accuse him of spending his time dallying with Cleopatra rather than making war and protecting the empire.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger comes from Sicyon with the news that Fulvia is dead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EGYPT. MESS.">Egyptian Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Egyptian Messenger brings Cleopatra the news of Antony&#8217;s marriage. Knowing that his news will be unwelcome, he takes as long as possible to actually state it. When Cleopatra begins to strike him, he begs her not to kill the messenger &#8212; what has happened is not his fault. Thogh not necessarily a coward, he is terrified when Cleopatra begins beating him and draws a knife on him. He refuses to lie, but when he returns to describe Octavia, he very diplomatically hedges and manages to phrase everything about her in a way that will be to Cleopatra&#8217;s advantage. He then makes a mistake, however: being a young man, he thinks Octavia is old at thirty, not realizing that Cleopatra herself is well past that age, and that he has just made a grave mistake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. EGYPT. SERV.">First Egyptian Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The First Egyptian Servant announces Thidias&#8217;s arrival to Cleopatra. He later takes Thidias to be whipped.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. EGYPT. SERV.">Second Egyptian Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Egyptian Servant [mute role] helps drag away Thidias to be whipped.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 1. SOLD.">Antony&#8217;s First Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ANT. SOLD.">All Antony&#8217;s Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s First Soldier at Antony&#8217;s camp believes that they may prevail over Caesar the next day. Having heard the unearthly music, he suggests finding out whether anyone else has, and to trace it to find out how far it can be heard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 2. SOLD.">Antony&#8217;s Second Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ANT. SOLD">All Antony&#8217;s Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s Second Soldier has heard a rumor, likely about strange music. He is uncertain of victory. He identifies the music as meaning that Hercules is abandoning Antony.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 3. SOLD.">Antony&#8217;s Third Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ANT. SOLD">All Antony&#8217;s Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s Third Soldier identifies the music as coming from under the earth, and realizes that this is not a good omen for their side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 4. SOLD.">Antony&#8217;s Fourth Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ANT. SOLD">All Antony&#8217;s Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s Fourth Soldier thinks (hopes?) that the strange music is a good omen for Antony&#8217;s side in the coming battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAPT. ANT. ARMY.">Captain of Antony&#8217;s Army</persname>
<persdescription>Captain of Antony&#8217;s Army is primed for battle the morning of the battle before Alexandria.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAES. 1. SOLD.">Caesar&#8217;s First Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s First Soldier brings Enobarbus the news that Antony has sent all of his treasure after him. Enobarbus does not believe him, but the soldier assures him that it is true.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAES. SENT.">Caesar&#8217;s Sentry</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s Sentry is the commander of the Watch patrolling the camp. As it is a bright night, he believes the battle will start early. He recognizes Enobarbus during the latter&#8217;s repentance, and thinks it more important to hear what he says than to comfort him, in case it concerns Caesar. Once their time of duty is up, he decides that they should take the body with them, as Enobarbus is a person of some importance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAES. 1. WATCH.">Caesar&#8217;s First Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s First Watchman is aware that the last day&#8217;s battle was a closely run thing, and wants to talk to Enobarbus, but is prevented by the Sentry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAES. 2. WATCH.">Caesar&#8217;s Second Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>Caesar&#8217;s Second Watchman thinks that Enobarbus is only sleeping, and after his death holds some hope that he may recover.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 1. GUARD.">Antony&#8217;s First Guardsman</persname>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s First Guardsman is crestfallen at his flawed suicide, but refuse to give him the final blow to end his suffering, not being willing to be the one who ended his life. He nevertheless agrees to carry Antony to Cleopatra&#8217;s monument, where he helps lift him up to the Queen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. 2. GUARD.">Antony&#8217;s Second Guardsman</persname>
<persdescription>Antony&#8217;s Second Guardsman is crestfallen at his flawed suicide, but refuse to give him the final blow to end his suffering, not being willing to be the one who ended his life. He nevertheless agrees to carry Antony to Cleopatra&#8217;s monument, where he helps lift him up to the Queen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. GUARD.">First Roman Guard</persname>
<persdescription>The First Roman Guard comes to tell Cleopatra about the Clown who insists on speaking to her, and lets him in. He later comes to bring a message from Caesar only to find that Cleopatra is dead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. GUARD.">Second Roman Guard</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Roman Guard is called in by the first guard when the latter discovers Cleopatra dead, and suggests finding Dolabella.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. SOLD.">First Roman Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>The First Roman Soldier [mute role] accompanies Proculeius on his visit to Cleopatra, and sneaks up on the Queen while she is distracted.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. SOLD.">Second Roman Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Roman Soldier [mute role] accompanies Proculeius on his visit to Cleopatra, and sneaks up on the Queen while she is distracted.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POM. 1. SERV.">Pompey&#8217;s First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Pompey&#8217;s First Servant bringing in the banquet (dessert) at the feast on Pompey&#8217;s galley notes how Lepidus continues drinking even though he likely knows he shouldn&#8217;t. He also appears to mock Lepidus as being of little note to the world.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POM. 2. SERV.">Pompey&#8217;s Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Pompey&#8217;s Second Servant bringing in the banquet (dessert) at the feast on Pompey&#8217;s galley comments on how Lepidus is either asking to no longer have drinks pressed on him, or begging the other two triumvirs to cease quarreling. The fact that it clearly isn&#8217;t working does not leave him impressed.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>