<PERSONAE playtitle="As You Like It">
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="AUD.">Audrey</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Audrey is a goatherd Touchstone lusts after, and perhaps even loves. She is unlearned, honest, looks for honesty in others, does not consider herself good-looking, and is virtuous. She is quite willing to marry Touchstone, as it will allow her to rise in the world, and does not understand what the problem with having Martext do so is. She does not know how to conduct herself in courtly company.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="PHE.">Phebe</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Phebe is a dark-featured, black-haired, large-eyed shepherdess beloved by Silvius. She takes his metaphors literally and is insulted by them, has a sarcastic edge to her tongue and is not afraid to use it on his wooer. She falls completely in love with a young man who insults her for being too proud, and uses Silvius to deliver a letter to him for her. She cannot understand why Ganymede will not return her feelings until the end of the play, when it turns out that Ganymede is actually a woman. Having promised to wed Silvius if she ever refused Ganymede, she accepts to do so.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CEL.">Celia</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Celia is Duke Frederick&#8217;s daughter. When the latter took power, she became acquainted with her cousin Rosalind, and they were soon inseparable. Though she may love him, she does not like her father, particularly when he wrongs Rosalind; and when he banishes her, she insists on following along. It is she who has the idea that they run away to the Forest of Arden to seek Rosalind&#8217;s father. She is amused at her cousin&#8217;s falling head over heels for Orlando, given her propensity to laugh at love. She is saucy enough to make the occasional bawdy joke and teases Rosalind mercilessly while still playing along with all her plots. She grows worried that Rosalind is taking things too far. She is somewhat more given to common sense than Rosalind, coming up with the idea of disguise, thinking to take their jewels and riches with them when they flee court, which allows them to buy the cottage where they stay, and preferring to take a nap to sighing over an absent lover. She falls in love with Oliver when they meet, and he with her, and they decide to marry without the excessive courtship that marks Orlando and Rosalind&#8217;s love. Shorter than Rosalind, she is a great favorite of Touchstone&#8217;s, whom she persuades to follow her and Rosalind to the forest.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="ROS.">Rosalind</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Rosalind is the Old Duke&#8217;s daughter. When Duke Frederick took power, he did not exile her, and she and her cousin Celia soon became inseparable friends. She cannot forget the fact of her father&#8217;s exile, however, and this sometimes leaves her depressed. Long-tongued and witty, she is a great dissector of love, but is not immune to it: she becomes instantly enamored of the young wrestler who challenges Charles. Banished by Duke Frederick, she flees with Celia to the Forest of Arden, dressed as a boy named Ganymede to ward off unwanted attentions. The news that Orlando is in love with her and in the forest sets her all a-flutter. She takes advantage of her anonymity and male dress to learn to know him better and to cure him of his habit of writing bad poetry. With her plan of teaching him to woo her while she is still in disguise, she is able to have a courtship without all of the attendant dangers. She also plays with others&#8217; love affairs, particularly when she intervenes between Phoebe and Silvius to berate the former for being too harsh. It unfortunately turns out that Phoebe prefers a domineering and tactless man to a poetic one, and she falls quite in love with Ganymede. Rosalind insists that love is not nearly as serious as everyone makes it out to be, and despite her giddy descriptions to Celia of just how much she is herself in love it is not until she faints at seeing the bloody evidence of Orlando&#8217;s injury that thinks start to look truly serious. When Orlando decides that he has had enough of play-acting, Rosalind brings it all to an end by staging her reappearance as herself. Precisely how she convinces the god of marriage to attend is not recorded. She is unusually tall for a woman.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="HYM.">Hymen</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Hymen is the God of Marriage. He appears to link the four couples at the end of the play, restoring Rosalind to her father so that he may give her to Orlando.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="WILL.">William</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>William is a countryman in love with Audrey. He is 25, reasonably well-off, unschooled, courteous in removing his hat to a social superior, and completely outclassed by Touchstone&#8217;s verbal skills and threats, a short speech from whom is enough to convince him to give up on the girl.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="SIL.">Silvius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Silvius is a young shepherd, desperately in love with Phoebe and unwilling to believe that the aged can possibly understand his torment. He woos Phoebe poetically, which is unfortunate as she has no taste for metaphor. He is willing to do all she commands, including deliver a letter that he presumes to be angrily written to an insulting young man. He is appalled to discover that Phoebe has fallen for said young man. He can catechize what love is when required.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="COR.">Corin</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Corin is an old shepherd in the Forest of Arden. He does not own the sheep he tends, as he is another man&#8217;s worker. When a young man learns that Corin&#8217;s employer is selling his house and livelihood from under him, and offers to buy it and to continue Corin&#8217;s employment, the old man is happy to act as intermediary in the sale. He is a realist, and does not consider himself any worse than a greater man, recognizing that different levels of society require different ways of being, and being perfectly content with the ways required by his shepherd&#8217;s life. He does not let himself get overly drawn in to Touchstone&#8217;s games of wit.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="SIR OLI.">Sir Oliver Martext</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Sir Oliver Martext is a country vicar who is not considered likely to do his job well, which is the very reason Touchstone hopes to use him rather than another for his marriage to Aubrey. He insists that mockery will not keep him from remaining a clergyman.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="TOUCH.">Touchstone</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Touchstone is Duke Frederick&#8217;s jester, and so fond of Celia that he is willing to abandon the court to follow her to the forest, for all that he does not enjoy rural life. His folly is based on a solid ground of common sense, for he will have little to do with the high-flying phrases of love surrounding him, much preferring to mock poetry and to woo Audrey for determinedly physical reasons. He hopes to marry her with the help of Sir Oliver Martext for the very reason that it will be easy to break the wedding on the grounds of an incompetent ceremony once he&#8217;s had enough of the goatherd. He mocks Jaques by imitation without the latter realizing it, and attempts to debate matters with all comers, though Corin manages to defeat him by refusing to play along. His greatest gift is perhaps his ability to see both sides of an argument, but this does not mean that he is fair: he is not above using his courtly ways to mock and overawe simpler folk, particularly when he threatens William. In many ways, he is Jaques&#8217;s non-melancholic mirror.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="DEN.">Dennis</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Denis is Oliver&#8217;s servant. He brings in Charles the wrestler.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="ADAM.">Adam</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Adam is an old servant of Sir Rowland&#8217;s, who greatly affections Orlando. He is almost 80 years old but still physically fit, and does not approve of his new young master&#8217;s injurious ways. He has served the de Boys for 63 years, saving a great deal of money, which he offers to Orlando when he overhears Oliver&#8217;s plan to burn the boy to death. He recommends flight to the forest to the young man, and follows him, but his strength fails from starvation. Orlando carries him to Duke Senior&#8217;s campsite, where he is given food to revive him.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="ORL.">Orlando</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Orlando is the youngest son of the deceased Sir Rowland de Boys. His eldest brother Oliver mistreats him, refusing to educate him as he does the second son Jaques. He is an excellent wrestler, noble, well-loved by all who know him, proud of his birth and intelligent, as well as young and tongue-tied in front of women. He falls head over heels in love with Rosalind on speaking to her. Gaining Duke Frederick&#8217;s enmity for beating his favorite wrestler and being Sir Rowland&#8217;s son, and with his eldest brother planning to burn him to death in his sleep, he flees to the Forest of Arden with Adam. He is faithful to the faithful old man, carrying him on his back when he can no longer walk. Starving, Orlando attempts to rob Duke Senior and his men of food, only to discover that they will share it willingly. He is a very bad poet, and writes poems in praise of Rosalind that he hangs up on the trees around the woods. He does not listen to criticisms of his writing, but on meeting Ganymede accepts to play the game of learning how to woo a woman, learning in the process to love genuinely rather than playing at it. Coming across his brother in danger from both a snake and a lioness, he almost leaves Oliver to be killed, but his nobility of spirit prevents him from doing so. The two are thereby reconciled. Orlando is taken about at the fact that Oliver falls in love and convinces Aliena to marry him as quickly as he does. He becomes rather confused about Ganymede, but trusts him for the sake of his love for Rosalind. He has chestnut hair and no more than the beginning of a beard.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="OLI.">Oliver</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Oliver is the eldest son of Sir Rowland de Boys, and his heir. Detesting his youngest brother for no reason that he can himself fathom, Oliver refuses to educate him, keeps the money he is due away from him, and plots his death. He is scornful and malicious, not above spreading lies about Orlando to convince Charles to have no mercy when wrestling with him, and envious that people love Orlando more than they do him. Incensed by Orlando&#8217;s beating Charles, he plans to burn Orlando to death in his sleep. When Orlando flees, Oliver is charged by Duke Frederick to find him, on pain of exile, with all his valuables held as surety in the meantime. Admitting to his hatred for his brother merely has him thrown out. He seeks Orlando till his beard has grown unkempt and his clothes ragged. Falling asleep, he suddenly wakes to find Orlando busy fighting a lioness that was waiting to eat him. He reconciles himself with his brother, and is sent by him to explain to Ganymede why he cannot appear himself. He is somewhat suspicious of Ganymede, not believing his protestations of counterfeiting when he faints; he also falls thoroughly in love with Aliena, woos her, and convinces her to marry him in an instant, intending to give all of his wealth to Orlando and to live with her as a shepherd.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CHA.">Charles</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Charles is the Duke&#8217;s wrestler. An honorable fellow, he comes to dissuade Oliver from letting Orlando participate in the wrestling the next day. As his reputation is at stake, he refuses to be gentle with any challenger, and thinks it only fair to warn a gentleman of the fact. Convinced by Oliver that if he does anything other than kill Orlando, the latter will poison him, he decides to fight him as best he can, and to give up wrestling if he does not win. Orlando beats him; and what he does with the rest of his life is not recorded.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="LE BEAU.">Le Beau</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Le Beau is a courtier of Duke Frederick&#8217;s. He is a gossip, excited about wrestling, and thinks that Celia and Rosalind would greatly enjoy seeing Charles break people&#8217;s ribs. He is honorable enough to warn Orlando to flee from Duke Frederick after his victory over Charles, and correctly predicts that the usurping duke will soon cease to be friendly to his niece.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="JAQ.">Jaques</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Jaques is a lord in Duke Senior&#8217;s party, a man who affects melancholy and whose name sounds the same as another word for &#8216;chamberpot.&#8217; He seeks out excuses for his melancholic outlook, whether it be asking for more depressing music or looking at a wounded deer. He is nevertheless capable of mocking his fellow lords, is brought to great merriment by meeting Touchstone (without realizing that the jester has been making fun of him), and attempts to get to know every person he meets despite his protestations that he does not much like people. He was once quite the ladies&#8217; man, but now is something close to Duke Senior&#8217;s jester, though instead of providing foolery he provides long discourses on the ways of the world and expounds on well-worn clich&amp;eacute;s such as the Ages of Man. Affected though it may be, and proud of it though he maybe, his melancholy takes a serious turn at the end of the play when he chooses not to join in the reveling accompanying his companions&#8217; restoration to their fortunes, voluntarily excluding himself from happiness so as to go and learn from the converted Duke Frederick.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="AMI.">Amiens</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Amiens is a lord attending on the exiled Duke. He is a musical man, often singing, though he attempts to get out of singing for Jaques.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="DUKE F.">Duke Frederick</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Duke Frederick is a usurper, who took the throne from his brother and banished him from the land. He is moody, greedy, and peremptory. He dislikes people who have a better reputation than he does, and holds the grudge even to their children. He kept his niece Rosalind at court when he took over, latterly because of his daughter Celia&#8217;s affection for her cousin, but grows to worry that she plans treason against him, as well as that she overshadows Celia and may try to keep the latter from inheriting. He therefore banishes her. He appropriates all the wealth of the noblemen who flee to the forest to be with his brother, and when he sends Oliver to find Orlando, he takes over the de Boys estates until Oliver returns. He is always accompanied by attending lords whom he can send to carry out his orders. When the number of nobles voluntarily leaving to join the banished Duke grows too high, he raises an army to seek his brother out and kill him, but meets a religious man on the way and is soon converted, relinquishing his government and becoming a hermit in a cave, where he will be joined by Jaques.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="DUKE S.">Duke Senior</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Duke Senior was exiled to the Forest of Arden when his younger brother usurped his throne. He accepts this with great philosophy, finding life in the forest superior to life at court, partly because it is a more honest life. He is surrounded by many lords who have either been exiled with him or come of their own accord out of opposition to the new regime. He particularly enjoys the company of Jaques, whom he does not take as seriously as Jaques does himself. He is charitable and welcoming. Though he does not recognize his daughter Rosalind in her disguise as Ganymede, he sees some similarities between the two; he also does not recognize his niece when she is dressed as a shepherdess. His affection for the dead Rowland de Boys leads him to accept Orlando into his company, and to consider him worthy to be his son-in-law. On the announcement that he has been restored to his dukedom, he chooses to take the time for some non-courtly merriment before returning to the real world.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="JAQ. DE B.">Jaques De Boys</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Jaques de Boys is the second son of Sir Rowland. Unlike his younger brother Orlando, he is sent away to school and treated as well as he should be by Oliver. He appears at the end to announce Duke Frederick&#8217;s conversion to the religious life. He is not to be confused with the Jaques who attends Duke Senior.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="1. LORD. COURT.">First Lord at Court</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>First Lord at Court is one of Duke Frederick&#8217;s constant attendants, and interrogates Celia&#8217;s attendants in the wake of her flight.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="2. LORD. COURT.">Second Lord at Court</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Second Lord at Court is one of Duke Frederick&#8217;s constant attendants; he discovers that Touchstone has gone with the missing ladies, and that they both had been commenting appreciatively on Orlando.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="1. LORD. ARD.">First Lord in Arden</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>First Lord in Arden is one of the exiled Duke&#8217;s followers. Along with Amiens, he spots Jaques as the latter apostrophizes a wounded deer, and reports it to the Duke, knowing that the latter enjoys speaking to Jaques when he&#8217;s in these moods. He helps to Duke to find Jaques, and later hunts down a deer and is jokingly borne in triumph by the other lords for it.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="2. LORD. ARD.">Second Lord in Arden</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Second Lord in Arden is one of the exiled Duke&#8217;s followers. He is among those who spy on Jaques sorrowing over the wounded deer, and joins the lords in singing the First Lord&#8217;s hunting triumph.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="1. PAGE.">First Page</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>First Page is one of Duke Senior&#8217;s company. He has a high opinion of his singing abilities.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="2. PAGE.">Second Page</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Second Page is one of Duke Senior&#8217;s company, and an enthusiastic singer.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
  </PERSONAE>