<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="A Comedy of Errors">

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LUCE.">Luce</persname>
<persdescription>Luce, also known as Nell, is a maid at Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s. She has little patience with loud ruffians at the gate, whom she consigns to the stocks.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LUC.">Luciana</persname>
<persdescription>Luciana is Adriana&#8217;s sister, and dwells with her and Antipholus of Epheseus. She can preach on the natural submission of women to men as well as anyone, and tries to calm her sister down when she grows impatient with her husband. However, she does not scruple to tell her brother-in-law off, nor to insult the servants. She also advises Antipholus of Syracuse to at least pretend to still love his wife if he doesn&#8217;t. She is unnerved to suddenly find herself courted by him, and to swear him swear that he is unmarried. Convinced that he is mad, she becomes both pitying and terrified of him. She defends her sister&#8217;s actions to the Abbess, and recommends to Adriana to beg the Duke for help. Once all the confusions are sorted out, it is understood that she will be properly wooed by Antipholus of Syracuse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ADR.">Adriana</persname>
<persdescription>Adriana is Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s wife, and a proto-feminist distraught that her husband is paying attention to another woman and irritated that men are not as bound as women are, nor women as free as men. She does not think her sister has much right to judge her opinions, as Luciana lacks a husband to grieve her and therefore doesn&#8217;t actually know what she&#8217;s talking about. She feels deeply wronged by her husband&#8217;s constant desertions, though he swears that his interactions with the Courtesan are entirely respectable. She pleads with her husband to come home for lunch, disturbed as she is by his jesting and pretense that he doesn&#8217;t know her. Grieved by the news that Antipholus of Syracuse has been flirting with her sister, she bursts into a fine flurry of insults at him. She is soon convinced that he is mad, however, and fetches Doctor Pinch to cure him. When her husband escapes into the priory, she attempts to reason with the Abbess to have him sent forth, but is denied, and she must sue to the Duke instead, though she somewhat overstates her case. Of wealthy birth, she married Antipholus of Ephesus at the Duke&#8217;s entreaty. She is emotional, and giving to beating her servants.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ABB.">Aemilia</persname>
<persdescription>Abbess Aemilia is an abbess in Ephesus, highly respected by all. She was shipwrecked years ago and lost her husband, as well as her twin sons, in the wreck. She approves of the concept that wives should chide their husbands for spending time with other women, but also chides the wives for complaining too much. She refuses to have the sanctuary of her house breached, insisting that she will treat Adriana&#8217;s husband&#8217;s madness herself. Discovering the identity of the man in her care, she rushes outside to explain everything to the Duke and see her husband again for the first time in decades. She holds a great feast at the abbey to celebrate the reunion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PINCH.">Doctor Pinch</persname>
<persdescription>Pinch is a conjurer and exorcist hired by Adriana to cure Antipholus of Epheseus of his madness. He is extremely lean, bearded, with deep-set eyes and a yellow cast to his face. Determining that both the Ephesan Antipholus and his servant Dromio are possessed, he reveals that his cure for this is affliction is to have them tied up and left in a dark room. This is an unfortunate decision, as when they break free they set his beard on fire and poke him with a pair of scissors.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANG.">Angelo</persname>
<persdescription>Angelo is a goldsmith in Syracuse, the maker of a fine gold chain commissioned by Antipholus of Ephesus. He is not happy at being denied lunch at Antipholus&#8217;s. He is waiting to be paid for the chain to be able to settle his debt with the Second Merchant. He is chary of his reputation and confused by Antipholus of Syracuse&#8217;s actions, though finally convinced of the man&#8217;s unfortunate madness. He bears witness to all he knows before the Duke.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BALTH.">Balthazar</persname>
<persdescription>Balthazar is a merchant of Ephesus and a friend of the local Antipholus. When they are locked out of Antipholus&#8217;s house, he manages to calm the man down and prevent him from making a scandal by breaking down his own door.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="S. DRO.">Dromio of Syracuse</persname>
<persdescription>Dromio of Syracuse is Antiopholus of Syracuse&#8217;s slave. A quick-witted fellow, he has a good relationship with his master: despite the latter&#8217;s tendency to beat him, they often enter into flights of repartee where Antipholus gives Dromio free range to exercise his wit. He is deeply confused by the misunderstandings of the day, and wishes for a place to pray, being quickly convinced that he and his master are under a spell. At Adriana&#8217;s entreaty he keeps the gate to the house closed while she and his master dine, and uses a rude tongue against those who hope to come in. He is terrified of the fat kitchen-maid who lays claim to him, and runs to his master for safety, convinced she is a witch. He finds a ship for them to flee on, but also has to run for money from Adriana when Antipholus (of Ephesus) is arrested. Returning with the money to find Antipholus (of Syracuse) denying any knowledge of this, he is even more ready to believe that the courtesan is a devil when she comes to speak to them. Though with his master he begins to walk about with his sword drawn, he becomes slightly reconciled to the place, until they are suddenly on the verge of being tied up as madmen, at which point he hurries Antipholus (of Syracuse) into a nearby priory. He is greatly relieved when all the confusion is cleared up and he discovers that he will not have to marry Nell the kitchen-maid. His humor can be of a low sort, racist and scatological by turns, but he is a kind man, insisting that his twin of Ephesus take precedence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="E. DRO.">Dromio of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Dromio of Ephesus is Antipholus of Ephesus&#8217;s slave. He has the misfortune of having both a master and a mistress given to beating him, though he may find some consolation in the love of Nell the kitchen-maid. He endures them patiently, though he is not afraid to run away when need be to escape the blows, nor to complain of how beatings is all he has ever known from his master. He is completely flummoxed by the misunderstandings of the day, not understanding the cause of the number of beatings he receives, nor for that matter why he finds himself tied up as a madman. He is freed when Antipholus (of Ephesus) chews through their ropes, and they join to torment the exorcist, Dromio pricking him with a pair of scissors. From here on he no longer considers himself to be bound to Antipholus of Ephesus, merely to be his servant. He is charmed to meet his brother, delicately complimenting him and insisting that they be equals.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="S. ANT.">Antipholus of Syracuse</persname>
<persdescription>Antipholus of Syracuse is Egeon&#8217;s son. Separated from his twin at birth, at the age of eighteen he decided to travel the world to find him, and has been searching for him these last seven years. He is attended by Dromio of Syracuse. He is a cautious traveler, terrified of the possibility of magic, and weary of the inhabitants of Ephesus, since he has heard that they are all sorcerers. Though he allows his Dromio a fair bit of leeway in terms of mockery, and likes to play straight man to his wit, Antipholus of Syracuse has his limits, and is not restrained in the use of his fists when he thinks his slave has gone too far, particularly if it concerns money. He soon becomes convinced that he is someway or other be-spelled, especially when a beautiful woman begins to call him husband and bid him to come home, and he allows himself to be entranced, though he finds the woman&#8217;s sister far more attractive than she, and begins to woo her. Rejected, he decides that things have gone too far and that it would be best to leave before nightfall. He is confused when a passing goldsmith gives him a necklace made specially for him and refuses to take money for it at once, and the occurrence merely reaffirms his decision to leave. As every person he meets on the street greets him, and Dromio (of Syracuse) arrives speaking of having seen him arrested, and a courtesan comes snuggling up to him and asking for a ring back, he grows completely panicked and begins to wander about with his sword drawn. Coming across the goldsmith again, who swears that he has denied to pay for the chain, challenged to a fight by a merchant for forswearing himself, and seeing his supposed wife announce to all and sundry that he is mad, he is thoroughly discombobulated and runs into a priory for sanctuary, where he discovers that the Abbess is his long-lost mother, that his father is in town and about to be executed, and that his twin brother also lives in town and that he has been being confused with him all day long. Discovering this, he promises to renew his wooing of Luciana, this time more lawfully.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="E. ANT.">Antipholus of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Antipholus of Ephesus was brought up in Corinth, never knowing his father, and brought to Ephesus by Duke Menaphon of Corinth. Duke Solinus of Ephesus, Menaphon&#8217;s nephew, became his patron, and he served worthily in his wars. The Duke arranged for his marriage to a wealthy lady, Adriana, and he became one of the richest and best-known merchants in Ephesus, known for his honor and good credit. His marriage is not entirely a success, though: he spends a great deal of time with a Courtesan, often dining with her, though he insists that he&#8217;s not up to anything illicit with her. His wife chides him endlessly for this, and this merely drives him further from her. He is not prepared, however, to return home to find his own door locked against him and his wife denying him entry. Enraged, he is only barely prevented from knocking down his own door, and decides to give an expensive necklace he commissioned for his wife to the courtesan instead. Meeting the goldsmith Angelo after lunch, he is confused to be told that he has already received the necklace, and to find himself arrested for non-payment. Soon finding himself also declared mad and possessed, he is incapable of resisting when he is tied up and thrust into a dark room, but he chews his way through the ropes binding him and escapes, tormenting the exorcist Dr. Pinch by setting his beard on fire before finding the Duke to call for justice against his wife, whom he is certain is at the base of all his ills. Finding himself called &#8216;son&#8217; by an old man about to be executed, he is even further discombobulated, but it is soon revealed that he has a twin brother who&#8217;s been taken for him all day, that the local Abbess is his mother and the old man his father. He immediately offers to pay Egeon&#8217;s ransom, but the Duke rejects the need for it. He is a choleric man, much given to beating his slave Dromio of Ephesus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EGE.">Egeon</persname>
<persdescription>Egeon is an old man of Syracuse who sneaks into the city to seek for his lost twin son Antipholus. A great traveller, he has not had the easiest of lives, having lost his wife and one of his sons in a tempest, and then having the remaining son vanish in his quest to find his brother. Recognised as a Syracusian and captured, he is sentenced to be beheaded unless he can pay a ransom of a thousand marks. His pleas to Duke Solinus are unavailing, but the tale of his woes touches the Ephesian ruler, who allows him to roam the town to find someone who will pay the ransom for him by sundown. He is unsuccessful in this, but does find his son &#8212; who denies ever having met him. Things are soon cleared up when it is revealed that both of his twins are present in town, as is his lost wife, who just happens to be an Abbess there. Egeon is not the happiest of men, living under sentence of death as he is, and convinced at the end that his son is ashamed of him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUKE.">Solinus, Duke of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>Duke (Solinus) of Ephesus rules his town with great respect for law, insisting that he cannot go against the set rules even if he wishes to, though he is willing to bend them a little on occasion. He rigidly enforces the law that requires a thousand marks from every Syracusian merchant found within the boundaries of Ephesus. He has been patron to Antipholus of Syracuse for twenty years, ever since he was brought to town by the Duke&#8217;s uncle Menaphon of Corinth and fought in the Duke&#8217;s wars, and arranged for his marriage to the rich lady Adriana. The Duke is able to pity, is intelligent enough to be the first to link Egeon&#8217;s tale to the mysterious happenings of the day, and willing to break his oath about being unable to undo the law when he so chooses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. MER.">First Merchant</persname>
<persdescription>The First Merchant warns Antipholus of Syracuse to hide his identity, given the penalty for a Syracusian to be caught in Ephesus. He leaves his traveling companion to take care of some business, though promising to join him again in the evening.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. MER.">Second Merchant</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Merchant is on the verge of a journey to Persia, and therefore needs every penny he can get. He has lent a substantial amount of money to Angelo which he now wishes to have repaid. He has not been a pressing creditor, but when money is required he is quick to hire out an officer to arrest Angelo if the latter should default. As he needs to leave quickly, he has no inclination to listen to a sparring match between Angelo and Antipholus of Ephesus and has Angelo arrested. He is shocked to hear Antipholus of Syracuse deny events that he has witnessed, and challenges him to fight, though he regrets this when he realizes that the man is mad. He testifies before the Duke to all he knows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JAIL.">Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>The Jailer has custody of Egeon, and accompanies him in his search for someone to pay his ransom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="COUR.">Courtezan</persname>
<persdescription>A Courtezan counts Antipholus of Epheseus among her favored clients, and entertains him often enough to make his wife jealous. She is an excellent conversationalist, with a mix of wildness and gentleness that greatly pleases men. In return for being promised a gold chain by the Antipholus she knows, she lets him have a diamond ring of hers. When she meets him again (as she thinks) and he denies the fact, she decides he is mad, and decides to tell his wife a slightly trumped-up tale in hopes of getting the worth of the ring back, as she cannot afford to lose its worth. She bears witness of what she knows before the Duke, and receives her ring back at the end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger rushes in to warn Adriana to flee from her husband, who has broken loose from his bonds. He is clearly terrified.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="OFF.">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer is a debt recovery officer, who can be hired to arrest defaulters. Once he has done so, he is at risk of having to pay the debt himself if he lets his prisoner escape. He trusts Adriana&#8217;s promise to pay when the latter has her husband tied up, and is terrified of the Syracusan Antipholus and Dromio when he sees them with swords drawn.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HEAD.">Headsman</persname>
<persdescription>The Headsman [mute role] is in charge of executing Egeon, and leads him to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>