<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Coriolanus">

<persona>
<persname short="VOL.">Volumnia</persname>
<persdescription>Volumnia is Coriolanus&#8217;s mother, a stiff-backed, haughty, proud and unbending woman. She loves her son dearly, but particularly loves his honor, and would rather see him dead than lose that honor. She has brought him up to share these ideals, and she therefore bears a great deal of responsibility for how he has turned out and the character traits that doom him. A ruthless matron, she is delighted to hear that her grandson is torturing butterflies, as this makes him like his father and presages well for the future, and has absolutely no patience with her daughter-in-law Virgilia&#8217;s weeping weakness and fear. She is delighted to hear that Coriolanus has been wounded, as it offers visible proof of his valor. She instructs him in how to win people over, knowing just how to play on him to convince him to do so. Volumnia despises the common people, if possible even more than does her son, but is spared by them due to her gender. Still, when it comes down to it she loves the idea of Rome more, and sacrifices Coriolanus to it when she convinces him to abandon his attack on the city.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AUF.">Tullus Aufidius</persname>
<persdescription>Tullus Aufidius is the leader of the Volscian army and Rome and Coriolanus&#8217;s greatest enemy. Refusing to give in to the fact that he is constantly beaten in battle by the Romans, he fights them time and again, meeting Coriolanus in single combat a dozen times, though never winning. This engenders in him a powerful hatred for his enemy, though he respects him. This respect allows him to greet Coriolanus as a friend when the latter is banished and comes to join the Volscians in their new campaign against Rome. He is soon envious, however, at how his soldiers begin to take the Roman as their commander, and he plans to use Coriolanus as a weapon against Rome and to destroy him afterwards &#8212; a plan in which he is successful. He is not entirely displeased when Coriolanus chooses not to attack Rome, as it gives him an excuse to bring the Roman down. Aufidius seems at times to be the Volscian equivalent to Coriolanus, but unlike the Roman, he is capable of deceit and can work within the framework of government.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LIEU. AUF.">Lieutenant to Aufidius</persname>
<persdescription>Lieutenant to Aufidius is a faithful follower of his general, and is disturbed to see Coriolanus win the hearts of his fellow soldiers, as it diminishes Aufidius.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NIC.">Nicanor</persname>
<persdescription>Nicanor is a Roman turncoat who spies for the Volscians and has shaved off his beard to not be recognized by his former compatriots.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROM. HER.">Roman Herald</persname>
<persdescription>A Roman Herald precedes the returning victorious Roman army, making the formal announcement of Coriolanus&#8217;s feats and new honorable name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BOY.">Young Martius</persname>
<persdescription>Young Martius is Coriolanus&#8217;s young son, who takes after his father both in looks and in his taste for torturing butterflies. He shows some spirit when brought to plead with his father not to attack Rome, swearing not to be killed but to run away long enough to grow old enough to fight back.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BRU.">Junius Brutus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. MEN. AND BRU.">Both Menenius and Brutus</persname>
	<persname short="BOTH BRU. AND SIC.">Both Brutus and Sicinius</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Junius Brutus is an old bearded man named as one of tribunes of the Roman people after the latter&#8217;s riots force the establishment of that office. Disturbed by Coriolanus&#8217;s popularity and the likelihood that he will be named Consul, he begins to plot with his fellow tribune Sicinus to bring about Coriolanus&#8217;s downfall. He is irritated at the commons&#8217; decision to accept Coriolanus as Consul and rejection of his own advice as how to prevent this. He is duplicitous enough to take the blame for Coriolanus&#8217;s nomination. Part of his reason for wishing to be rid of Coriolanus is to demonstrate to the aristocracy that the tribunes possess genuine power. Having made the mistake of banishing Coriolanus rather than killing him, Brutus proves to be a useless, self-satisfied and deluded leader, refusing to face facts when informed that the exiled man is returning with an army to conquer Rome. Reduced to begging his old enemies to plead with Coriolanus, he loses all his popularity and is captured by a mob that threatens to kill him slowly if the attack carries on.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIC.">Sicinius Velutus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH BRU. AND SIC.">Both Brutus and Sicinius</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Sicinus Velutus is an old bearded man named as one of the tribunes of the Roman people after the latter&#8217;s riots force the establishment of that office. He is disturbed by Coriolanus&#8217;s clear disdain for the common people, and worries that he will take away their rights if he is named Consul. He therefore plots with his fellow tribune Brutus to bring about Coriolanus&#8217;s downfall. Not without reason he refuses to trust Coriolanus&#8217;s attempts at humility, but to achieve his end of destroying the man he slips into duplicity and subterfuge, pushing Coriolanus into public anger and treasonous words. He makes the mistake of merely banishing him instead of killing him, thereby putting all of Rome at risk. He proves to be a useless, self-satisfied and deluded leader, refusing to face facts when informed that Coriolanus is advancing on Rome with an army and reduced to begging with his enemies to go and plead with the rebel and hiding from the mob that has sworn to kill him slowly if Volumnia and the others do not succeed in turning Coriolanus back. For all that he acts in the people&#8217;s best interest, he does not actually like them much himself.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MEN.">Menenius Agrippa</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. MEN. AND BRU.">Both Menenius and Brutus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Menenius Agrippa is an old Roman patrician, beloved by the people due to his charming honesty about his own failings. He enjoys drinking, isn&#8217;t overly fussed about his job, stays up too late, talks forthrightly but doesn&#8217;t hold a grudge. The regard the commons have for him allows him to disguise the fact that he doesn&#8217;t like them very much. Still, he is able to quell a riot simply by telling the rioters a story. He is very fond of Coriolanus, though not blind to his faults. He does all he can to have Coriolanus named Consul, but also tries to tutor the young man in the political arts. Coriolanus&#8217;s failure disheartens him, and he lets his displeasure with the commons be known. Generally good-natured, and afraid of being hurt, Menenius is at first unwilling to beg with the rebelling Coriolanus when he returns to sack the city. Coriolanus&#8217;s refusal to listen to him still shocks Menenius to the core. Menenius&#8217;s good-nature camouflages his deep, unthinking belief in aristocracy and its rights.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="COM.">Cominius</persname>
<persdescription>Cominius is the chief Roman general, a senator in overall command of the war against the Volscians. An older man and a good soldier, he is driven to huge enthusiasm by Caius Martius&#8217;s exploits, and gives him the honorary name of Coriolanus when he refuses any further reward. He offers the official speech about Coriolanus&#8217;s worthiness to be Consul to the Senate, and realizing that speaking nicely is not the younger man&#8217;s strong suit also offers to help coach him in speaking to the commons. When Coriolanus is banished he offers to go with him for a month to see that he is well set-up elsewhere, but is rejected. He is sent by Rome to try and bargain with Coriolanus when the latter attacks the city, but is pushed aside. Cominius is an honorable man who is aware that Coriolanus has his faults, but still thinks him ill-used.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LART.">Titus Lartius</persname>
<persdescription>Titus Lartius is a Roman senator and general who fights with Coriolanus at Corioles, though he is less audacious that his fellow commander. He is a meticulous officer who plans well, but does not have the stroke of genius that characterizes Coriolanus. He is left to take control of Corioles after victory is achieved, but is unable to keep the Volscians properly contained.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LIEU. LART.">Lieutenant to Lartius</persname>
<persdescription>Lieutenant to Lartius is charged with guarding the ports the Romans have captured from the Volscians.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Caius Martius</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="COR.">Coriolanus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Caius Martius, called Coriolanus, is a Roman general of aristocratic birth, a deeply proud man of deep integrity and an astounding lack of social skills. He has been a soldier all his life and does not understand civilian life. Extremely awkward when not fighting, he dislikes being praised for what he has done, refusing monetary rewards and not wishing to hear himself lauded. He expects to be honored for his achievements by being given high office, but he refuses to do anything more for the sake of being nominated, even though this is long-standing tradition. He despises the common people, and since he is unable to hold his tongue, they are well-aware of it. An extreme right-winger, he cannot play politics, as he is incapable of hypocrisy and only once in his life attempts to practice it, with ludicrous results. It is his misfortune to be named Consul at a time when it is necessary for him to attempt to charm the common folk. He is an extraordinary soldier, of unmatched bravery and huge physical power, and despises those who are less than he. He particularly dislikes cowardice, and sees no reason why everyday people should have any say in government when they do nothing for the defense of the city. The only emotion he is truly capable of expressing is anger, though he has an unbounded respect for his mother Volumnia, who can do with him as she pleases. Volumnia brought him up to share her unbending ideals, and many of the character traits that doom Coriolanus can be laid at his mother&#8217;s door. His care for his own wife Virgilia, and for his son Young Martius, is much less than his love for his mother. Beyond them, his only friends are his commanding officer Cominius and old Menenius, who has loved him as a father. Perhaps his strongest bond is with his enemy Aufidius, with whom he has fought a dozen times, always winning but never able to put him fully out of action. His respect for Aufidius is so strong that it is to him that Coriolanus flees when he is banished from Rome. Hugely arrogant, unbending, bad-tempered, and deeply self-centered, Coriolanus is nevertheless finally broken by his care for his mother, and gives in to her even when he knows it will destroy him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VIR.">Virgilia</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH VIR. AND VAL.">Both Virgilia and Valeria</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Virgilia is Coriolanus&#8217;s wife, a young woman who loves her husband and is terrified at the thought of anything happening to him. She is ruthlessly dominated by her mother-in-law Volumnia, who has no patience with her fear of Coriolanus being wounded or killed. She is rather quiet, though she attempts to show some spirit on occasion, but spends most of her time crying. She is completely overborne by Volumnia, and makes little mark on Coriolanus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GENT.">Gentlewoman</persname>
<persdescription>A Gentlewoman serves Volumnia and Virgilia, and announces the arrival of Valeria.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAL.">Valeria</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH VIR. AND VAL.">Both Virgilia and Valeria</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Valeria is a lady of Rome renowned for her chastity and nobility, who keeps up with the news. She finds the sight of Young Martius torturing a butterfly quite charming. She is sent by the Romans to plead with Coriolanus for mercy along with Volumnia, Virgilia and Young Martius.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CIT. ANT.">Citizen of Antium</persname>
<persdescription>A Citizen of Antium shows the disguised Coriolanus where Aufidius&#8217;s house is.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ADR.">Adrian</persname>
<persdescription>Adrian is a Volscian who is oddly friendly with a Roman named Nicanor, and acts as a spy for the state.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger comes to fetch Caius Martius (later Coriolanus) with the news that he is needed to defend Rome from the attacking Volscians. He later informs Brutus and Sicinius that the Senate is gathering when it is rumored that the Volscians are attacking under Coriolanus&#8217;s leadership. He spreads the news of the ladies&#8217; success in pleading with Coriolanus when he hears of it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger comes to inform Caius Martius (later Coriolanus) and Lartius of Cominius&#8217;s whereabouts. He reports back to Cominius that he saw the Romans beaten, not having stayed long enough to witness otherwise.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger brings Brutus and Sinicus their summons to the Capitol to hear Coriolanus’s nomination as Consul. He is taken aback at the public reaction to the returning hero. He later summons the two tribunes to the Senate when it becomes clear that the Volscians are attacking Rome under Coriolanus’s leadership. He also advises Sinicius to run for it after Brutus is captured by the mob.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. SEN.">First Roman Senator</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="SENATORS.">Roman Senators</persname>
	<persname short="LORDS AND SENATORS.">Lords and Senators</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Roman Senator requests that Martius (later Coriolanus) join Cominius in the war against the Volscians. He later attempts to keep Coriolanus from speaking rashly in front of the commonality and thereby loses his consulship, but fails. He tries to remedy to the situation, getting Coriolanus to leave and calming the tribunes down enough to use due process before acting against Coriolanus. This does not do his side of the quarrel much good.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. SEN.">Second Roman Senator</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="SENATORS.">Roman Senators</persname>
	<persname short="LORDS AND SENATORS.">Lords and Senators</persname>
</persaliases><persdescription>The Second Roman Senator urges Coriolanus to leave the Forum before he is torn to pieces by the mob, in the hopes that they can be calmed down in his absence. He later sings the praises of Volumnia and the other two ladies as she returns from her successful pleading with Coriolanus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. VOL. SEN.">First Volscian Senator</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. VOL. SEN.">All Volscian Senators</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Volscian Senator trusts Aufidius&#8217;s opinion about the Romans and how much they know. Standing on the walls of Corioli, he baits the Roman army with the news that Aufidius has them surrounded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. VOL. SEN.">Second Volscian Senator</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. VOL. SEN.">All Volscian Senators</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Volscian Senator entrusts the Volscian army to Aufidius.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. SOLD.">First Roman Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. SOLD.">All Roman Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Roman Soldier refuses to follow Caius Martius (later Coriolanus) inside the gates of Corioli, considering such an action idiotic in the extreme.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. SOLD.">Second Roman Soldier</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. SOLD.">All Roman Soldiers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Roman Soldier refuses to follow Caius Martius (later Coriolanus) inside the gates of Corioli, considering such an action idiotic in the extreme.</persdescription>
 </persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM.">First Roman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Roman has gone to the battle against Corioli, but only stays long enough to pick up some loot and take off again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM.">Second Roman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Roman has gone to the battle against Corioli, but only stays long enough to pick up some loot and take off again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. ROM.">Third Roman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Roman has gone to the battle against Corioli, but only stays long enough to pick up some loot and take off again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="USH.">Usher</persname>
<persdescription>An Usher [mute role] accompanies Valeria on her visit to Volumnia and Virgilia.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCOUT.">Scout</persname>
<persdescription>A Scout [mute role] leads Lartius and his army to the Roman camp.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VOL. SOLD.">Volscian Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>A Volscian Soldier urges Aufidius to leave the field of battle and evade capture. He is afraid of Coriolanus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. OFF.">First Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The First Officer is one of the officials of the Senate, in charge of preparing the chamber for events. He thinks Coriolanus a good man, but is not altogether convinced that things will go well with his nomination.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. OFF.">Second Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Officer is one of the officials of the Senate, in charge of preparing the chamber for events. He is quite impressed by Coriolanus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. ROM. CIT.">First Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Roman Citizen is a leader of the famished rioting of the people, who detests the patricians, but is willing to give Menenius time to speak against the rioting, with the result that he is made to look a fool. He does not much like Coriolanus, but admits he has done good service, and is in the end convinced to vote for him as Consul. He is however just as quickly convinced to change his mind when he is reminded of Coriolanus&#8217;s pride and the likelihood that he will have little care for the rights of the commons. Listened to by his fellows, he claims he can command 1000 others to follow his lead. He is delighted with the peace that follows the strongman&#8217;s banishment, but as soon as he hears that Coriolanus is returning at the head of an army, he insists that he was sorry to banish him at the time. He is not committed to any particular faction beyond his own comfort and safety, and is rather a coward. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. ROM. CIT.">Second Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Roman Citizen participates in the famished rioting of the people, but is a fair-minded person who insists that Caius Martius (later Coriolanus) should not be accused falsely, not matter how hated he may be. He later agrees to give Coriolanus his vote for the consulship, but thinks he was overly proud when he asked, and is quickly convinced to take his vote back. He is listened to by his fellows, and claims he can command 500 others to follow his lead. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. ROM. CIT.">Third Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Roman Citizen is one of the famished rioters who hates Coriolanus but is later persuaded to vote for him as consul before quickly being persuaded to vote against him instead. When Coriolanus is banished and returns at the head of an army to ransack Rome, the Third Citizen insists that the banishment was done against his will, even though he acquiesced in it. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="4. ROM. CIT.">Fourth Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fourth Roman Citizen is one of the famished rioters who hates Coriolanus but is later persuaded to vote for him as consul. He points out to Coriolanus that the common people do not have much reason to like him, and is soon persuaded to take back his vote. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="5. ROM. CIT.">Fifth Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Fifth Roman Citizen is persuaded to vote for Coriolanus as consul, but is quickly persuaded to change his mind. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="6. ROM. CIT.">Sixth Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Sixth Roman Citizen is persuaded to vote for Coriolanus as consul, but is quickly persuaded to change his mind. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="7. ROM. CIT.">Seventh Roman Citizen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. ROM. CIT.">All Roman Citizens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Seventh Roman Citizen is persuaded to vote for Coriolanus as consul, but is quickly persuaded to change his mind. He is part of the mob of plebeians that riots in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest, and approves his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. AED.">First Aedile</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. AEDILES.">Both Aediles</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Aedile is an officer commanded by the tribunes, empowered to arrest citizens at their command. Beaten up when he attempts to arrest Coriolanus, he prepares the citizens to proceed against Coriolanus by due process on Brutus and Sicinius&#8217;s orders.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. AED.">Second Aedile</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. AEDILES.">Both Aediles</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Aedile is an officer commanded by the tribunes, empowered to arrest citizens at their command. He is beaten up when he attempts to arrest Coriolanus. He is later sent whip whip a man for spreading the rumor that the Volscians are attacking.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SERV.">First Servingman</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. SERV. AND 2. SERV.">Both First and Second Servingmen</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Servingman works serving at Aufidius&#8217;s feasts. He is not the most loyal of servants, being quick to admire the poor gentleman who pushes his way in and willing to admit that Aufidius has been beaten more than a few times. He enjoys war and is a great gossip.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SERV.">Second Servingman</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. SERV. AND 2. SERV.">Both First and Second Servingmen</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Servingman works serving at Aufidius&#8217;s feasts. He is impressed by the disguised Coriolanus&#8217;s appearance, even though he thinks he may have to break his head to get him to leave. He enjoys war and is a great gossip.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. SERV.">Third Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Servingman works serving at Aufidius&#8217;s feasts. He tries to talk rather too much to Coriolanus. He is a great gossip and loves the thought of the war starting up again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. WATCH.">First Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Watchman guards the Volscian camp and is not even a little impressed by Menenius&#8217;s claims to be a special friend of Coriolanus&#8217;s. He is completely convinced of the rightness of Coriolanus&#8217;s cause.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. WATCH.">Second Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Watchman guards the Volscian camp and is not even a little impressed by Menenius&#8217;s claims to be a special friend of Coriolanus. He is a rather sarcastic type.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. CONSP.">First Conspirator</persname>
<persdescription>The First Conspirator is offended at how Coriolanus is taking Aufidius&#8217;s glory, and particularly that he chose not to attack Rome. He helps to kill the Roman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CONSP.">Second Conspirator</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Conspirator is quite willing to join with Aufidius if he decides to go through with his plot, and is certain that they will get away with it as the Volscians will remember how many of their kin Coriolanus killed. He helps to kill the Roman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. CONSP.">Third Conspirator</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Conspirator feels that there is a chance at success in the plot to kill Coriolanus, as the people have no fixed opinion about him, and recommends that he be killed before he has a chance to speak to anyone and perhaps convince them. He helps to kill the Roman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. VOL. LORD.">First Volscian Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL VOL. LORDS.">All Volscian Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Volscian Lord is deeply disappointed in Coriolanus for not sacking Rome, but is willing to wait for an explanation. He is taken aback at Aufidius&#8217;s summary killing of the Roman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. VOL. LORD.">Second Volscian Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL VOL. LORDS.">All Volscian Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Volscian Lord tries to keep the peace and does not wish to see Coriolanus killed without a fair hearing, but his plea is doomed by Coriolanus&#8217;s temper. He considers that Aufidius acted on instinct.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. VOL. LORD.">Third Volscian Lord</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL VOL. LORDS.">All Volscian Lords</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Volscian Lord insists that Coriolanus&#8217;s body be treated with respect.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALL VOL.">Volscians</persname>
<persdescription>The Volscians accept Coriolanus among them as their general despite his arrogance when he promises to fight for them against Rome, but are quick to remember how many of their kin he has killed when given an excuse to do so, and approve of his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VOL. SOLDS">Volscian Soldiers</persname>
<persdescription>Volscian Soldiers [mute roles] follow Aufidius to battle, and rescue him during his duel with Coriolanus. They get little thanks for this.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALL. ROM. SOLD.">Roman Soldiers</persname>
<persdescription>Roman Soldiers are hugely impressed by Coriolanus, and cheer him to the skies when he is given his new name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PATRICIAN">Patrician</persname>
<persdescription>A Patrician is one of the old aristocracy of Rome, and speaks for them. He offers bail on Coriolanus&#8217;s behalf when the Tribunes wish to arrest the general, and tries to calm him down.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PATRICIANS">Patricians</persname>
<persdescription>Patricians [mute roles] are the old aristocracy of Rome, and approve of Coriolanus as Consul as he will keep the rabble in its place. They are willing to pay bail for him when the Tribunes attempt to arrest him, and accompany him to his house to offer him counsel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALL PLEBEIANS.">Plebeians</persname>
<persdescription>Plebeians [mute roles] are the lower class of Rome, driven to riot by starvation and later led by the nose by their Tribunes. They riot in support of Coriolanus&#8217;s arrest and approve his exile.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>