<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Cymbeline">
<persona>
<persname short="HEL.">Helen</persname>
<persdescription>Helen is a lady attending on Imogen, who has no use for Cloten but is not averse to taking his gold, though she does him no favors in return.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="IMO.">Imogen</persname>
<persdescription>Imogen is Cymbeline&#8217;s daughter and the heir to his throne. A beautiful girl with blue eyes, she is obedient and generally docile, but has an iron backbone and will not be moved against her own desire and integrity. She proves this when she marries Posthumus behind her father&#8217;s back and refuses to divorce him, or pay any attention to the attempted seductions of Cloten, even though the King her father is in favor of that match. She is open and honest, though her innate politeness prevents her from fully expressing her opinions until she is pressed too far. She is also chaste, and puts off her husband from the marriage bed &#8212; their marriage may not even be consummated. She can be extremely headstrong, whether in keeping to her room or galloping off to meet Posthumus, disguising herself as a boy named Fidele, or entering in service to her father&#8217;s enemy. She is extraordinarily courageous, and has excellent instincts, knowing exactly whom to trust even when she cannot explain why, and also knowing that her stepmother means her no good. Horrified at Posthumus&#8217;s accusations against her and desire to see her dead, she still loves him and forgives him when he repents; nevertheless, waking out of a drugged sleep she is incapable of recognizing that it is not his headless body that she wakes up next to, but Cloten&#8217;s. She is delighted to discover that the two young men she befriended in the cave are actually her brothers, and that she will therefore not inherit the throne. A well-educated young lady who enjoys reading in bed, she has a mole on her left breast.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="QUEEN.">Queen</persname>
<persdescription>The Queen is Cymbeline&#8217;s second wife, a beautiful widow, and a rather classic evil stepmother. She marries Cymbeline for the sake of having him adopt her son Cloten as heir, after which she intends to poison him. She also hopes to do away with her stepdaughter Imogen, and makes a start by ruining her marriage by moving Cymbeline to oppose it. A great dissembler, she convinces almost everybody of her sweetness, but both Imogen and Dr. Cornelius see through her, the latter choosing not to let her get her hands on any deadly poisons, but giving her innocuous sleeping potions instead. She attempts to corrupt everyone who crosses her path in her quest to have Cloten marry Imogen. She also meddles in politics and encourages Cymbeline to defy the Romans, thereby precipitating a war. She falls ill when Cloten vanishes, and as she lies dying begins to be remorseful for all her evils, and confesses them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRENCH.">Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>A Frenchman is one of Philario&#8217;s friends, who met Posthumus once in France, where he managed to stop a quarrel between the Briton and some other Frenchmen. He thinks the question of a woman&#8217;s chastity not worth fighting over.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAP.">Roman Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The Roman Captain reports to Lucius on the progress of the reinforcements the general has asked for, and sees whether Fidele/Imogen is alive when the Romans find him/her asleep on a headless corpse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PHIL.">Philarmonus</persname>
<persdescription>Philharmonus the Soothsayer accompanies Lucius when the latter invades Britain, providing divinations, though he manages to completely misinterpret his premonitory dream. He makes up for it by elucidating the meaning of the gold tablet Posthumus wakes up with.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="COR.">Cornelius</persname>
<persdescription>Cornelius is a physician at Cymbeline&#8217;s court who has been teaching the Queen the medicinal use of plants. He does not trust her when she begins to question him about more dangerous concoctions, and disbelieves her insistence that she merely wishes to poison rats, cats and dogs. He therefore tricks her by given her powerful sleeping potions instead of poisons. He later forgets about having done so. He is unable to save the Queen when she falls ill, but hears her confession and reports it to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PIS.">Pisanio</persname>
<persdescription>Pisanio is Posthumus&#8217;s servant, a loyal man who acts in his master&#8217;s best interests even when commanded otherwise. He remains behind in Britain to serve Imogen and serve as a go-between with Posthumus while he is in Rome. He is horrified at being ordered to murder Imogen, not least because this means Posthumus thinks him capable of being a murderer. He therefore comes up with the idea of dressing Imogen as a man and sending her all on her own to become a servant to the Romans, her father&#8217;s enemies, in the hopes that she may perhaps manage to make her way to Posthumus. When interrogated as to Imogen&#8217;s whereabouts, he sends Cloten off to the mountains to seek her, indirectly sending him to his death. He does not think to mistrust the Queen&#8217;s assurance that the box he takes from her contains medicine.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUC.">Caius Lucius</persname>
<persdescription>Caius Lucius is a noble Roman, an ambassador to the British court who is later given command of the invading Roman army. He is deeply respected by all, including his enemies, and he deeply regrets the necessity of warring on Cymbeline when the latter refuses to pay tribute. He is a kind man and takes the boy Fidele for a page out of pity when he meets him, little dreaming that he is in fact Cymbeline&#8217;s daughter Imogen. Captured in battle, he refuses to consider the fortunes of the day as having marked one party as right or wrong, just as he refuses to beg for mercy. He is shocked and hurt that Fidele will not ask Cymbeline to save his life. His reaction to Cymbeline&#8217;s decision to pay the tribute to Rome despite having won the battle is not recorded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JACH.">Jachimo</persname>
<persdescription>Jachimo is a young Italian nobleman, the brother of the ruler of Sienna, and a rascal with a low opinion of women&#8217;s morality. A betting man and a seducer with no self-esteem problems, he is certain of his ability to seduce the chastest of new wives. Not a man willing to lose a bet, when his wiles prove no match for Imogen&#8217;s faithfulness, he resorts to trickery, for which he came prepared. He is much more taken by Imogen than he expected, and his quasi-rape of her in her sleep marks him. Though he still goes through with his plan, it gnaws at him, and the results leave him stricken with remorse. He is grateful for the chance to make public confession and to offer up his life to Posthumus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PHI.">Philario</persname>
<persdescription>Philario is an old Roman nobleman who was a friend of Posthumus&#8217;s father and welcomes the son as an honored guest when he is banished to Rome. He is disturbed at how quickly the young men in his house fall to discussing their women and disapproves deeply of the bet on Imogen&#8217;s chastity. He is fond of Posthumus, and tries to find a way to put Jachimo&#8217;s tale in doubt, but he is unsuccessful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ARV.">Arviragus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ARV. AND GUI.">Both Arviragus and Guiderius</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Arviragus, known as Cadwal, is Cymbeline&#8217;s second son, but is aware of this fact as he was kidnapped at the age of two by Belarius and brought up by him as a hunter in a cave along with his elder brother Guiderius. Twenty years later, he is growing irritated at being brought up like an animal and wishes to have some experiences to talk about when he&#8217;s old. He is a great hunter and hopes for a chance to be a great warrior. He feels an immediate sympathy for the boy Fidele and adopts him as his brother. He is heart-broken at the boy&#8217;s death, but delighted to later discover that firstly, he&#8217;s still alive and secondly, he&#8217;s actually their sister Imogen. He insists in going to fight the Roman invasion, no matter what Belarius says, and distinguishes himself in the battle along with Guiderius and Belarius, saving the King&#8217;s life and turning back the tide of fleeing Britons. He is a fairly simple-minded fellow, both eager for glory and tender-hearted.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GUI.">Guiderius</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ARV. AND GUI.">Both Arviragus and Guiderius</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Guiderius, known as Polydore, is Cymbeline&#8217;s eldest son, but is unaware of this fact as he was kidnapped at the age of three by Belarius and brought up by him as a hunter in a cave along with his younger brother Arviragus. Twenty years later, he is growing irritated by his lack of formal education and wishes to know what the real world is like. A great hunter, he longs to have a chance to be a great soldier as well. He feels an immediate sympathy for the boy Fidele and is excessively fond of him; He is heart-broken at the boy&#8217;s death, but delighted to later discover that firstly, he&#8217;s still alive and secondly, he&#8217;s actually their sister Imogen. Quite blunt, he does not take kindly to insults and has no qualms about cutting off Cloten&#8217;s head. Hearing of the Roman invasion, he insists on going to fight it, with or without Belarius&#8217;s permission, and greatly distinguishes himself in the fight, saving Cymbeline&#8217;s life with the help of his brother and supposed father as well as turning the fleeing Britons back to the fight. He refuses to apologize for killing Cloten and is only saved from death himself by being revealed as the King&#8217;s son. He has a mole on the back of his neck.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BEL.">Belarius</persname>
<persdescription>Belarius is a banished lord who calls himself Morgan. Once one of Cymbeline&#8217;s greatest generals, he was falsely accused of treason and in revenge kidnapped the King&#8217;s two young sons with the help of their nurse Euriphile, whom he married. Living in a cave, he brought up the boys as hunters, insisting to them that the courtly world was not worth knowing. Despite his age, he is still a magnificent fighter; he is also a great storyteller whose tales of his past exploits fire up the lads and leave them dreaming of matching them. He preaches the values of a simple, communal life, where all hunt and those who do less well in finding game do the cooking and washing up. He is a great believer in heredity and bloodlines. He knew Cloten when the latter was a child at the court and still remembers him and the tone of his voice. When the two princes insist on fighting in the war against the Romans, he joins them, and does great service, earning Cymbeline&#8217;s recognition. Physically powerful, he is covered with scars and bears a white beard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POST.">Posthumus Leonatus</persname>
<persdescription>Posthumus Leonatus is a young man of good family whose father died before his birth. Brought up by Cymbeline almost as a son, he is nevertheless too poor to be considered by him for a son-in-law, and is banished when he dares to marry his childhood companion, the Princess Imogen. He is renowned as being one of the best of men, courteous, well-trained, and educated, but also a man not afraid of a quarrel. He rests an infinite trust in Imogen&#8217;s faithfulness, to the extent of being willing to make a very stupid bet on it; he is in fact quite easily convinced that she is false, and his loathing of her becomes as great as was his love. His deception turns him into a rampant misogynist and a murderer-by-proxy. He repents when he is convinced that Imogen is dead, however, and turns suicidal. He is not a subtle man, nor one to do things by halves. He blames Italy for having changed him into a murderer, and takes on all the penance he can when he returns to Britain to atone for his deeds. Recovering Imogen, he is magnanimous, and pardons Jachimo, the chief cause of his unhappiness. Posthumus suffers from his lack of family. He is a well-shaped man, physically the same dimensions as Cloten.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLO.">Cloten</persname>
<persdescription>Cloten is Cymbeline&#8217;s stepson, the Queen&#8217;s son by her first marriage, and a remarkably stupid man. The ultimate spoiled brat, he is destined by both King and Queen to marry the Princess Imogen, and by the Queen at least to therefore be named heir to the throne. Unfortunately for them all, he is quite unable to woo said Princess, as he is rude, self-involved, dense, quarrelsome, foul-mouthed, and snobbish, as well as a bad gambler and an overdressed fop surrounded by sycophants &#8212; not to mention rather smelly. He is also full of bravado, and gives this full sway at an important diplomatic meeting, thereby precipitating a war by offering up admittedly patriotic insults to an ambassador. A man with a crude mind, he is so insulted that Imogen prefers the poor Posthumus to himself that when she runs after the latter he plans to follow, find them, and commit murder on the man and rape on the woman. Literal-minded, Cloten cannot understand a figurative insult, and thinks that Imogen merely prefers Posthumus&#8217;s clothes to his own. Rather a buffoon, Cloten is never the less a well-shaped man, physically almost identical to Posthumus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CYM.">Cymbeline</persname>
<persdescription>Cymbeline, King of Britain, is a cranky old man led by the nose by his second wife. Though he brought up the orphaned Posthumus Leonatus, he considers the young man too poor to be worthy of being his son-in-law, and is furious when he learns that his daughter Imogen has married him in secret. He is not the brightest of monarchs, having been easily convinced that his friend Belarius was a traitor, just as he fails to see Cloten as a fool. By his first wife he had three children; the two boys (Guiderius and Arviragus) were kidnapped and are presumed dead. He tends to react to matters rather than initiate them, is a good warrior but still needs to be rescued in a battle, and rejects Roman sovereignty more because his people won&#8217;t stand for it than or of personal belief &#8212; as evidenced, perhaps, by his decision to submit to the Romans just after his armies give them a licking. He is a courteous and conservative man, not a deep thinker, and rather slow on the uptake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT.">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman has been at Cymbeline&#8217;s court for many years, knows most of the gossip, and does not mind sharing it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GENT.">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman is apparently newly-arrived at court, for he does not know either the latest gossip or the old.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. LORD.">First Lord</persname>
<persdescription>The First Lord is one of Cloten&#8217;s sycophants, following him about and fawning on him, boosting his self-esteem. He manages to save Cloten from himself from time to time by assuring him that as the King&#8217;s stepson, it would be unworthy of him to fight with anyone not of his own rank, thus preventing him from entering into duels where he would invariably be beaten. He is later sent as safe-conduct to escort Lucius to the border when the latter&#8217;s embassy fails.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. LORD.">Second Lord</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Lord is one of Cloten&#8217;s sycophants, though he much prefers mocking him behind his back. He has absolutely no illusions about Cloten, and feels extremely sorry for Imogen. He is later sent as safe-conduct to escort Lucius to the border when the latter&#8217;s embassy fails.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY.">Lady Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Attendant on the Queen gathers flowers and plants for the Queen&#8217;s &#8216;medical&#8217; experiments.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OTH. LAD.">Other Ladies</persname>
<persdescription>Other Ladies attending on the Queen gather flowers and plants for the Queen&#8217;s &#8216;medical&#8217; experiments.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DUTCHMAN.">Dutchman</persname>
<persdescription>A Dutchman [mute role] is one of Philario&#8217;s friends.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SPANIARD.">Spaniard</persname>
<persdescription>A Spaniard [mute role] is one of Philario&#8217;s friends.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SING.">Singer</persname>
<persdescription>A Singer and musicians sing an aubade to Imogen at Cloten&#8217;s command.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger announces Caius Lucius&#8217;s approach to Cymbeline. The King later sends him to summon Imogen, but he reports that the Princess will not answer the door. He later fetches the imprisoned Posthumus to the King&#8217;s side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SEN.">First Senator</persname>
<persdescription>First Senator announces the Emperor&#8217;s decision to send the nobility to fight in Britain rather than the professional soldiers, who are busy elsewhere.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SEN.">Second Senator</persname>
<persdescription>Second Senator confirms that Lucius will lead the invasion of Britain.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRI.">Tribune</persname>
<persdescription>A Tribune double-checks the Emperor&#8217;s orders with the Senators, and clarifies the reasoning behind them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. BRIT. CAP.">First British Captain</persname>
<persdescription>First British Captain is deeply gratified at the British victory, and properly grateful to the mysterious men who achieved it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. BRIT. CAP.">Second British Captain</persname>
<persdescription>Second British Captain noticed the presence of the rather poor-looking man who helped the other three that won the battle. He does not like Romans much.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BRIT. SOLD.">British Soldiers</persname>
<persdescription>British Soldiers [mute roles] seize Posthumus at their captain&#8217;s command when he claims to be a Roman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BRIT. LORD.">British Lord</persname>
<persdescription>A British Lord fled from the battle against the Romans, and is amazed to find that the battle was won after his departure. He is taken aback at Posthumus&#8217;s rage.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. JAIL.">First Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>The First Jailer is very familiar with taverns, and does not think of death as any great evil; in fact, he thinks death something of a convenience. He does his best to cheer up those who are about to be hanged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. JAIL.">Second Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Jailer is not a particularly sympathetic man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUP.">Jupiter</persname>
<persdescription>Jupiter is King of the Gods, and does not appreciate being told by a pack of ghosts that he is unjust.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SICI.">Apparition of Sicilius Leonatus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL GHOSTS">All Ghosts</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Apparition of Sicilius Leonatus is the ghost of Posthumus&#8217;s father, and thinks that Jupiter really ought to have better things to do than make Posthumus miserable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MOTH.">Apparition of the Matron</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL GHOSTS">All Ghosts</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Apparition of the Matron is the ghost of Posthumus&#8217;s mother, who died in childbirth; she thinks that Jupiter really ought to have better things to do than make Posthumus miserable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="APP. 1. BRO.">Apparition of First Brother of Posthumus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BROTHERS.">Apparition Brothers of Posthumus</persname>
	<persname short="ALL GHOSTS">All Ghosts</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Apparition of First Brother of Posthumus is the ghost of Posthumus&#8217;s eldest brother, who died in the war and still bears his wounds. He thinks that Jupiter really ought to have better things to do than make Posthumus miserable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="APP. 2. BRO.">Apparition of Second Brother of Posthumus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BROTHERS.">Apparition Brothers of Posthumus</persname>
	<persname short="ALL GHOSTS">All Ghosts</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Apparition of Second Brother of Posthumus is the ghost of Posthumus&#8217;s second-older brother, who died in the war and still bears his wounds. He thinks that Jupiter really ought to have better things to do than make Posthumus miserable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GUARD.">Guard</persname>
<persdescription>A Guard [mute role] seizes Guiderius when the latter admits to having killed Cloten.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>
