<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Double Falsehood">

<persona>
<persname short="D. BERN.">Don Bernard</persname>
<persdescription>Don Bernard is Leonora&#8217;s father, a crusty old man who claims to have sympathy for the young and for women&#8217;s right to choose their own husbands, but shows little signs of it. He wishes Leonora would find a richer young man than Julio, and has far more consideration for the business transaction aspect of marriage than for anything as silly as love. Not very self-aware, he does not realize that he could be talking about himself when he describes his father-in-law as a blockhead. His distemper at Leonora&#8217;s continued refusals to marry Henriquez grows to violence when she still refuses at the altar; the only explanation he can come up with is that she has gone mad. He only realizes how wrong he&#8217;s been when Leonora is abducted from the convent where she&#8217;d taken refuge, and the realization brings him to tears. He is rather an old fool, but not a malicious one.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RODER.">Roderick</persname>
<persdescription>Roderick is the Duke of Andalusia&#8217;s eldest son, and a decent, upright young man. He is concerned about his younger brother Henriquez&#8217;s actions, though he puts them down to youth rather than evil disposition. Their father sends him to keep an eye on the younger man. Though growing ever more suspicious of what Henriquez has been up to, he agrees to help his brother abduct Leonora from a convent. The evidence mounting against Henriquez convinces him, however, and he decides to force his brother to admit to his wrongs by publicly confronting him with the various witnesses. So long as honor is satisfied all around, he is not concerned with punishing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAST.">Master of the Flocks</persname>
<persdescription>The Master of the Flocks hires the disguised Violante as a shepherding apprentice. He soon realizes that &#8216;Florio&#8217; is in fact a woman, and as he is a man with very precise ideas about what to do when a woman unexpectedly falls into one&#8217;s hands, he quickly intends to take advantage of the situation. He is not the most sympathetic of men, particularly when he is interrupted before he can have his way with Violante. He is coarse and rather brutal, and enjoys drinking.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GER.">Gerald</persname>
<persdescription>Gerald is Henriquez&#8217;s servant. Able to arrange for a concert under a lady&#8217;s window, he is trusted to send messages, but not to know their content.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LOP.">Lopez</persname>
<persdescription>Lopez is a villager, Fabian&#8217;s neighbor. He overhears Henriquez&#8217;s ravings the night after his rape of Violante, and is concerned for the young man&#8217;s sanity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HENR.">Henriquez</persname>
<persdescription>Henriquez is the Duke of Andalusia&#8217;s second son, and is in the process of sowing his wild oats, much to his father&#8217;s despair. Though wild and driven by his desires, he is not incapable of introspection. He is fully aware of the extent of his faults when he commits them, but this awareness does not alter his behavior; after raping Violante, he manages to rationalize that because she did not utter a sound, she was not truly resisting. Asked by his friend Julio to look after Leonora, he takes the opportunity to get Julio out of the way and woo the lady for himself, his passion for Violante being quite forgotten. Just as he blames Violante for not resisting vocally during her rape, he blames Leonora for causing him to fall in love with him. He obtains the consent of Don Bernard, Leonora&#8217;s father, to marry her thanks to his social rank, which he is not shy of pulling. He is a good liar when he needs to be, which is quite often. Faced with the evidence of his wrongdoing, he repents and chooses to act honorably, leaving everyone (presumably) happy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VIOL.">Violante</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="FLO.">Florio</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Violante is a poor, young lady being wooed by Henriquez. Of humble birth, she has no desire to join the greats of this world, preferring her village. She therefore pays little attention to Henriquez&#8217;s blandishments. She is also worried that should he have his ways with her, he would then abandon her. Despite his promises to marry her, she still refuses him, and he rapes her. Though she resists him, she remains entirely silent during the act. Shamed and dishonored, she flees her father&#8217;s house, finally disguising herself as a shepherd boy named Florio, in the hopes of following Henriquez and shaming him. The disguise is not entirely successful: both the mad Julio and the Master of the Flocks realize that she is a woman, and the latter attempts to rape her, though Roderick&#8217;s arrival saves her in this instance. She enjoys singing to herself, and accompanies herself on the lute. There is no evidence of her ever being in love with Henriquez, rather wishing that he marry her to repair the crime he has committed against her and to restore her honor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAM.">Camillo</persname>
<persdescription>Camillo is Julio&#8217;s father. He sent his son to France to perfect his education, though he does not think overmuch of his abilities. He also finds Julio&#8217;s clothes extravagant. He is full of wise advice for his son, but with his neighbors he has the reputation of being a bit nutty. Quite well-off, he is a bluff fellow with little time for the fussiness of polite society, telling Don Bernard that he considers him a liar, not to mention accusing the Duke&#8217;s son Roderick of evil practices to his face. Hearing of his son&#8217;s madness, and then of his death, he becomes despondent and looks forward only to death. He is overjoyed when Julio turns out to be alive. He is 71 years old and suffers from gout.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LEON.">Leonora</persname>
<persdescription>Leonora is Don Bernard&#8217;s daughter and in love with Julio. She is a good, obedient child until her father interferes in her hopes to marry Julio, at which point she begins to defy him. She is aware of her place in society and that though well-off she is not from the highest ranks of society; she worries that when Julio is sent to court it will change him and make him forget her. She is aghast at Henriquez&#8217;s betrayal of his friend and refuses to marry him, being prepared to stab herself rather than go through with the wedding ceremony. Her attempts to escape by hiding in a nunnery are defeated when she is abducted from it by Henriquez and his brother Roderick. She is a determined young woman, and far from shy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUL.">Julio</persname>
<persdescription>Julio is Camillo&#8217;s son, who is deeply in love with Don Bernard&#8217;s daughter Leonora. An obedient son, he refuses to propose to her without his father&#8217;s approval, upon which Don Bernard&#8217;s consent depends. He is a friend of Henriquez&#8217;s &#8213; or at least believes himself to be one &#8213; and is an excellent, French-educated horseman who dresses rather too well for his station in life. Taking after his father, he is hot-blooded, emotional and passionate, and tends to overreact, never more perhaps than when he goes mad. He has little care for the court, especially when it takes him away from Leonora. Betrayed by Henriquez, he loses his wits, letting the gloomy side of his personality take over just as he loses control of his temper. He remains sensitive to music, though. He is quick to disguise himself to gain access to Leonora, and very physically affectionate when he finally gets her back. He is also generous enough to forgive Henriquez.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FAB.">Fabian</persname>
<persdescription>Fabian is a villager, Lopez&#8217;s neighbor. He overhears Henriquez&#8217;s ravings the night after his rape of Violante, and is concerned for the young man&#8217;s sanity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CITIZ.">Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>A Citizen knows most of the main characters and likes them, and is quickly bribed to carry a letter from a clearly disobedient daughter. He is touched by Leonora&#8217;s plight and somewhat concerned by Julio&#8217;s fervor. This concern turns out to be justified when Julio goes mad, and the Citizen must report this to the young man&#8217;s father. He gets no thanks for delivering that particular piece of news.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAID.">Maid</persname>
<persdescription>A Maid serves Violante, and lets her know that Gerald has brought her a letter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DUKE.">Duke Angelo</persname>
<persdescription>Duke Angelo is the ruler of Andalusia, and Roderick and Henriquez&#8217;s father. An old man, he is making preparations for his death and his succession. Not a fool, he is as suspicious of Henriquez as he is fond of Roderick, but this does not imply that he does not love his younger son. He is a just and honorable man, if old-fashioned and having strong views about the rights of parents. His main concern is that there should be order in the world.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SHEP.">First Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>The First Shepherd thinks that Julio would be a fine man were he not mad. He notes the madman&#8217;s attentiveness to music, and thinks that it may be worthwhile to pay attention to his ravings. He is not however so foolish as to not be afraid of Julio&#8217;s propensity to beating people up. He enjoys a good drink.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SHEP.">Second Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Shepherd is convinced that there&#8217;s always a woman to blame if a man goes mad. Julio takes him for Henriquez and attempts to murder him, or at least to pull his nose off. He is less sympathetic to the mad young man than the First Shepherd is, though he too thinks that Julio looks like he&#8217;d be an excellent fellow when sane.</persdescription>
</persona>


<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT.">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman accompanies Julio out of town when the latter goes mad, attempting to bring him to his right wits again. He is unimaginative and unromantic, and a bit of a snob about country folk&#8217;s musical abilities.</persdescription>
</persona>
 
<persona>
<persname short="2. GENT.">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman accompanies Julio out of town when the latter goes mad, attempting to bring him to his right wits again. He is very responsive to music and is far more sensitive to emotion than his friend the First Gentleman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERV.">Servant to Violante</persname>
<persdescription>The Servant to Violante is extremely faithful to her. He finds her the shepherd&#8217;s clothing she will use as a disguise.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ATT.">Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>An Attendant announces Roderick&#8217;s arrival to the Duke.</persdescription>
</persona>
 
<persona>
<persname short="CHURCH.">A Churchman</persname>
<persdescription>A Churchman [mute role] comes to Don Bernard&#8217;s house to marry Henriquez and Leonora. He never quite gets to do so.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADIES.">Ladies Attending on Leonora</persname>
<persdescription>Ladies attending on Leonora accompany her to her wedding and tend to her when she faints.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>