<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Edward III">

<persona>
<persname short="">King of Bohemia</persname>
<persdescription>The King of Bohemia is an ally of King John, and brings his forces to the French King&#8217;s aid. He is killed during the battle of Cr&amp;eacute;cy. Historically, this is best explained by the fact that he was blind.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Villiers</persname>
<persdescription>Villiers is a French Lord, a prisoner of the Earl of Salisbury. He is freed in return for a safe-conduct for the Earl. He is a deeply honorable man who is horrified at the idea of being prevented from keeping his word.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Lorraine</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Lorraine is a high-ranking French aristocrat, King John&#8217;s ambassador both to England and Scotland. He is quick to anger and foolhardy enough to draw his sword in the presence of King Edward, but shows more diplomacy with the Scottish King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Philip</persname>
<persdescription>Philip is the younger son of King John of France. He is a brave lad with a taste for battle and a blunt appreciation of realities, considering possession nine-tenths of the law. Confident of French victory, he sends Prince Edward a religious book as a consolation before battle, being certain that Edward will not live out the day. Philip is somewhat disquieted by the evil presages just before battle, but is quickly ready to reassure the common men. He is horrified at being defeated by such a smaller force. He is captured in battle. Historically, he was 14 years old at this time, and won the moniker &#8216;The Brave&#8217; for his deeds in the battle of Poitiers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Charles</persname>
<persdescription>Charles of Normandy is the eldest son of King John of France. Proud and insulting, he can find excuses to get out of keeping one&#8217;s promises, but once he has given his word he will hold to it even against his father&#8217;s displeasure. Ready to call an old man a dotard to his face, he also sends a message to Prince Edward advises him to run away before a battle. Charles is a brave man. Historically, he escaped the battlefield at Poitiers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">John de Valois, King of France</persname>
<persdescription>John de Valois, King of France, was named King after the last son of King Philip le Bew (le Bel) died. Haughty, overly self-assured, and rather a snob, he is nevertheless a genuinely brave man when he has his back to the wall. His own arrogance puts him in that position perhaps more often than strictly necessary, but his defiance of Edward&#8217;s invasion does make some rather good points. Beaten time and again in battle, he is overly optimistic about the likelihood of a French victory, bouncing back from defeat and misinterpreting prophecies to suit his hopes. He has the instincts of a good leader, he insists on reassuring his troops no matter how he feels himself when his confidence is shaken by more portents. Unfortunately, he cannot back up either these instincts or his quite genuine qualities with any military abilities. He is also wrathful, choleric, and authoritarian, willing to break all the rules of chivalry when he is in a temper with no care for the honor of his lords. He refuses to the end to admit that Edward has any justice on his side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gobin de Grey</persname>
<persdescription>Gobin de Grey is a French prisoner who shows the English a ford over the river Somme, in return for which he receives both his liberty and rather a lot of money.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Mountford</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Mountford is a claimant to the Dukedom of Brittany, which the Earl of Salisbury has been helping him to conquer. In thanks for the English help, he swears allegiance to King Edward once his campaign is successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Robert of Artois</persname>
<persdescription>Robert Earl of Artois is a Frenchman who has had to flee from France; arriving in England and being named Earl of Richmond by King Edward, he convinces the latter that he has a better claim to the French throne than does King John. Regarded as a traitor by the French, he becomes one of Edward&#8217;s war leaders, following the King to Scotland before going on to France and accompanying the Prince of Wales to the battle of Poitiers, where he captures the French King&#8217;s son Phillip. He is a brave man who is fond of Prince Edward and horrified that King Edward will do nothing to help his own son when the latter is in a bit of a fix.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Copland</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Copland is an English esquire who captures King David of Scots in battle but refuses to hand him over to Queen Philippa, as he insists that he will only give the prisoner to the King in person. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir William Mountague</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Mountague is a young English knight from the North of the country who rushes to report to King Edward that the peace with Scotland has been breached and that his aunt the Countess of Salisbury is besieged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lodowick</persname>
<persdescription>Lodowick is a confidant of King Edward&#8217;s, well-read and literate, and who knows the King better than many do. Asked by the monarch to write a love letter on his behalf, he is unable to get anywhere, as the King is being a backseat driver and literary critic throughout. His attempts at writing a formal and fashionable epistle do not please the King at all. He puts up with being used as a go-between even though he is perfectly well aware that the Countess is unlikely to reciprocate the King&#8217;s feelings.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Percy is a nobleman from the North of England who travels to France to inform King Edward that his enemy King David of Scotland has been captured in battle thanks to the Queen&#8217;s efforts in fighting the Scots.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Audley</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Audley is an old English nobleman who accompanies the Prince of Wales to the war. He is taken aback by the King&#8217;s refusal to send any aid to the Prince when the latter is in danger. Unafraid of death, he is able to stiffen the backs of those much younger than himself. He is mortally wounded at the battle of Poitiers. Honorable and generous, his final thoughts are for those dependent on him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury is an English nobleman, the husband of the Countess of Salisbury, and never does find out what King Edward&#8217;s plans for his wife were. He is off in France fighting to allow the Earl of Mountford to rule over Brittany. Eager to join King Edward in his war against the French, he arranges for a safe-condct for himself and his men from his prisoner Villiers in exchange for the latter&#8217;s freedom. Convinced by King John that the Prince of Wales is dead, he brings this false report to King Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Derby</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Derby is an English nobleman whom King Edward sends off to convince the earl of Hainault and the Emperor of Germany to provide aid to the English war against France. He is confused at the King&#8217;s distraction over the Countess of Salisbury, and distraught at the thought of Prince Edward&#8217;s death in battle. He is a compassionate man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Warwick is one of King Edward&#8217;s noblemen, an old man who is the Countess of Salisbury&#8217;s father. Deeply honorable, he is horrified when the King tricks him into swearing to convince his daughter to sleep with the lustful monarch, but makes a rather half-hearted attempt at doing so. He is greatly relieved when she&#8217;ll have none of it. Warwick is named Warden of the North to defend England against the Scots while King Edward is off beating up the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Prince Edward</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Edward is King Edward&#8217;s son, the Prince of Wales, and history&#8217;s Black Prince &#8212; also, therefore, the father of Richard II. A young man who looks a good deal like his mother Queen Philippa, he is the ideal knight, a brave and brilliant fighter who in his very first battle beats a far superior force and kills the King of Bohemia. Deeply patriotic, he bridles at insults to England or the English, and absolutely refuses to act in any way that risks ruining their reputation. Scornful and proud, he does not take well to being mocked, but is a true friend to those he loves, such as Audley. Victory makes him thirsty for more.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Countess of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Countess of Salisbury, Warwick&#8217;s daughter and Salisbury&#8217;s wife, is an English noblewoman who has the misfortune of being captured by the Scottish King and of being rather good-looking, attracting the attentions of not only Earl Douglas and King David but also of King Edward. Though a well-brought-up, well-behaved, and respectable lady, she has a sarcastic edge to her tongue when need be, and does not refrain from mocking the Scots when they are on the verge of running away. A loyal subject, she nevertheless absolutely refuses to entertain the idea of cheating on her husband with the King, out-arguing him on the subject and in the end out-maneuvering him completely into giving up his importuning. She is both brave and extremely clever.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Philippa</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Philippa is King Edward&#8217;s wife, a brave woman who is not afraid, even while heavily pregnant, to take charge of the war against the Scots. She is proud and does not like having her authority put into question. However, she is merciful, and often pleads with her husband to pardon others, as she is at times the only one who can calm him down. In particular she saves the lives of the six rich Citizens of Calais. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl Douglas</persname>
<persdescription>Earl Douglas is a Scottish lord who is rather taken with the Countess of Salisbury, but has no intention of staying to be captured by the English when they come to deliver her, and instead runs away as fast as he can.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">David, King of Scotland</persname>
<persdescription>King David of Scots is, despite his brave promises to the French, a bit of a wimp. He is more concerned with who should get the Countess of Salisbury than with checking whether the English might be coming to deliver her, and runs away as soon as he hears that they&#8217;re on their way. Trying to attack England in Edward&#8217;s absence, he ends up being captured by the English.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Edward III</persname>
<persdescription>Edward III is the King of England, a passionate man used to getting his own way. A proud man, he is insulted at the idea of being forced to do homage to the French King when he can claim the throne of France for himself. He does not act quite as nobly as he ought to, and is easily distracted from his wars by a pretty lady; in fact, he is quite able and willing to make a fool of himself over one. His attempts to woo the Countess of Salisbury provoke a burst of both lyricism and literary criticism from him, neither of which suit him, along with distracting him from his job. Luckily for England, as well as his own reputation, he recovers. He knows the value of propaganda, and quarters his arms with those of France even before fighting for the throne of that country begins. He is a proud but tough father to his son Prince Edward, refusing to give him any help on the battlefield so that he will not learn to expect any. Though generous by nature, Edward can also be cruel and vindictive, as in his plan to slaughter the six richest men of Calais in retribution for the city&#8217;s earlier refusal to surrender. His wife Queen Philippa is able to sway him on this, however. Edward is not an overly complicated man, being direct and generally acting as honor dictates, but his temper and desires can get in the way of that on occasion &#8212; and as he is not overly complicated, he follows them where they lead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Scottish Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>First Scottish Messenger warns King David of the approach of an enemy army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Scottish Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Second Scottish Messenger informs King David that the Scots have suddenly been attacked.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Polish Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Polish Captain leads forces to the aid of King John of France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">French Mariner</persname>
<persdescription>A French Mariner comes to tell King John that he has spotted the English fleet, and that King Edward has had the gall to quarter his arms with those of France. Sent back to the battle, he returns to inform the King that the French have lost, and many of their ships have been sunk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Frenchman is a cautious man who thinks it much more prudent to save as many of his personal belongings and store them (and himself) in a safe place when armies are on the march. He prefers not to fight on the French side as he believes that Edward is in the right.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Frenchman is a cautious man who thinks it best to get out of the path of war when armies are marching.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Frenchman is an overly optimistic man who has not heard of the approaching English and does not see them as being worth fleeing from. He soon learns better.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fourth Frenchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Frenchman witnesses the devastation caused by the English invasion and rushes about warning all those he meets to get to safety while they can.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Frenchwoman</persname>
<persdescription>A Frenchwoman has heard of prophecies suggesting that the war is going to be devastating, and cautiously thinks she should get herself and her children out of the path of war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The First Herald [mute role] carries in the coat of armor that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Herald [mute role] carries in the helmet that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Herald [mute role] carries in the lance that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fourth Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Herald [mute role] carries in the shield that King Edward gives to his son Prince Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Poor Inhabitant of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>A Poor Inhabitant of Calais is one of several kicked out of the town as he is far too weak to help in the defense of the city. He is saved from starving to death by King Edward&#8217;s generosity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Five Poor Inhabitants of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>Five Poor Inhabitants of Calais [mute roles] are kicked out of the town as he is far too weak to help in the defense of the city. They are saved from starving to death by King Edward&#8217;s generosity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First French Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The First French Captain comes to inform King Edward that the burgesses of Calais have decided to surrender, and has his own opinion about trusting in monarchs.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The First French Herald is sent by King John to offer terms to Prince Edward to avoid a battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Second French Herald is sent by Charles of Normandy to Prince Edward to suggest that he should take the opportunity to flee before battle becomes inevitable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second French Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The Second French Captain captures the Earl of Salisbury as he tries to make his way to Prince Edward, and brings him to King John.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First English Esquire</persname>
<persdescription>The First English Esquire helps rescue Audley from the French. He is concerned by Audley&#8217;s wounds.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second English Esquire</persname>
<persdescription>The Second English Esquire helps rescue Audley from the French. He does not like the idea of Audley dying. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">English Herald</persname>
<persdescription>An English Herald announces to King Edward and Queen Philippa that Prince Edward has won at Poitiers and captured King John.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The First Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who along with five others accepts to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man. He begs Edward to keep his word to spare the city, pointing out that the two-days&#8217; truce is not yet over.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who along with five others accepts to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants.  He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man, and swears to the truth of this on the peril of his immortal soul.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who accepts with five others to sacrifice himself for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fourth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Citizen of Calais is one of the six richest men of Calais who accept to sacrifice themselves for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants.  He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fifth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The Fifth Citizen of Calais is one of the six rich men of Calais who accept to sacrifice themselves for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sixth Citizen of Calais</persname>
<persdescription>The Sixth Citizen of Calais is one of the richest men of Calais, who accepts to sacrifice himself along with five others for the sake of the rest of the city&#8217;s inhabitants. He has suffered so much during the siege that it is hard to believe he was a prosperous man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Third French Herald is sent by Prince Philip of France to offer Prince Edward a consoling religious book.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>