<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Hamlet">

<persona>
<persname short="KING.">Claudius, King of Denmark</persname>
<persdescription>Claudius is Old Hamlet&#8217;s brother, uncle to Hamlet, and the present King of Denmark. He murdered the latter out of love or lust for Gertrude and the crown. Where his brother was a warrior, Claudius prefers diplomacy to resolve international situations, just as he prefers poison to the sword. He is voluble and his language seductive and convincing. He also knows how to delegate, whether it be having Norway restrain Fortinbras, England execute Hamlet, or Laertes murder the prince when England fails. He and his chief minister spy a great deal, and his personal guards are mercenaries. His conscience is guilt-stricken by his brother&#8217;s murder, but he cannot bring himself to genuine repentance due to his unwillingness to give up all the things it brought him. He drinks a great deal and engages in many public displays of affection with Gertrude. He is not over-loved by the people, for fear of whom he dare not publically move against Hamlet, and who are easily roused to rebellion by Laertes. He pities Ophelia and likes Polonius, and is besotted with his queen. He orders that Ophelia be buried with ceremony instead of as a suicide. Though at first convinced of Hamlet&#8217;s madness, he is soon suspicious of the young man, realizes that the prince is somehow aware of his guilt, and begins to plot his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GHOST.">Ghost of Hamlet&#8217;s Father</persname>
<persdescription>The Ghost of Old Hamlet haunts the castle of Elsinore. Having been murdered by his brother, he wanders the night, waiting for a chance to speak with his son. As he was unable to confess to his sins before death, he lives in Purgatory during the day. He charges Hamlet to revenge his murder, and when the prince takes too long about it reappears to spur him on. In life, he was an excellent warrior. A physically impressive specimen in life, he is very pale, bearded, his hair graying, and wears the armor he was wearing at his greatest victory, carrying a truncheon. He is at times suspected of being an evil spirit who has taken on Old Hamlet&#8217;s shape to wreak havoc on Denmark.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OPH.">Ophelia</persname>
<persdescription>Ophelia is Polonius&#8217;s daughter. In love with Hamlet, she is obedient to her father and listens to her brother, though she is spirited enough to accuse him of potential hypocrisy. She obeys Polonius&#8217;s order to refuse to receive any more mail from Hamlet and not to see him, and turns over to her father what letters she does receive. She truly believes in Hamlet&#8217;s love, and though she agrees to trick him when commanded to by Claudius and Polonius, she is devastated when Hamlet turns on her, and believes in his madness. Nevertheless, she is able to banter somewhat with him at the play. Her father&#8217;s death at Hamlet&#8217;s hand drives her mad, in which state she undoes her hair and sings songs while accompanying herself on a lute. Her ravings touch on her father and her betrayal by Hamlet. Playing with flowers, she falls into the river and drowns, though whether this was intentional or not is uncertain.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="QUEEN.">Getrude, Queen of Denmark</persname>
<persdescription>Gertrude is the widow of Old Hamlet and the present wife of Claudius, Hamlet&#8217;s mother, and the Queen. She is not a native Dane. She married her brother-in-law quickly after her husband&#8217;s death, but has mostly repressed whatever feelings of guilt she has for doing so. She loves her son deeply, insisting on keeping him by her, though she is not as well-aware of his friendships as she thinks. Like Hamlet, she finds Polonius&#8217;s orotund speeches tedious. She is convinced that Hamlet is mad, and hopes to cure him, but can find no way to do so. Despite what Hamlet considers her great age (she is at least 44), she still enjoys the physical pleasures of marriage. She is brave, willing to physically restrain Laertes from attacking Claudius, but cannot fight back against Hamlet&#8217;s verbal assaults. She does not at first know Ophelia, and is frightened of her madness, but is devastated by her death, since she had hoped the girl might marry Hamlet once she heard of her son&#8217;s love for her. She does not think much of her subjects, and worries that Ophelia&#8217;s madness may make them suspicious. She recognizes that she has been poisoned by her last drink.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FORT.">Fortinbras</persname>
<persdescription>Fortinbras is the Prince of Norway, a warlike young man with energy to spend. He intends to revenge his father, Old Fortinbras, who was killed in a duel with Old Hamlet and thereby lost some Norwegian lands to Denmark. Restrained from doing so by his uncle the king of Norway, he invades Poland instead, to capture a useless little plot of land. This greatly impresses Hamlet. On his return, he passes through Denmark, and happens to arrive just as everyone dies. Since the entire royal family of Denmark is dead, he claims the throne on the basis of some old connection, Hamlet having already spoken in his favor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRAN.">Francisco</persname>
<persdescription>Francisco is a guard at Elsinore. He is slightly depressed, or at least unhappy about having to work cold nights.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAR.">Barnardo</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH MAR. AND BAR.">Both Barnardo and Marcellus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Barnardo is a guard at Elsinore, charged with the midnight round. On two separate nights he has seen the ghost of Old Hamlet while standing guard. With Marcellus, he tells the tale to the skeptical Horatio; when the latter witnesses the apparition, he cannot resist a little dig at the scholar&#8217;s disbelief. He suspects that the ghost appears in warning about the possible coming war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Marcellus</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH MAR. AND BAR.">Both Barnardo and Marcellus</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Marcellus is a guard at Elsinore, Barnardo&#8217;s companion on the midnight round. With him, he witnesses the apparition of the ghost. He convinces Horatio to join them for the watch on the third night. He knows more about ghosts than Barnardo, and known to Hamlet. He risks physically restraining the latter from following the ghost, but later swears himself to silence over the whole matter of the haunting. He is concerned about the warlike preparations going on in Denmark, and feels that something is wrong in the world.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HOR.">Horatio</persname>
<persdescription>Horatio is a friend of Hamlet&#8217;s, a fellow student at Wittenberg University. He is well-known enough in Elsinore for Marcellus and Barnardo to go to him for advice about the ghost they have seen. He is both learned and skeptical, not entirely willing to believe in every legend about the supernatural but knowing the habitual reasons why ghosts return from the grave. Though Hamlet has not seen him since he came from Wittenberg for Old Hamlet&#8217;s funeral, he soon becomes the prince&#8217;s one confidant. He is cautious about the ghost, afraid of its intentions, but accepts Hamlet&#8217;s vouching of its good faith. He does not give in much to emotion. He watches Claudius throughout the performance of the play and is convinced of his guilt. He is the first witness of Ophelia&#8217;s madness and convinces Gertrude to accept to see her. He goes to greet Hamlet on his secret return to Denmark. Hamlet considers him his best friend; he contemplates suicide at the catastrophic outcome of the duel, though insisting that he does so in a stoical manner rather than out of passion. Hamlet convinces him to live so as to tell the world the story, which he will do.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POL.">Polonius</persname>
<persdescription>Polonius is Claudius&#8217;s long-bearded chief counselor. An old and respected man, he is opinionated, never uses one word when ten will do, speaks as a minor literary critic, is occasionally forgetful, and enjoys reminiscing about his days at university, where he took part in amateur dramatics and had a taste for the ladies. He is careful not to appear ambitious, and considers his daughter too lowly a bride for a prince. He expects full obedience from his daughter, and offers wise moral precepts to his son, while thinking nothing of having him spied on and using Ophelia as bait for Hamlet. He spies a great deal on everybody, and insists that matters of state come before more private ones, even the madness of the heir to the throne.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HAM.">Hamlet</persname>
<persdescription>Hamlet is the Prince of Denmark. Devastated by his father&#8217;s death, he had nevertheless hoped to succeed him, only to see his uncle Claudius both be chosen as king and marry his mother. This does nothing for his depression. Beloved by the people, he is thirty years old, a superlative fencer, a student at the university in Wittenberg, introspective, and suspicious. He is in love with Ophelia, or at least has been courting her. He keeps on his mourning clothes despite the royal wedding and wishes to return to Wittenberg to escape this new Denmark. Virtually suicidal, he is roused to action by the news that his father&#8217;s ghost has been seen, though he is skeptical enough to double-check the claims of the ones who have seen it. This lack of concern for his life is strong enough, however, that he does not care what danger the ghost may lead him to. The ghost&#8217;s revelation that he was murdered by Claudius gives Hamlet a reason for his hatred of his uncle. He decides to mimic madness to avert suspicion, and may at times actually slip into genuine madness. He uses his madness as a license to speak his genuine feeling about Polonius. Highly intelligent, he catches on to Rosencrantz and Guildenstern&#8217;s mission within a few sentences, and runs rings around their attempts to diagnose him. He has a great love of theatre, knowing the players personally and having heard them perform plays almost never performed, as well as knowing exactly what play exists to trap Claudius, writing lines to be added to it, and having a great deal of advice on how to act for the professionals. His loathing of his uncle is visceral, and he also spits out detestation for himself, women, makeup, and his traitorous friends. He is disgusted at the idea of his mother having sex, much less enjoying it, believing that middle-aged ladies do not feel desire. His hatred for Claudius leads him to forgo an excellent opportunity to kill him, out of concern that his uncle might end up in heaven instead of hell. Discovering that Claudius intended him to be executed as soon as he set foot in England, he has no compunction about having this done to Rosencrantz and Guildenstern instead. This new ruthlessness follows him when he returns to Denmark after having been captured by pirates. His conscience clear, he is determined to bring the matter to an end. Distressed by Ophelia&#8217;s death, he does not take his first opportunity. He accepts the duel with Laertes with a sense of fatalism, though claiming that all the injuries he did to his opponent were done in madness. Hearing that he has been poisoned, he finally kills Claudius, refuses to give a valedictory speech, prevents Horatio from killing himself and asking him to tell the whole story, and naming Fortinbras as the best successor to the throne of Denmark.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OSR.">Osric</persname>
<persdescription>Osric is a young courtier at Claudius&#8217;s court. Rich and little more, he is affected in his speech and manner, removing his hat in Hamlet&#8217;s presence without ceasing to flourish it about. He is enough of a fencer to be the judge of the bout between Hamlet and Laertes.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GUIL.">Guildenstern</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH ROS. AND GUIL.">Both Rosencrantz and Guildenstern</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Guildenstern is a childhood friend of Hamlet&#8217;s, inseparable from Rosencrantz. Quieter than the latter, he adds to his pronouncements, and is honest enough to admit that he and Rosencrantz were sent for. He makes certain that he is not overshadowed by his companion, and is willing to tell Hamlet to make sense. He is slightly less of a crawler than is Rosencrantz, and does not know how to play the recorder. He accompanies Hamlet on his ship to England, continues after Hamlet is captured by pirates, and has his head chopped off on arrival.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROS.">Rosencrantz</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH ROS. AND GUIL.">Both Rosencrantz and Guildenstern</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Rosencrantz is a childhood friend of Hamlet&#8217;s, inseparable from Guildenstern. He knows more about the theatre than does the latter. Called to court by Claudius to spy on Hamlet, both are incompetent enough that he realizes this after a few sentences between them. Rosencrantz is a crawler before Claudius, and somewhat overdoes his compliments. He accompanies Hamlet on his ship to England, continues after Hamlet is captured by pirates, and has his head chopped off on arrival.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="COR.">Cornelius</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH COR. AND VOL.">Both Cornelius and Voltemand</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Cornelius is a courtier at Claudius&#8217;s court. He is sent with Voltemand to Norway, to inform that country&#8217;s king of how his nephew Fortinbras is threatening Denmark, and to convince him to restrain the young man. His mission is highly successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VOL.">Voltemand</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH COR. AND VOL.">Both Cornelius and Voltemand</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Voltemand is a courtier at Claudius&#8217;s court. He is sent with Cornelius to Norway, to inform that country&#8217;s king of how his nephew Fortinbras is threatening Denmark, and to convince him to restrain the young man. His mission is highly successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAER.">Laertes</persname>
<persdescription>Laertes is Polonius&#8217;s son, who prefers life in Paris to Elsinore. He has some of his father&#8217;s moral sententiousness, but both his sister and father suspect that he may not be as upright as he puts out. His father&#8217;s death affects him so much that he returns enraged from Paris and raises a rebellion against Claudius. The sight of his mad sister shifts him from rage to grief and allows Claudius to convince him of Hamlet&#8217;s guilt. He is willing to do anything for revenge, no matter how treacherous or how dangerous to his soul. He is an excellent fencer.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="P. KING.">First Player (Player King)</persname>
<persdescription>The First Player has, with his company, known Hamlet for some time. He remembers a speech from a play that was never acted, and recites it most affectingly, to the extent of having tears in his eyes. He is willing to insert some new lines into the play Hamlet calls for them to perform. He plays the King in that performance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="P. QUEEN.">Player Queen</persname>
<persdescription>The Player Queen is an adolescent boy who has recently had a growth spurt, but whose voice has not yet broken.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="P. PRO.">Player Prologue</persname>
<persdescription>The Player Prologue gives the fifteen-word opening to the spoken part of the players&#8217; performance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="P. LUC.">Player Lucianus</persname>
<persdescription>The Player Lucianus plays the murderer in the play. He overdoes his melodramatic evil grimaces on his entrance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. CLO.">First Clown (Gravedigger)</persname>
<persdescription>The First Clown is a gravedigger. He is convinced that Ophelia ought to be considered a suicide. He is a joking fellow who sings as he digs, is much given to wordplay, and is proud of his profession. He knows all the skulls in a grave he digs up, and knew Yorick.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CLO.">Second Clown (Gravedigger)</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Clown is the first gravedigger&#8217;s straight man. He is aware that when it comes down to it, Ophelia is only being properly buried because of her rank.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAER. FOL.">Laertes&#8217;s Followers</persname>
<persdescription>Laertes&#8217;s Followers convince the mob to let Ophelia through and enter the room where Claudius and Gertrude are confronting Laertes.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GENT.">Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>A Gentleman brings the sailors to Horatio.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="REY.">Reynaldo</persname>
<persdescription>Reynaldo is a servant and spy of Polonius&#8217;s able to put up with the latter&#8217;s absent-minded wanderings. He is sent to spy on Laertes in Paris and discover just what the young man is up to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LORD.">Lord</persname>
<persdescription>A Lord comes to double-check that Hamlet is still planning to fence with Laertes, and to ask the prince on the Queen&#8217;s behalf to be nice to Laertes before the bout begins.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger, possibly a member of Claudius&#8217;s Swiss guard, bursts in to tell the King to flee from the mob that Laertes has roused and which is breaking in to the palace. He later brings Hamlet&#8217;s letters to the royal couple.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SAIL.">First Sailor</persname>
<persdescription>The First Sailor is one of the pirate crew that captures Hamlet. He brings letters from the prince to Horatio, the King, and the Queen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. AMB.">First Ambassador</persname>
<persdescription>The First Ambassador from England arrives at Elsinore with the news of Rosencrantz and Guildenstern&#8217;s execution just after everyone dies. He crosses paths with Fortinbras, who has his army salute him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAP.">Norwegian Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Norwegian Captain in Fortinbras&#8217;s army has no illusions about the campaign they are engaged in.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOCTOR.">Doctor of Divinity</persname>
<persdescription>A Doctor of Divinity officiates unwillingly at Ophelia&#8217;s funeral. He performs the shortest ceremony he can, being convinced that she was in fact a suicide. He is not shy of giving his opinion on the matter to the bereaved Laertes.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>