<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry VI, Part 2">

<persona>
<persname short="">King Henry the Sixth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry VI, head of the Lancastrian party, is a young, weak, overly pious monarch with absolutely no political sense, who would much rather be in his study reading than having to rule a country, and relies excessively on his councilors. Shy and awkward, his response to everything is to praise God and quote pious clich&amp;eacute;s, even when reading a prediction of his own deposition. He is overborne by his wife Margaret and oblivious to her love for Suffolk. His greatest desire is for peace between all his noblemen and his subjects, but his pleading has little effect. He has full trust in Gloucester, and follows his lead in everything until the latter is tossed out by the other members of the nobility. Despite his conviction of Gloucester&#8217;s innocence, Henry does not have the strength to go against the will of all the other noblemen and the Queen. The extent of his reliance on Gloucester is such that he faints on learning of the Duke&#8217;s death. He is easily bullied, though he strives for justice at all times and comes to recognize that he is not as good a ruler as he should be. He is baffled and disconcerted when York denies his claim to the throne. A determined pacifist in a court of combative, violent enemies, he is a sympathetic figure, if only because he is so utterly out of his depth. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Gloucester is the King&#8217;s uncle, the brother of Henry V, and Lord Protector of the realm, the same character as in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>. He is a good man, beloved by the people, and doing his best under trying circumstances. He can be haughty, however, and sometimes needs to lash out and be heard; his care for England is shocked and insulted by the terms of the King&#8217;s marriage treaty, and he makes his opinion known. He is aware of his tendency to lose his temper, and out of self-control prefers to remove himself from a room before he says or does anything unforgivable. He loves his wife Eleanor greatly, though he is worried at her ambitions; despite his love his regard for justice will not allow him to help her when she is condemned, though partly this is because he knows that his public position is precarious and that helping her would harm him. He is a worried man who feels the weight of his duties strongly, though he is still wily and able to see through Simpcox&#8217;s trick easily. Deposed by the nobility&#8217;s coup, he suspects all too well what will follow his disgrace. He is an old man with a large, cared-for beard. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Cardinal Beauford</persname>
<persdescription>Cardinal Beauford is the same as the Bishop of Winchester of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>, King Henry&#8217;s illegitimate great-uncle, a wily, hypocritical priest who masks his hatred of his nephew Gloucester behind piety. He attempts to undermine the Duke at all times, under the pretence of safeguarding the kingdom. He joins with Suffolk to bring down Gloucester&#8217;s wife by setting her up to be caught consulting a magician, and is one of the masterminds of the coup that brings Gloucester down. Appointed Gloucester&#8217;s jailer, he facilitates his nephew&#8217;s death. On his deathbed, all of his sins come back to him, and he begins to rave in fear of death, terrified of what awaits him. Few people trust him, for good reason.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Richard Plantagenet, Duke of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of York, head of the Yorkist party, is the Richard Plantagenet of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>, an English nobleman convinced that his claim to the throne is better than King Henry&#8217;s. He is a proud and ambitious man who aims to make himself King, and is ready to take actions he knows to be of questionable morality to do so. He joins in the plot against the Duchess of Gloucester, is a prime mover of the coup that overthrows Gloucester himself, and he urges Cade to rebel for the sake of seeing what popular opinion will think of a challenge to Henry&#8217;s rule and providing an excuse to bring his army home, no matter the cost to the country. Leaving aside the question of Henry&#8217;s right to the throne, York despises him as being unfit to wear the crown. He has an ongoing feud with Somerset and Suffolk, but joins with the latter to plot Gloucester&#8217;s death. Sent to Ireland to put down a rebellion, he leaps at the chance to raise an army, and having subdued the Irish uses it to push his claims in England. Though he attempts to present himself as a loyal subject for as long as possible, the longer he spends as a mere subject the more enraged he grows, and seeing Somerset at liberty after being told he had been imprisoned proves the final straw, and he openly announces his rebellion, despite having only the Nevilles (Salisbury and Warwick) on his side, along with his sons Edward and Richard. His revolt leads to the battle of Saint Albans, which he wins; the rest of his career can be found in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Edward Earl of March</persname>
<persdescription>Edward Earl of March, of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s eldest son, leading one portion of York&#8217;s army. He is a brave man and an able soldier. His further career is chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three.</NAMEREF></persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Richard Plantagenet</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Plantagenet, of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s third son and the leader of one portion of his army. He is a loyal son and an able soldier, killing Somerset personally. He is a hunchback with an excellent sense of repartee. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Somerset</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Somerset, of the Lancastrian party, is one of the younger members of the English nobility, who has an ongoing feud with the Duke of York (see <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>) and dislikes the Duke of Gloucester. He joins with the Cardinal to help overthrow the latter, but also makes plans with Buckingham to rid themselves of the Cardinal as well. Named Regent of the English possessions in France, he is badly beaten by the French. His proximity to the King on his return provides an excuse for York to return with his army from Ireland; Somerset agrees to put himself into custody to calm York down, but his appearance at liberty drives the Duke to openly publish his rebellion. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Suffolk</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Suffolk (William de la Pole), of the Lancastrian party, is an English nobleman who fell passionately in love with Margaret when he met her, and being unable to wed her as he was already married, arranged for her to marry King Henry so he could keep her close (see <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>). In doing so he agreed to extremely disadvantageous terms for England in the treaty between England and Margaret&#8217;s father. He is a masculine, seductive man, but also a conniving, power-hungry courtier, and insanely prideful and disdainful of common people. He detests both Gloucester and the Duke of York, and schemes to bring about their downfalls. He is willing to partner with his enemies to bring down another one, and joins with York to arrange for Gloucester&#8217;s death. Having already arranged for the Duchess of Gloucester&#8217;s trafficking with magicians, and for her discovery, he also takes the murder of Gloucester into his own hands. He is unable to face down Warwick&#8217;s accusations, however, and is banished. He is hated by the people for what he has done to national prestige and for killing the Duke; even pirates despise him, and execute him on finding out who he is. His head then spends a great deal of time being fondled by Margaret.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Buckingham</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Buckingham is an English nobleman who dislikes the duke of Gloucester and aims to replace him. Though he joins with the Cardinal to try and dislodge him, arguing that the King is old enough to reign on his own, he in fact aims to simply replace Gloucester as Protector, leaving the Cardinal behind. Part of the plot against Gloucester&#8217;s Duchess, he is one of those who arrests her for consulting magicians. He helps Clifford to put down Cade&#8217;s rebellion by promising to pardon the rebels, and becomes one of the King&#8217;s chief councilors, sent to parley with York when the latter brings his army back from Ireland. Despite his personal ambitions, he is loyal to the King and not unkind to the common folk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Clifford</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Clifford, of the Lancastrian party, is an old nobleman highly loyal to the King. He is sent with Buckingham to convince Cade&#8217;s followers to abandon their rebellion, and twice manages to win them over by his speeches. When York insists that he is the rightful King, all Clifford can think is that York has gone mad, and he has no qualms about recommending his immediate execution. He is Henry&#8217;s main defender against the Yorkist forces. He is an excellent fighter, but York has the better of him. His final thought is that how one dies is more important than the fact of dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Young Clifford</persname>
<persdescription>Young Clifford, of the Lancastrian party, is Lord Clifford&#8217;s son. He loves his father dearly and follows his lead in insulting the Duke of York and his family when the latter claims the throne. The death of his father strikes him hard, and he swears to have revenge. Where this oath leads him can be discovered in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury, of the Yorkist party, is the Earl of Warwick&#8217;s father and an old nobleman whose chief care is for the good of the realm. He at first prefers to support the Duke of Gloucester against the machinations of the Cardinal and Somerset for that reason. He is convinced by York and Warwick&#8217;s arguments as to York&#8217;s right to the crown, and swears to help bring him to the throne, though that means abandoning Gloucester to his fate. He has the common touch and is able to parley with a mob. Despite his age, he is a fierce fighter. His family crest is a bear chained to a staff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Warwick, of the Yorkist party, is Salisbury&#8217;s son and a supporter of the Duke of York. A great fighter, he is horrified and enraged when the counties he won by battle in France are handed back over without any form of compensation as part of King Henry&#8217;s marriage treaty. His temper often gets him into trouble, as he bursts out whatever thoughts he has without regard for his place. He is quick to accept York&#8217;s claim to the throne as valid. He is convinced that Gloucester was murdered when he sees the Duke&#8217;s corpse, and opportunistically rouses the commons to riot as a way of getting rid of Suffolk. Insulted by Clifford, he swears to kill him personally at Saint Albans, but recognizes York&#8217;s superior claim. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Scales</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Scales is the officer in charge of the defense of the Tower of London. He scarcely has enough men for the task, but still tries to send some help to the Mayor against the rebels.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Say</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Say is mistakenly believed by Cade&#8217;s rebels to be responsible for the losses in France, partly because he can speak French; he is also hated for heavy taxation. He nobly refuses to follow the King to safety at Killingworth, so as to not attract the rebels against the King there. He is a well-educated man, a diplomat and judge rather than a warrior, none of which do him any favors when he is captured. Despite all his pleading, he is executed, and his head used as a trophy and battle-standard by Cade&#8217;s men.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir Humphrey Stafford</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Humphrey Stafford raises the King&#8217;s army and tries to disperse Cade&#8217;s riot in its early stages. He is not the most diplomatic of fellows, as he is enraged at the sight of the lower classes rebelling. He has all the rebels proclaimed traitors, but is killed in the ensuing fight.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">William Stafford</persname>
<persdescription>Stafford&#8217;s Brother, William, joins Sir Humphrey in his attempt to disperse Cade&#8217;s followers with words. He is particularly concerned with discrediting Cade, and suspects (correctly) that the latter is working at the Duke of York&#8217;s instigation. He is killed in the first battle of the rebellion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Stanley</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Stanley is named as Dame Eleanor&#8217;s jailer by the King, and insists to her that he will treat her as she is used to being treated, except for the whole being a prisoner on an island thing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Vaux</persname>
<persdescription>Vaux goes to tell the King of the Cardinal&#8217;s strange illness and impending death; he gives the news to the Queen on his way.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Matthew Goffe</persname>
<persdescription>Matthew Goffe [mute role] is a Londoner killed by Cade&#8217;s rebels.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Alexander Iden</persname>
<persdescription>Alexander Iden is an esquire of Kent, quite removed from the rebellion, a quiet, unambitious man who merely wishes to live his life in peace and quiet, keeping his wealth up and giving charity to the poor. He is shocked to find a starving man stealing from his garden, particularly when the man insults him. Though essentially peaceful, Iden will not bear a slur on his honor, and challenges the man to fight. Only after killing him does he discover that his enemy is Cade, and he is delighted to have made an end of the rabble-rouser. He brings Cade&#8217;s head to the King and is knighted for the deed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lieutenant</persname>
<persdescription>The Lieutenant is a pirate leader whose crew captures Suffolk and two gentlemen as he attempts to escape to France. He is concerned by Whitmore&#8217;s bloodthirstiness, being himself much more interested in possible ransom money. Though a pirate, he loves his country and hates Suffolk for what he has done to it, and his rage bursts out when he finds the man in his hands. He has Suffolk killed to make sure he cannot come back.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Shipmaster</persname>
<persdescription>The Shipmaster pilots the pirate ship that captures Suffolk and the gentlemen, and plans to make a great deal of money by ransoming his share of the captured prisoners.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Master's Mate</persname>
<persdescription>The Master&#8217;s Mate is the Master&#8217;s second-in-command on the pirate ship that captures Suffolk and the gentlemen, and follows the Master&#8217;s lead in setting a ransom amount for his prisoner&#8217;s freedom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Walter Whitmore</persname>
<persdescription>Walter Whitmore is one of the pirate gang that captures Suffolk and the gentlemen. He is a bloodthirsty man who is in a terrible mood due to the casualties that were inflicted on his crew during the battle, not to mention having lost an eye in the fight. He swears to kill his prisoner rather than ransom him. He hates Suffolk as much as anyone, and is delighted to have the chance to kill him, suggesting that he may torture him before killing him. He has a lower-class accent and pronounces his first name &#8216;Water&#8217;.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">John Hume</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Hume is a priest has been bribed by the Cardinal and Suffolk to push the Duchess of Gloucester towards thinking of making her husband King, and to convince her to take the forbidden step of consulting magicians in the hopes of furthering her plans. He has a great love of gold, and so long as he is paid doesn&#8217;t think too hard, and thus does not foresee that he will himself be caught in the net and hanged for having collaborated with the conjurers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">John Southwell</persname>
<persdescription>John Southwell is a priest who assists Bolingbrook in his conjurations. He is hanged for his pains when the conjurers are arrested and tried.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Roger Bolingbrook</persname>
<persdescription>Roger Bolingbrook is a conjurer who works with Margery Jordan and has been hired by the Duchess of Gloucester to raise a spirit and commit the forbidden act of asking for the King&#8217;s horoscope. He likes to make himself impressive, and can command one spirit out of hell. Caught in the act, he is hanged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Thomas Horner</persname>
<persdescription>Thomas Horner is an armorer who has claimed that the Duke of York has a better right to the throne than the King. When denounced for this by his apprentice, Peter, he claims that the latter is merely taking revenge for having been punished. Ordered to fight to prove his claim of innocence, he gets thoroughly drunk first and is killed. He confesses to his treason before dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Peter Thump</persname>
<persdescription>Peter Thump is Horner&#8217;s apprentice. Hearing his master claim that the Duke of York is the rightful King, he takes the opportunity to denounce his master. He is a coward, and convinced he will be killed in the fight with Horner. He refuses the drinks pressed upon him by the other apprentices, and is therefore able to best his very drunken master, killing him. He is a simple man, but kind, with many friends.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Clerk of Chatham</persname>
<persdescription>Emmanuel, the Clerk of Chatham has the misfortune of being able to read, write, and count, and to be caught by Cade&#8217;s rebels just as he is giving his students homework. Making the mistake of claiming that education is a good thing, he is hanged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mayor of Saint Albans</persname>
<persdescription>The Mayor of Saint Albans leads a procession bringing Simpcox to the King, eager to show off evidence of the power of Saint Alban&#8217;s shrine, the town&#8217;s main tourist attraction. Convinced by Gloucester&#8217;s puncturing of Simpcox&#8217;s claim, he sends for the Beadle to whip the man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Saunder Simpcox</persname>
<persdescription>Saunder Simpcox is a poor man and a fraud who travels the country pretending to be lame and to have been miraculously cured of blindness.  Unfortunately for him he does not have a mind quick enough to outfox Gloucester, who sees through him, and he ends up being whipped out of town. This does not diminish his credit with some of the simpler townsfolk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Jack Cade</persname>
<persdescription>Jack Cade is a Kentishman who has served the Duke of York and is set by him to rise a rebellion against King Henry under the name of John Mortimer. Cade takes his instructions a bit too seriously, and soon develops excessive delusions of grandeur. He is a good leader, though, or at least an excellent rabble-rouser, able to convince his men to follow him in a plan that is the establishment&#8217;s worst nightmare of a lower-class rebellion: all to be equal, property (including wives) to be communal, and books to be burnt. Resolutely anti-intellectual, Cade kills anyone who can read, burns all the records, and uses evidence of education as a good excuse to die. While preaching equality, he insists on being treated as a king, soon having those who don&#8217;t killed. Though he occasionally gets a sense of how insane his actions are, he soon gets past that. His idea of power is to be able to eat and drink as much as he likes and the right to sleep with any woman he wishes to. Despite the fact that he is almost mad, he is sensible enough to flee when things go against him. On the verge of starving to death while in hiding, he tries to rob a garden and is killed by a man who does not even know who he is.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">George Bevis</persname>
<persdescription>George Bevis is one of the commoners who join Cade&#8217;s rebellion. A workman, he sees no worth in any man who doesn&#8217;t do the sort of job he does. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">John Holland</persname>
<persdescription>John Holland is one of the commoners who join Cade&#8217;s rebellion. He has a confused understanding of common sayings, and is in the end not entirely impressed by Cade. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Dick the Butcher</persname>
<persdescription>Dick the Butcher is a large, physically powerful man, essentially Cade&#8217;s second-in-command, though he clearly does not believe a word of Cade&#8217;s claims to noble blood, or misunderstands Cade&#8217;s intentions entirely, as he tries to build up Cade&#8217;s credibility by pointing out what a criminal he is. He joins the rebellion for the joy of anarchy, a chance to kill lawyers and have his way with women. He enjoys killing. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Spirit</persname>
<persdescription>A Spirit (Asmath) is a creature from the underworld controlled by Margery Jordan and Bolingbroke. Being commanded to appear on earth is painful for him. He predicts the future in ambiguous ways.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Simpcox&#8217;s Wife</persname>
<persdescription>Simpcox&#8217;s Wife follows her husband and helps to propagate his fraudulent claim of being lame and recently cured of blindness. While Simpcox never admits to being a conman, his wife is willing to tell the Duke of Gloucester that they only did it out of poverty.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Margery Jordan</persname>
<persdescription>Margery Jordan is a witch who works with Roger Bolingbrook and has been hired by the Duchess of Gloucester to raise a spirit a commit the forbidden act of asking for the King&#8217;s horoscope. She can raise the spirit Asmath. Captured with the others, she is burnt alive at the stake for her witchcraft.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duchess Eleanor of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>The Duchess of Gloucester (Dame Eleanor Cobham) is the wife of the Duke of Gloucester, a woman who enjoys the trappings of wealth and power a great deal. Ambitious and prideful, she considers her husband rather weak, and wishes that he would put his nephew aside and become King himself. She is haughty and looks down on Queen Margaret, who is poorer and less well-dressed than she is. She also sees Margaret&#8217;s character clearly, though she lacks the ability to see her own faults. In her ambition she takes the dangerous step of consulting a fortune-teller, not realizing that she has been set up, and is arrested for the illegal act of forecasting the King&#8217;s fate. As a noblewoman, she is spared death, but is publicly humiliated before being banished.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Queen Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Margaret, of the Lancastrian party, is King Henry&#8217;s wife, the daughter of a penniless French nobleman, who brings no dowry with her to her marriage. Meeting her husband, she soon finds him to be a great disappointment, thoroughly unmanly and non-regal. She has little patience for his bookishness and piety. Besides, she is deeply in love with Suffolk, who arranged for her marriage in the first place (see Henry VI Part One). A prideful woman, she cannot stomach the Duchess of Gloucester&#8217;s high-and-mighty airs, nor the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s control of government, and she soon joins the court intrigues to bring them down, aiming to set her husband firmly in control of the country. As she herself can easily bully the King, she will therefore rule herself. Intelligent and cunning, she has a strong temper, but is also capable of coldly plotting an enemy&#8217;s death. She stiffens Henry&#8217;s spine as they are defeated in battle by York. Her further adventures are chronicled in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Three</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Murderer </persname>
<persdescription>The First Murderer smothers Gloucester on Suffolk&#8217;s orders. He is not particularly bothered by this. As Suffolk is banished soon after, it is unlikely he is ever paid for the job.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Michael</persname>
<persdescription>Michael is one of Cade&#8217;s rebels. He sees Stafford&#8217;s army approaching and runs to advise Cade to escape. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Smith the Weaver</persname>
<persdescription>Smith the Weaver joins Cade&#8217;s rebellion but is not impressed with Cade&#8217;s claims of noble blood. He provides evidence that the Clerk of Chatham has been giving boys homework, leading to the Clerk&#8217;s execution. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Royal Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Royal Messenger comes to summon Gloucester to a hawking party at Saint Albans.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Petitioner</persname>
<persdescription>The First Petitioner hopes to receive help from the Duke of Gloucester against one of the Cardinal&#8217;s servants, who has taken all he has.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Petitioner</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Petitioner represents the village of Melford, and hopes for help from the Duke of Gloucester against Suffolk, who has enclosed the common lands around the village, plunging all the villagers into poverty. He accidentally allows Suffolk to see his petition first.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gloucester's Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s Servingman [mute role] is ordered by the Duke of York to invite Salisbury and Warwick to dinner after York arrests the Duchess.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Beadle of Saint Albans</persname>
<persdescription>The Beadle of Saint Albans is a town official whose tasks include whipping common malefactors. He is very matter-of-fact about this aspect of his job.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Neighbor</persname>
<persdescription>The First Neighbor is a friend of Horner&#8217;s, and hopes to rouse his fighting spirit by giving him a drink, contributing to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Neighbor</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Neighbor is a friend of Horner&#8217;s, and hopes to rouse his fighting spirit by giving him a drink, contributing to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Neighbor</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Neighbor is a friend of Horner&#8217;s, and hopes to rouse his fighting spirit by giving him a drink, contributing to his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Prentice</persname>
<persdescription>The First Prentice (Robin) is a friend of Peter&#8217;s, and hopes to help him overcome his fright before the fight by giving him a drink.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Prentice</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Prentice (Will) is a friend of Peter&#8217;s, and hopes to help him overcome his fright before the fight by giving him a drink.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Prentice</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Prentice (Tom) [mute role] is a friend of Peter&#8217;s, and hopes to help him overcome his fright before the fight by giving him a drink. He hopes Peter will win as a blow for prentices against masters.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Herald</persname>
<persdescription>A Herald is sent to summon Gloucester to a session of Parliament, the first of Henry&#8217;s reign that Gloucester has not called himself.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sheriff of London</persname>
<persdescription>The Sheriff of London is in charge of Dame Eleanor&#8217;s penance, and conducts her through the streets of London as she performs it. He is a dutiful man who performs his tasks to the letter. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Post</persname>
<persdescription>A Post comes from Ireland to warn the English government of a rebellion that has broken out there.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Murderer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Murderer is struck with remorse after having helped smother Gloucester.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman is captured by pirates while traveling on the same ship that is conveying Suffolk to France. He blanches a little when he hears how much he&#8217;ll have to pay to gain his freedom, but prefers doing so to being killed. He is allowed to go and fetch the ransom for himself and his companion, and takes the opportunity to bring Suffolk&#8217;s body and head to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman is captured by pirates while traveling on the same ship that is conveying Suffolk to France. He blanches a little when he hears how much he&#8217;ll have to pay to gain his freedom, but prefers doing so to being killed. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Royal Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Royal Messenger rushes to the court to warn the King that Cade&#8217;s rebels have made it to the suburb of Southwark in London, and that the court is therefore in grave danger.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Royal Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Royal Messenger brings news to the King that Cade is on the verge of capturing London Bridge, the gateway to the city, and that the citizens of London are joining the rebels.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First London Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>The First London Citizen warns Lord Scales that Cade has passed the Bridge into London itself, and transmits the Mayor&#8217;s plea for aid.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">London Citizens</persname>
<persdescription>London Citizens [mute roles] are retreating from Cade&#8217;s rebels after the latter takes the Bridge. At Lord Scales&#8217; order they go to Smithfield to gather an army to counterattack.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Rebel Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>A Rebel Soldier rushes to bring Cade the news that a royal army has gathered against the rebels. Unfortunately, he has not heard the new order not to call Cade by his real name, and he is killed before delivering his message.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Rebel Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Rebel Messenger brings Cade the news that the rebels have captured Lord Say. He is quite overjoyed at the thought, as he blames Say for heavy taxes. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fourth Royal Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Royal Messenger comes to tell the King that York has returned from Ireland and brought his army with him, and that he is calling for Somerset&#8217;s disgrace.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Iden&#8217;s Men</persname>
<persdescription>Iden&#8217;s Men [mute roles] are five of Alexander Iden&#8217;s servants.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">One Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>One Citizen is convinced of Simpcox&#8217;s cure and rushes to tell anyone who will listen about it, up to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Citizens of Saint Albans</persname>
<persdescription>The Citizens of Saint Albans are apparently not very intelligent, or perhaps have a need to believe in the efficacy of their town&#8217;s shrine, the main tourist attraction. They prefer to believe Simpcox&#8217;s sudden ability to run a miracle by Saint Alban rather than the result of a whipping.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sawyer</persname>
<persdescription>A Sawyer [mute role] is one of Cade&#8217;s rebels. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Best&#8217;s Son</persname>
<persdescription>Best&#8217;s Son, the Tanner [mute role] is one of Cade&#8217;s rebels. In the end, he is easily swayed and convinced to abandon Cade.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Falconers</persname>
<persdescription>Falconers [mute roles] are a part of the King&#8217;s hunting party, calling back the hawks that have flown off.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">York's Guards</persname>
<persdescription>York&#8217;s Guards [mute roles] accompany York and Buckingham when they burst in on the Duchess of Gloucester at the conjuration (scene 1.4); they escort the conjuring party and the Duchess away.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gloucester's Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s Servingman [mute role] is ordered by the Duke of York to invite Salisbury and Warwick to dinner after York arrests the Duchess.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">York's Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>York&#8217;s Attendant [mute role] is sent by his master to summon the Duke&#8217;s sons and their armies to York&#8217;s side to intimidate King Henry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Rebel Poleman</persname>
<persdescription>Rebel Poleman returns from the execution of Say and Cromer with their heads on the end of poles, and has a great time making them kiss.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Commoner</persname>
<persdescription>First Commoner is the spokesperson of the mob of ordinary citizens who gather to protest Gloucester&#8217;s death and demand Suffolk&#8217;s execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Commoners</persname>
<persdescription>Commoners are ordinary citizens who, hearing of Gloucester&#8217;s death and convinced that he has been murdered by Suffolk, form a mob to demand Suffolk&#8217;s head.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gloucester's First Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s First Attendant follows his Lord to witness Dame Eleanor&#8217;s penance, dressed in mourning. He gives Gloucester the time.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gloucester's Second Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s Second Attendant follows his Lord to witness Dame Eleanor&#8217;s penance, dressed in mourning. He offers to carry her off from the Sheriff, but his offer is refused.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>