<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry VI, Part 3">

<persona>
<persname short="">King Henry the Sixth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry VI, head of the Lancastrian party, is Margaret&#8217;s husband, Prince Edward&#8217;s father, and the desperately peace-loving monarch of a war-torn country. Desperate to keep his throne, he agrees to adopt the Duke of York as his heir instead of his own son, and from that point is no longer an active member of the fight, being pushed out of the role of leader by his wife and simply used as a pawn by all sides. Considered a weakling by the warlike members of his court, Henry is a pious and book-loving man completely out of his depth in a role that does not suit him, who feels the wounds that civil war causes his country deeply but can do nothing to cure them. He is aware of the weakness of his claim to the throne, but still feels that as an anointed monarch he cannot give up his claim. He dreams of the simple life of the shepherd but is not comfortable as a penniless refugee in Scotland. He is frightened of his wife, who bullies him. Not quite as dense as people believe him to be, he can see all too clearly how things will go as well as how things are, and this knowledge grows into prophecy as he looks at the young Earl of Richmond. He retreats more and more from worldly matters, to the extent that when he is freed from the Tower and restored to the throne his first act is to appoint Warwick and Clarence to run the kingdom for him while he retires to a life of meditation and praying &#8212; something not unlike what he led in prison all the same. He knows very well that Richard has come to kill him, and manages to discomfort him with his certainty and his fearless prophecies of disaster to be laid at Richard&#8217;s feet. A deeply kind man, Henry is, depending on one&#8217;s viewpoint, either a wimp or a visionary pacifist. His ghost returns in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Edward, Prince of Wales</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Edward, of the Lancastrian party, is the son of Henry VI and his Queen, Margaret. He is very much his mother&#8217;s son, haughty, stubborn, and quick to insult. He pays little attention to his father, regarding him as a weakling, and rejecting his injunctions to restraint. Eager to fight for his rights, he is recklessly unwilling to bow to superior force, and even when captured by his enemies refuses to speak the slightest word that might imply a surrender, making his death at Yorkist hands even more certain than it ever was. He is slaughtered in front of his mother&#8217;s eyes. His ghost returns in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lewis the Eleventh, King of France</persname>
<persdescription>Lewis the Eleventh is the King of France, the son of the Dauphin of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF>. Not wishing for war to resume between England and France, he chooses to ally himself with Edward when assured by Warwick that the latter has the support of the people, though Lewis insists that he fully intends to be a friend to Margaret in her exile. He changes his mind on discovering that Edward has married, thereby dishonoring the Lady Bona whom he was meant to be wooing and Lewis himself. In his rage Lewis agrees to fund and arm Margaret and Prince Edward so that they can reclaim the throne for Henry. Though pragmatic and business-like, Lewis stands upon his honor and cannot stomach an insult.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Exeter</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Exeter, first of the Lancastrian and then of the Yorkist party, is at first a strong supporter of King Henry, but has to admit that the Duke of York&#8217;s claim to the throne is unanswerable. He remains one of Henry&#8217;s soldiers after York breaks his oath, and guards his King when Edward returns to take back the crown. He is more concerned by Edward&#8217;s persuasive powers than by his military worth. He is captured with King Henry and not heard of again. Exeter is intimidated by Queen Margaret.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Oxford</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Oxford, of the Lancastrian party, is a supporter of King Henry who follows Queen Margaret to France. Though at first he argues for Henry&#8217;s right to the throne, when challenged, it is soon revealed that the true reason for his allegiance has less to do with right and wrong than with desire for revenge on the Yorkists for the deaths of his father and brother. He follows Warwick when the latter rebels, and is one of the party that sneaks up and captures King Edward. He agrees with Somerset that Richmond should be safeguarded. Militarily-minded, he is always on the lookout for ways to increase the number of soldiers on his side, whether by raising new ones or joining with other armies. Captured by the Yorkists, he is sent away to prison. He returns in <persnameREF>Richard III.</NAMEREF></persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Northumberland, of the Lancastrian party, is a powerful Northern supporter of King Henry. Though he despises the Duke of York, he ends up moved by his suffering. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Somerset</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Somerset, first of the Yorkist and then of the Lancastrian party, is the son of the Somerset of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Two</NAMEREF>, whose head is carried in by Richard in the first scene. Though he appears won over to the Yorkist cause, he follows Clarence when the latter defects to Warwick. Guessing that there is more fighting to come, he convinces Oxford that they should send young Richmond abroad to keep him from harm&#8217;s way. Somewhat downcast by Warwick&#8217;s death and the Queen&#8217;s late arrival to battle, he is revived by Prince Edward&#8217;s valiant speech. Captured in battle, he has his head lopped off.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Westmorland</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Westmorland begins as a strong supporter of King Henry, but he is disgusted at what he sees as the latter&#8217;s defeatism and weakness and abandons him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Richard Plantagenet, Duke of York</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Plantagenet, Duke of York, head of the Yorkist party, is the same character as in <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part One</NAMEREF> and <persnameREF>Part Two</NAMEREF>. Victorious in battle, he is able to impose his will on King Henry, though rather than simply take the crown he agrees to let Henry reign for the rest of his life, on the understanding that York&#8217;s family will succeed &#8212; and for that matter be the true rulers of England during the rest of Henry&#8217;s life. He is however easily convinced by his sons to break the oath he has sworn and attempt to dethrone Henry again. Over-confident in military victory, he is beaten and captured by Queen Margaret. He is at first silent under her torments, denying her the satisfaction of seeing him broken, but he cannot endure this forever, and in the ends spits out his rage, hatred and grief at Margaret and Clifford, bringing Northumberland to the verge of tears. Proud and deeply ambitious, he also loves his family deeply, particularly his youngest son Rutland, whose death breaks his spirit. He is particularly close to his son Richard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Clifford</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Clifford, of the Lancastrian party, is the Young Clifford of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Two</NAMEREF>. He is an angry and vindictive man, bent only on revenging his father&#8217;s death at Yorkist hands, and determined to slaughter the entire family of York. Brutal and unsentimental, he enjoys toying with his victims before killing them, and wholeheartedly joins in with Queen Margaret&#8217;s torment of York before finally stabbing him. He is disgusted at Henry&#8217;s weakness, but still attempts to shore him up and to convince him to act decisively and violently. His allegiance shifts more and more to Margaret and Prince Edward, who shows signs of being the sort of King Clifford wants. Shot through the neck with an arrow, he still manages to rant against the absent Henry before fainting. Found and tormented by the three York boys, it is uncertain at what point he actually dies.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Edward, Earl of March</persname>
<persdescription>Edward, Earl of March, of the Yorkist party, is later Duke of York and King Edward IV; he is the same as the Edward of <persnameREF>Henry VI, Part Two</NAMEREF>. A loyal son, he has occasional attacks of conscience about the things he does, though these are mainly afterthoughts. He is not as intelligent as his brother Richard, nor quite as ambitious as either his brothers or his father, and is an unrepentant, uncontrolled womanizer, who would much rather go wenching than rule and does not necessarily accept the word &#8216;No.&#8217; Among his conquests is Warwick&#8217;s niece, something Warwick is willing to overlook at first. Edward does share his family&#8217;s morbid sense of humor, gleefully mocking Clifford (or his body). He is greatly dependent on Warwick for both advice and power, and is generally happy to let the older man lead. Rather feckless when he first becomes King, he never takes any of his brothers&#8217; complaints seriously; thinking George merely petulant, Edward does not realize that he is alienating him, nor that Richard is hoping to take the crown himself. He trades his help for sexual favors, and though he tries to be subtle about his meaning, he is rather crude in his advances to Lady Gray. His decision to marry her brings both his brother and Warwick to rebellion. He attempts to imitate Henry IV (see <persnameREF>Richard II</NAMEREF>) when he returns to England claiming that he only wants his dukedom back, but is soon bullied into going after the crown again. He may feel guilt-stricken about this, refusing to let King Henry speak when they capture him. He is respected more as a persuasive speaker and well-loved man than as a fighter in his own right. Despite his somewhat repressed conscience, he stabs Prince Edward in front of his mother&#8217;s eyes. He does not, however, give orders for King Henry&#8217;s death. He is delighted when his wife gives him a son. How his reign turns out can be discovered in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Edmund, Earl of Rutland</persname>
<persdescription>Edmund, Earl of Rutland, of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s youngest son, a boy still being tutored and too young to fight. Captured by Clifford, he is slaughtered by the latter despite his pleading for his innocence. He is terrified of the man, and terrified of dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Warwick, first of the Yorkist and then of the Lancastrian party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s great supporter and friend, and later the chief power behind the throne to King Edward, then the instrument of his dethroning. He is somewhat full of himself and his ability to gift the crown to whomsoever he pleases, but this arrogance is based on the fact that this ability is genuine. He is a fighter and strongly believes that the might of arms is proof of justice. He is appointed guardian of King Henry after the Yorkists take power at the beginning of the play, but when Queen Margaret raises an army he is defeated by her in battle and can only rush to join the York sons and advise them. He becomes the mastermind behind Edward&#8217;s rise to the throne, both militarily and politically. He stands on his honor and is a fiery man who hates fleeing from battle and can be deeply vindictive towards those who have wronged him. He joins the York brothers in their mocking of the dying or dead Clifford, and renounces his allegiance to Edward when the latter makes a fool of him and humiliates him in front of the French King. Edward&#8217;s doing so, by marrying behind Warwick&#8217;s back, is the final straw, and Warwick remembers then that he has good cause to hate the Yorkists as well. His turn to the Lancastrian side comes out of personal hatred and desire for revenge rather than for any higher reason or conviction, though he claims that Edward is not worthy of the crown. He is deeply self-confident, at times over-confident, but this serves him well as it allows him to take great risks, such as capturing King Edward in his tent. Generally uncompromising and authoritarian, he is a much more decisive and dominant man than the Kings he serves. He is aware that he is the strongest prop to any cause he serves, and that his own death will lead to the fall of that cause. He has very black hair.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">George</persname>
<persdescription>George (Duke of Clarence), first of the Yorkist party, then of the Lancastrian, then of the Yorkist again, is the Duke of York&#8217;s second son. The weakest of the three grown sons of York, he is not present at the battle until after his father&#8217;s death, though he joins his brothers in time to Towton and is with them to mock the dying Clifford. Edward&#8217;s career as a seducer amuses him, but he is outraged when his brother decides to marry the Lady Gray, and he is not shy about letting his opinion of Edward&#8217;s lack of political judgment known. Envious of his brother&#8217;s position and conscious of his own lack of means, he marries Warwick&#8217;s younger daughter and joins the Earl&#8217;s side when the latter rebels against Edward. He is among those who capture Edward by surprise, and witnesses his de-crowning by Warwick. He is made joint Protector of the realm with Warwick by King Henry when the latter is restored, but when called to actually fight against the returned Edward, he refuses and returns to his brother&#8217;s side. He does not like having his two-facedness pointed out to him, and uses it as his excuse when he stabs Prince Edward. He refuses to kill Queen Margaret, and guesses that his brother Richard has gone to kill King Henry. His further career can be found in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Richard</persname>
<persdescription>Richard (Duke of Gloucester), of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s third son. Particularly close to his father, he is the most intelligent and ruthless of the Duke&#8217;s sons. He is a limping hunchback with a withered left arm, though h is also an excellent and murderous fighter, and just how crippled he is physically and how much of it is in his mind is uncertain. His awareness of his own deformities verges on the pathological, and is not helped by the fact that they are the first thing his enemies use to insult him. He is a great mocker with a morbid sense of humor and little sense of morality &#8212; he convinces his father to break his oath on the basis of a ridiculous technicality. Tougher than his brothers, he insists on knowing how York died and refuses to weep, preferring to plot revenge. He is particularly enraged at Clifford for the latter&#8217;s murder of Richard&#8217;s younger brother Rutland, and is determined to kill him himself, though he is unsuccessful in this. He is amused at his brother Edward&#8217;s philandering, but becomes worried when the King decides to marry. The prospect of becoming yet further down in the line of succession crystallizes his realization that he wishes to be King himself, something of which there were only hints before. He remains loyal to Edward during Warwick&#8217;s rebellion because only with Edward safely on the throne can he himself hope to take it. He arranges for Edward&#8217;s escape from captivity and helps him beat the Lancastrian forces, later joining to kill Prince Edward. He also convinces Clarence to give up his allegiance to Warwick and return to his brothers&#8217; side. He then takes it upon himself to murder King Henry, with whom he has a disquieting conversation. Richard sets himself up as a unique sort of person and argues that it is the fault of the fate that left him deformed that bears the responsibility for his twisted mind. Just how far he is willing to go in his quest for the crown can be discovered in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Norfolk</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Norfolk, of the Yorkist party, is one of the Duke of York&#8217;s supporters. He stays loyal after York breaks his oath and after his death, joining Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Marquess Montague</persname>
<persdescription>Marquess Montague, first of the Yorkist and then of the Lancastrian party, is Warwick&#8217;s brother and a strong Yorkist supporter, who helps convince York to break his oath and go back to war. He disapproves of King Edward&#8217;s marriage with the Lady Gray, thinking it poor foreign policy. Nevertheless, he at first stays loyal to the King when Warwick rebels, but soon joins his brother&#8217;s party. He is killed in the final battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Earl of Pembroke</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Pembroke [mute role], of the Yorkist party, is a supporter of King Edward&#8217;s, who is sent to raise an army when the King hears of Warwick&#8217;s rebellion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Hastings</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Hastings, of the Yorkist party, is a supporter of King Edward&#8217;s who believes that the only defense England needs against France is the English Channel, and that therefore considerations of foreign policy have nothing to do with the King&#8217;s marriage. He has been given a rich bride by the King. He helps Edward to escape from captivity and helps convince him to stop pretending to only be claiming his dukedom. His career as Lord Chamberlain to the Yorkist Kings is chronicled in <persnameREF>Richard III.</NAMEREF></persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Stafford</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Stafford [mute role], of the Yorkist party, is a supporter of King Edward, sent to raise an army to fight the rebellious Warwick.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Mortimer</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Mortimer, of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s uncle. With his brother Sir Hugh, he brings troops to help York against Queen Margaret&#8217;s army, and is killed in the resulting battle while trying to rescue his nephew.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir Hugh Mortimer</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Hugh Mortimer [mute role], of the Yorkist party, is the Duke of York&#8217;s uncle. With his brother Sir John, he brings troops to help York against Queen Margaret&#8217;s army, and is killed in the resulting battle while trying to rescue his nephew.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Henry, Earl of Richmond</persname>
<persdescription>Henry, Earl of Richmond [mute role] is a young boy in whom King Henry sees great promise. He grows up to be the Richmond of <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Rivers</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Earl Rivers, of the Yorkist party, is the Lady Gray&#8217;s brother, raised to the nobility after his sister becomes Queen. When Edward is defeated and captured by Warwick, Rivers attempts to comfort his sister. The rest of the Earl&#8217;s career can be found in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir William Stanley</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Stanley [mute role], of the Yorkist party, is a knight loyal to the Yorkist cause, who helps Richard arrange Edward&#8217;s escape.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Montgomery</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Montgomery, of the Yorkist party, is a loyal Yorkist who, hearing of King Edward&#8217;s return, raises a troop and goes to join him at York. He is disgusted at Edward&#8217;s claims to only want his dukedom back, and threatens to take his men away and tell no-one else to help Edward unless he agrees to claim the crown again. He is an irascible man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Somervile</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Somervile, of the Lancastrian party, is a follower of Warwick&#8217;s, sent to call Clarence for help.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Tutor to Rutland</persname>
<persdescription>A Tutor, of the Yorkist party, is the Earl of Rutland&#8217;s teacher, a deeply loyal man. When Clifford offers to spare his life because of his calling, he refuses and asks to be killed as well if Rutland is to die. Clifford dismisses him and his plea to spare Rutland&#8217;s life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mayor of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Mayor of York is a peace-loving old man who does not wish to disturb matters. He is also rather gullible, and accepts the assurance that Edward is King Henry&#8217;s friend and that he is only claiming his Dukedom rather easily.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mayor of Coventry</persname>
<persdescription>The Mayor of Coventry [mute role] is present as Warwick gathers his forces against Edward, and opens the gates of his city to all of Warwick&#8217;s supporters and their armies.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lieutenant of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Lieutenant of the Tower is charged with caring for King Henry when he is imprisoned, and treats the royal captive well. When Henry is captured a second time, the Lieutenant takes charge of him again, and when commanded to leaves him alone with Richard of Gloucester.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nobleman</persname>
<persdescription>A Nobleman, of the Yorkist party, comes to inform King Edward that King Henry has been captured.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">A Son That Has Killed His Father</persname>
<persdescription>A Son That Has Killed His Father, of the Lancastrian party, was forced into serving in King Henry&#8217;s army. Though he is aware that he may be killed by the end of the day, he still pillages the man he has just killed in the hopes of finding money on him, just in case he survives. Discovering that the dead man is his father, who was in Warwick&#8217;s army, he is broken and horrified, and can&#8217;t imagine how his mother is going to react.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">A Father That Has Killed His Son</persname>
<persdescription>A Father That Has Killed His Son fought hard in the battle of Towton and is intent on getting all the riches off his victim&#8217;s body when he discovers that the dead man is his son. He curses the age that makes such things possible, and refuses to fight any longer.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Queen Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Margaret, of the Lancastrian party, is King Henry&#8217;s wife, the mother of his son Prince Edward, and the strongest defender of his cause. She considers her husband a weakling and is horrified and appalled that he would give up their son&#8217;s rights in return for peace. Her love for her son is her strongest impetus after the humiliation the Yorkists have practiced on herself and Henry, and she is willing to risk everything to make sure that Prince Edward can inherit the throne. To her enemies&#8217; sexist dismay, she reveals herself to be a good general and leader of men, one capable of rousing speeches. She is acknowledged to be the true leader of the Lancastrian cause, as she can bully Henry into doing what she will. She does suffer from some insecurities, however, and when she captures the Duke of York her relief bursts forth in her hysterical, sadistic taunting of the man before killing him. Beaten, she seeks help from the King of France, her kinsman, but due to her weakness at this point it is only Warwick&#8217;s defection and the personal insult to himself that make Lewis agree to help. For the sake of regaining the crown for Henry and her son, she is willing even to make an alliance with the Warwick who has insulted and belittled her and was the main cause of her defeat. They are ultimately unsuccessful, however, and Margaret&#8217;s crowing over the death of York&#8217;s youngest son is paid back to her when she must watch her own son murdered before her eyes, and then is left to live herself. Though it is ordered that she be exiled to France at the end of the play, she returns in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lady Grey</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Gray, of the Yorkist party, is a very attractive widow who has lost her lands when her husband was killed fighting on the Yorkist side. She petitions King Edward to get them back, not expecting that he will offer a trade instead: her body for her lands. She utterly refuses, being willing to lose her lands to avoid prostituting herself, but is shocked to hear him offer marriage instead. She is keenly aware that she is far too low-born to be Queen of England, but is in the end convinced. Her family immediately begins to gain wealth and power, to the disgust of the higher nobility. She attempts to build bridges to the royal brothers, but is not successful. Her marriage does not makes for a particularly happy life, as she is beset with the dislike of the nobility and the fears of civil war, which send her running to sanctuary when Warwick returns and captures Edward. She bears Edward a son by the play&#8217;s end. How this turns out can be discovered in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lady Bona</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Bona is King Lewis&#8217;s sister, and a valuable pawn in the political marriage game. Warwick intends for her to marry King Edward to form a peace treaty between France and England. She is quite willing, but she is insulted and enraged when it turns out that Edward has married already, thereby dishonoring her. She presses her brother to join with Margaret to dethrone Edward in revenge.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Yorkist Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Yorkist Messenger comes to warn the Duke of York that Queen Margaret has raised an army and is leading it against him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Norfolk Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Norfolk Messenger, of the Yorkist party, is sent by his master to ask Warwick for help against Queen Margaret and her army.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Lancastrian Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Lancastrian Messenger brings news to Queen Margaret and her commanders that the Yorkist army is on the march and that the Duke of York is being proclaimed King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Gamekeeper</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gamekeeper is out hunting deer with his fellow when they come across King Henry. He is much more experienced than the Second Gamekeeper, is a storyteller, and recognizes the King first. He forces Henry to see that the people no longer consider him the King, essentially pointing out that the common people are not much touched by the quarrels of the nobility, and carry on their lives without caring who exactly is King, merely obeying the office. He answers the question of whether they have broken an oath when the Second Gamekeeper doesn&#8217;t. He carries a crossbow.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Gamekeeper</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gamekeeper is out hunting deer with his fellow when they come across King Henry. Less experienced than the First Gamekeeper, he has what he thinks is a brilliant idea about using crossfire to catch the deer, only to have it pointed to him that this actually lessens their chances. When they realize that they have a chance to capture the former King, the Second Gamekeeper is the one who first approaches Henry and questions him to make sure they have the right man. He has no answer to Henry&#8217;s question about whether they have broken an oath and lets the Fist Gamekeeper answer. He carries a crossbow.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Post</persname>
<persdescription>A Post brings over the mail from England to the French court, and is sent back to tell King Edward just how it was received, and to bring the combined defiance of the French, Margaret, and Warwick to him. He is scared of losing his head for repeating their messages to Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Watchman, of the Yorkist party, leads the sentries guarding King Edward as he sleeps in his tent. He is fairly confident that they will be able to do their job, but runs away when Warwick and his fellows attack.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Watchman, of the Yorkist party, is one of the sentries guarding King Edward as he sleeps in his tent. He is fully confident that they can guard against all comers and approves of Edward&#8217;s bravado, but runs away when Warwick and his fellows attack.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Watchman, of the Yorkist party, is one of the sentries guarding King Edward as he sleeps in his tent. He is rather more skeptical of the value of honor and bravado than his fellow guards, and would much rather be safely behind walls. He runs away when Warwick and his companions attack.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Huntsman</persname>
<persdescription>A Huntsman, of the Lancastrian party, is charged with guarding King Edward in his captivity, even as they go hunting. Given the choice of following when Edward escapes, he admits that living is preferable to being hanged for letting him go.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Warwick's Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Warwick&#8217;s Messenger brings his master news that King Edward has escaped from custody.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Yorkist Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>A Yorkist Soldier reads out the official proclamation of Edward&#8217;s claim to the throne at the gates of York.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Oxford Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>An Oxford Messenger, of the Lancastrian party, lets the Earl of Warwick know where his master and his forces are.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Montague Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Montague Messenger, of the Lancastrian party, lets the Earl of Warwick know where his master and his forces are.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Lancastrian Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Lancastrian Messenger brings Queen Margaret and her commanders the news that Edward and his army are nearby and prepared for battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Aldermen of York</persname>
<persdescription>Aldermen of York [mute roles] accompany the Mayor as he debates with the returning Edward.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nurse Bess</persname>
<persdescription>Nurse Bess [mute role] carries the infant son of King Edward (also named Edward) when the King has his brothers pledge loyalty to his heir.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord Bourbon</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Bourbon [mute role] is King Lewis&#8217;s admiral, sent by the latter to help Margaret and Warwick invade England.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Prince Edward (Ned)</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Edward (Ned) is a newborn baby, King Edward&#8217;s son, confusingly enough called Edward as well. His fate can be discovered in <persnameREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Yorkist Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Yorkist Messenger witnesses the capture and torment of the Duke of York, and runs to tell the York brothers that their father&#8217;s head is on top of the gates of York and their younger brother has been killed.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>