<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry IV, Part 2">

<persona>
<persname short="KING.">King Henry the Fourth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry IV is the same as the Bullingbrook of Richard II and the King of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. Much older and wearier now, he suffers dreadfully from insomnia and lingering guilt over his usurpation of the throne. Rebellions against him continually keep him from going on crusade to Jerusalem as he hopes to do in expiation of his guilt. He is subject to fits where his vision blurs before he falls unconscious, and slips into coma-like sleeps where it is impossible to tell if he is still alive. If continual treasons against him and physical illness were not enough, his cares are increased by the fact that his eldest son and heir, Prince Harry, is a wastrel who spends most of his time in bars and has even been thrown in jail for being publicly disorderly. The King is too ill to lead his armies against the new rebellion himself, and has to entrust his forces to his second son, John of Lancaster rather than to his heir. Henry has lost all hope for Prince Harry, and is driven to the point of begging his three other sons to restrain their brother once the latter takes the throne. The combination of paternal disappointment and worry for his kingdom drives him to a passionate outburst even on his deathbed. He is reconciled with Harry just prior to his death. Known as a crafty politician, Henry is still enough of one as he lies dying that he can recommend that Harry avoid rebellions against himself by spending all of the nobles&#8217; energies in fighting wars elsewhere. Haunted by a prophecy that he should die in Jerusalem, he fulfills it by insisting on being carried to a chamber of that name within his palace. Henry is as much as he can be a just king, glad to have servants who respect the law, and approving of the Lord Chief Justice for not treating Prince Harry any differently from other troublemakers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRINCE.">Prince Henry</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Harry, sometimes known as Monmouth, is the same as the Prince of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. Despite his apparent reformation in that play, he has since the battle of Shrewsbury gone back to his disreputable ways, playing pranks on Falstaff, mocking Poins, consorting with prostitutes and tavern-keepers. He has even been sent to prison after being publicly disorderly and slapping the Lord Chief Justice in court. He spends much less time with Falstaff, however, beginning to neglect him and preparing for his rejection once he takes the throne. Despite what King Henry and the whole world believes, he loves his father, but he is aware that saying so would have him tagged as a hypocrite because of his past conduct. He is extremely concerned about how he appears to the world, due to his master plan of setting himself up as a wastrel so that his reputation will be enhanced when he gives up that behavior on taking the throne. He is very quick to pick up the crown when he thinks that his father is dead; though he insists he did so to get used to the idea of kingship, his excuses are undercut by the fact that they are spoken in retrospect, and do not fully match what the audience saw on stage. As he is extremely successful at playing roles, the truth behind his feelings remains unknown. As King, he tests the loyalty of the Lord Chief Justice to make certain that fear of his new power will not undercut the old man&#8217;s honesty. His rejection of Falstaff and rounding up of his old companions has exactly the effect that he planned it to. Both as Prince and as King it is difficult to discern what his genuine emotions are; whether casting off his dissipation causes him any pain is up to the performer. Taking his father&#8217;s last words of advice, he plans a war in France to occupy his noblemen&#8217;s minds and energies and thus forestall rebellion. How this turns out can be discovered in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="P. JOHN.">Prince John of Lancaster</persname>
<persdescription>Prince John of Lancaster is King Henry&#8217;s second son, and Prince Harry&#8217;s brother &#8212; the same as in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. A humorless man who drinks no alcohol and puts up poorly with Falstaff, he is a cold politician with a lawyer&#8217;s instinct for precise, hairsplitting words that enable him to trick the rebels into letting their soldiers go, thus avoiding a battle. He is quick to have rebels executed. He knows and respects the Lord Chief Justice, and shares his opinion of Prince Harry until the latter reassures them of his reformation. He has his ear to the ground and has a fair idea of what the new King&#8217;s next actions will be.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GLOU.">Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester is one of King Henry&#8217;s sons, and Prince Harry&#8217;s brother. As his father grows weaker, he grows worried about the public restlessness at the odd portents suggesting that the King is dying. He is as uncertain of Prince Harry&#8217;s worth as the others. He returns in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLAR.">Thomas, Duke of Clarence</persname>
<persdescription>Thomas, Duke of Clarence is one of King Henry&#8217;s sons, and Prince Harry&#8217;s brother. Of the King&#8217;s four sons, he is the closest to Harry, something that the King hopes will allow him to be a good influence once Harry takes the throne. He is worried about his father&#8217;s health. He returns in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NORTH.">Henry Percy, Earl of Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Northumberland is the same as the Northumberland of <persnameref>Richard II </persnameref>and <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. Having once helped Henry IV to usurp the throne, he is now theoretically rebelling against him. However, at the beginning of the play he is still pretending to be sick, which was his excuse for not joining his son Hotspur at the battle of Shrewsbury, leaving the latter under-strength; and he will later choose not to reinforce the Archbishop of York and the other rebels, with much the same results. The death of his son breaks his heart and leads him to rage against the King and help organize the second rebellion, but he is convinced by his wife and daughter-in-law to wait and see who will overcome rather than join in from the start. Waiting in Scotland, he raises an army with Lord Bardolph, but is beaten in battle by the Sheriff of Yorkshire. He is an old man, highly respected and powerful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ARCH.">Richard Scroop, Archbishop of York</persname>
<persdescription>Scroop, Archbishop of York is the same as the character of the same name in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. Longing for revenge for the death of his brother Stephen (see <persnameref>Richard II</persnameref>), he grows convinces that the ills afflicting the country can be laid squarely at Henry IV&#8217;s door for his usurpation of the throne. He lends dignity to the rebellion by bringing the weight of his position behind it, and uses revenge for Richard II&#8217;s overthrow and murder as the official excuse for the uprising. He despises the common people, partly for their changeable opinions, and blames them for the state of affairs as it was Bullingbrook&#8217;s popularity with them that allowed him to easily take the throne. He is not as bright as he thinks he is, nor as good a judge of character; his certainty about what the King will do does not take into consideration the character of Prince John, whom he trusts far too readily, with the unfortunate result that he gets his head chopped off. He is an older man, whose beard is turning white.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MOWB.">Lord Mowbray</persname>
<persdescription>Thomas, Lord Mowbray is the Earl Marshal of England, who joins the rebellion against the King. He is the son of the Mowbray of <persnameref>Richard II</persnameref>, who was supposed to fight a duel to the death with Bullingbrook, now King Henry IV. Not particularly intelligent, he is the most hot-headed of the rebels, partly for his father&#8217;s sake, though his understanding of that situation is less than perfect. He disapproves of the peace that the Archbishop negotiates with Prince John, as he would rather have fought it out; as it turns out, he is quite right to wish so, since the peace simply has him arrested and beheaded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HAST.">Lord Hastings</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Hastings is one of the rebels against King Henry IV. More optimistic than either the Archbishop or Lord Bardolph, he discounts the necessity of Northumberland&#8217;s support in making plans, trusting in the fact that the king&#8217;s own forces are divided into three armies in different parts of the country. Certain that the King is weak, he is foolish enough to think that a few threats will suffice, and he agrees to disperse the rebel army once Prince John has sworn to rectify the wrongs the rebels complain of. This overconfidence gets his head chopped off.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="L. BARD.">Lord Bardolph</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Bardolph is one of the rebels against King Henry IV, who having heard that all was going well for their party rushes to the Earl of Northumberland&#8217;s to tell him that they&#8217;ve won. Not the best of news-gatherers, he forgets to double-check his sources, and is reluctant to admit that he was wrong. He proposes continuing the rebellion despite the scale of the defeat at Shrewsbury. He is much more cautious in planning the second campaign, insisting that it be properly thought out before it is begun. He is well-known enough to the Earl of Northumberland that the latter&#8217;s staff allow him access to the Earl&#8217;s house. He joins the latter in Scotland, where they raise an army but are defeated by the Sheriff of Yorkshire. Lord Bardolph is not to be confused with Falstaff&#8217;s companion of the same name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRA.">Travers</persname>
<persdescription>Travers is one of Northumberland&#8217;s servants, whom he sent to find out news of the battle of Shrewsbury. Returning, he can bring no certain news, only report that Lord Bardolph suggested things were going well but that he passed another gentleman who claimed just the opposite. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="COL.">Sir John Colevile</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Coleville is one of the rebels against King Henry IV. He surrenders to Falstaff after the rebels are tricked into defeat. He insists that in the place of his leaders he would have fought Prince John instead, and also that he only rebelled because of his superiors. This excuse does not do him any good, and he is carted off to be executed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WAR.">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>Warwick is one of King Henry&#8217;s noblemen, a loyal, reasonable and optimistic man. He seeks at all times to reassure his master and to help his comfort, whether it be in lowering the estimates of the rebels&#8217; strength or hushing the princes to keep the King from hearing their discussion of his coming death. He is the only member of the court to suspect that Prince Harry&#8217;s dissipation might be a deception. Despite his reassurances to the King on the matter, however, he is concerned that Harry will prove the disappointment all the other courtiers fear. He returns in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WEST.">Earl of Westmorland</persname>
<persdescription>Westmorland is one of Henry IV&#8217;s lords, the same character as in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. Prince John sends him as an emissary to the rebels, with whom he argues at length over the justice of their cause. Mowbray&#8217;s misunderstanding of history leads him to scorn the young man. As the Prince&#8217;s second-in-command, he is an essential part of the plot to arrest the rebel leaders, convincing them that all is well, drinking with them, and offering a reasonable excuse for why the royal army has not dispersed. He has no philosophical difficulties with acting dishonorably towards traitors.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SURR.">Earl of Surrey</persname>
<persdescription>Surrey [mute role] is a nobleman highly trusted by Henry IV, one of the first he speaks to when he receives news of the new rebellion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BLUNT.">Sir John Blunt</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Blunt [mute role] is one of King Henry IV&#8217;s noblemen, among the first he calls when he hears of the new rebellion. He is sent with Prince John to deal with the Archbishop&#8217;s army, and is charged with taking Coleville and his men to be executed. He accompanies Prince John back to the palace.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GOW.">Gower</persname>
<persdescription>Gower brings news to the Lord Chief Justice that the King and Prince Harry have returned from the wars in Wales and that part of the army has gone to reinforce Prince John&#8217;s forces against the rebels. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HAR.">Harcourt</persname>
<persdescription>Harcourt is a messenger who comes from Scotland to announce to the King that Northumberland and Lord Bardolph have been defeated.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CH. JUST.">Lord Chief Justice</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Chief Justice is the highest judge of the land, equivalent to the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. An old man with a strong sense of his responsibilities, he once imprisoned Prince Harry for public disorderliness after the latter hit him across the face in court. Upright and honest, he loathes Falstaff and all he stands for, and especially his influence on the heir to the throne. He worries about what will occur when the latter takes the throne, and fears that all the good done in Henry IV&#8217;s reign will be undone by Henry V. Refusing to flatter, he resists the temptation to speak well of Falstaff to the new King, and does not apologize for having sent him to prison. He is rewarded by keeping his place and being promised that he will be the new King&#8217;s chief advisor, and is later given charge of ensuring that Falstaff obey his banishment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POINS.">Poins</persname>
<persdescription>Poins is Prince Harry&#8217;s companion and accomplice, leading him on in his dissipated life. He is little more respectable than Falstaff and his crew, with whom he has an ongoing rivalry. Not overly rich, as he is a younger son, he has a rather small wardrobe. He is not afraid of speaking his true opinions before the Prince.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FAL.">Sir John Falstaff</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Falstaff is an excessively fat, excessively drunken, excessively cowardly, excessively witty, and excessively incorrigible rogue. Utterly shameless, he can talk his way out of almost any situation and rationalize any action, though he does not pull the wool over most courtiers&#8217; eyes. Commoners are much more easily impressed by him. He is convinced that he still has Prince Harry&#8217;s love and that when the latter comes to the throne he will be the most influential man in the kingdom. Being rather poor, Falstaff tends to borrow inordinate amounts of money from people; he charms Hostess Quickly so much that even after she attempts to have him arrested for debt he can milk yet more money from her. He has often proposed marriage to her, keeping her in hope even as she arranges for him to enjoy Doll Tearsheet&#8217;s favors. He is very fond of Doll, the only person in whose presence he admits to feeling his age. He is not only fat and white-bearded: too much eating has given him gout, and too much time with whores has struck him with venereal disease, and he can no longer even tell which pains are caused by which disease. He has something of a feud with the Lord Chief Justice, who despises him and his influence on the Prince. He is easily bribed into letting draftees avoid the army, and can justify doing so. Calling on his old acquaintance Justice Shallow while mustering soldiers, he is able to cajole him into lending him a thousand pounds, for the sake of which he puts up with the old man&#8217;s nattering. Hearing of Prince Harry&#8217;s accession to the throne, he is so excited that he gallops full-tilt to London, willing to steal horses to do so, where he interrupts the new King&#8217;s coronation procession in the most shocking fashion. Rejected by the King, he attempts to convince his companions and himself that this is merely Harry putting on a show for the sake of respectability, but on being arrested by the Lord Chief Justice his argument falters. What happens to him afterwards is told in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BARD.">Bardolph</persname>
<persdescription>Bardolph is one of Falstaff&#8217;s followers, a man with a huge red nose and red marks all over his face. He is Falstaff&#8217;s assistant, collecting money from the drafted men who wish to bribe their way out of the army, fighting Pistol, delivering messages, and so forth. A rogue, he is arrested along with Falstaff at the end of the play. Not to be confused with the rebel Lord Bardolph, his further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PIST.">Pistol</persname>
<persdescription>Ancient Pistol is an officer in the army, an ensign-bearer. He is a swaggering braggart, trying to intimidate everyone he meets, speaking in overblown terms and stuffing his speech with foreign phrases and curses. It is said that he and Doll Tearsheet beat a man who later dies of his injuries. Pistol rushes to find Falstaff when Henry IV dies, hoping to rise in favor with the new King as Falstaff does. Unfortunately for him, this merely leads to his arrest. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RUM.">Rumor, the Presenter</persname>
<persdescription>&lt;span class=&quot;shakestext&quot;&gt;Rumor, the Presenter speaks the Prologue of the play, reminding us of what occurred in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref> and setting the scene for the confusion of the first scene. &lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;shakestext&quot;&gt;Dressed in a costume covered in wagging tongues, Rumor is quite proud of itself and its effect on the world, and delighted at the opportunity to spread false news about the result of the battle of Shrewsbury. &lt;/span&gt;</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERV.">Servant to the Lord Chief Justice</persname>
<persdescription>Servant to the Lord Chief Justice does not appreciate Falstaff&#8217;s wit, and is incensed at the suggestion that he is not an honest man. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. DRAW.">Second Drawer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Drawer is a barman at Hostess Quickly&#8217;s tavern. He sets the table for Falstaff&#8217;s dessert alone with Doll Tearsheet, and goes to find the musicians to accompany it. He remembers a number of the Prince&#8217;s jokes on Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PORT.">Porter</persname>
<persdescription>The Porter guards the Earl of Northumberland&#8217;s gate. He knows Lord Bardolph well enough to let him go through to the orchard without further ado when the latter arrives.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EPILOGUE.">Epilogue</persname>
<persdescription>Epilogue comes forward at the end to plead for mercy from the audience. He also offers to dance a jig for them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOLL.">Doll Tearsheet</persname>
<persdescription>Doll Tearsheet is a whore who is a particular favorite of Falstaff&#8217;s. She is drunken and has a remarkably foul mouth. She is fond of Falstaff, or at least makes a good show of it; she is also fond of raging at him. She is arrested and sentenced to be whipped for whoring at the end of the play, though she puts up a good fight (at least in words) against the beadles come to take her. She displeases Hostess Quickly by ending up pregnant, and is accused of having helped Pistol beat a man who later died of his injuries. She is quite good-looking, as common harlots go.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HOST.">Hostess Quickly</persname>
<persdescription>Hostess Quickly (often known as &#8216;Mistress Quickly&#8217;) is the owner of the Boar&#8217;s Head tavern in Eastcheap, and a bit of a madam on the side. She is the same as the Hostess of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. She does not have the best command of the English language, and often messes up her words. She is entirely under Falstaff&#8217;s spell, and has known him for 29 years: though he is indebted to her for a massive amount and continually puts of repaying her by promising to marry her instead, the moment he begins to speak to her he is able to convince her to lend him more, even though it may require her to pawn her richest possessions. She is also quick to offer Doll Tearsheet&#8217;s services to the fat knight. Despite her trade, the Hostess wishes to be seen as a respectable woman, and dislikes rowdy customers like Pistol. She is rather dithering, and sent all of a flutter whenever the Prince of Wales shows up in her inn. She is well-able to insult when need be, and is not pleased when Doll ends up pregnant, as it will hurt trade. She is arrested at the end of the play; her further adventures can be found in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY P.">Lady Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Percy is the widow of Hotspur, the daughter-in-law of the Earl of Northumberland and his Lady. She grieves deeply for her husband, and convinces her father-in-law not to join immediately with the new rebellion but to wait and see how things turn out, not wishing to lose him as well as her husband. She has the courage to use his own desertion from the first rebellion against him. She is the same as the Lady Percy of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY N.">Lady Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Northumberland is the Earl of Northumberland&#8217;s wife. Grieving for the death of her son Hotspur, she helps her daughter-in-law persuade her husband to not join the rebellion, recommending Scotland as a good vantage-point from which to observe events.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRAN.">Francis</persname>
<persdescription>Francis is one of the drawers (barmen) at Hostess Quickly&#8217;s tavern; he is the same character as the Francis in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>. He knows Falstaff&#8217;s tastes well, and has no problems with helping Prince Harry to play a trick on the fat knight.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BULL.">Bullcalf</persname>
<persdescription>Bullcalf is a countryman drafted to the King&#8217;s army. He is a muscular fellow who does not want to go to war. When faking a cough doesn&#8217;t succeed in getting him out of it, he resorts to bribery instead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FEE.">Feeble</persname>
<persdescription>Feeble is a countryman drafted to the King&#8217;s army. A tailor for women, he is an honest man and a loyal subject, willing enough to go to battle, even when he sees that it is possible to bribe his way out of it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WART.">Wart</persname>
<persdescription>Wart is a countryman drafted to the King&#8217;s army. He is extremely poor, and clearly starving. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MOUL.">Mouldy</persname>
<persdescription>Mouldy is a countryman drafted to the King&#8217;s army. He is not the brightest of fellows, but while he cannot catch one of Falstaff&#8217;s jokes, he is intelligent enough to know that bribery can get him out of going to war. He takes care of his mother.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SNARE.">Snare</persname>
<persdescription>Snare is one of two sergeants (with Fang) hired by Hostess Quickly to arrest Falstaff for debt. They are not exactly successful in this endeavor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DAVY.">Davy</persname>
<persdescription>Davy is Justice Shallow&#8217;s servant. He is on familiar terms with his master, able to shift the subject of conversation and to make some attempts at wit to him. He dreams of seeing London some day. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIL.">Silence</persname>
<persdescription>Silence is a Justice of the Peace, whose daughter has Shallow as a godfather. As befits his name, he does not speak much, but he enjoys singing, especially once he has had a few drinks. Married to Shallow&#8217;s cousin, he pays for her brother&#8217;s stay at the university. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHAL.">Shallow</persname>
<persdescription>Shallow is a Justice of the Peace, an old, thin, decaying man verging on senility, at least 70 years old. He is close to Justice Silence, to whose daughter he is godfather. A great babbler, he is rarely quiet, and is forever remembering his days in university &#8212; or at least telling tales about his days in university. He has known Falstaff since that time, when he was a starving student. Now rich, he looks forward to the possibility of using Falstaff as a connection to court. He is nevertheless deeply involved in his country living, looking into the smallest details of the local life. He thinks himself much more wicked than he is, not realizing that in terms of drinking he is entirely out of his depth with Falstaff and his cronies. He is an honest and loyal servant of the King, not catching on to why Falstaff allows the two best men he drafts to go free. He lends Falstaff the enormous sum of a thousand pounds on expectation of getting it back when Prince Harry becomes King, so certain is Falstaff of the Prince&#8217;s favor. He follows the fat knight to Harry&#8217;s coronation, swept away by promises of lordship and who knows what else, and ends up arrested and sent to the Fleet prison.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAGE.">Falstaff's Page</persname>
<persdescription>Falstaff&#8217;s Page was given to him as a servant by Prince Harry. A good disciple to his master, he learns wit and insults from him, and serves him well. His further career can be found in <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PETO.">Peto</persname>
<persdescription>Peto is one of Falstaff&#8217;s gang. He brings Prince Harry the news that some grave matter of state is afoot, and that soldiers are looking for Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MOR.">Morton</persname>
<persdescription>Morton was present at the battle of Shrewsbury, and hurries to Northumberland&#8217;s to tell him of the defeat and of Hotspur&#8217;s death. He is reluctant to admit him, but soon overcomes his fears and blames Northumberland to his face for the defeat. He persuades Northumberland to stick to the rebellion, and to help the Archbishop of York in his new uprising. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FANG.">Fang</persname>
<persdescription>Fang is one of two sergeants (along with Snare) hired by Hostess Quickly to arrest Falstaff for debt. They are not exactly successful in this endeavor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SNEAK.">Sneak</persname>
<persdescription>Sneak is the leader of a group of musicians who play at Hostess Quickly&#8217;s tavern, available for hire for private parties.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHAD.">Shadow</persname>
<persdescription>Shadow is a countryman drafted to the King&#8217;s army. He is a very slender man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. DRAW.">Third Drawer</persname>
<persdescription>Will, the Third Drawer, is the third barman at Hostess Quickly&#8217;s tavern. He learns of the Prince and Poins&#8217;s plan to trick Falstaff and warns the other drawers not to let Falstaff know.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger comes to warn the rebel leaders of the approach of the royal army, and to offer a guess as to its size.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BEAD.">Beadle</persname>
<persdescription>The Beadle is charged by the constables of the watch with having Doll Tearsheet publicly whipped for whoring. He has rather a hard time of arresting her and Hostess Quickly, as neither of them comes quietly. However, he has no qualms about having them bodily dragged away. He is a thin man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. STREWER.">First Strewer</persname>
<persdescription>The First Strewer is one of the royal servants in charge of making sure the street for the new King&#8217;s procession is covered with rushes so that the nobility need not walk in the muck. He does not think they have put enough down.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. STREWER.">Second Strewer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Strewer is one of the royal servants in charge of making sure the street for the new King&#8217;s procession is covered with rushes so that the nobility need not walk in the muck. Having heard the trumpets sound, he is worried that they are running out of time.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. STREWER.">Third Strewer</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Strewer is one of the royal servants in charge of making sure the street for the new King&#8217;s procession is covered with rushes so that the nobility need not walk in the muck. Though he hastens the job on, he thinks they have enough time to get the job done before the procession comes by.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OFFICER.">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer is a captain in the rebel army. He is sent to discharge the soldiers and give them their pay when the loyal forces and the rebels come to an agreement.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>