<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry IV, Part 1">

<persona>
<persname short="1. CAR.">First Carrier</persname>
<persdescription>The First Carrier (Mugs) is transporting goods on the road between Canterbury and London, and resting at the inn near Gads Hill. He is among the group robbed by Falstaff and his gang. He is not impressed by the quality of the inn. He is cautious and knows very well what sort of tricks thieves get up to in such places. He recognizes Falstaff and denounces him to the Sheriff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OST.">Ostler</persname>
<persdescription>Ostler takes care of travelers&#8217; horses at the inn.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHER.">Sheriff</persname>
<persdescription>The Sheriff is told of the robbery and goes searching for Falstaff. He does not expect to find the Prince of Wales at the Boar&#8217;s Head tavern instead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY. MORT.">Lady Mortimer</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Mortimer is Glendower&#8217;s daughter, a pretty Welsh lady who enjoys singing and does not speak a single word of English. She loves her husband Mortimer dearly.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY. P.">Lady Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Percy is Hotspur&#8217;s wife, and Mortimer&#8217;s sister. Greatly in love with her dashing husband, she has a relationship of mutual scolding and insults with him which can lead one to wonder what exactly they feel for each other, or whether they are still in middle school, but which seems like genuine affection. She insists on knowing everything Hotspur is up to, though this is not the most successful insisting. Her further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BARD.">Bardolph</persname>
<persdescription>Bardolph is one of Falstaff&#8217;s cronies, who assists at the robbery of Gadshill. He has been following Falstaff for seven years now, and claims that Falstaff&#8217;s plans for making themselves look as though they had been beaten up is the first time he&#8217;s thought the fat knight was going too far. He is not an overly brave man, but follows Falstaff to the wars all the same. He is most noticeable for his huge and red nose, and for the various red marks on his face that almost disfigure him. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PETO.">Peto</persname>
<persdescription>Peto is one of Falstaff&#8217;s cronies, who assists at the robbery of Gadshill. He is quite willing to admit to Falstaff&#8217;s lies when the latter is not in hearing, but never disagrees with the fat knight to his face. He rides with Prince Harry to muster soldiers. His further adventures can be found in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GADS.">Gadshill</persname>
<persdescription>Gadshill is a highway robber who often teams up with Falstaff and his crew. He has an arrangement with the Chamberlain at the inn near Gads Hill, by which the Chamberlain tells Gadshill who the best guests to rob are, in return for a cut of the takings. He is fairly certain of escaping retribution, if only because of Falstaff&#8217;s friendship with the Prince.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POINS.,THIEVES.">Edward Poins</persname>
<persdescription>Ned Poins is one of Prince Harry&#8217;s tavern companions, with a taste for practical jokes &#8212; particularly those played on Falstaff. He serves as link between Gadshill and Falstaff, and is a great favorite of the latter&#8217;s, who has known him for 22 years. He is close to Prince Harry, and assists him in mocking the fat knight. His further adventures can be found in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIR M.">Sir Michael</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Michael is a member of the Archbishop of York&#8217;s household, who is sent to carry the Archbishop&#8217;s messages to his fellow rebels. He does not see why his master is quite so worried about the outcome of the battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FAL.">Sir John Falstaff</persname>
<persdescription>Falstaff is an extremely fat, lying, thieving, cowardly, drunken, and utterly shameless rogue with a talent for telling tales and rationalizing his actions. He is very fond of Prince Harry, who seeks out his company, and who can match him in battles of wit, along with being one of the only people to ever poke through his lies. Harry&#8217;s protection allows Falstaff to get away with a great deal, and he hopes that when the lad becomes King this will continue. His tales get bigger and bigger the more he tells them, but when challenged he generally finds a way to climb out of the hole he has dug himself into. He is addicted to sack, of which he consumes a monstrous amount. He never pays his bills. Some of his rationalizations on the matter of bravery will appear to be merely common sense: he presents a contrasting view of the world to the one that rules Hotspur, Douglas, Blunt and the rest of the warriors in this play. A realist who is always on the lookout for ways to make money, he attempts to draft rich people into the King&#8217;s army, being perfectly aware that they will buy their way out of this, and then recruits the poorest and most useless people as soldiers, being perfectly aware that their only purpose in the battle is to be killed. He does not look forward to fighting, leads his soldiers to the death, and makes sure he has a bottle of booze on him in the middle of the battle. He plays dead to avoid being killed by Douglas, but then revives and attempts to boast that he killed Hotspur, whom he claims wasn&#8217;t quite dead yet. He uses self-mockery as one of his endearing qualities, and to a certain extent plays the role of Harry&#8217;s court jester. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VER.">Sir Richard Vernon</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Vernon comes to warn Hotspur of the King&#8217;s forces and of Glendower&#8217;s inability to join up with the other rebels in time. He is greatly impressed by Prince Harry, and attempts to get across to Hotspur that the Prince may be a genuine adversary, despite his wild reputation. He is far more cautious than either Hotspur or Douglas, but has little influence on them. He generally ends up giving in to what his superiors decide, even when it goes against his own better judgment. Captured in the battle, he is sent off to be executed by the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GLEND.">Owen Glendower</persname>
<persdescription>Owen Glendower is a Welsh war leader who has rejected Henry IV&#8217;s lordship over Wales, and fought off his armies three times already. Reputed to be a wizard, he insists that he is one and that his birth was accompanied by startling portents of his greatness. He restrains his temper at Hotspur&#8217;s skepticism and rudeness. His one magical demonstration is having music suddenly play from no visible source, but it is possible that he simply has musicians hidden and waiting for a signal. He is not the most tender of fathers. Brought up in the English court, he is an excellent singer and harp-player; he is also long-winded and mystical, to the annoyance of some. He is unable to bring his army to England in time for the battle between the rebels and the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOUG.">Archibald, Earl of Douglas</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Douglas is a Scottish lord warring on Henry IV, who was badly beaten by Hotspur. When the latter decides to rebel against the King, he approaches Douglas through his captured son and convinces Douglas to join with him to fight the English monarch. Extremely brave, he is nevertheless discomfited by the news that Glendower will be unable to join the other rebels in time. He spends the battle attempting to kill Henry IV, who has disguised a great number of people as him; when Douglas kills Blunt as one of them, he swears that he would not have bothered if he had not thought the man to be the King. Finally meeting the real monarch, he is on the verge of beating him when Prince Harry comes to his father&#8217;s rescue. Refusing to acknowledge even the existence of the concept of fear, he nevertheless flees after a brief fight with the prince. He also does not seem to notice that Falstaff is merely playing dead. After the battle, Prince Harry lets him go out of respect for his valor. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ARCH.">Richard Scroop, Archbishop of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Archbishop of York is brought into the rebellion thanks to his thirst for revenge over the death of his brother Stephen Scroop (see <persnameref>Richard II</persnameref>). Worried that the battle will be lost due to lack of men, he warns the other rebels who will not be present to prepare themselves for attack by the King. Where this leads can be found in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MORT.">Edmund Mortimer, Earl of March</persname>
<persdescription>Mortimer is an English nobleman captured in battle by Glendower, whose claim to the throne is better than Henry IV&#8217;s. The King refuses to believe that he did not go over to the Welsh willingly, possibly as an excuse to be rid of a rival. Mortimer is descended from an older branch of the royal family than Henry IV, and was proclaimed heir to the throne by Richard II, whom the King took the throne from. Now married to Glendower&#8217;s daughter, he is persuaded to join the rebellion against Henry IV. His marriage is somewhat marred by the fact that his wife only speaks Welsh and he only speaks English. He is not present at the battle between the rebels and the King, though the latter ends the play promising to go fight against him. How he spends the rest of his life can be discovered in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HOT.">Henry Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Hotspur (Sir Henry Percy) is a nobleman from the North, Northumberland&#8217;s son, and the most dashing man of the age. He is an extraordinary fighter, and the ultimate&#8217;s man&#8217;s man, with no time for music, poetry, mysticism, home life, or anything much other than battle. Hot-tempered and excitable, he despises loafers and non-fighters, and is brought to anger when confronted by an effeminate dandy just after a battle. He despises King Henry IV for what he considers the King&#8217;s lack of proper thankfulness for the Percies&#8217; help in setting him on the throne, and when he finds himself treated disrespectfully in public council, Hotspur aims at rebellion. He has no greater love in his life than danger and honor, and actively seeks it out; his temper often carries him too far, but he is almost impossible to restrain. He refuses to wait for reinforcements before engaging the King in battle because the honor of victory will be greater with fewer numbers. He is rather simple-minded, particularly compare with the other two Henries of the play, the politician Henry IV and the dissimulating Henry Prince of Wales. He takes the latter&#8217;s slumming as an excuse to disregard him, and never considers him a proper threat until they are busy fighting each other to the death. He is not a good guest: he is unable to restrain his opinions, easily bored, and rather rude. He also shows little regard for his wife, though their bantering may be their way of showing each other their love. He is the age&#8217;s ideal of a good nobleman, to the extent that the King rather wishes that Hotspur were his son rather than the apparently dissolute Harry. He is given to using his rallying call &#8216;Esp&amp;eacute;rance&#8217; (Hope) as a swear word.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NORTH.">Henry Percy, Earl of Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>Northumberland is Hotspur&#8217;s father and the brother of the Earl of Worcester. He is the same as the Northumberland of <persnameref>Richard II</persnameref>. More cautious than either his brother or (especially) his son, he tries to calm Hotspur down. Failing, he conveniently falls ill just before the battle between the rebels and the King, and thereby avoids execution. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WOR.">Thomas Percy, Earl of Worcester</persname>
<persdescription>Worcester is an English nobleman, Northumberland&#8217;s brother and Hotspur&#8217;s uncle. Back in the reign of Richard II, it was his refusal to declare the returning Bolingbroke a traitor that sparked the general rebellion that led to the latter taking the throne as Henry IV. Worcester considers that he has never been properly regarded for what he did at the time and the good it did for the King, and fears that the fact that the King is indebted to him makes Henry IV dislike him. Though the King believes that Worcester sets his nephew Hotspur on, even the Earl thinks that the younger man is rather wild, and tries to calm him down, not to mention point out to him that he is often rather rude. Still, it is Worcester who forms the first plans for the rebellion. Wiser than Hotspur, he realizes that the absence of the young man&#8217;s father, Northumberland, will leave the rebels looking weaker than they are and cause doubts among their soldiers. He also knows that Hotspur is likely to take the King&#8217;s word about the possibility of forgiveness, and surrender; Worcester, more cautious, has no trust in either Henry IV or Hotspur&#8217;s good sense. He is captured after the battle, and executed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BLUNT.">Sir Walter Blunt</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Walter Blunt is a knight in King Henry&#8217;s service, high-ranked enough that messengers report to him, though he is not a member of the landed nobility. Known to all as a good soldier, he is sent by the King to parley with the rebels in the hopes of avoiding battle. He considers that the whole history of how Henry IV came to the throne has nothing to do with present matters. In the battle, he is one of those who disguise themselves as the King to distract the enemy, which leads him to be targeted and killed by Douglas.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WEST.">Earl of Westmorland</persname>
<persdescription>Earl of Westmorland is one of King Henry&#8217;s noblemen. He reports to the King the events of the Council meeting that the latter has missed, particularly the news of rebellion in Wales. He greatly admires Hotspur and considers Glendower a savage. He is not impressed by Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAN.">Prince John of Lancaster</persname>
<persdescription>John of Lancaster is Henry IV&#8217;s younger son, Prince Harry&#8217;s brother. Unlike his brother, he attends his father at court, and has in fact taken Harry&#8217;s place at the council. The battle against the rebels is the first time he takes to the field, and he acquits himself well, revealing himself to be both a good fighter and brave.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRINCE.,THIEVES.">Henry, Prince of Wales</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Harry is King Henry&#8217;s eldest son and the heir to the throne. He is his father&#8217;s despair due to the fact that he spends all of his time in bars, running around with a bad crowd. He is close to Falstaff, though how fond he is of the old fat knight is uncertain. Quick-witted, he has the common touch, and is able to get the scum of the earth to cheer him and be his friends. His antics have got so out of hands that he has been banned from the King&#8217;s council, where his brother John has replaced him. He is a huge disappointment to the whole of the nobility, and Hotspur in particular disregards him entirely. He enjoys wordplay and mockery, particularly of Falstaff, and enjoys the latter&#8217;s stories and tall tales. What is not realized, either by his father, the court, or his companions, is that no matter how much he may enjoy his dissipated ways, Harry&#8217;s wastrel ways are in fact a coldly calculated act, a part he&#8217;s playing so that when he becomes King he can immediately gain the allegiance of respectable people by instantly turning over a new leaf. He is an excellent soldier, able to best both Douglas and Hotspur in single combat, and loves his father a lot more than he tends to let on. He loses his sense of humor in battle, and does not keep up the mask he wears most of the time as well as he does in the tavern. Asking for the right to determine Douglas&#8217;s sentence, he lets him go out of respect for his valor. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref> and <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="KING.">King Henry IV</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry IV is the Bullingbrook of <persnameref>Richard II.</persnameref> Never forgetting his own usurpation of the throne from Richard II, he cannot help but notice similarities between the state of affairs at the time and the one he finds himself in now. He intends to keep his authority intact, though by overdoing this he provokes Hotspur to rebellion. He is afraid of the existence of Edmund Mortimer, Richard&#8217;s chosen heir, and sees parallels between the former king&#8217;s behavior and that of his son Harry. The latter&#8217;s way of life leaves the King in despair, as the King still despises the memory of Richard&#8217;s effeminate and populist ways. He wishes that his son were more warlike than he has appeared to be to date. Though he is himself an excellent politician (or a vile one, if you ask Hotspur), whose actions are calculated for effect, he fails to see that the Prince is doing much the same. The King smiles a great deal without necessarily meaning it. He is nevertheless a merciful King, executing far fewer people than might be expected. He still hopes to go on a crusade to Jerusalem to expiate his part in the murder of Richard II, but is prevented by the rebellion. He puts no great store in Harry&#8217;s promises to change, but grudgingly gives him a chance to prove himself. The King feels old and weary, though he is able to mount a spirited defense of his rights against the rebels. He is no longer as good a fighter as he was, almost being defeated by Douglas before Harry comes to his aid. The rest of his life is chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CAR.">Second Carrier</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Carrier is transporting goods on the road between Canterbury and London, and resting at the inn near Gads Hill. He is among the group robbed by Falstaff and his gang. He is not impressed by the quality of the inn. He is cautious and knows very well what sort of tricks thieves get up to in such places.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. TRAV., TRAVELLERS.">First Traveler</persname>
<persdescription>The First Traveler is carrying a large sum of money, which he has been foolish enough to mention aloud at the Inn. Due to the amount he has on him, he chooses to travel with others. He is kind to horses. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. TRAV., TRAVELLERS.">Second Traveler</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Traveler is part of the company of travelers who are going along together in the hopes of discouraging thieves. They are unsuccessful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERV.">Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Hotspur&#8217;s Servant has been ordered by him to make all ready for his departure to meet the other rebels.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRAN.">Francis</persname>
<persdescription>Francis is an indentured servant at the Boar&#8217;s Head tavern, essentially a waiter. He has already worked there for two years and has another five to go before he can be a free man. The Prince uses him as the butt of jokes which he does not understand. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HOST.">Hostess</persname>
<persdescription>The Hostess is the owner of the Boar&#8217;s Head tavern in Eastcheap. She is greatly impressed at having the Prince of Wales among her patrons, though Falstaff keeps her in despair, as he never pays his tab. She enjoys playacting and swears a lot. We meet her again, under the name of Mistress Quickly, in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>, <persnameref>The Merry Wives of Windsor</persnameref>, and <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger comes from the Earl of Northumberland to warn Hotspur that he is ill and cannot join the other rebels. He confirms that Northumberland&#8217;s has seen doctors, who are worried about him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger brings letters from an unknown sender to Hotspur, which the latter claims he has no time to read.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger warns Hotspur that the King and his forces are advancing on the rebels and that it is time to fight back.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHAM.">Chamberlain</persname>
<persdescription>Chamberlain works at the inn, and tells Gadshill who the best guests to waylay are. He receives a cut of the profits for every robbery he recommends.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VINT.">Vintner</persname>
<persdescription>The Vintner is essentially the barman at the Boar&#8217;s Head. He dislikes seeing Francis idle rather than hard at work.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>