<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry VI, Part 1">

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger brings news to the English court of how the French have taken back vast amounts of territory since Henry V dies. He lays the blame squarely at the feet of the quarreling English nobility, and has the courage and anger to tell them to shape up.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAP.">Papal Legate</persname>
<persdescription>Papal Legate comes from the Pope to crown the Bishop of Winchester as a Cardinal, and receives Winchester&#8217;s bribe money in return to bring back to the Pope. He also brings letters from the Pope requesting that Henry make peace with France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FIENDS.">Fiends</persname>
<persdescription>The Fiends [mute roles] are demons who have helped Joan de Pucelle achieve victory. They refuse to give her any more help despite all her offers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PUC.">Joan de Pucelle</persname>
<persdescription>Joan de Pucelle is history&#8217;s Joan of Arc, though she is no saint in this play. An plain-spoken woman with no doubts whatsoever, she breezes through all difficulties, seeing at once that Reignier is not the Dolphin, convincing the French to follow her, vanquishing the English, talking her way out of blame, vanquishing again, and convincing the Duke of Burgundy to join the French cause. She is an excellent fighter, better at swordplay than Charles is. Other than all-out assault, she is also adept at tricking her way into advantageous situations and capturing cities that way. Though she claims to be a maid and helped by the Virgin Mary, it turns out that she actually talks with demons, and probably sleeps with the entirety of the French leadership. She has a sharp tongue, mocking the English well, and swearing with great effect when she is captured. She grows more and more full of herself as time goes on, and in the end refuses to recognize her father, insisting that she is in fact nobly born. Desperate to avoid death, she swears that she is a virgin and then that she is pregnant, but cannot decide on an identity for the father. She is burned alive at the stake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="COUNT.">Countess of Auvergne</persname>
<persdescription>Countess of Auvergne is a patriotic Frenchwoman who thinks she will be able to deal a terrible blow to the English by capturing Talbot, and not incidentally become very famous. Unfortunately for her, he sees through her trick before he even meets her. She is bemused to find him a physically unimpressive man, and quite seduced by him once he tricks her &#8212; unless, of course, she is merely flattering out of fear for her life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Margaret is Reignier of Anjou&#8217;s daughter, and sets stock by his empty claim to be a King. Captured by Suffolk, she is oblivious to the fact that he falls in love with her on sight, though she feels more than a twinge in the same direction herself. She attempts to immediately get down to business with him and to work out a ransom, and becomes impatient with his lack of attention to her. She is proud, though not unaware of the poverty of her position. She agrees to marry King Henry, though with no great passion. Where this leads may be discovered in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHEP.">Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>A Shepherd is Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s father, who has been searching for her since she ran away. A simple man, he is desolated by the fact that she is going to die, and horrified when she denies him. His love turns to hate when she refuses to accept his blessing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PORT.">Porter</persname>
<persdescription>The Porter is charged by the Countess of Auvergne to lock the doors to her house once Talbot has entered in.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERG.">French Sergeant</persname>
<persdescription>The French Sergeant is in charge of setting sentinels to watch for the English.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GEN.">General of the French Force at Bordeaux</persname>
<persdescription>General of the French Force at Bordeaux detests Talbot, and rejoices to be able to inform him that he has fallen into a trap from which he cannot escape.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="M. GUN.">Master Gunner of Orléans</persname>
<persdescription>Master Gunner is in charge of the French artillery at Orl&amp;eacute;ans. He wishes to accomplish a great act that will bring him to the attention of the French leadership, and for that purpose has aimed a gun at a point where the English noblemen will come to look at the town. After three days of waiting for them, he is exhausted and sets his son to watch instead, which as far as his hopes of gaining recognition go is a mistake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GOV. PARIS.">Governor of Paris</persname>
<persdescription>The Governor of Paris attends Henry&#8217;s coronation as King of France and swears to accept no other King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAST.">Bastard of Orléans</persname>
<persdescription>The Bastard of Orl&amp;eacute;ans is a French nobleman, the first to meet Joan de Pucelle and the one who brings her to Charles&#8217;s camp. He is greatly impressed by her and her intelligence. He is a vindictive man who wishes to have Talbot&#8217;s body torn to pieces and mocks the dead John Talbot. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALAN.">Duke of Alanson</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Alanson is a French nobleman, one of Charles the Dolphin&#8217;s generals. He thinks little of the English and is therefore shocked when they succeed in beating him back. A rather brainless fellow, he becomes quite a worshipper of Joan. He counsels Charles to take the peace treaty that makes him King and ends the war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BUR.">Duke of Burgundy</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Burgundy is King Henry&#8217;s uncle, and a faithful supporter of the English until he is seduced to the French side by Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s arguments and accepts that he is himself a Frenchman. His defection marks the end of English hopes in France. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="REIG.">Reignier, Duke of Anjou</persname>
<persdescription>Reignier, Duke of Anjou is an impoverished French nobleman who holds the purely cosmetic title of King of Naples. One of Charles&#8217;s main generals, he is as willing as his master to let Joan de Pucelle save their skins. When his daughter Margaret is captured by Suffolk, he is at first worried, but when the Englishman asks to have her married to King Henry, Reignier is quick to agree so long as the English stop attacking him. He is vainglorious and not particularly intelligent, though he does counsel Charles to take the peace treaty that makes him King and ends the war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHAR.">Charles, Dauphin of France</persname>
<persdescription>Charles, Dauphin of France, and later King, is King Henry&#8217;s rival claimant to the throne of France. Following a string of victories, he has himself crowned King of France. He is greatly helped by the young lady Joan de Pucelle, who is a much better fighter than he is and with whom he is passionately in love. He is himself a bit of a coward, reneging on his word not to run away until he sees that he actually is in danger of death. He does not like taking responsibility and is quick to blame others. He is happily hypocritical when need be, swearing to a peace treaty he has no intention of keeping, and is a bit of a lightweight. Historically he is the same as the Dauphin of <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAW.">Lawyer</persname>
<persdescription>A Lawyer, of the Yorkist party, is present at Somerset and Richard Plantagenet&#8217;s quarrel at the Temple (law school). On the basis of a point of law, he takes Richard&#8217;s side in their dispute.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAS.">Basset</persname>
<persdescription>Basset, of the Lancastrian party, is a young Englishman who follows and supports the Duke of Somerset, insulting the Duke of York in Vernon&#8217;s presence. He is willing to fight for his master&#8217;s cause, to the point of asking the King to make an exception in the law against dueling so that he may fight Vernon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VER.">Vernon</persname>
<persdescription>Vernon, of the Yorkist party, is a young Englishman who follows and supports Richard Plantagenet from the start, taking his side at the quarrel in the Temple Garden. He insults the Duke of Somerset in Basset&#8217;s presence, and is willing to fight for his master&#8217;s cause, to the point of asking the King to make an exception in the law against dueling so that he may fight Basset.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WOODV.">Woodvile</persname>
<persdescription>Woodvile is the Lieutenant of the Tower of London, charged with its defense. He refuses entry to the Duke of Gloucester on the Bishop of Winchester&#8217;s orders, precipitating a street brawl.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAY.">Mayor of London</persname>
<persdescription>The Mayor of London is left shaking his head at the silliness of noblemen and their quarrels after he is forced to read the Riot Act to two of the highest magnates in the land and their men. When brawling breaks out yet again, he has no option but to beg the King for help. He is an ordinary civilian, more concerned with commerce than with the in-fighting of the nobility or the war in France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GAR.">Sir Thomas Gargrave</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Gargrave is an English knight who is part of the force besieging Orl&amp;eacute;ans and is an expert on artillery placement, though he disagrees with the other expert, Glansdale. He is killed outright by the volley of cannon fire that also kills the Earl of Salisbury.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GLAN.">Sir William Glansdale</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Glansdale is an English knight who is part of the force besieging Orl&amp;eacute;ans and is an expert on artillery placement, though he disagrees with the other expert, Gargrave.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUCY.">Sir William Lucy</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Lucy rushes to both Richard Duke of York and the Duke of Somerset to plead for reinforcements to help Talbot in his last battle, and is horrified at how they let their private quarrel intervene and use it as an excuse not to do so, and blame the other. Returning to the site of battle, he is distraught to find him dead. He can be pompous, and thinks little of the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FAL.">Sir John Falstaff</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Falstaff is a cowardly English knight who twice runs away from battle, leaving Talbot in grave difficulty, a fact that in one case leads to Talbot&#8217;s capture. He freely admits to valuing his own life more than anything, and is publically disgraced by Talbot in retaliation. He is not the same as the Falstaff of the <persnameref>Henry IV</persnameref> plays or <persnameref>The Merry Wives of Windsor</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MOR.">Edmund Mortimer, Earl of March</persname>
<persdescription>Mortimer is an English lord who has been imprisoned for most of his life. Richard II&#8217;s chosen heir, he was displaced by King Henry&#8217;s grandfather, Henry IV, when the latter usurped the throne. He was part of a rebellion against the latter which failed, after which he was sent to jail (see <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>). Knowing himself to be dying, he calls his nephew Richard Plantagenet to his side to tell him of all this and let the young man know that he has more right to the throne than does the current King. He is very old, weak, and almost blind. Historically he is the same as the Mortimer of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JOHN.">John Talbot</persname>
<persdescription>John Talbot is the son of Lord Talbot, whom he loves and admires deeply. Imbued with the same ideals of knighthood, he refuses to leave the field of battle when his father asks him to, not being willing to risk being branded a coward. He is a courageous fighter, and bests Charles the Dolphin in combat, but his temper gets the best of him and he plunges into the fiercest part of the battle, where he is killed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TAL.">Lord Talbot</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Talbot, the Earl of Shrewsbury, is the greatest of the English generals in France, a man whose successes are so great that the mention of his name alone is enough to make the French run away. Though not a physically impressive man, he has great presence and commands intense loyalty from his men. He is a larger-than-life character, raging, proud, and with a great sense of humor and mockery. He is aware of how much he owes to his men, and regards them highly. He is distraught at being bested by Joan. He is not taken in by the Countess of Auvergne, suspecting a trap as soon as he receives her invitation. He is the ideal of English knighthood and knows it; he stands up for it and enforces its standards on those around him, punishing Falstaff for failing them. He loves his son and tries to make him leave their final battle, but fails. He holds as long as he can before falling in battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SUF.">Earl of Suffolk</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Suffolk (William de la Pole), of the Lancastrian party, is a young English nobleman, a friend of Somerset&#8217;s. He captures Margaret in the wars and is absolutely smitten by her, to the extent that he proposes to marry her to his King simply so he can have her close; being married already he cannot himself wed her. What this leads to is chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SAL.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury is an English nobleman and war commander who is besieging Orl&amp;eacute;ans, and a great friend of Talbot&#8217;s. Convinced that he is on the verge of capturing the city, he has half of his face torn away by a cannonball. He lingers for some minutes before dying. Historically he is the same as the Salisbury of <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WAR.">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>Earl of Warwick, of the Yorkist party, is a young English lord, a friend of Richard Plantagenet&#8217;s. Asked to mediate in the quarrel between Richard and the Duke of Somerset, he takes Richard&#8217;s side; he also presents the petition to the King that restores Richard to his inheritance. He acts as a restraint on Richard&#8217;s more violent instincts, holding him back from saying anything unforgivable. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PLAN.">Richard Plantagenet</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Plantagenet, head of the Yorkist party, is the son of the Earl of Cambridge, who attempted to assassinate the King&#8217;s father (see <persnameref>Henry V</persnameref>). His father&#8217;s action left Richard deprived of all his wealth and titles until these are officially returned to him by the King, making him Duke of York. Richard feels the shame of this deeply, and is very touchy on the subject; his quarrel with Somerset on the matter leads to a breach that will turn into the War of the Roses. He is convinced that he has a better right to the throne than Henry VI does, and in law he does, as he is descended from an elder branch of the royal family. Named to a combined command of the army in France with Somerset, he lets his quarrel with the latter overbear the good of the country, and refuses to send aid to the beleaguered Talbot, thus causing the hero&#8217;s death; he refuses to accept any responsibility for this. He has the luck to capture Joan de Pucelle, and has her burnt alive, mocking her brutally beforehand. Richard can be pitiless, and is enraged when he hears of peace behind declared between England and France. He is ambitios and does not always manage to disguise this fact. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SOM.">John Beauford, Duke of Somerset</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Somerset, of the Lancastrian party, is a young and haughty lord, who despises Richard Plantagenet for being the son of a traitor, and is incensed when the latter is restored to his father&#8217;s lands and named Duke of York. His quarrel with Richard on this matter leads to a breach that will become the War of the Roses; he does not hold to his word to give in if more people side against him than with him. Named to an equal command with the new Duke of York in France, he refuses to collaborate with him, thereby leaving Talbot without help and causing his death. He refuses to accept any blame for Talbot&#8217;s demise. He cares only for his own good, nothing for the kingdom. He returns in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WIN., CAR.">Henry Beauford, Bishop of Winchester</persname>
<persdescription>The Bishop of Winchester is the bastard son of the King&#8217;s great-grandfather. He is a crafty, hypocritical, sly man of high ambitions, who has a permanent feud with the Duke of Gloucester. He pretends to be highly pious but in fact acts only for his own material gain, and to become the most powerful man in the kingdom he plans to abduct the King from Gloucester&#8217;s care. Failing, he swears to be friends with the Duke, but doesn&#8217;t mean it. He bribes the Pope into naming him a cardinal, which gives him equal rank with Dukes, and is sent by the King to treat for peace with the French. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EXE.">Thomas Beauford, Duke of Exeter</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Exeter is King Henry&#8217;s great uncle; historically he is the same as the Exeter of <perstitleref>Henry V</perstitleref>. A fierce and warlike man, he is charged with the young King&#8217;s personal safety. He sees all too clearly what the quarrels between the various English aristocrats portend, and does not wish to live to see himself proved right. He is a member of the old guard, devoted to the memory of Henry V.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BED.">Duke of Bedford</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Bedford is Regent of France, in charge of continuing the war against the French and safeguarding Henry V&#8217;s conquests. An older man, he is impatient with the quarreling of the other English lords, being more concerned with the war than with their squabbling. He has a hard time believing that a woman could have any military ability. He falls ill as the fortune of battle shifts and shifts again, but forces himself to stay alive long enough to witness Roan being re-taken from the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GLOU.">Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Gloucester is King Henry&#8217;s uncle and Lord Protector, charged with the safety of the King in his youth and the government of the realm until he comes of age. Historically he is the same as the Gloucester of Henry V. He has an all-abiding hatred of the Bishop of Winchester and carries on an endless feud with him, no matter how much it may harm the kingdom. Due to this hatred, he has little regard for the Church. The King is greatly dependent on him, a fact that Gloucester is used to; he is appalled when the King disregards his advice on the matter of his marriage. He is willing to be convinced to calm down his quarreling with the Bishop, but still loses his temper every time he is in the prelate&#8217;s presence. Though loyal, he is more concerned with himself and his ward than for the realm itself. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="KING.">King Henry the Sixth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry VI is a very young, rather simple-minded monarch, of excessive piety and naivet&amp;eacute;, who relies almost entirely on his uncle the Duke of Gloucester. Becoming King while still a child, he is wide-eyed at the scuffles between his uncles, and cannot command as a King should; rather he begs, and occasionally cries. His greatest desire is for peace among his noblemen, though he believes entirely in his right to the French throne. He has absolutely no political sense, and agrees to Suffolk&#8217;s proposal that he should marry Margaret without considering any of the arguments against the match. He is generally a passive character, reacting to events rather than causing them. He returns in <perstitleref>Henry VI, Part Two</perstitleref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger brings to the English court the news that Charles has had himself crowned King, and that many great nobles of France have flocked to his side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger brings news to the English court of Talbot&#8217;s capture and Falstaff&#8217;s cowardice.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. WARDER">First Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The First Warder of the Tower refuses to open the gates to Gloucester, as he has his orders not to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. WARDER">Second Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Warder of the Tower insists that no-one can be let in, whoever they are.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GLOU. SERV. ATT.">Gloucester's First Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s First Serving Attendant follows his master and fights for him at the Tower of London, and continues to brawl with Winchester&#8217;s men in the street. When forbidden to use weapons, he uses stones instead. He is a very combative man. He wears a blue coat that marks him as Gloucester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GLOU. SERV. ATT.">Gloucester's Second Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Gloucester&#8217;s Second Serving Attendant insists that he and his friends and family will fight to the death for Gloucester&#8217;s honor. He seems slightly more intelligent than his fellows, as well as more resilient, going to a pub rather than to the doctor&#8217;s when wounded. He wears a blue coat that marks him as Gloucester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OFF.">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer reads out the Riot Act to Gloucester, Winchester and their followers as they riot, at the Mayor&#8217;s command.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="M. GUN. BOY.">Master Gunner&#8217;s Boy</persname>
<persdescription>The Master Gunner&#8217;s Boy is the son of the Master Gunner of Orl&amp;eacute;ans, set to keep a lookout for the English nobility and to fetch his father so that the latter can shoot at them should they appear. However, preferring to get the glory himself, he shoots the gun off himself, killing Gargrave and Salisbury.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="4. MESS.">Fourth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Messenger comes to warn Talbot that the French have been joined by Joan de Pucelle and the Dolphin and are coming to raise the siege of Orl&amp;eacute;ans.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SENT.">First Sentinel</persname>
<persdescription>The First Sentinel does not appreciate his job, as it is most uncomfortable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SENT.">Second Sentinel</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Sentinel [mute role] keeps watch with the First Sentinel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ENG. SOLD.">English Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>An English Soldier knows perfectly well how much the French fears Talbot, and uses the fact to enrich himself by scaring them off with only the sound of Talbot&#8217;s name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS. COUNT.">Messenger of the Countess</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger of the Countess delivers the Countess of Auvergne&#8217;s invitation to Talbot. He knows how to flatter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. KEEPER.">First Keeper</persname>
<persdescription>The First Keeper is in charge of Mortimer&#8217;s prison. He is kind to his prisoner, and arranges a meeting with Richard Plantagenet when Mortimer asks him to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. KEEPER.">Second Keeper</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Keeper [mute role] is one of the guards of Mortimer&#8217;s prison. He helps carry the prisoner out to see Richard Plantagenet.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WIN. SERV. ATT.">Winchester's Serving Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>Winchester&#8217;s Serving Attendant follows his master and fights for him at the Tower of London, and continues to brawl with Gloucester&#8217;s men in the street. When forbidden to use weapons, he uses stones instead. He is not impressed by all the threats that Gloucester&#8217;s men make. He wears a tawny coat that marks him as Winchester&#8217;s man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SOLD.">First Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>The First Soldier is one of Joan de Pucelle&#8217;s disguised group that sneaks into Rouen, and enjoys a good pun.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAPT.">Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Captain is an English officer disgusted at Falstaff&#8217;s cowardice. When Talbot is surrounded by the Dolphin&#8217;s forces, he is sent to beg Somerset to send reinforcements.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="5. MESS.">Fifth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fifth Messenger informs the Duke of York that the French armies have met and joined together, and that the full French force is attacking Talbot.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCOUT.">Scout</persname>
<persdescription>A Scout brings the French leadership the news that the two English armies have met and combined.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AMB. EMP.">Ambassador from the Emperor</persname>
<persdescription>Ambassador from the Emperor [mute role] has brought the Emperor&#8217;s request that England and France should make peace to King Henry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AMB. ARM.">Ambassador from the Earl of Armagnac</persname>
<persdescription>Ambassador from the Earl of Armagnac [mute role] has brought the Earl&#8217;s request that there should be peace between England and France to King Henry, and his offer of his daughter&#8217;s hand.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TAL. TRUMP.">Talbot&#8217;s Trumpeter</persname>
<persdescription>Talbot&#8217;s Trumpeter [mute role] follows his master and summons the French General to talk.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FR. HER.">French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>French Herald [mute role] brings Lucy to the Dauphin&#8217;s tent under a safe-conduct.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SOLD. WATCH.">Soldier of the Watch</persname>
<persdescription>Soldier of the Watch is an English guard who lets Joan de Pucelle into Rouen, believing her story that she and her group are going to market.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>