<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Henry V">

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="KATH.">Katherine</persname>
<persdescription>Katherine is the daughter of Charles VI of France. She is aware from the start of the war that she is likely to be married off to Henry in any peace treaty, and starts to learn English as soon as she can. A demure girl, she is shocked by how gross and vile English sounds, but is still a quick learner. She is at first uncertain of whether she actually wishes to marry Henry, though she accepts the need, but he manages to charm her, if only by making her laugh at his terrible French. She still finds him a bit shocking in the speed with which he moves on with this.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="Q. ISA.">Queen Isabel</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Isabel is Charles of France&#8217;s wife. She is flirtatious and flattering towards the English when they meet, softening the tone of the meeting greatly and making it more welcoming for them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. AMB.">Ambassador of France</persname>
<persdescription>The Amabassador of France bears the Dauphin&#8217;s insulting present and message to King Henry. He has sense enough to be slightly scared of delivering it, and makes it very clear that he is only the messenger.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MONT.">Montjoy</persname>
<persdescription>Montjoy is the Herald of the French King, Charles&#8217;s official mouthpiece; his word can be considered that of the King himself. He likes King Henry well enough, but does not think he stands any chance against the French. He brings Henry the various offers to ransom himself he is made, and later announces the French surrender. His certainty is broken by the English victory.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GOV.">Governor of Harfleur</persname>
<persdescription>Governor of Harfleur holds the city for the King of France, and holds off King Henry&#8217;s siege for as long as he can. When it becomes apparent that no help will reach them in time and that Henry&#8217;s threats are real, he surrenders the city.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GRAND.">Grandpr&#233;</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Grandpr&#233; is a French nobleman and soldier who leads the first line of Frenchmen at Agincourt and therefore has a lot of leisure to study the English before the battle begins. He is not impressed by what he sees. He is killed in the battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="RAM.">Rambures</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Rambures is a French nobleman and soldier with absolutely no doubt of victory over the English. He is a betting man who commands the French crossbows at Agincourt. He is killed in the battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CON.">Constable of France</persname>
<persdescription>The Constable of France (Charles Delabret) is a high-ranking French nobleman, one of the more cautious of the French war leaders. He listens carefully to the ambassadors&#8217; report about King Henry, and is impressed by it. However, he is unprepared to find the rest of the English army as powerful and warlike. Reassured by the fact that the English are few in number and starving, he is supremely confident of victory at Agincourt. He considers the Dauphin foppish and full of himself, and is an honorable man somewhat disappointed at how small a task they have. Seeing that they have lost, he insists on returning to the fray and dying there, which he does.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BERRI.">Duke of Berri</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Berri [mute role] is a French nobleman sent by King Charles to raise an army and prepare France for defense against King Henry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BRIT.">Duke of Britain</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Britain is a French nobleman sent by King Charles to raise an army and prepare France for defense against King Henry. He is disdainful of the English as being descended from his neighbors, the Normans, whom he does not regard very highly. The English victories hit hard at his manhood.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BOUR.">Duke of Bourbon</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Bourbon is a French nobleman and war leader. He can scarcely grasp the extent of the French disaster, and rallies the other noblemen to return to the fight, though he is so shocked by the defeat that he refuses to try to regroup and counter-attack with discipline, preferring a desperate and wild charge. He is captured by King Henry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ORL.">Duke of Orleance</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of Orleance (Orl&#233;ans) is a French nobleman and war leader who thinks better of the Dauphin than most. He disdains the English, and is supremely confident of victory over them. He is shocked by the strength of the English, and realizes how foolish the French have been, but can see that they could still win were they not in a panic.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BUR.">Duke of Burgundy</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Burgundy is a neutral party in the war, as loyal to England as to France, and therefore serves as negotiator between the two parties after the Battle of Agincourt. He feels the damage done to the country in a way that the two Kings do not. The agreement to the peace treaty pleases him greatly, and leaves him less depressed; he is able to mock King Henry over his quickly-gained intimacy with Katherine, and make some juicy comments about women to him. He is a politician rather than a warrior, and concerned with the damage the war does to commerce.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DAU.">The Dauphin</persname>
<persdescription>The Dauphin is the son of King Charles of France, and heir to the throne (Dauphin). He is a headstrong, impulsive, condescending and foolish young man who disregards King Henry entirely and pays the price for it. Thinking it a great joke, he sends tennis balls to Henry as being better suited to his age, and by doing so precipitates the war. He is infuriated when Harfleur falls and insists on joining the army to fight the English, despite his father&#8217;s order to the contrary. He adores his horse, and is vaingloriously overconfident about the French chances. Defeat leaves him distraught. His is disinherited by the terms of the peace treaty, which states that Henry will take the throne after Charles&#8217;s death. Historically, the Dauphin is the same character as Charles the Dauphin in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. KING.">Charles the Sixth</persname>
<persdescription>Charles VI is the King of France, whose claim to the throne King Henry does not recognize. Somewhat timid, he is brought to a great deal of trouble by his son the Dauphin. Rather than lead his armies himself, he sends his noblemen to do so for him. He knows too well what has happened to the French in the past, and is more cautious than either his headstrong son or most of his commanders. He is capable of being roused, however, particularly by the pressure of his followers. He is gracious in defeat, and at least sounds as though he believes the treaty he signs is a good thing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HER.">English Herald</persname>
<persdescription>English Herald joins Montjoy to make an agreed-upon list of the dead after the battle, and reports these back to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BOY.">Boy</persname>
<persdescription>Boy is in the service of Pistol, Nim, and Bardolph, and was once Falstaff&#8217;s page, in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. Quick-witted and intelligent, he speaks French well, and slowly comes to understand just how cowardly and unworthy his masters are. He himself is made of much finer stuff and promises to be a decent man; unfortunately, he is killed along with the other boys when the French attack the luggage train.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BARD.">Bardolph</persname>
<persdescription>Bardolph is one of Falstaff&#8217;s old companions and now a soldier in the French army, the same character as the Bardolph of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. Noticeable for his huge red nose and his pockmarked face, he is a coward and a rogue, but still has enough presence to be able to stop Nim and Pistol from actually fighting. His main concern in France is looting, which is unfortunate, as he is caught and executed for it by Exeter. The King has no mercy for him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="NYM.">Nym</persname>
<persdescription>Nym is a corporal in the army, and one of Falstaff&#8217;s former companions. He had been engaged to Hostess Quickly, and is downcast and angered that she married Pistol instead. He admires the King even though he blames him for Falstaff&#8217;s death. He is a lamentable failure as a soldier, as he prefers robbing and keeping away from the fight. He is not very talkative. Caught thieving in France, he is hanged for his pains.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PIST.">Pistol</persname>
<persdescription>Pistol is the same character as the Pistol of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>, formerly one of Falstaff&#8217;s companions and now a soldier in Henry&#8217;s army, with the rank of Ancient (Ensign). A great braggart, he talks in a mix of quotations from plays, foreign languages, and excessive, over-the-top oaths, all designed to impress his listeners with his bravery, manliness and experience, none of which actually exist. A coward, he hides from battle; his main reason for joining the army is the chance to make money from looting. He is quick-tempered, quick to insult and quick to pull his sword, though not necessarily to fight. He is able to convince Fluellen that he is a great soldier for some small time, but is soon found out. He is a racist who despises the Welsh, a pickpocket, and a liar. He does have friends, however, and attempts to save Bardolph&#8217;s life, as well as having a great fondness for the King despite everything. Newly married to Hostess Quickly, he shows every sign of being genuinely in love with her, and is saddened at her death. He returns to England to make a living by telling tall tales of his exploits in France, having being robbed of his chance at riches by the King&#8217;s order to kill all prisoners.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WILL.">Williams</persname>
<persdescription>Michael Williams is a soldier in the English army, a friend of Alexander of Court and John Bates. Rather cynical, he does not put much faith in propaganda, and admits to having no idea whether King Henry is in the right in waging his war. He has a keen appreciation for the effects of war on the actual soldiers, and thinks that the King bears some responsibility for what happens to them, though he is a loyal subject and obeys him without question. Despite this loyalty, he does not think much of the promises of great men, and is willing to fight for his doubts. On discovering that the man he pledged to fight with was the King himself, he manages to extricate himself from the difficulty by arguing that he would never have said those things to the King&#8217;s face, while not denying his charge. His honesty sees him well rewarded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="COURT.">Court</persname>
<persdescription>Alexander Court is a soldier in the English army, a friend to John Bates and Michael Williams. He is on the lookout for the start of the say.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BATES.">Bates</persname>
<persdescription>John Bates is a soldier in the English army who rather wishes he wasn&#8217;t in France. Though he admits it is his duty to follow the King, he does not look forwards to the battle, being certain that far too many men will die. He is a down-to-earth sort, exasperated by soldiers in the same army starting to fight one another when they have a battle the next day.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="JAMY.">Jamy</persname>
<persdescription>Captain Jamy is a Scottish officer in the English army who enjoys listening to a good dispute over the proper way to fight a war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MAC.">Macmorris</persname>
<persdescription>Captain Macmorris is an Irish officer in the English army, in charge of digging the mines at the walls of Harfleur. He is touchy, suspects people of looking down on him for being Irish, and swears a lot. He does not much appreciate being told how to do his job by Fluellen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FLU.">Fluellen</persname>
<persdescription>Captain Fluellen is a Welsh officer in the English army who is obsessed with military history and deeply proud of his nationality. A bookworm and a know-it-all, he is not shy about offering his opinions on how war should be conducted, and only respects soldiers whom he considers to have a good enough knowledge of Antiquity&#8217;s rule for warfare. A stickler for discipline, he refuses to intervene on behalf of a thief, forces soldiers who are hanging back to join the front lines, and insists that soldiers keep silent at night even when there is no secret as to where they are. He worships King Henry and is very proud of the monarch&#8217;s links to Wales. Though at first taken in by Pistol&#8217;s convincing portrait of a great soldier, he soon comes to see him for what he truly is; when Pistol spends some time insulting Wales and the Welsh, Fluellen beats him and forces him to eat a leek (the national symbol of Wales).</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GOW.">Gower</persname>
<persdescription>Captain Gower is an officer in the English army who is friendly with Fluellen, if somewhat overwhelmed by the Welshman&#8217;s know-it-all-ness. He sees through Pistol much more quickly than most others and has no respect for him whatsoever. Though he thinks Fluellen takes things too seriously, he respects him and often takes his advice, if only to keep him quiet. He is a man of great common sense who keeps the peace between the Welsh, Irish, and Scottish officers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ERP.">Sir Thomas Erpingham</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Erpingham is an old, white-haired soldier in the English army, well-respected by the men. He summons the King&#8217;s war council, and lends Henry his cloak.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GREY.">Sir Thomas Grey</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GREY. AND SCROOP.">Grey and Scroop</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Grey is a traitor against King Henry, hired by the French to murder the King with the help of Cambridge and Scroop. He insists that he is glad to have been found out.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SCROOP.">Lord Scroop</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GREY. AND SCROOP.">Grey and Scroop</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Henry, Lord Scroop of Masham is a traitor against King Henry, hired by the French to murder the King with the help of Cambridge and Grey. He has been one of Henry&#8217;s closest and most trusted friends, making his betrayal particularly painful for the King. Though he offers no explanation for his treason, his family links to the executed Archbishop of York (see <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>) may provide a clue.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAM.">Richard, Earl of Cambridge</persname>
<persdescription>Richard, Earl of Cambridge is a traitor against King Henry, hired by the French to murder the King with the help of Grey and Scroop. He has intended for some time to kill Henry; by his own admission, the French bribery merely hastened him along. He does not attempt to defend himself. He is a slick actor, though he overdoes his praise of Henry a little.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ELY.">Bishop of Ely</persname>
<persdescription>The Bishop of Ely is worried that the Church will lose most of its revenue, and works with the Archbishop of Canterbury to avoid this by convincing Henry to go to war against France. He is rather impressed by the King, especially compared to how he acted when heir to the throne (see both parts of <persnameref>Henry IV </persnameref>for details).</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CANT.">Archbishop of Canterbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Archbishop of Canterbury incites King Henry to war against France, mostly to get the Church out of having to lose most of its revenue. His explanations for why Henry is in the right can be somewhat overwhelming. He is pleased by the change in Henry since he became King. (See both parts of <persnameref>Henry IV</persnameref> for further details.)</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WAR.">Earl of Warwick</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Warwick is the King&#8217;s cousin, whom Henry involves in his prank on Fluellen and Williams. His commonsense worries about the odds against the English are washed away by Henry&#8217;s speeches. He is the same as the Warwick of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WEST.">Earl of Westmorland</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Westmorland is one of King Henry&#8217;s noblemen, who helps to incite him to war against France. He despises traitors. He is the same as the Westmorland of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SAL.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Salisbury is one of King Henry&#8217;s noblemen, in charge of one section of the English army. He is well-aware of how dangerous the English position is. Historically he is the same as the Salisbury of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="YORK.">Duke of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of York is the King&#8217;s cousin. A good soldier, he is thirsty for glory, and begs the chance to be at the very front of the English army at Agincourt, where he wins glory by dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EXE.">Duke of Exeter</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Exeter is King Henry&#8217;s uncle and one of his chief supporters and closest advisors. The King tends to call on him when something needs doing, whether it is opening a gift or arresting traitors. A man eager for war, who helps to convince Henry to attack France, he is sent as ambassador to the French court. A defiant and unbending man, he is utterly loyal and rather intimidating. He can be emotional when faced with the death of a friend, however. Given the command of Harfleur after Henry captures it, he nevertheless follows the army and is present at Agincourt, and later at the peace negotiations with the French. Historically he is the same as the Exeter of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CLAR.">Thomas, Duke of Clarence</persname>
<persdescription>Thomas, Duke of Clarence [mute role] is King Henry&#8217;s brother, the same character as in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. He is a member of the King&#8217;s council and follows his brother to the wars. He assists in the treaty negotiations with the French.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BED.">John, Duke of Bedford</persname>
<persdescription>John, Duke of Bedford is King Henry&#8217;s brother, and the same as the John Duke of Lancaster of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. A member of the King&#8217;s Council, he follows Henry to the wars. He is more cautious than his brother, and disgusted at the traitors. Historically he is the same as the Bedford of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GLOU.">Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester is King Henry&#8217;s brother, the same as the Humphrey of Gloucester of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. He is a good soldier and strongly supports his brother in his endeavors in France. Historically he is the same character as the Humphrey Duke of Gloucester of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="K. HEN.">King Henry the Fifth</persname>
<persdescription>King Henry V is the same characters as the Harry of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref> and <persnameref>Part Two</persnameref>. He is a young man who when he was heir to the throne pretended to be dissolute so that he would impress his subjects by becoming a good man the moment he took power. Intent on being seen as the perfect king, he is often cold, and though he is eager to go to war he insists on being convinced he has a right to do so. He is a great speechmaker, able to rouse his audience to great enthusiasm, and he uses this skill well, needing little excuse to deliver an oration. He is merciless, though he calls it justice, not only refusing to save an old friend from hanging but saying he is pleased this has happened; at a moment&#8217;s fear in the middle of battle, he orders all French prisoners killed. Nevertheless, he still enjoys pranks, setting Williams to fight Fluellen before revealing that the soldier&#8217;s quarrel is with him. He is pious, and believes God to be on his side. He is afraid all the same that his father&#8217;s usurpation of the throne (see <persnameref>Richard II</persnameref>) will play against him even though he has tried to atone for that crime. Though he rejects Williams&#8217;s argument that he will bear some guilt in the death of his soldiers, he still feels some unease, simply due to all the cares that press down on him as King. He is rarely alone, and thus allowed little time for introspection; almost everything he says is for public consumption. He is somewhat shy and not a little bumbling when he attempts to woo Katherine, particularly as his French is atrocious. He is very charming when he chooses to be, however, and earns extraordinary loyalty from his men. He dies little after the end of the play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CHORUS.">Chorus</persname>
<persdescription>The Chorus leads the audience through the play, explaining those things that the theatre lacks the ability, the budget, or the time to show. Somewhat apologetic in manner, he nevertheless urges that the audience have their part to play in the performance, and insists that they use their imaginations to supplement what&#8217;s missing from the stage. Chorus is a bit of a cheerleader for the King, presenting a triumphant, patriotic story, and ignoring anything that might happen on stage to challenge that view, though he is forced to admit that Henry&#8217;s triumph didn&#8217;t last, as can be seen in the various <persnameref>Henry VI </persnameref>plays.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. MESS.">French Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The French Messenger comes to tell the French leaders that the English have prepared for battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. SOLD.">French Soldier</persname>
<persdescription>French Soldier (Monsieur le Fer) is captured by Pistol on the battlefield. Rather panicked and something of a coward, he is terrified of his captor&#8217;s promises of death, and offers a small fortune to be ransomed instead of killed. Having done this much, he has his throat cut by Pistol when King Henry orders the prisoners to be killed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. ATT.">French Court Attendant</persname>
<persdescription>The French Court Attendant announces the arrival of the Duke of Exeter to the French King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HOST.">Hostess</persname>
<persdescription>Hostess is the same as Hostess Quickly of <persnameref>Henry IV, Part Two</persnameref>. Despite having become engaged to Nim, she has recently married Pistol. She attends Falstaff in his last hours, trying to keep him comfortable. She is not overly happy to see all her men go off to war, but lets them. Her foolishness (see <persnameref>Henry IV</persnameref>) seems to have vanished in the wake of Falstaff&#8217;s death and the start of the war: though she still misuses language, she is a much quieter woman. Riddled with venereal disease, she is killed by them while Pistol is in France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ALICE.">Alice</persname>
<persdescription>Alice is Catherine&#8217;s waiting-woman. She has lived in England previously, and remembers something of the language, though perhaps not as much as she thinks she does. She praises the princess&#8217; learning ability to the skies, but still has to act as interpreter when King Henry arrives to woo the girl.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>
