<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<PERSONAE playtitle="Henry VIII">
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">King Henry the Eighth</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>King Henry VIII is not exactly the Holbein portrait yet. A young man still growing into his rule, he relies much too much on the advice of Cardinal Wolsey, but grows to be a worthy king over the course of the play. Not paying enough attention to the business of the state, he allows Wolsey to enact a number of measures that harm the people, something he himself wishes to avoid. He spends his time impressing the King of France or playing in masques rather than in governing. He can be short and irritable with people, especially though who disturb him, and is at times too brusque for his own good. His temper is feared by his courtiers. Though he loves and admires his wife Katherine, his conscience begins to bother him when the question of the legitimacy of his marriage comes up; and the more he is convinced that he must divorce her, the worse he treats her. However, he both meets and begins showing favor to Anne Bullen well before the failed attempt to try the Queen. He comes to dislike the officials of Rome, and realizes that their interests are not necessarily his; when Wolsey&#8217;s corruption is laid bare to him, he places his trust instead in Protestants, and tests them before trusting them. He has the common touch, managing to relate to people on a personal level despite their difference in status. By the end of the play he prefers to expose his enemies by placing them in a position where they must make their genuine thoughts clear, thereby gaining undeniable evidence, rather than trusting the word of unreliable witnesses as he does in Buckingham&#8217;s trial. He also learns to identify and discount mere flattery. The lessons he learns from having had too much confidence in Wolsey allow him to mature into a wise King.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Cardinal Wolsey</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cardinal Wolsey is King Henry&#8217;s Lord Chancellor and chief adviser. He is deeply ambitious, thoroughly corrupt, and very generous. The son of a butcher, he has made his way up in the world through his own abilities, despite the hatred of noblemen who regard him as an upstart. Despite his protestations, he works for himself before the King, installing his puppets in all the major jobs he can to surround the King with his own people, working against both Katherine and Anne Bullen, and hoping to become Pope. He overtaxes the people behind the King&#8217;s back and refuses to take responsibility for it, bribes witnesses to bring about Buckingham&#8217;s downfall, makes peace treaties without consulting the King, has his own personal symbol added to the coinage, and amasses a vast personal fortune, as he inherited none. He is a slippery speaker, proclaiming his meekness and goodwill, but he is intensely proud, something recognized by all of his enemies, though not by the King, who trusts him implicitly until he sees visual proof of Wolsey&#8217;s machinations. He is named by the Pope co-judge with Campeius of the validity of Queen Katherine&#8217;s marriage to the King. He becomes agitated when he realizes that the King&#8217;s love for Anne Bullen is making him act independently and listen to heretics. He realizes that he is done for as soon as he discovers that the King has read the letters he sent to the Pope and found out how much he has planned to use to bribe his way to the papacy, but he still refuses to accept his fall unless it is confirmed by the King in person. He takes his fall with resignation and philosophy. Despite everything he is loyal to the King. A bureaucrat to the last, he insists on making a complete inventory of all that he owns when it is confiscated by the King. After his death, even his enemies admit that he was a remarkable man, highly generous and a lover of learning. He enjoys a good party, and knows the King well enough to realize that he must be one of the masked men who crash his feast, and recognizes him behind his disguise.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Cardinal Campeius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cardinal Campeius is sent by the Pope to act as co-judge with Wolsey in the matter of the validity of the King and Queen&#8217;s marriage. He becomes friendly with Wolsey, and intends to help him become Pope. With Wolsey, he tries to argue Queen Katherine into agreeing with the King, but in unsuccessful. Unlike Cranmer, he refuses to judge the Queen in her absence. He leaves the country without taking official leave of the King, to the latter&#8217;s wrath.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Capuchius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Capuchius is the ambassador of Queen Katherine&#8217;s nephew, the Holy Roman Emperor. He has not seen Katherine since before her divorce. He is sent by the King to see how Katherine is doing, but is in time only to receive a letter to King Henry that is essentially her will. He promises to do what he can to see it honored.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Cranmer, Archbishop of Canterbury</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cranmer, Archbishop of Canterbury is a priest won over to the reforming side of the church. As a Protestant, he is loathed and despised by conservative Catholics such as Gardiner. As the King&#8217;s divorce proceedings make no progress, Cranmer grows close to the monarch, undoing Wolsey&#8217;s hold on the King. He is an upright, honorable, honest and incorruptible man, whose manner is so different from Wolsey&#8217;s that it gains the King&#8217;s trust after the latter&#8217;s fall. Cranmer is an emotional man, prone to weeping with happiness. He does not defend himself when brought to trial before the royal council, merely insisting on his own honesty and good faith until he is able to counterattack with the King&#8217;s trust in him. He agrees to embrace Gardiner as a friend despite the latter&#8217;s persecution of him. He is named as Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s godfather by the King, and baptizes her, prophesying that she will become the greatest monarch England as ever known. Despite his great humility and goodness, he is capable of sarcasm, and he has no qualms about divorcing the king from Queen Katherine in her absence.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Duke of Norfolk</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Duke of Norfolk is a cautious friend of Buckingham&#8217;s who attempts to keep him for acting or speaking too rashly. He is more charitable than the rest of the nobility, having some admiration for Cardinal Wolsey and not thinking overly ill of him. His opinion changes as the Cardinal&#8217;s actions cause more and more damage, particularly to Queen Katherine, and he joins those working to topple Wolsey. The King sends Norfolk to announce his sentence on the Cardinal. Though he respects Cranmer, Norfolk is a member of the council that attempts to judge him for heresy, having become Earl Marshal, though he takes no active part in the interrogation. He carries the rod of marshalship that identifies him as Earl Marshal in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Duke of Suffolk</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Charles, Duke of Suffolk is one of King Henry&#8217;s close friends and game partners. He thinks it more likely that desire for Anne Bullen explains the King&#8217;s wanting a divorce than remorse over having married his brother&#8217;s widow. He comes to admire Anne once he knows her, and is aware of the plans for her coronation before they are common knowledge. He is not a supporter of Wolsey, and joins in Surrey&#8217;s condemnation of him once he has fallen. He does not play games as well as does the King, unless the latter is distracted. Having become High Steward, he is a member of the council that attempts to judge Cranmer for heresy, though he takes no active part in the interrogation and tried to dissuade the council from bringing Cranmer to trial. He carries the white rod of office that identifies him as High Steward in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Duke of Buckingham</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Duke of Buckingham is a loyal and hot-tempered lord who detests and despises Cardinal Wolsey, and suffers for it. He dislikes Wolsey for a variety of reasons, including his influence with the King, his corruption, and the fact that he is not an aristocrat. His outspoken enmity for the Cardinal, the very mention of whom can send him into a rage, leads to his downfall when he is accused by a vengeful former employee whom Wolsey chooses to listen to. He is found guilty of high treason when he is unable to refute the testimony brought against him. He is an excellent speaker and known as such, and highly educated, but the suspicion of treason on him is high because his father once rebelled against a King (see <NAMEREF>Richard III</NAMEREF>). He dies well.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Earl of Surrey</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Earl of Surrey is Buckingham&#8217;s son-in-law and is delighted to be able to join a plot to topple Cardinal Wolsey, who caused Buckingham&#8217;s fall and sent Surrey to rule Ireland so that he could not be around to plead for him. He spits out accusations at the Cardinal once he has fallen but cannot get him to admit to any wrongdoing. He carries a rod of silver with a dove on it in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession. He is a member of the council that attempts to judge Cranmer for heresy, though he takes no active part in the interrogation.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Chamberlain</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Chamberlain is the head of the King&#8217;s household, an old-fashioned, conservative chauvinist who doesn&#8217;t want to see English noblemen dressing like Frenchmen and who has an eye for the ladies.  Cardinal Wolsey takes care to keep him on his good side, but as the Cardinal&#8217;s arrogance grows so do the Chamberlain&#8217;s worries. He approves of Anne Bullen as the King&#8217;s love, thinking her fit to breed. He is a loyal man who carries out his duties to the fullest and is frustrated when his porter cannot keep a mob from the door.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Chancellor</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Chancellor is King Henry&#8217;s head of government, a position held by Cardinal Wolsey until his downfall. He has charge of the Great Seal, which must be affixed to make a law come into effect, and which is carried in front of him on grand occasions. He takes part in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession, but is a good, conservative Catholic concerned about Cranmer&#8217;s newfangled religious ideas, and heads the meeting of the council that attempts to judge the Archbishop for heresy, and condemns him to the Tower before Cranmer pulls out his trump card of the King&#8217;s favor. Though we are told that Sir Thomas More has taken over the job, historically, by the time of the trial More was no longer Chancellor (see <NAMEREF>Sir Thomas More</NAMEREF> for details).</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Gardiner</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Gardiner, King Henry&#8217;s secretary and later Bishop of Winchester, is entirely Wolsey&#8217;s creature, placed as the King&#8217;s secretary by the Cardinal because he will obey the latter before the former. A conservative Catholic, as bishop he becomes the spearhead of opposition to Anne Bullen, Cranmer, and the other heretics, not hiding his hope that Anne will die in childbirth, even though he escorted her to her coronation. He arranges for Cranmer to be tried by the council, a meeting at which he acts as prosecutor. He is a nasty man, but a smooth and sycophantic flatterer to the King. He agrees to embrace Cranmer as a friend at the King&#8217;s command.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Bishop of Lincoln</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Bishop of Lincoln attends Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial. He is the first prelate that the King turned to when he began to have doubts about the validity of his marriage, and suggested that the matter be tried in the open.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Abergavenny</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Abergavenny is Buckingham&#8217;s son-in-law, and detests Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s as much as the older man, particularly because the terms of the peace with France. He is arrested at the same time as his father-in-law.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Sands</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Walter Sands is a blunt country lord who despises the French fashions invading the English court. He appreciates the presence of young ladies and enjoys flirting with them. He appreciates Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s generosity.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Sir Henry Guilford</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Sir Henry Guilford is a young man who serves Cardinal Wolsey and acts as his master of ceremonies.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Sir Thomas Lovell</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Sir Thomas Lovell is a knight close to the King, who appreciates Wolsey&#8217;s generosity and despises French fashion. He is charged with conducting Buckingham partway to his execution, a task he is not happy with. He comes to let the King know that Queen Anne is in labor, and refuses to be drawn into Gardiner&#8217;s hatred of Protestants.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Sir Anthony Denny</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Sir Anthony Denny is sent by the King to fetch Archbishop Cranmer to the King.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Sir Nicholas Vaux</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Sir Nicholas Vaux is charged with taking custody of the Duke of Buckingham from Lovell, and leading him to his execution. He tries to bring Buckingham in suitable state, but the Duke stops him from doing so, considering it ludicrous to treat him so well when he is about to die.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Cromwell</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>

	Cromwell is Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s prot&amp;eacute;g&amp;eacute;. He loves his master, and is brokenhearted at the Cardinal&#8217;s fall from power. At Wolsey&#8217;s command, he offers his services to the King, and becomes secretary of the royal council. As such he is present at the meeting that attempts to judge Cranmer for heresy. As he himself favors the Protestant cause, he attempts to defend the Archbishop, and earns Gardiner&#8217;s enmity in doing so. He is vindictively overjoyed to see the Archbishop&#8217;s enemies discovering themselves to be on the bad side of the King.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Wolsey's First Secretary</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Wolsey&#8217;s First Secretary follows the Cardinal with his paperwork, including the deposition of Burckingham&#8217;s Surveyor. He later sends out the order rescinding the over-taxation, adding the suggestion that this occurred at the Cardinal&#8217;s suggestion.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Griffith</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Griffith is Queen Katherine&#8217;s Gentleman Usher, in charge of walking before her to official functions and of controlling access to her presence. He remains her servant after her divorce, and can tell her of Wolsey&#8217;s last days. He is a charitable man, willing to speak good of the dead Cardinal to his enemy the Queen after she has listed his faults. He cares greatly for his mistress, and does all that he can to make her passing bearable.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Doctor Butts</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Doctor Butts is the King&#8217;s personal physician.  He is shocked to see Cranmer being treated like a nobody before his trial, and goes to be certain that the King is aware of it.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Garter King-of-Arms</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Garter King-of-Arms is the chief Herald of the realm. As such he is part of the coronation procession of the new Queen, and announces the Princess Elizabeth to the world. He wears a coat emblazoned with a coat of arms and wears a crown on official occasions.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Buckingham&#8217;s Surveyor</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Buckingham&#8217;s Surveyor lost his job when the Duke&#8217;s tenants complained about him. He accuses his former master of treasonable thoughts, producing a great many hearsay details as proof. Buckingham suspects him of having been bribed by Cardinal Wolsey, and Queen Katherine is concerned that he may be acting out of revenge, but he swears he is honest.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Brandon</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Brandon is charged with arresting the Duke of Buckingham and Lord Abergavenny, a task he finds distasteful, along with the others accused of plotting with him. He brings along a sergeant-at-arms to do the official arrest.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Sergeant-at-Arms</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Sergeant-at-Arms is brought by Brandon to arrest the Duke of Buckingham. He carries the silver mace into Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Doorkeeper of the Council Chamber</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Doorkeeper of the Council Chamber is under orders not to let Archbishop Cranmer into the Council Chamber until he is called, despite his rank.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Porter</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Porter is in charge of keeping people out of the palace, but is not having much luck the day of Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s christening. He attempts to beat the crowds back, but even physical violence does not seem to have much of an effect. The enthusiasm of the crowd, and how close they are pressed together, makes him suspect that there will be a lot of new births in nine months&#8217; time. He and his man have to clear a path for the christening procession to pass through, no easy task. He is a cantankerous man at the end of his tether.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Gardiner&#8217;s Page</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Gardiner&#8217;s Page lights his way when he walks about at night, and keeps track of the time.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Crier</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Crier is an official at Queen Katharine&#8217;s trial, whose office is to summon the participants.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Queen Katherine</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Queen Katherine is King Henry&#8217;s wife of twenty years, a Spanish princess, widow of his elder brother Arthur, and the mother of his daughter. She is a kind and intelligent woman beloved by her subjects, whom she cares for deeply. She is an enemy of Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s, but does not engage him directly, preferring to raise matters subtly with the King. She is suspicious of the honesty of Buckingham&#8217;s Surveyor. Her world is turned upside down when the King informs her that he wants a divorce, as he fears that he has done wrong by marrying his brother&#8217;s widow, despite the fact that the wisest men of the time agreed to the marriage at the time, and that this is why they have had no living male child. Passionate and noble, she refuses to agree to the divorce, openly pleads her own cause, and refuses her enemy Wolsey as judge, appealing over his head to the Pope. Having no allies, she is unable to win her cause, though she puts up a valiant fight. She is enraged at being betrayed by the Church, and saddened that she can find no-one to help her, however much the people pity her. She refuses to come to any court to plead her case, and is therefore divorced in her absence. Growing ill in her exile in the country, barely able to walk, she cannot help but be glad to hear of Wolsey&#8217;s death. Despite her disgrace she insists on being treated as a Queen, refusing to acknowledge the change forced on her. Her final thoughts are to beg the King to be good to those that served her, and to keep her honor intact by being buried according to her state. She has a vision of being welcomed into heaven that makes her death much easier to bear. Nobody has a bad thing to say about her.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Anne Bullen</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Anne Bullen is a young lady at court, one of Queen Katherine&#8217;s gentlewomen. One of the guests at Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s feast, she completely charms the King without realizing who the masked gentleman is. Beautiful, kind, pitying, demure and modest, she sees and regrets what is happening to Queen Katherine, and claims that she would not wish to be in her place. Suddenly named Marchioness of Pembroke, she is worried about what this might imply, and hopes that the Queen will not here of this, seeing as Katherine is losing all she has just as Anne begins to receive. She is a Protestant, which earns her Cardinal Wolsey&#8217;s enmity. The King marries her in secret even before his divorce from Katherine is pronounced, and has her crowned once it is official. She then falls pregnant and gives birth to the future Queen Elizabeth.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Old Lady</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Old Lady is Anne Bullen&#8217;s chaperone. A raunchy, worldly woman, she mocks the young woman for her claims to not want a rich position in life. She enjoys suggestive jokes and can see what the King&#8217;s gift to Anne portends. She has been at court for 16 years, but has not profited by it. She becomes one of Anne&#8217;s attendants when the latter becomes Queen, and is one of the women helping her in labor; she brings the news of the child&#8217;s birth to the King, bursting into his presence without respect. Though given a large reward for the news, she aims for more.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Patience</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Patience is Queen Katherine&#8217;s waiting-woman. After Katherine has her vision she sees the change in the Queen&#8217;s complexion and realizes that she is dying. She serves her mistress to the end.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Prologue/Epilogue</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Prologue/Epilogue comes forward to set the tone at the beginning of the play, explaining to which sectors of the audience the play may be expected to appeal, and asking the audience to lend its minds a little to imagining those aspects that the players cannot present. He returns at the end to admit that the play is unlikely to please anyone but women, since it presents them so well, but to suggest that the men will not dare refuse to clap when their lady friends are doing so.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Wolsey's Second Secretary</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Wolsey&#8217;s Second Secretary follows the Cardinal with his paperwork, and informs Wolsey that Buckingham&#8217;s Surveyor is ready to be interrogated.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">First Gentleman</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>First Gentleman is an everyday Londoner who likes to keep up with what&#8217;s going on. He is part of the public witnessing the duke of Buckingham&#8217;s trial, and finds it a pity that he is condemned. He is deeply suspicious of Cardinal Wolsey, a suspicion he shares with his friend the Second Gentleman, who he meets up with again at Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation. This time he has with him a list of all the noblemen receiving new offices on the occasion. He can recognize and knows the names of all the high nobility of the land, and is rather a news junkie. He is cautious enough to know not to badmouth the Cardinal in public.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Second Gentleman</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Second Gentleman arrives too late to actually witness the Duke of Buckingham&#8217;s trial, and must hear of it secondhand from the First Gentleman. He dislikes Cardinal Wolsey, and realizes that the common people do as well. He hears about the troubles between King Henry and Queen Katherine before they are common knowledge, and gossips about them. He does not keep up with the news quite as much as the First Gentleman does, and at their next meeting, at Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation, relies on him for extra details about what&#8217;s going on. He does not recognize all the high personages of the realm. He is deeply impressed by Anne and her beauty.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Tipstaves</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Tipstaves [mute roles] are officers of the court who precede Buckingham as he is led from court to execution; one carries an axe with its blade towards Buckingham, signifying that he is condemned.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Halbadiers</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Halbadiers [mute roles] guard the Duke of Buckingham as he is led to execution.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">First Scribe</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The First Scribe is an official at Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial, and begins the proceedings by ordering that the King be called into the court. He is dressed as a doctor (scholar).</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Second Scribe</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Second Scribe is an official at Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial, and begins the proceedings by ordering that the Queen be called into the court. He is dressed as a doctor (scholar).</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Bishop of Ely</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Bishop of Ely [mute role] attends Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Bishop of Rochester</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Bishop of Rochester [mute role] attends Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Bishop of Saint Asaph</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Bishop of Saint Asaph [mute role] attends Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Priests</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Priests [mute roles] carry silver crosses into Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial, marking the court as a religious one.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Gentleman Purse-Bearer</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Gentleman Purse-Bearer [mute role] follows the Lord Chancellor with a purse containing the Great Seal of England.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Gentlemen Bearers</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Gentlemen Bearers [mute roles] bear silver pillars into Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial. They later carry bowls for receiving gifts in Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s christening procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Archbishop of Canterbury</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Archbishop of Canterbury [mute role] attends Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial, which he agreed the King might hold. He is later replaced by Cranmer.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Noblemen</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Noblemen [mute roles] carry the Sword of State and the Mace, respectively, into Queen Katherine&#8217;s trial, marking it as a high State occasion.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Third Gentleman</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Third Gentleman arrived early enough at Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation to get a good place to see it all, though he ends up escaping from the press of people and the stench of their sweat and bad breath. He is deeply impressed by Queen Anne. He is closer to the court and of higher rank than the First and Second Gentlemen, and knows more of what goes on behind closed doors than they do. He enjoys letting this be known. He is still not quite used to the fact that Wolsey has fallen.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Six Vision Dancers</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Six Vision Dancers, [mute roles] dressed in white, crowned with bays, wearing gold masks and carrying branches of bay or palm dance in a vision Queen Katherine has as she approaches death, seemingly promising her entrance into heaven.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Messenger</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Messenger informs Queen Katherine that Capuchius has come to see her. Aware of her new status as mere Princess Dowager as opposed to Queen, he treats her with much less reverence than she is used to, to her displeasure. He apologizes when he has this pointed out to him, but is banished forever from Katherine&#8217;s sight.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Pursuivants</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Pursuivants [mute roles] are officials of no great importance milling around outside the Council Chamber, with whom Cranmer is forced to mix while waiting to be called in.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Pages</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Pages [mute roles] are boys and young men who attend on the nobility, persons of no great importance who are milling around outside the Council Chamber and with whom Cranmer is forced to mix while waiting to be called in.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Porter&#8217;s Man</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Porter&#8217;s Man has been trying to beat back the crowds pressing in to see the Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s christening, but has only succeeded in breaking his cudgel and being pelted with pebbles by boys. Despite his valor in hitting members of the public on the head, he has been forced back into the palace. Along with the Porter he attempts to clear a pathway for the christening procession to pass along.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Servant</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Servant is a worker in the royal larder, but is trapped in the crowd pressing to see the Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s christening, and cannot get back in to his work despite his pleading with the Porter.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Vergers</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Vergers, [mute roles] carrying short silver wands, open the procession into the Legatine Court, marking this as a religious occasion.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Aldermen of London</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Aldermen of London [mute roles] precede the Lord Mayor in the Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s christening procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Four Noblemen</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Four Noblemen [mute roles] have the honor of carrying the canopy over the Princess Elizabeth in her christening procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Marchioness Dorset</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Marchioness Dorset [mute role] is Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s second godmother.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Princess Elizabeth</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Princess Elizabeth [mute role] is a baby covered with a very rich mantle, who will grow up to be Queen Elizabeth I.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lady</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Lady [mute role] carries the train of the Princess Elizabeth&#8217;s mantle in her christening procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Choristers</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Choristers sing in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Gentlewoman</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Gentlewoman is one of Queen Katherine&#8217;s attendants, who sings while accompanying herself on the lute.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Two Judges</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Two Judges [mute roles] lead the coronation process of Queen Anne, establishing the legal side of the ceremony.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Lord Mayor of London</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lord Mayor of London [mute role] bears his mace of office in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Marquess Dorset</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Marquess Dorset [mute role] carries the royal scepter in Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Four Barons of the Cinque Ports</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Four Barons of the Cinque Ports [mute roles] are noblemen from the five cities on the shore of the narrowest part of the English Channel, that defend against invasion. They have the honor of holding a canopy over the new Queen&#8217;s head in her coronation procession.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Bishop Stokesly of London</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Bishop Stokesly of London [mute role] escorts Queen Anne to her coronation.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Duchess of Norfolk</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Duchess of Norfolk [mute role] is an old lady, who has the honor of carrying Queen Anne&#8217;s train in her coronation procession. She is later named godmother to the newborn Princess Elizabeth, and carries the baby to and from her christening.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Countesses</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Countesses [mute roles] form the end of Queen Anne&#8217;s coronation procession. They wear small crowns denoting their rank.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Gentleman</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Gentleman is shocked and appalled that the Old Lady should attempt to burst in on the King, but is unable to hold her back from doing so.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="">Council Guards</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Council Guards [mute roles] are called in to escort Cranmer to the Tower.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
  </PERSONAE>