<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<PERSONAE playtitle="Julis Caesar">
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CAES. SERV.">Caesar's Servant</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Caesar&#8217;s Servant brings his master the disturbing news that the augurers sacrificed a beast in which they could not find a heart.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="POR.">Portia</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Portia is the daughter of Cato and the wife of Brutus. She is proud of both of these, and is the definition of a stoic Roman woman. Highly intelligent, she cannot be fobbed off by Brutus&#8217;s excuses, as she knows him too well. She insists on sharing all that she can of his life. She is worried about him and his intentions, and when Brutus leaves for the Capitol intent on killing Caesar, she is a nervous wreck. When civil war breaks out and she realizes the strength of Brutus&#8217;s enemy, she commits suicide.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CAL.">Calphurnia</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Calphurnia is Caesar&#8217;s wife. She is barren, which Caesar hopes will be cured during the race at Lupercal if Antony touches her as he passes by. She is disturbed by bad dreams the night before Caesar&#8217;s death, premonitory nightmares which cause her to cry out in fear in her sleep. Though she has never trusted in premonitions before, she attempts to keep Caesar from going to the Capitol, convinced that it would mean his death. She is partly successful, but Decius&#8217;s re-interpretation of her dream carries more force with Caesar, who leaves with his murderers.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="PIN.">Pindarus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Pindarus is Cassius&#8217;s Parthian bondman. With some regret, he kills Cassius at the latter&#8217;s request as the price of his freedom, and flees somewhere where he&#8217;ll never be found.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="DAR.">Dardanius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Dardanius is a soldier in Brutus&#8217;s army, one of the last to survive and follow him. He refuses to help Brutus kill himself.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="LUC.">Lucius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lucius is Brutus&#8217;s young servant. He finds one of the anonymous letters left to spur Brutus on in his master&#8217;s study, and is confused when Portia sends him to look at Brutus arriving at the Capitol without having any message to send or receive. He follows Brutus to the wars, caring for him and also serving as a guard. He plays an instrument and sings for Brutus when the latter requests it, even when he is deeply tired.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="STRA.">Strato</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Strato is a soldier in Brutus&#8217;s army. He accepts to hold the sword Brutus throws himself on. This sign of obedience convinces Octavius to take him into his service, which he accepts on condition that Messala give him a reference.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CLAU., BOTH VAR. AND CLAU.">Claudio</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Claudio is a sentry in Brutus&#8217;s army, charged with guarding Brutus&#8217;s tent at night.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CLI.">Clitus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Clitus is a soldier in Brutus&#8217;s army, one of the last to survive and follow him. He refuses to help Brutus kill himself.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="VAR., BOTH VAR. AND CLAU.">Varrus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Varrus is a sentry in Brutus&#8217;s army, charged with guarding Brutus&#8217;s tent at night.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="VOL.">Volumnius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Volumnius is an officer in Brutus&#8217;s army, and an old schoolfellow of his. He refuses to help Brutus kill himself.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CATO.">Young Cato</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Young Cato is a soldier in Brutus&#8217;s army. Portia&#8217;s brother, he is as proud of his lineage as she is, and truly believes in the conspirators&#8217; cause. He dies proudly proclaiming both these facts.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="MES.">Messala</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Messala is a messenger in Brutus&#8217;s army. He brings the news of the massacre of Senators perpetrated by the triumvirate. He is somewhat taken aback by the extent of Brutus&#8217;s stoicism in the face of the news of his wife&#8217;s death. Captured by Octavius, he vouches for Strato&#8217;s character after the latter tells him how Brutus died.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="TIT.">Titinius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Titinius is an officer in Cassius&#8217;s army. Sent to see whether an approaching troop is friendly or not, he returns with good news to Cassius only to find the latter dead. A true Roman loyalist, he commits suicide to join his commander.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="LUCIL.">Lucilius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lucillius is an officer in Brutus&#8217;s army. Highly loyal, he pretends to be Brutus on the battlefield in the hopes of being killed and thereby giving Brutus a chance to live. Though this fails, the time spent in his capture and recognizing him does buy Brutus time to flee.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="POET.">A Poet</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Poet is a companion of Cassius. He has little sense of rhythm or rhyme, and attempts (poorly) to moralize to Brutus and Cassius.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CIN. POET.">Cinna, a Poet</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cinna the Poet has the misfortune of having the same name as one of Caesar&#8217;s murderers, and of not being known for good writing. He is torn to pieces by a mob.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="SOOTH.">Soothsayer</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Soothsayer warns Caesar of the Ides of March, without giving any further details, being thereby accounted a dreamer. As he goes to the Capitol on the day, he is accosted by Portia, who worriedly questions him. When Caesar complacently suggests that he was wrong, the Soothsayer warns him that he is not considering everything.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="ART.">Artemidorus of Cnidos</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Artemidorus learns of the conspiracy against Caesar and attempts to warn him, but is unable to get his message through.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="MUR.">Murellus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Murellus is one of the Tribunes of the People of Rome. He is incensed to see common workers leaving aside their jobs on a day when they are not allowed to do so, particularly as they do so to honor Caesar. He reminds them that they are celebrating Caesar&#8217;s victory over a man they used to love and honor. Convinced by his fellow Tribune Flavius to remove the marks of favor from Caesar&#8217;s images throughout the city, he is arrested and never heard from again.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="FLAV.">Flavius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Flavius is one of the Tribunes of the People of Rome. He is incensed to see common workers leaving aside their jobs on a day when they are not allowed to do so, particularly as they do so to honor Caesar. He convinces his fellow Tribune Murellus to go and remove all signs of honor from Caesar&#8217;s images throughout the city, in the hopes of keeping Caesar humble. For this he is arrested and never heard from again.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CIN.">Cinna</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cinna is one of the conspirators against Caesar. He has a distinct way of walking. He leaves one of the anonymous letters for Brutus, and is one of the more enthusiastic killers. An unfortunate poet with his name is torn to pieces by a mob instead of him.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="MET.">Metellus Cimber</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Metellus Cimber is one of the conspirators against Caesar. He suggests Ligarius as another possible member of their cause. He is charged with begging Caesar for his brother&#8217;s repeal, thereby giving the conspirators the opportunity to surround Caesar before killing him.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="DEC.">Decius Brutus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Decius Brutus is one of the conspirators against Caesar. He attends the meeting at Brutus&#8217;s house when they bind each other to the murder, and queries whether only Caesar should die. He goes to Caesar&#8217;s house to urge him to go to the Capitol, reinterpreting Calpurnia&#8217;s foreboding dream, claiming that the Senate intends to give Caesar a crown, and playing on his vanity. He is one of those who kneels to surround Caesar and prevent him from fleeing.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="LIG.">Caius Ligarius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Caius Ligarius is one of the conspirators against Caesar. He spoke well of Pompey and was mistreated by Caesar for doing so, which he bears against the dictator. Learning that Brutus is involved in the conspiracy, he visits him to be certain of his purpose, and on being reassured joins in with the others whole-heartedly.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="TREB.">Trebonius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Trebonius is one of the conspirators against Caesar. He attends the meeting at Brutus&#8217;s house when they bind themselves to the murder. He is charged with getting Antony out of the way prior to the deed, and witnesses his flight from the Capitol. He also presses a suit on Caesar that distracts the dictator from reading Artemidorus&#8217;s petition. </DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CASCA.">Casca</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Casca is a cynical Roman with no great taste for Caesar&#8217;s fooling over the crown. He disdains the mob and their poor oral hygiene as much as he disdains Cicero&#8217;s elitist erudition. His poise is shattered by the storm and eerie events of the night, and in that state is convinced by Cassius of the need for Caesar&#8217;s death. He agrees with the need to have Brutus on board for the sake of convincing the people of the justness of their cause. He at first wants Cicero to be asked to join as well, but Brutus quickly convinces him otherwise. He is the first to strike Caesar at the Capitol.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CAS.">Cassius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cassius is a noble Roman, and the mastermind behind Caesar&#8217;s assassination. He observes people and takes little enjoyment from life other than what allows for a sardonic smile. He is pettily jealous of Caesar for being, as he sees it, a weaker human being than he is himself, and despises those who make him out to be almost a god. He plays on Brutus&#8217;s honor and descent from the Brutus who freed Rome from monarchy to have him join him in murdering Caesar. Once he has succeeded in doing so, however, he quickly loses his place at the head of the conspiracy to Brutus. He agrees to Brutus&#8217;s willingness to let Antony live, and his later letting Antony speak to the crowd, but with deep misgivings. He and Brutus fall out further during the war over a series of miscommunications over financing, but they reconcile themselves. He considers himself a better soldier than Brutus, and his instinct not to bring the fight to the enemy is the right one, but again he allows Brutus&#8217;s arguments to sway him. He grows superstitious at the war goes on, despite his previous scoffing at omens. Convinced that all is lost when his army is beaten by Antony&#8217;s, and that Brutus has also been defeated, he has his bondman kill him, thus dying as he had promised to rather than be captured.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="BRU.">Marcus Brutus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Brutus is a noble Roman, descended from the Brutus who liberated Rome from the tyrannical monarchy of the Tarquins. He is greatly honored for his lineage and personal nobility by the people of Rome, and Caesar is particularly shocked to find him among those stabbing him to death. A logician, he is able to talk himself into anything, including the murder of Caesar, while never noticing how his logic forever betrays him. He desperately attempts to keep the conspiracy honorable, neither requiring an oath nor murdering anyone other than Caesar. Believing that everyone will be swayed by good logical argument, he thinks that the people of Rome will approve of the nobility of their act. He offers the mob of plebeians a prose logic-chopping to explain his acts, and at first carries the day, but Antony&#8217;s open emotionalism quickly overturns this. He falls out with Cassius during the war over misunderstandings about money, but is reconciled to him. He still offers strong logical reasons for bad decisions that will in the end cost them the war. He loves and admires his wife, a being at least as stoical and honorable as he. He plays the part of the stoical Roman well: when Messala brings him news of Portia&#8217;s death, he does not let on that he is already aware of it, leaving the messenger to wonder at the strength of his response. He disapproves of his father-in-law Cato&#8217;s suicide, but resolves to do the same if need be to avoid being captured. He is fond of his servants and treats them well, and enjoys music. At first frightened by Caesar&#8217;s ghost, he takes heart again, but its second appearance to him, at the battle of Philippi, convinces him that his life is at an end. Needing assistance to end his own life, he has a very difficult time finding anyone willing to help him. None of his old friends will, only a soldier he barely knows. In death, he is admired as being the only one of the conspirators to have joined in the deed for an idealistic reason.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="POP.">Popilius Lena</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Popillius is a Senator of Rome. He knows that Cassius has something in mind at the Capitol, and wishes him luck, bringing about a moment of fear for the conspirators.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="PUB.">Publius</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Publius is a Senator of Rome. An old man, he pushes Artemidorus aside when the latter tries to give his letter to Caesar. Present at the murder, he does not flee with the rest of the crowd, but remains in place in shock. He is sent out by the killers to tell the world that nobody else is threatened with harm.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CIC.">Cicero</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Cicero is a Senator of Rome. An older, gray-haired man, he is rather an elitist, he is highly intelligent, given to speaking Greek so that only the educated can understand him, dislikes being crossed by anyone, and will not join anything he has not himself begun, this last being the only reason he is not asked to join the conspiracy against Caesar. He possesses a strong reputation for wisdom among the population. He is put to death during the purges carried out by Octavius and Antony after Caesar&#8217;s death.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="LEP.">M. Aemilius Lepidus</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Lepidus is a Senator of Rome. He is present at Caesar&#8217;s death, and flees from it. An excellent soldier if not the most intelligent of men, he becomes the third ruler of Rome along with Octavius and Antony after Caesar&#8217;s death. He acquiesces in his brother&#8217;s execution during the triumvirate&#8217;s takeover. His further adventures can be found in Antony &amp; Cleopatra.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="ANT.">Mark Antony</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Mark Antony is Caesar&#8217;s closest companion. A young man much given to reveling, enjoying music and plays, he runs in the sacred race of the Feast of Lupercal, touching Calpurnia on the way in the hopes of curing her barrenness. A great upholder of obedience to Caesar, he is not as good a judge of men as his mentor, discounting Caesar&#8217;s opinion of Cassius. Brutus underestimates him severely, considering little more than an extension of Caesar. Antony manages to con the conspirators, particularly Brutus, into letting him speak to the crowd after the murder. He accepts to say nothing negative about the conspirators in his funeral oration, and circumvents this by his constant references to them as &#8216;honorable men&#8217;. In contrast to Brutus&#8217;s prose logic-chopping, he gives a shrewdly emotional speech to the crowd, showing them Caesar&#8217;s body and reading them his will, whipping them to a fury. He is ruthless enough to add his own nephew to the list of Romans to be purged once he, Octavius and Lepidus join forces to resist the conspirators. He has little use for Lepidus and does not appreciate Octavius&#8217;s lack of respect for his greater age and experience. Once Brutus is dead, he is willing to praise him for his idealism. His further adventures can be found in Antony &amp; Cleopatra.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="OCT.">Octavius Caesar</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Octavius is Caesar&#8217;s nephew. Called to Rome by his uncle, he is greeted on its outskirts by the news of Caesar&#8217;s death. Despite Antony&#8217;s warnings, he enters Rome before it is safe, and goes to Caesar&#8217;s house, where he meets Lepidus and Antony. He is not easily impressed, and refuses to let Antony take the main leadership role in the war against the conspirators, simply announcing what he intends to do and letting the other deal with the fact. This does not necessarily serve him well: he is not as great a general as Antony, and his force is defeated by Brutus&#8217;s at the battle of Philippi. He is defiant towards the conspirators, though willing to honor them once they are dead. He is proud of his family name. His further adventures can be found in Antony &amp; Cleopatra.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CAES.">Julius Caesar</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Julius Caesar is a great general of Rome, who has recently won a civil war against Pompey and returns to Rome in triumph. He is beloved by many, almost to idolatry, and hated by some. He is somewhat old, not as physically powerful as he believes, deaf in the left ear, and subject to epileptic fits. He is also pompous and given to speaking of himself in the third person. He is hopeful that his wife&#8217;s barrenness may be cured during the Feast of Lupercal. A good leader of men, he has good instincts about them that he does not always listen to. He refuses to be crowned king when the crowd approves his refusal, despite an evident desire to accept the crown. He is swayed by his wife&#8217;s fears for a time, but the thought of receiving a crown, and appeals to his vanity &#8212; such as the thought that he might be considered a coward &#8212; convince him to go to the Capitol in spite of Calpurnia&#8217;s premonitions. He plays the role of Caesar to the hilt, insisting on his constancy, equanimity, and refusal to budge. He does not notice how he is surrounded when the conspirators kneel to prevent him from fleeing, and is shocked that Brutus is among the men stabbing him. He returns as a Ghost to warn Brutus that they will meet again at Philippi. Brutus takes his second appearance as a sign that his time is come.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="MESS.">Messenger</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Messenger brings Octavius and Antony the news that Brutus and Cassius&#8217;s armies are marching.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="OCT. ATT.">Octavius&#8217;s Attendant</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Octavius&#8217;s Attendant is sent by his master to give Antony a message, and arrives at the Capitol to find him with Caesar&#8217;s body. He helps Antony carry Caesar&#8217;s body to the Forum, where he witnesses Antony&#8217;s speech before returning to Octavius to tell him which way the wind is blowing. He returns to Antony to tell him where to find Octavius, and of the conspirators&#8217; flight.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="COB.">Cobbler</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Cobbler leaves his shop to go see Caesar&#8217;s triumph, and takes the whole day off. He encourages others to do the same. He is not impressed by the Tribunes who ask him why he is not working, and twits them mercilessly before finally answering their questions.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="2. SOL.">Second Soldier</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>Second Soldier in the conspirators&#8217; army gives the order to cease marching to his fellow men. He may be either Brutus&#8217;s or Cassius&#8217;s follower.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="1. SOL.">First Soldier</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>First Soldier in the conspirators&#8217; army gives the order to cease marching to his fellow men. He may be either Brutus&#8217;s or Cassius&#8217;s follower.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="5. PLEB., ALL PLEBEIANS.">Fifth Plebeian</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Fifth Plebeian is convinced by Brutus&#8217;s speech explaining the murder of Caesar and believes that the murderer will have all of Caesar&#8217;s qualities and none of his vices. He is then quickly convinced by Antony&#8217;s speech that this opinion is wrong. He remembers that Caesar refused to take a crown the day before, and is insistent on hearing the will. He helps to foment the mob&#8217;s rampage.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="4. PLEB., ALL PLEBEIANS.">Fourth Plebeian</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Fourth Plebeian is at first convinced by Brutus&#8217;s explanation for the murder of Caesar, calling for a statue to be raised to the murderer, but he is willing to listen to Antony. The latter&#8217;s speech causes him some doubts, and he is soon fully convinced that the conspirators were unworthy murderers. He is emotional, moved by the sight of Antony&#8217;s tears and pledging to die for him. He joins the rampaging mob. He is not a fan of poetry.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="3. PLEB., ALL PLEBEIANS.">Third Plebeian</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Third Plebeian knows Brutus to be noble, and soon wishes to have him in charge of Rome. By calling for Brutus to be the new Caesar, he both offers evidence that the conspirators&#8217; fears of Caesar&#8217;s dictatorship were founded and that he has completely mistaken Brutus&#8217;s point. Knowing Antony to be noble, he is convinced by his speech as well. Joining the revengeful mob, he helps tear Cinna the poet to pieces before telling the others exactly which houses to burn down.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="2. PLEB., ALL PLEBEIANS.">Second Plebeian</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The Second Plebeian follows Cassius to hear his explanation for Caesar&#8217;s murder. He joins the mob murdering Cinna the poet.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="1. PLEB., ALL PLEBEIANS.">First Plebeian</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>The First Plebeian chooses to listen to Brutus when the latter comes forward to explain his murdering Caesar. He is easily convinced that Caesar was a tyrant, but Antony&#8217;s speech causes him some doubts. He is soon converted to Antony&#8217;s cause by the sight of Caesar&#8217;s body, and is the first to suggest arson, calling on his fellows to burn the conspirators&#8217; houses with torches lit at Caesar&#8217;s pyre once they have honorably immolated the corpse. He knows that Cinna is the name of one of the conspirators, and helps to tear to pieces the first man of that name he and his companions come across.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
    <PERSONA>
      <NAME short="CAR.">Carpenter</NAME>
      <DESCRIPTION>A Carpenter leaves his shop to go see Caesar&#8217;s triumph, dressed in his best clothes.</DESCRIPTION>
    </PERSONA>
  </PERSONAE>