<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="King John">

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="LADY F.">Lady Faulconbridge</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Faulconbridge is a lady of Northamptonshire and widow of Sir Robert Faulconbridge. Some years ago, when her husband was off on an embassy, she had a brief fling with the then-king, Richard Coeur-de-Lion (the Lionhearted), which resulted in the birth of her son Philip; her second son, Robert, was born to her actual husband. When she hears that her two sons have gone to court to work out who should be the heir, she rushes after to defend her honor. She insists that Philip is legitimate until she hears that he has denied his name himself and been knighted, upon which she immediately admits that he is indeed a bastard, though she insists that it took King Richard some time to seduce her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="BLANCH.">Blanch of Spain</persname>
<persdescription>Blanch of Spain is King John&#8217;s niece and daughter to the King of Castile. She is an obedient girl who is willing to be used as a political pawn until war breaks out again and she finds her loyalties torn. Somewhat na&#239;ve, she is shocked to discover that she cannot restore the peace her marriage was meant to seal by pleading. Once married, however, she follows custom and accompanies her husband, even though he is on his way to wage war on her uncle. She shows some evidence of a mocking tongue, though she may simply be a wide-eyed, admiring girl.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="CONST.">Constance</persname>
<persdescription>Constance is the widow of King John&#8217;s elder brother Geoffrey, and Prince Arthur&#8217;s mother. Convinced of her son&#8217;s right to the throne (and of the danger to his life if John remains in power), she calls on Philip of France to help her have Arthur declared King of England. A high-spirited woman, she does not understand the concept of diplomacy, flying into rages at the least provocation. She is an excellent ranter who knows how to use language to her advantage, but she is careless, insulting everybody who does her the faintest slight. She does not like many people, but is still shocked when the men who had sworn to uphold her casually break their oaths. An expert mocker, she hates her mother-in-law Elinor. She nevertheless hopes that things can be resolved without bloodshed. Possessed of a melodramatic character, Constance is sometimes thought by others to be playing a role; but however wildly expressed, her emotions are genuine and deeply felt. She adores her son, and is (rightly) terrified of what may happen to him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="EL.">Queen Elinor</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Elinor, widow of Henry II, is King John&#8217;s mother. History&#8217;s Eleanor of Aquitaine, she is an old and decrepit woman still in full possession of her senses. She is much stronger-willed (and more intelligent) than her son; she is also still quite capable of flirting with her newly-discovered grandson, the Bastard. She is John&#8217;s chief counselor, and fully aware that his claim to the throne is less than strong. Adept at diplomacy, she believes it is a better solution than war, and quickly sees the benefit of Hubert&#8217;s suggestion that Blanch and Lewis marry. Her reputation is not good, possibly with good reason: she may have forged a will to allow John to succeed to the throne, and may also distract Arthur specifically so that John can entice Hubert into murdering the boy. Living mostly in France, she is John&#8217;s chief information-gatherer about the preparations for war, and her death leaves him ill-informed about the coming French invasion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CHAT.">Chatillion</persname>
<persdescription>Chatillion is a nobleman of France, set as an ambassador by King Philip to John, to formally challenge the latter&#8217;s right to the throne. He is overtaken on the trip to France by John&#8217;s forces, and arrives back at Philip&#8217;s side only just in time to warn the latter that the English army is at hand.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MEL.">Melune</persname>
<persdescription>Melune is a French Count, a friend of Hubert de Burgh&#8217;s, and one of Lewis&#8217;s chief counselors during the Dolphin&#8217;s war against England. He is among the French lords who swear to kill the rebellious English lords once the war is won. When he is mortally wounded in battle, however, his conscience awakens, and he remembers that along with having English friends, his grandfather was English; he therefore reveals the plot to the rebels.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PAND.">Cardinal Pandulph</persname>
<persdescription>Pandulph is the Cardinal of Milan and a legate of the Pope, sent to enforce obedience from John. Full of his own authority, he is a sly, hair-splitting politician, and a very persuasive man. In his quest to bring John to heel, he excommunicates the English King and threatens the French monarch with the same sentence if he does not immediately make war on John. He has little sympathy for Constance, whose claims for her son he finds rather a distraction from the main point of John&#8217;s disobedience. He tempts Lewis into invading England, and uses this invasion as an argument that persuades John to submit himself to the Pope. Having no more need of the French army, he attempts to call off the attack, but a little too late. When Lewis realizes that his invasion has failed, he uses Pandulph as a go-between to negotiate terms with the English.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AUST.">Lymoges, Duke of Austria</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Austria, also called Lymoges, was responsible for the death of the previous King of England, Richard Coeur-de-lion (the Lionhearted). He is a foolish braggart who goes around wearing a lion-skin in memory of that fact, betrays his oaths easily, and threatens while rarely acting on his threats. Taunted by the Bastard, he finds himself beheaded by the latter in combat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LEW.">Lewis, the Dauphin</persname>
<persdescription>Lewis is the Dauphin (heir to the throne) of France, and King Philip&#8217;s son. Like his father a good speaker of empty phrases, he is quite willing to marry Blanch for political reasons and speak the part of the lovelorn swain, but he is far more hot-blooded than Philip and likes a good opportunity for war. He is able to be swayed by Pandulph into making war in his own right for the throne of England, and once he has been convinced to do so refuses to step back, not intending to merely be Pandulph&#8217;s tool. He is a young man, and rather cold; while he accepts the services of the rebellious English noblemen, he fully intends to execute them once they have served their purpose. He is also proud and foolish, not realizing the extent to which his success in England is tied to Pandulph. When the English lords hear of his plans for their deaths and return to John, he does finally accept that he will not win, and goes back home.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="K. PHI.">Philip, King of France</persname>
<persdescription>Philip, King of France, is an able politician who uses Constance&#8217;s claims on behalf of Arthur as an excellent excuse to make war on England and try to wrest control of England&#8217;s lands in France. When he sees an opportunity to acquire those lands without wasting any blood, he is quick to seize it. He is not overly troubled by his oaths, and is quick to join with whoever suits his purposes best. However, he is enough of a loyal son of the Church that when John is excommunicated he is convinced by Pandulph to abandon his recent agreement with the English king &#8212; though it may be that seeing John in a bad position, he simply realizes that this would be a good time to fight him. He is a good speaker of empty phrases, and though he feels some pity for Constance, he in general dismisses her and thinks that she overplays her part. He gives over the war against England to his son Lewis.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PETER.">Peter of Pomfret</persname>
<persdescription>Peter of Pomfret is a poor man who has foreknowledge of the future, and tells everyone he meets that John will give up his crown before Ascension Day. This leads to his arrest and imprisonment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GUR.">James Gurney</persname>
<persdescription>James Gurney is a servant of the Faulconbridges, who accompanies Lady Faulconbridge when she rushes to court to defend her honor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BAST.">Philip, the Bastard</persname>
<persdescription>The Bastard, first known as Philip Faulconbridge, is knighted and renamed as Sir Richard Plantagenet by King John when the latter comes to agree that the young man is his brother Richard the Lionhearted&#8217;s bastard son. An excellent fighter, hugely energetic, the Bastard is glib and extraordinarily cheeky, to the extent that John sometimes has to rein him in. Utterly guileless, he has no qualms about giving up a guaranteed income for the sake of a new name and the opportunities afforded by serving the King. He is a charmer, quickly getting his grandmother Elinor&#8217;s approval and becoming one of John&#8217;s closest advisers. He is loyal to his uncle, and thinks nothing of being sent to ransack monasteries to find money for the wars. Impatient with the dithering of the citizens of Angers, he suggests that the town be destroyed before anyone decides who owns it, while seeing the advantage that the enemy might end up destroying itself at the same time. He is a fair man, willing to fight Salisbury to allow Hubert have a chance to explain himself, even though he shares Salisbury&#8217;s opinion of the man. John gives him complete command of the English forces to fight off the French after Pandulph fails to arrange a peace. The Bastard grows up over the course of the play: starting as merely high-spirited, his experience with politics soon makes him extremely cynical about the world, and he resolves to make the most of it; but he slowly comes to realize that there are things more important, and he leads the English noblemen in their resolve to keep their land free from French invasion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ROB.">Robert Faulconbridge</persname>
<persdescription>Robert Faulconbridge, son of Sir Robert Faulconbridge, is a young gentleman of Northamptonshire who is convinced that his elder brother Philip is in fact the bastard son of the former King. Since if this were proved, he would become his father&#8217;s heir, to the tune of 500 pounds a year, he decides to openly challenge the inheritance, despite what this does to his mother&#8217;s reputation. He is thin, with spindly legs; he is also earnest and much duller than his brother like most people.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HUB.">Hubert de Burgh</persname>
<persdescription>Hubert de Burgh is a leading citizen of Angers, a town in France belonging to England. He refuses to open the gates of the town to either John or Philip until they have settled between them who ought to be King of England, hoping that this will avoid having his town sacked by either party. When at the Bastard&#8217;s suggestion the two instead team up to destroy Angers first, Hubert quickly comes up with another plan, the marriage of Blanch and Lewis. With John therefore confirmed as King of England, Hubert rallies to his side and becomes a trusted ally &#8212; enough that John entrusts him with Arthur&#8217;s death. Unfortunately for John, Hubert turns out to be a soft-hearted fellow, who becomes great friends with Arthur and in the end cannot bring himself to blind the boy. He pretends to John that he has gone through with the execution, but when he finds John casting all the blame on him, he first points out that he received orders, and then admits that Arthur is alive. He remains loyal to John despite everything, and when the latter is poisoned rushes to find the Bastard. Hubert attempts to do what is right, but is often confused as to what that might be. He looks like an evil man, and this prompts others to think the worst of him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BIG.">Lord Bigot</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Bigot is one of John&#8217;s noblemen. He joins Salisbury and Pembroke in their search for Arthur&#8217;s body. Arthur&#8217;s death convinces him to join the others in their betrayal of John. He stands upon his rank and uses it as an insult against Hubert, as well as calling the Bastard by his original name, not acknowledging his royal blood.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SAL.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>Earl of Salisbury is one of King John&#8217;s noblemen. He is sent to give the news of the peace between France and England to Constance, and is uncomfortable in the duty. He dislikes too much pomp and is appalled at John&#8217;s decision to be crowned a second time, though he accepts that the King&#8217;s orders must be obeyed. An upright and honorable man, he refuses to follow John any longer when he comes to believe that the King has had Arthur murdered. He vows to revenge Arthur&#8217;s death on finding the boy&#8217;s body, refusing to have any trust in Hubert&#8217;s protestations of innocence. He is the first of the rebellious nobles to make contact with the army of France, and leads them in their desertion to Lewis&#8217;s side. He is torn by his rebellion, however. Warned by Melun of Lewis&#8217;s treachery, he leads the rebellious nobles in returning to the King of England, and is present at John&#8217;s death. He is insulting when roused to anger, refusing to give the Bastard his new name of Plantagenet and instead referring to him as Faulconbridge.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ESSEX.">Earl of Essex</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Essex is one of John&#8217;s noblemen. He is the first to hear of the Faulconbridge dispute, and asks that John judge it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PEM.">Earl of Pembroke</persname>
<persdescription>Earl of Pembroke is one of King John&#8217;s noblemen. He lets his disapproval of John&#8217;s second coronation be known, but does not overly object to it, as he had been chosen to be the noblemen&#8217;s spokesman for requesting that Arthur be put at liberty. He knows in advance that John has given orders for Arthur&#8217;s death, and believes in Hubert&#8217;s guilt. He is capable of a sardonic jab at John&#8217;s crocodile tears over the boy. Horrified by Arthur&#8217;s death, he joins Salisbury in rebelling and going over to the French side, where he is worries and bears in mind that a French defeat will mean their lives. He repents on hearing that a French victory will mean their lives as well, and returns with the others to John&#8217;s side, where he attends on the King as he lies dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ARTH.">Arthur</persname>
<persdescription>Arthur, Duke of Britain, is John&#8217;s nephew, the son of his dead older brother Geoffrey. As such, by the laws of primogeniture he has a better right to the throne than John has. Quite young, his rights are pushed forwards far more by his mother than by himself; though he plays his role, he is at best a pawn, pushed around as need be and used as an excuse by Philip. Captured by John, he is given into the keeping of Hubert, to whom he grows very attached. He is a kind-natured boy who feels keenly that all that happens to him and because of him is not his fault. He is for good reason scared of his uncle, though he still finds it hard to believe that John orders his eyes to be put out. He succeeds in pleading for his eyesight and life with Hubert, but he is still afraid and plans to escape. Disguised as a ship-boy, he attempts to escape his prison by jumping from the castle walls, but this is not successful, as he merely ends up dead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="P. HEN.">Prince Henry</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Henry is King John&#8217;s son and heir. He is an obedient child, insistent that his dead father&#8217;s wishes be carried out, and loves his father deeply. He hopes that the poisoned King will heal, but does not truly expect that he will. He is not the jolliest of princes, but he is honorable, and successfully begs John for the pardon of the rebellious lords when they return to the fold.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="K. JOHN.">King John</persname>
<persdescription>King John is the youngest of Elinor&#8217;s three sons and the last one living; he takes the throne despite the fact that the second of the three brothers left an heir. Sly, slippery, and deeply insecure, John is keenly aware of how uncertain his claim to the throne is. He depends a great deal on his mother, following her advice on everything. Though John acts the part of a King well, there is a distinct weakness to him; he relies on others to do things for him, be it Elinor, the Bastard, or Hubert. He refuses to accept the authority of the Pope until he can no longer afford not to, and pillages the monasteries and abbeys of England to pay for his wars. When things go wrong, he tries to plead that he is not at fault; he does not directly order Arthur&#8217;s death, but speaks highly suggestively to Hubert until the latter confirms that he has understood the King&#8217;s wishes. Once he has Hubert&#8217;s agreement, John does however put the order in writing. He loses whatever respect his noblemen had for him when he has himself crowned a second time to reaffirm his title after defeating Arthur&#8217;s supporters; the news of the French invasion and of his mother&#8217;s death disconcert him greatly, and he suddenly finds his position very shaky. He grows depressed after submitting to Pandulph, and gives over the command of his armies to the Bastard. He is poisoned by a monk, and dies after suffering from a high fever. He is a deeply ambiguous figure, as all the other characters are aware.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EXEC.">Executioner</persname>
<persdescription>Executioner does not like to be ordered to help blind a young boy, insisting that the order must be legitimate. He is nevertheless prepared to carry out his job, though he prefers not to witness the actual deed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="E. HER.">English Herald</persname>
<persdescription>English Herald is a representative of John, somewhat in the nature of a press secretary or spokesperson. He announces the score of the battle between John and Philip, insisting that his side won.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="F. HER.">French Herald</persname>
<persdescription>French Herald is a representative of Philip, somewhat in the nature of a press secretary or spokesperson. He announces the score of the battle between John and Philip, insisting that his side won.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SHER.">Sheriff</persname>
<persdescription>Sheriff [mute role] brings the case of the Falconbridge inheritance to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">The Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger comes from France to warn John of the coming invasion, of which he is scared. He also has to report the death of the Queen Mother to the King. He is later sent by the Bastard to request that John retreat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FR. MESS.">French Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The French Messenger reports to Lewis that the English lords have abandoned him.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>