<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="King Richard II">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="K. RICH.">King Richard the Second</persname>
<persdescription>Richard II is King of England, John of Gaunt&#8217;s nephew and Bullingbrook&#8217;s cousin. Authoritarian, unwilling to listen to good advice, friendly with persons not of noble birth, he is not the sort of king likely to earn his noblemen&#8217;s love. He over-taxes the country, finding many new ways of raising revenue, most of which appears to be wasted. Richard most likely had some part in his uncle the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s death, and is worried that this will come to light. A great talker, Richard is given to flights of fancy rhetoric, something quite beyond his cousin Bullingbrook. He believes strongly in the divine right of Kings, and when misfortune comes upon him often compares himself to Jesus. He is nevertheless insecure enough that when faced with utter rebellion, he gives up his throne to his cousin without ever being directly asked to do so. He is keenly aware of the dangers attendant on kingship, especially those who are rebelled against, and just how few die a natural death. He is not very sensible, and refuses to listen to the good advice of old people, preferring to listen to his flattering friends. He respects John of Gaunt highly until the latter reproaches him on his conduct, at which point he quite overreacts at the old man. Needing money to fight a war in Ireland, he is foolish enough to confiscate the wealth of the recently-deceased Gaunt, not heeding his uncle York&#8217;s warnings that this will undermine his own right to the throne. Absent from England for a day too long, he is left bereft of friends and quite unable to fight off Bullingbrook&#8217;s rebellion. He is aware that all is over for him apparently even before Bullingbrook has concluded this, and follows orders docilely once he realizes that there is nothing to be done. With no option but to give up the crown, he still manages to completely upstage his cousin while officially relinquishing the state to him. He grows contemplative in prison. Though he has shown no great signs of bravery in the rest of his life, this son of the Black Prince is energetic enough in his own defense when his murderers come upon him, managing to steal a weapon from one and kill two of them before being struck down. By all appearances, he is very fond of his wife.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GAUNT.">John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster</persname>
<persdescription>John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster, is Richard&#8217;s uncle, Bullingbrook&#8217;s father, and probably the most respected man in the kingdom. An old man, he is one of the sons of Edward III. He is deeply loyal, both to the King and to his country, and is broken-hearted that the one is betraying the other. He is also immensely rich, a fact his nephew is well-aware of. He loves his son Bullingbrook dearly, though he expects obedience from the young man. He finds his loyalties divided between love for his son and respect for his sovereign, but he allows the latter to overcome the former, agreeing to Bullingbrook&#8217;s exile despite his wish that his son could stay, and refusing to look too far into the matter of his brother Gloucester&#8217;s murder. He is keenly aware of his age, and frightened at what Richard will do once he is no longer present to offer his counsel &#8212; not that he thinks Richard listens to him much in the first place. When he knows himself dying, he is willing to tell his nephew just what he thinks of his rule, in one last forlorn hope of reforming him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="YORK.">Edmund of Langley, Duke of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of York is Richard&#8217;s uncle, John of Gaunt&#8217;s younger brother; when the latter dies, he is left the last living son of Edward III. An old, easily confused, and rather doddering old man, he is named regent of England by Richard despite his manifest lack of ability for the role. Kindly and well-intentioned, he is desperate to do the right thing. He is fully aware of Richard&#8217;s defects, particularly his extravagance and liking for fashion, but like his brother he is loyal to the crown, though he finds it difficult. He scolds his nephew when the latter appropriates Gaunt&#8217;s wealth after his death, pointing out that denying Bullingbrook his inheritance makes a mockery of Richard&#8217;s own right to the throne. This protest is ineffective, as are most of York&#8217;s protests. He talks a great deal about what he would do if he could, but he generally resigns himself to following the flow of events. His attempt to remain neutral in the contest between Richard and Bullingbrook is a lamentable failure, though he does attempt to restrain Bullingbrook from going too far. He regrets what is done to Richard, but once he has sworn fealty to Bullingbrook as King, he is firm in his loyalty, even to denouncing his son Aumerle at the risk of his life. He is not the most patient of husbands.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BULL.">Henry Bullingbrook</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="K. HEN.">King Henry IV</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Bullingbrook &#8212; or Henry of Derby, Duke of Hereford &#8212; is John of Gaunt&#8217;s son, Richard&#8217;s cousin, and later King Henry IV, once he has removed his cousin from the throne. He is extremely popular with the common people, something which disquiets his cousin. He is much quieter than Richard, less given to rhetorical flights, and is often silent at major turning points in his life. He is an excellent fighter, willing to risk his life on his honor&#8217;s behalf. He adores his father. On the latter&#8217;s death, he returns from exile to claim the lands that Richard has stolen from him. At this stage, he may either be a cunning politician already planning to take the throne, or he may genuinely only intend to claim his inheritance, but in either case events move very quickly. Nevertheless, it is not until his uncle York has agreed not to fight him that he announces his plans to execute the King&#8217;s favorites, taking over a right that he does not technically have. He insists to Richard that he does not intend to depose him, but does not object when his cousin offers to abdicate. Once he is in power, he attempts to sort out the mystery of his uncle the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s death, which was at the root of his banishment, but with no success. Often monosyllabic, he distinguishes himself from Richard by his general refusal to make great speeches or otherwise engage in wordplay. He leaves the dirtier duties of his usurpation to Northumberland, especially the many executions that accompany his takeover. He attempts to be merciful when he can. Though he does not show much evidence of emotion after his return to England, Henry IV is a worried father about his eldest son, who is a wastrel spending all of his time in bars (see later plays for details). He does not order Richard&#8217;s death, but does speak suggestively on the matter in the presence of a man who will take him seriously. Faced with Richard&#8217;s body, he insists he didn&#8217;t want this to happen, and swears to make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem to earn forgiveness for the crime. As will be seen in the later plays starring him (Henry IV Part One and Part Two), he never quite gets around to it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="AUM.">Duke of Aumerle</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. GREEN. AND BAGOT. AND AUM. AND BUSHY.">All Green, Bagot, Aumerle and Bushy</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Aumerle is the son of the Duke and Duchess of York, and therefore Richard and Bullingbrook&#8217;s cousin. He is very much of Richard&#8217;s party; though he asks the exiled Bullingbrook to write to him, he is happy to slander him to the King. Rather a crawler, he overdoes his devotion to Richard somewhat. He accompanies the King to Ireland. When they return to find England almost completely under Bullingbrook&#8217;s control, Aumerle attempts to rally the King and give him some hope. He later counsels the King against fighting to the death. He attempts to bluster his way out of being found guilty of his uncle Gloucester&#8217;s murder, and later joins a conspiracy to kill Bullingbrook after the latter has become King Henry IV. He quickly repents when he is found out, and his mother&#8217;s entreaties save his life. He is not the most intelligent of men, nor the most honorable; arguably he is completely out of his depth in the court.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOW.">Thomas Mowbray</persname>
<persdescription>Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk, is accused by Bullingbrook of having been responsible for the murder of the Duke of Gloucester, as well as of corruption on a grand scale. He forcefully denies all these charges; he also cannot bear to retract his own accusations against Bullingbrook, for fear of losing his honor by taking back what he has said. He sets great store by royal blood, and is cautious in his counter-accusations until reassured by Richard that Bullingbrook&#8217;s nobility will not be weighed in the matter of their quarrel. Deeply attached to England, he is distraught at being exiled. Though he denies having been a traitor to the last, in his exile he goes on crusade, often a way of atoning for sins. He is forty years old.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SURREY.">Duke of Surrey</persname>
<persdescription>Surrey is an English nobleman who swears that Fitzwater is lying about what Aumerle said concerning the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s death. He is an older man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SAL.">Earl of Salisbury</persname>
<persdescription>Salisbury is an English earl loyal to Richard. He attempts to keep a large Welsh force together to help Richard defeat Bullingbrook, but the King&#8217;s late arrival from Ireland prevents this. He is downcast at the mere one-day delay that could have saved the King. He is later executed by Henry IV&#8217;s men under Northumberland&#8217;s command.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BERK.">Lord Berkeley</persname>
<persdescription>Berkeley is an English lord serving the Duke of York. He is careful not to get overly involved in the politics of the moment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BUSHY.">Sir John Bushy</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. GREEN. AND BAGOT. AND AUM. AND BUSHY.">All Green, Bagot, Aumerle and Bushy</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>John Bushy is one of Richard&#8217;s friends, deeply disliked by the nobility for being a commoner and having the King&#8217;s ear. A well-spoken flatterer, he attempts to cheer up the Queen after Richard leaves for Ireland. He grasps immediately that there is little hope of military victory against the returned Bullingbrook. He is executed by the latter on a variety of charges.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BAGOT.">Sir John Bagot</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. GREEN. AND BAGOT. AND AUM. AND BUSHY.">All Green, Bagot, Aumerle and Bushy</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>John Bagot is one of Richard&#8217;s friends, deeply disliked by the nobility for being a commoner and having the King&#8217;s ear. He is perfectly aware that the common people are not overfond of Richard due to his heavy taxation. Rather than join Bushy and Green in hiding at the Earl of Wiltshire&#8217;s when Bullingbrook returns, he chooses to go to Ireland to warn the King. Captured by Bullingbrook, he accuses Aumerle of the Duke of Gloucester&#8217;s death, apparently saving himself by turning state&#8217;s evidence for the new King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GREEN.">Sir Henry Green</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. GREEN. AND BAGOT. AND AUM. AND BUSHY.">All Green, Bagot, Aumerle and Bushy</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Henry Green is one of Richard&#8217;s friends, deeply disliked by the nobility for being a commoner and having the King&#8217;s ear. He convinces Richard of the necessity of going to war in Ireland, but hearing of Bullingbrook&#8217;s return rushes to tell the King not to leave. However, he arrives too late. He is aware that only Richard&#8217;s love keeps him and his other friends safe. He is put to death by Bullingbrook on a variety of charges.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="NORTH.">Earl of Northumberland</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Northumberland is an English nobleman with little love for Richard. When the King leaves for Ireland, Northumberland draws most of the rest of the nobility into a conspiracy against him to help Bullingbrook return. He quickly becomes Bullingbrook&#8217;s second-in-command and hatchet-man, and is the first to begin to regard Richard as deposed. He is a prosaic man, though he manages to entice Richard to leave the security of Flint Castle, and insists that Richard&#8217;s deposing be carried through to the letter as the Commons insist, including forcing Richard to agree that he has done wrong and is therefore justly overthrown. He is quite unsentimental, quick to cease speaking respectfully to the deposed King and to force him and his Queen to part, not to mention arrest the Bishop of Carlisle. He is generally in charge of executions for Henry IV. His further adventures can be found in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PERCY.">Henry Percy</persname>
<persdescription>Harry/Henry Percy is Northumberland&#8217;s son. Quick to join the rebellion in his father&#8217;s wake, he is a good soldier, often used as a scout to discover the strength of castles that might resist. He is willing to swear to Fitzwalter&#8217;s good faith and honor, and is capable of tracking down Bullingbrook&#8217;s wild son. His further adventures are chronicled in <persnameref>Henry IV, Part One</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ROSS.">Lord Ross</persname>
<persdescription>Ross is a nobleman greatly dissatisfied with Richard&#8217;s rule and over-taxation. Afraid of what might come next, he is quickly won over to Bullingbrook&#8217;s rebellion by Northumberland.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WILLO.">Lord Willoughby</persname>
<persdescription>Willoughby is an English nobleman quick to listen to plans in Bullingbrook&#8217;s favor, being exasperated by Richard&#8217;s bad rule and the fear of what new exactions he may come up with. He is particularly unhappy that Richard has raised up commoners like Bushy and Green and allowed them to act like noblemen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FITZ.">Lord Fitzwater</persname>
<persdescription>Fitzwater is a young English nobleman who swears that he heard Aumerle boast of being responsible for the death of the Duke of Gloucester. He is hot-blooded and ready to fight for his cause. Whether or not he is correct is never resolved.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAR.">Bishop of Carlisle</persname>
<persdescription>The Bishop of Carlisle is loyal to Richard out of principle. With the courage of his convictions, he publically speaks up against Bullingbrook&#8217;s taking the throne at the moment the man announces that he will do so. Along with his arguments about the illegality of usurpation, he predicts the whole of the Wars of the Roses (which are explored in Henry IV, Parts One and Two, Henry V, Henry VI, Parts One, Two and Three, and Richard III). He is immediately arrested for doing so. Luckily for him, he is committed to the care of the Abbot of Westminster, who quite agrees with him, and invites him to supper. He is a brave man, quite willing to fight if need be. King Henry leaves him free if he will swear to remain peaceful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ABBOT.">Abbot of Westminster</persname>
<persdescription>Abbot of Westminster is grieved at Richard&#8217;s deposition. Agreeing with the Bishop of Carlisle&#8217;s denunciation of its illegality, he forms a plot to assassinate the new King Henry. This fails when Aumerle, who is in on the conspiracy, accidentally lets his father see a letter on the subject, causing the whole plot to be revealed. The Abbot is executed for this.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MAR.">Lord Marshal</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Marshal is an official at the English court, whose job includes the regulating of tournaments and official duels. He is charged with making certain that all actions in a joust are carried out according to the rules. His role is comparable to that of the referee in a sports game, only with much greater importance, seeing as men will die in these games. He is a friend of Bullingbrook&#8217;s, and insists on accompanying him as far as he can when the latter is banished.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SCROOP.">Sir Stephen Scroop</persname>
<persdescription>Stephen Scroop is a follower of Richard&#8217;s, who comes to tell him of the extent of the rebellion, though he wishes he did not have to. He is present when Richard surrenders to Bullingbrook.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="EXTON.">Sir Pierce of Exton</persname>
<persdescription>Exton is an English knight who is convinced that Henry IV has surreptitiously given him orders to do away with Richard. Certain that acting on his interpretation of Henry&#8217;s words will do him a world of good, he takes his men to kill Richard. The sole survivor, he is left feeling that he has done something wrong. He is shocked when Henry disavows him and his action.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAP.">Welsh Captain</persname>
<persdescription>The Welsh Captain is in charge of an army of Welsh soldiers loyal to King Richard. When the latter does not return from Ireland as expected and his soldiers begin muttering that he is dead, he refuses to stay any longer by Salisbury&#8217;s side, seeing as his men will not. His action dooms the King, as Richard returns to England the day after he and his troops leave. He is superstitious.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="QUEEN.">Queen to King Richard</persname>
<persdescription>The Queen is Richard&#8217;s wife, a French princess. She is devoted to her husband, but has a great feeling of foreboding at his departure for Ireland. She is kept entirely out of the loop of politics, and only finds out about Richard&#8217;s capture when she overhears her gardener talking. She is generally melancholy, though this is mostly in reaction to events. The only action she takes of her own accord is going to see her husband as he is led to prison. She is disconcerted by Richard&#8217;s loss of poise, and disheartened by Northumberland&#8217;s refusal to let her join her husband in prison. She leaves for exile in France in despair.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="DUCH. YORK.">Duchess of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Duchess of York feels a great deal of pity for her nephew Richard after he is deposed and paraded through the streets. Past childbearing age, she is aghast at the idea that her husband would betray their son and send him to his death when the latter joins a treasonous plot. Out of love for her son she is willing to humiliate herself before her nephew. She does not think much of her husband.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="DUCH.">Duchess of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>The Duchess of Gloucester is the widow of the Duke of Gloucester, one of Richard&#8217;s uncles, who was murdered under mysterious circumstances &#8212; most likely at the King&#8217;s orders. She unsuccessfully attempts to convince her brother-in-law, John of Gaunt, to look into his brother&#8217;s death, and is distraught at his refusal. She is convinced of Mowbray&#8217;s guilt in her husband&#8217;s murder. She is friendly with her other brother-in-law, York.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KEEP.">Keeper</persname>
<persdescription>The Keeper is a jailer in charge of Richard in his imprisonment at Pomfret. Ordered by Exton to no longer taste Richard&#8217;s food before giving it to him, he admits as much to the deposed King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GARD.">Gardener</persname>
<persdescription>The Gardener tends the Duke of York&#8217;s gardens. Well-informed about current events, he is adept at relating what the plants in the garden and their problems of the state. He feels great pity for the Queen after he has to inform her of Richard&#8217;s captured state.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERV.">Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>The Servingman announces to York that Aumerle has left. Apparently not possessed of the best of memories, he suddenly remembers to mention that York&#8217;s sister-in-law has died. He is sent to gather the contents of York&#8217;s armory.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="1. LADY.">First Attending Lady</persname>
<persdescription>The First Attending Lady is one of the Queen&#8217;s attendants in her safe place at the Duke of York&#8217;s. She attempts to distract the Queen from her worries, suggesting games or telling tales, but is not successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="2. LADY.">Second Attending Lady</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Attending Lady, like the First, is one of the Queen&#8217;s attendants in her safe place at the Duke of York&#8217;s. A dancer and a singer, she attempts to distract the Queen from her worries, but is not successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. HER.">First Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The First Herald is Bullingbrook&#8217;s servant, and acts as his spokesperson at the tourney.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. HER.">Second Herald</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Herald is Mowbray&#8217;s servant, and acts as his spokesperson at the tourney.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. EXT. SERV.">Exton&#8217;s First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Exton&#8217;s First Servant confirms his master&#8217;s opinion about what Henry IV is expecting in regards to Richard. He is killed by the deposed King while trying to assassinate him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. EXT. SERV.">Exton&#8217;s Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Exton&#8217;s Second Servant confirms his master&#8217;s opinion about what Henry IV is expecting in regards to Richard. He is killed by the deposed King while trying to assassinate him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. GARD. MAN.">First Gardener&#8217;s Man</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gardener&#8217;s Man doesn&#8217;t quite see the purpose of wasting his time on keeping a garden in order when the whole world is in turmoil. That being said, he trusts the Gardener&#8217;s opinion on the matter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. GARD. MAN.">Second Gardener&#8217;s Man</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gardener&#8217;s Man is taken aback at the turn of events in the kingdom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="GROOM.">Groom</persname>
<persdescription>The Groom serves the royal stables, and is still loyal to Richard after his deposition. He sneaks into Pomfret to see the King one last time, where he tells Richard of how his favorite horse went over to Bullingbrook&#8217;s side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANOTHER LORD.">Another Lord</persname>
<persdescription>Another Lord joins with Fitzwater in swearing that Aumerle is lying, and is ready to fight to prove it so. Whether or not he is correct in this is never resolved.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>