<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Love&#8217;s Labour&#8217;s Lost">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="KING.">Ferdinand, King of Navarre</persname>
<persdescription>Ferdinand, King of Navarre, is not the most dedicated monarch in the world, preferring to hide away and study for three years instead of taking care of his kingdom. He even risks insulting his powerful neighbor, France, for the sake of his own pleasure and convenience. He hopes to make his realm an intellectual powerhouse, and as he shares his century&#8217;s opinion of women, he bans them from the court, fearing that they will distract his courtiers from their studies. In that he is quite correct, for the mere appearance of the Princess of France suffices to stop all thought of study, including from the King himself, who falls for her the moment he sees her. Though a great lover of language, he is unaware that he is a terrible writer, and hopes to woo the lady with poetry. He attempts to shame Longaville and Dumaine when he discovers they have broken their oath, but is quickly put in his place by Berowne. For all that he regards Berowne as a great mocker, he is one himself, so far as his dignity allows, and enjoys the opportunity to take him down a peg or too for falling in love with an unfashionably dark-complexioned woman. The King realizes that love is a serious thing when the Princess, now Queen, commands him to go to a hermitage for a year, and accepts to do so. How exactly the kingdom is to be run in his absence is not revealed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BER.">Berowne</persname>
<persdescription>Berowne is a lord at the court of Navarre, among the King&#8217;s best friends and one of the three who agree to join him on his scholarly retreat, though he is rather skeptical of the feasibility of the plan. He has a well-earned international reputation for mockery, and is accepted to be the most intelligent of the courtiers of Navarre, a fact that pleases him. He is looked up to by others, including the King, when it is necessary to get out of a tight spot, as he is able to rationalize anything if need be. He does not expect Rosaline&#8217;s ability to match him in wit, and is put slightly off-kilter by her ability, though even more so by having fallen in love with her. He recognizes that she is unfashionably dark-complexioned, and is amazed that he could fall for her even so. Love has long been the chief subject of his mocking, and he especially likes to comment on bad love poetry, though he commits some himself. Extremely long-tongued, he can riff for hours on a theme when he takes it up, and his linguistic extravaganzas continue even after he swears to give them up. His joking can be extremely nasty at times, and he is called on this by both Holofernes and Rosaline. He accepts Rosaline&#8217;s prescription to take the edge off his humor by spending a year comforting the dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LONG.">Longaville</persname>
<persdescription>Longaville is a tall young lord at the King of Navarre&#8217;s court, one of the three lords who agree to join the King on his scholarly retreat, convinced that three years without good food or women is not so long. Well-educated and a good fighter, he is well-regarded by the world, though he can be a little too nasty in his jokes and blunt in manner. He enjoys the opportunity to take Berowne down a peg by mocking him for falling in love with an unfashionably dark-complexioned woman. He himself, however, is just as strongly infatuated with Maria, and sends her a great deal of bad love poetry, along with a pearl necklace. By the end of the play, he has come to think that twelve months is indeed a long time to be away from Maria, especially as she does promise to marry him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUM.">Dumaine</persname>
<persdescription>Dumaine is a lord at the King of Navarre&#8217;s court, one of the three lords who agree to join the King on his scholarly retreat. The youngest of the four, he looks his age, being as yet unable to grow a beard. Good-looking and good-natured, he is not the brightest, though some of that is simply immaturity. He is an absolutely terrible poet, and inflicts his verses on Katherine when he falls for her, though he has the grace to also send her a present. He enjoys the chance to take Berowne down a peg by mocking him for falling in love with an unfashionably dark-complexioned woman, and also makes the most of the opportunity to laugh at the show of the Nine Worthies. He is concerned at the fact that the ladies thought he and his fellow lords were merely playing at love, but agrees to wait a year before seeing if Katherine will have him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BOYET.">Boyet</persname>
<persdescription>Boyet is a gossipy French lord attending on and counseling the Princess of France, quick to note that the young men have fallen for the ladies. An older man, he enjoys matching wits with the ladies, though either out of lack of ability or out of gallantry he generally allows the lady to win. Other men tend not to like him, as he is much better at becoming friendly with ladies than they are. He joins the lords of Navarre in mocking the pageant of the Nine Worthies. He has a great sense of humor and is delighted to be able to join in all the pranks on the young lords.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ARM.">Don Adriano de Armado</persname>
<persdescription>Don Adriano de Armado is an affected Spanish braggart, a man who thinks himself finer than he actually is and talks in mind-bogglingly fancy language, qualifying every word a dozen ways and taking paragraphs to get to the point. He thinks himself a great friend of the King&#8217;s, being blissfully unaware that he is considered a joke by the courtiers, who rely on him for amusement in their retreat. A dandy following all the latest fashions, including linguistic ones, he is in love with the completely unsophisticated Jaquenetta, and pursues her in all the ways a courtier is meant to, with poor results. He has a close relationship with his pageboy Moth, whom he relies on for conversation, even though the boy generally gets the better of him in battles of wit. Armado considers himself a soldier at heart. Humbled when it is publicly disclosed that Jaquenetta is pregnant by him and he is openly mocked by the lords, he sees himself for what he is, and has the decency to commit to becoming a mere peasant for Jaquenetta&#8217;s sake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="NATH.">Sir Nathaniel</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Nathaniel is the local curate, a man greatly impressed by Holofernes&#8217;s learning and by his own. He is always ready to give up his own opinions when the pedant tells him that they are wrong. He is convinced that being learned makes a man better than others, but there is no real malice in him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="HOL.">Holofernes</persname>
<persdescription>Holofernes is a pedant, and the local schoolteacher. He is highly respected by Nathaniel the curate and others for his learning and his abilities with language. A snooty linguistic prescriptivist, he is horrified at changes in the language and what he regards as mispronunciations, and uses them as an excuse to look down their users. His own literary endeavors are marked by an overreliance on alliteration, while his manner of speaking is afflicted with the need to offer several separate words to explain one concept, as though to prove that he has memorized a thesaurus. He is unable to ignore the mockery of the lords when he presents himself in the pageant of the Worthies, but has the courage to tell them how rude they are before he leaves the scene.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DULL.">Dull</persname>
<persdescription>Anthony Dull is the local constable, a blunt and unloquacious man who has no qualms about admitting that he has no idea what anyone else is talking about when they use their high-falutin&#8217; language. He himself tends to misunderstand large words, and therefore rarely tries to use them. He is not particularly intelligent, and neither embarrassed nor bothered by the fact.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="COST.">Costard</persname>
<persdescription>Costard is a swain at the court of Navarre who is caught chatting with Jaquenetta by Armado in spite of the King&#8217;s order that men are not to see women. Down-to-earth, he freely admits to rejecting the idea of the law, and tries to sneak out of his trouble by bandying words. He loves learning new and big words, especially when they relate to money, though he is incapable of pronouncing Don Armado&#8217;s name and makes a number of other mistakes, particularly with foreign names. His liking is so strong that he rewards Moth simply for being good with words. Being also unable to read, he mixes up the two letters he has to deliver and gives them to the wrong people. Armado&#8217;s rival for Jaquenetta, he insists that the Spaniard marry the wench when she turns out to be pregnant.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MOTH.">Moth</persname>
<persdescription>Moth is Don Armado&#8217;s page, a young, small, and extremely quick-witted boy who can not only hold his own with his master&#8217;s affected language, but best him at it. He does not take Armado overly seriously, and sometimes tries to put him in his place. Moth misses few opportunities for a joke; when he is used as a prologue by Berowne and the other lords to the Princess and her ladies, he tries to adapt the text to the actual circumstances, though this does not please the author of the text. He is not easily intimidated.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FOR.">Forester</persname>
<persdescription>A Forester is unable to keep up with the Princess&#8217; games of wit, but is rewarded for trying to all the same.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="PRIN.">The Princess of France</persname>
<persdescription>The Princess of France is her father the King&#8217;s heir, sent on an important diplomatic mission to Navarre. Though somewhat insulted by Navarre&#8217;s refusal to let her or her ladies into his court, she decides that the best response is to match wits with him rather than be offended. As she does not believe that the men&#8217;s declarations of love are genuine, she takes particular pleasure in setting them up for mockery. She is highly intelligent and a joyful woman, as well as a kind one; however, when the news of her father&#8217;s death comes, and she becomes Queen, grief and responsibility make her grow up. Unlike the King of Navarre who plans to abandon his kingdom for three years, she immediately prepares to return to her kingdom, and she imposes a task on the King in the hopes of making him reach something of the same level of maturity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="ROS.">Rosaline</persname>
<persdescription>Rosaline is a witty and intelligent lady attending on the Princess of France. She is unfashionably dark-complexioned and has black hair, and wears a cap on her arrival in Navarre. She refuses to be in the least impressed by Berowne or his professions of love, and resolves to make a fool of him. She is of similar height to the Princess, and plays her well enough to fool the lords. She has no taste for flights of poetry and enjoys puncturing overwrought language. Like her mistress, she thinks her lover not serious enough, and sets Berowne a penance to make him grow up and grow kinder if he wants to gain her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MAR.">Maria</persname>
<persdescription>Maria is a lady attending on the Princess of France who met Longaville at a family wedding and was rather impressed by him. She is dressed in white on their arrival in Navarre. She is (rightfully) unimpressed by Longaville&#8217;s poetic prowess, but nevertheless promises to marry him once her mistress&#8217; year of mourning is done.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="KATH.">Katherine</persname>
<persdescription>Katherine is a lady attending on the Princess of France who was rather impressed when she first met Dumaine, and is much less so when he breaks his oath and falls in love with her. She is quick-witted enough to keep pace with Rosaline. Loyal to her mistress, she refuses to marry Dumaine so long as the Queen is mourning herself, giving him time to grow up.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="JAQ.">Jaquenetta</persname>
<persdescription>Jaquenetta is a country wench who does not have the greatest reputation for virtue. Rather blunt, and completely without affectation, she is a simple soul, who trusts her parson and is worried about appearing before the King. She is two months&#8217; pregnant, presumably by Armado. When he asks to marry her, she insists that for three years he do an honest man&#8217;s work in the fields.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MARC.">Marcade</persname>
<persdescription>Marcade is a messenger from the court of France, who comes to inform the Princess that her father is dead and that she is therefore Queen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BLACK.">Blackamoors</persname>
<persdescription>Blackamoors [mute roles] play music for the lords when they are disguised as Russians.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. FR. LORD.">First French Lord</persname>
<persdescription>The First French Lord attends the Princess of France and her companions on her embassy to Navarre, and is able to tell her that Longaville is one of the King&#8217;s companions.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. FR. LORD.">Second French Lord</persname>
<persdescription>The Second French Lord [mute role] attends on the Princess of France and her companions on their embassy to Navarre.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>