<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Measure for Measure">
<persona>
<persname short="DUKE.">Vincentio, the Duke</persname>
<persdescription>Duke Vincentio is the ruler of Vienna. He does not much enjoy pomp and circumstance, and has spent a great deal of time off in his study, during which time many laws in his city have gone disregarded. Not wishing to be seen as a tyrant by suddenly changing his mind on the subject, he goes on a trip, leaving his powers in the hands of a man he knows will reestablish the rigors of the laws. At the same time, he decides to find out whether Angelo is in fact as pure as he seems to be, and disguises himself as a monk to keep an eye on matters. He is manipulative, though always with reasonably good motives. He prepares Claudio to die even though fully intending to save his life. He has known for a long time about Mariana&#8217;s betrayal by Angelo, and decides to take this opportunity to fix the situation for her. He also takes the opportunity of his disguise to try and find out what people think of him, and is shocked at Lucio&#8217;s slanders, as he thinks rather well of himself. Having a flair for the theatrical, he arranges matters to have the most dramatic reveal possible. Once he has let everyone know that he has been there all along and could have stepped in at any moment to stop things from going too far, that he could have demoted Angelo earlier and easily have saved Claudio&#8217;s life, but preferred to remain disguised, watch how things went and make them more interesting, he asks Isabella to marry him. She gives no answer, and he has to ask twice. He is very concerned that his own reputation be upheld, and is a firm defender of monarchs&#8217; rights to be considered the best of men.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANG.">Angelo</persname>
<persdescription>Angelo is a nobleman of Vienna chosen by the Duke to replace him during his absence. He is a morally rigorous puritan, inflexible, incorruptible, and well-known to be so; he is aware of all these facts, particularly the last. He either does not feel emotions or has disciplined himself to the extent that they have no effect on him. He abandoned Mariana, to whom he was betrothed, when her brother died and she found herself without money, and refused to offer her any consolation. Given the Duke&#8217;s full power during the latter&#8217;s absence, he immediately begins to impose his own moral rectitude on everyone, closing the brothels and condemning Claudio to death for knocking up his girlfriend. He rejects all of Escalus&#8217;s pleas for moderation. Isabella&#8217;s virtue, however, is just what it takes to seduce him. He is aware that what he is doing is wrong, and does all he can to hide it. Fully aware of his reputation for probity, he is willing to use it against Isabella and to protect himself. He brazens it out in front of the Duke, but when everything is revealed he is left hoping for nothing other than death, which he admits he deserves.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ESCAL.">Escalus</persname>
<persdescription>Escalus is an old lord at the Viennese court, a kind-hearted man who does not approve of over-severity. When the Duke leaves Vienna and has Angelo replace him, Escalus is named Angelo&#8217;s second-in-command. He insists to Angelo that he must at all times be allowed to speak his mind, though he will obey him. He attempts to convince Angelo to be less severe, believing death to be too great a punishment for doing something all men are tempted by. He is moved by Claudio&#8217;s plight and tries all he can to convince Angelo not to have him executed, especially as Claudio is a nobleman. He also lets Pompey and Mistress Overdone off with warnings until they&#8217;re caught once too often. He is deeply loyal and is outraged when Angelo&#8217;s virtue is called into question, and even more so when he hears of the Duke being slandered. His tender-heartedness does not include slanderers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLAUD.">Claudio</persname>
<persdescription>Claudio is a young gentleman of Vienna. Being betrothed to Juliet and fully intending to marry her, though waiting for financial reasons, he sleeps with her and gets her pregnant. As a rule this would not be an issue, but with Angelo enforcing the laws he finds himself arrested and scheduled to have his head chopped off. He does not enjoy being made a public show, and finds himself talking too much when he has a chance to speak with someone. No matter how much he prepares himself for the idea of death and convinces himself that he is ready to die, he still finds himself deeply fearful at the concept and grasps at any straw that will allow him to live. He respects his sister Isabella&#8217;s abilities, and loves her though in the fear of death he is willing to trade her chastity for his life. He is an immature young man, though old enough that he is bearded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUCIO.">Lucio</persname>
<persdescription>Lucio is a fop well-acquainted with brothels, who turns everything to dirty jokes. He has a bastard son by one of the prostitutes at Mistress Overdone&#8217;s, a fact he has denied in court for fear of being made to marry the mother. An egotist, he cannot resist thrusting himself into the spotlight. He is friendly to everyone he meets and speaks a great deal of his close links to the powerful, but cannot stop himself from slandering everyone the moment they are out of sight, up to and including the Duke, with the exception of Claudio, whose friend he is. He refuses to bail out Pompey, and informs on Mistress Overdone, with the result that both are carted off to jail. He is not the most pleasing of people; but it must be remembered that he does go, at Claudio&#8217;s request, to tell Isabella of her brother&#8217;s condemnation and to ask her to plead for his life to Angelo, and gives her good advice on how to do so &#8212; even if the result of this is not exactly what he and Claudio had in mind.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT.">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman is a fop, who spends a fair deal of time in brothels but is certain he has not caught any diseases there. He knows his clothes and his types of fabric very well, and has no desire for the King of Hungary to impose his policy on Vienna.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PROV.">Provost</persname>
<persdescription>The Provost is in charge of the jail and its prisoners, and of showing Claudio off in the streets as an example before his execution. He is not very happy about Claudio&#8217;s sentence, as he likes the lad and thinks that the fault was small enough. Since in the past he has had prisoners executed only to see them reprieved a bit too late, he double-checks in this case, as he is hopeful Angelo will relent. He is as kind to Claudio as his job allows, and lets himself be convinced by the disguised Duke to cheat Angelo and send someone else&#8217;s head in the place of Claudio&#8217;s.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRI. PET.">Friar Peter Thomas</persname>
<persdescription>Friar Peter Thomas is a monk who helps the Duke in his deception, giving him his monk&#8217;s robe and teaching him how to play the part convincingly. He suspects at first that the Duke is disguising himself for the sake of seducing some woman or other. The Duke later lets him know the whole story of Isabella and Mariana, and has him help with the staging of their denunciation of Angelo.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUST.">Justice</persname>
<persdescription>A Justice attends on Angelo and Escalus as they discuss how they will bring back the laws in full force.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VARR.">Varrius</persname>
<persdescription>Varrius [mute role] is a lord, a friend of the Duke&#8217;s. He accompanies the Duke on his supposed return from abroad.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ELB.">Elbow</persname>
<persdescription>Elbow is a constable, a man from the lower classes who constantly mangles his words. One of the officers charged by Angelo with cleaning up Vienna, he arrests Elbow and Froth, suspecting that the latter is having an affair with his wife. He is very concerned that it not be thought he had premarital sex with said wife.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FROTH.">Froth</persname>
<persdescription>Froth is a foolish gentleman who spends a great deal of his time in taverns. His father has recently died, leaving him a rich man. He will not look Escalus in the face when he is brought before the lord for being found in a brothel, and does not speak much. He is a good-looking man, or at least an inoffensive-looking one.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POM.">Pompey</persname>
<persdescription>Pompey Bum is Mistress Overdone&#8217;s bartender, and helps her in her pimping. He speaks a great deal and can almost talk his way out of risky situations simply by gabbling on so much that he wears out his listener. Though sent off with only a warning from Escalus the first time he is arrested for being a pimp, he returns immediately to his trade. He believes Lucio to be a genuine friend of his. He accepts to become an executioner&#8217;s assistant to gain his freedom, and is amused to recognize almost everyone imprisoned as former clients of Mistress Overdone&#8217;s. He is a fellow with a large rear end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ABHOR.">Abhorson</persname>
<persdescription>Abhorson is an executioner, who takes great pride in his job. He looks down on Pompey for being a pimp, considering him to be even lower on the social scale than he is himself, and is concerned that employing a pimp will bring executioners into disrepute.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAR.">Barnardine</persname>
<persdescription>Barnardine is a murderer who has been in jail for nine years without being executed. Slothful and drunken, he has rich and powerful friends who have helped him stay alive. The ultimate individualist, he simply refuses to be executed while he&#8217;s hung over; since this is his permanent state, he remains alive to this day. He is completely unafraid of death or any form of punishment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERV.">Servant</persname>
<persdescription>A Servant is Angelo&#8217;s doorman, in charge of letting him know when people wish to speak with him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ISAB.">Isabella</persname>
<persdescription>Isabella is Claudio&#8217;s sister, a devout, unbending novice to the order of Saint Clare, though she does not find them rigorous enough and wishes she could be even more strongly restricted by them. She is convinced by Lucio to plead for her brother&#8217;s life to Angelo, though needs the fop&#8217;s instructions on how to do so; she finds it a difficult task given that she quite agrees with Claudio&#8217;s death sentence and the reasoning behind it. She is fixated on her chastity and convinced that everyone holds it as highly as she does herself; she rejects all arguments distinguishing between chastity and virginity. Betrayed first by discovering that Angelo, an admirable man from her point of view, has become a lustful hypocrite, then by finding out that Claudio would prefer she let herself be raped rather than he be executed, she is consoled by the disguised Duke. She accepts his plan despite its questionable morality. She likes Mariana, and is persuaded by her to plead for Angelo&#8217;s life. She does not easily manage emotions other than judgmental anger, and is possibly a repressed masochist. Her reaction to the Duke&#8217;s proposal of marriage is unknown, though it is noticeable that he has to ask her twice.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MARI.">Mariana</persname>
<persdescription>Mariana is a young lady of Vienna who was once betrothed to Angelo. Her family&#8217;s wealth was lost when her brother drowned at sea, and as a result Angelo broke his promise to marry her. With her reputation damaged by his slandering her as an excuse, she retreated to an isolated priory. Though deeply depressed, she is still in love with Angelo five years after this happened. Willing to do anything to recapture his attention, she accepts to replace Isabella, thereby consummating her marriage without Angelo being aware of it. She plays her part before the Duke and is rewarded by being officially wed to Angelo, but must immediately plead for his life. She feels life to be rather cruel to her. Mariana is unaware that the consoling friar she often speaks to is in fact the disguised Duke.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUL.">Juliet</persname>
<persdescription>Juliet is Claudio&#8217;s betrothed. A simple girl and a childhood friend of Isabella&#8217;s, she slept with him since they were going to be married, and ended up pregnant. She is confused as to why her fianc&amp;eacute; is going to be executed for something barely even immoral, since they has perfectly consensual sex and had not married yet only for monetary reasons. Very close to giving birth, she is remorseful when questioned by a priest, and does not object to his dreadful puns about her pregnancy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FRAN.">Francisca</persname>
<persdescription>Francisca is a nun of the order of Saint Clare, who is in charge of instructing the novice Isabella as the latter prepares to take her vows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MRS. OV.">Mistress Overdone</persname>
<persdescription>Mistress Overdone is a madam. When her brothel is closed down by Angelo&#8217;s order, she quickly opens another one elsewhere. She feels very hard-done by, as a great number of men are ill, in the army, or too poor to be able to afford to use her services even before it becomes dangerous to do so. She continues to ply her trade even after three warnings, and is arrested for it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BOY.">Boy</persname>
<persdescription>A Boy attends on Mariana, singing sad songs to her to ease her boredom.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger brings Claudio&#8217;s final death warrant to the Provost with warnings from Angelo to have it executed quickly.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GENT.">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman is a fop, but one outclassed in wit by Lucio and the First Gentleman. He is not much of a churchgoer.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>