<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="The Merry Wives of Windsor">

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir John Falstaff</persname>
<persdescription>&lt;span class=&quot;shakestext&quot;&gt;Sir John Falstaff is a very fat rogue with no money but many plans to get some. &lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;shakestext&quot;&gt;An old, white-bearded man with great self-esteem, he has no doubts about his attractiveness to the ladies, and intends to use this supposed seductiveness to get his hands on some ladies&#8217; gold. Unfortunately for him he does not realize that he is not quite as much of a prize as he thinks, nor that both his targets (Mistress Page and Mistress Ford) are best friends and will show each other everything. He also does not think that his followers might ever turn on him. A great coward, Falstaff will undergo any humiliation to avoid being caught by a jealous husband, whether it is being snuck out in a laundry basket or dressing as a woman and being beaten as a witch. He is a great speaker who can talk himself out of almost any situation and enjoys the sound of his own voice to excess. Having absolutely no sense of morality, he has no qualms about conning people, beating up people who get in his way, and poaching another man&#8217;s deer. A drinker addicted to sack, his main purpose in life is to indulge himself, for which he needs money, the chief end of his endeavors. He is much more easily deceived than he thinks he can be, and he continues to trust the two merry wives as they make a fool of him time and again. Still, he is able to laugh at himself and recognize how well he has been served. &lt;/span&gt;</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Fenton</persname>
<persdescription>Master Fenton is a young, good-looking gentleman with a bit of a wild past who became very attracted to Anne Page when he discovered how rich her father is. Having spent most of his own money, he set his cap at her, but has since fallen genuinely in love with the girl. He is kind and rather too easy with his money. He has a wart above one eye.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Robert Shallow</persname>
<persdescription>Justice Robert Shallow is an old and respectable man, if somewhat foolish. A Justice of the Peace, and therefore the chief official of the law in town, he is a rich man with a deer enclosure where he alone is allowed to hunt. He hopes to marry his nephew Slender to Anne Page, and does what he can to push the match further. At times he has to take over the wooing himself, as his nephew is not very adept at the job. Over eighty years old, he remembers his youth fondly, and is delighted to join in with the plot to carry Anne off during the final prank on Falstaff. He thinks himself much more canny than he actually is.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Francis Ford</persname>
<persdescription>Master Frank Ford is a middle-aged, middle-class gentleman of Windsor afflicted with an almost pathological case of jealousy. Though he trusts his wife Alice with the household finances, he is convinced that she will not hesitate to cheat on him given the least opportunity, an opinion he holds of all women. He cannot understand why other husbands do not see the same risks he does about their wives. His suspicions run so deep that he is quite willing to make a fool of himself, and he disguises himself in order to try and discover via Falstaff whether he is right to be as paranoid as he is. His terror of being cuckolded pushes him into wilder and wilder behavior, and the fact that his neighbors mock him mercilessly each time he can produce no proof of his allegations does nothing to dampen him. He is not a man to do things by halves; when his wife and Mistress Page explain what has been going on, he becomes as extravagant in his apologies as he was in his jealousy. He is prejudiced against foreigners and fortune-tellers. He is a rich man, and willing to risk a fair bit of his money to find out whether his wife is faithful or not; he also buys the disguises for the children who dress as fairies. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">George Page</persname>
<persdescription>Master George Page is a wealthy gentleman of Windsor, married to Mistress Margaret and father of Anne and William. He is well-aware of his place in society and therefore rejects Master Fenton as a husband for his daughter, thinking him too high-born; he prefers a good, solid marriage with a rich man of Windsor, Master Slender. He finds Master Ford&#8217;s jealousy ludicrously over-the-top, and tries to calm him down, without much success. He loves and trusts his wife and is willing to follow her advice in most things, allowing her to be in charge of the family finances. Nevertheless, he tries to act behind her back to get Anne to marry Master Slender, never dreaming that Anne might deceive him and run off with her own choice of husband instead. He is a good-natured fellow who enjoys a good laugh.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">William Page</persname>
<persdescription>William Page is the young son of Master George Page and Mistress Margaret. A schoolboy, he is better at Latin than either of his parents think, though he is not overly enthusiastic about school. Along with his schoolfellows, he dresses up as a fairy to make a mock of Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sir Hugh Evans</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Hugh Evans is a Welsh parson and the schoolmaster of Windsor; he has not lost his very heavy accent either in English or in Latin, which is a source of much amusement to the others. A decent fellow, he tries to be a peace-broker in Windsor, though with only mixed success. He also attempts to help Slender&#8217;s suit to Anne Page, with the unfortunate effect of finding himself challenged to a duel by a choleric Frenchman. Though he tries to stiffen his backbone and go through with it, he is terrified at the idea and tries to reassure himself by singing. Evans has the typical teacher&#8217;s love of precise language, and will correct people if he catches them in error; Mistress Quickly&#8217;s mistakes and misunderstands baffle him almost completely. He is deeply concerned by Ford&#8217;s irrational behavior. Impressed by Mistress Page and Mistress Ford&#8217;s ingenuity, he is delighted to join in their final prank on Falstaff, and gets his students to play the fairies for it. Himself disguised, he is the first to press a candle-flame on Sir John. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Doctor Caius</persname>
<persdescription>Doctor Caius is a French physician, a short-tempered, easily offended man who is wooing Anne Page and does not wish to see anyone else moving in on her. Quick to judgment, he assumes that Evans is hoping to marry Anne himself, and immediately challenges the Welshman to a duel. Dr. Caius has an extremely heavy French accent and is not fully in command of English, which cannot be helped by the fact that his housekeeper is Mistress Quickly, herself not the best user of the language. Mistress Page supports him as Anne&#8217;s husband, and tries to arrange for him to run off with her during the final prank on Falstaff. Unfortunately for him, he is tricked by the girl herself, and ends up being married to a boy. As the local doctor and a man well-connected with the court, he is a respected citizen, despite his bad English and his choleric ways.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Host of the Garter Inn</persname>
<persdescription>Host of the Garter Inn is a rather merry innkeeper who is incapable of saying anything simply and likes showing off how many words he knows. Though he enjoys mocking foreigners, he likes both Evans and Caius and does not want to see them skewer one another, though he perhaps has too much fun making fools of them to stop their duel. He is not quite cautious enough to avoid having his horses stolen from him by some conmen, and the loss of money that represents leaves him open to Fenton&#8217;s promises of payment if he arranges the young man&#8217;s secret wedding with Anne. He likes playing tricks, for instance introducing the disguised Ford to Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Bardolph</persname>
<persdescription>Bardolph is one of Falstaff&#8217;s followers; when the fat knight can no longer afford to keep his men, he finds Bardolph a job as bartender for the Host. He is a rogue, a conman and a thief, but seems to do his new job honestly enough. He does not realize that the German guests at the inn are conmen themselves until they gallop off with the inn&#8217;s horses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Pistol</persname>
<persdescription>Pistol is one of Falstaff&#8217;s followers, a swaggering man who loves the sound of his own voice and is incapable of speaking like a normal human being, instead grandiloquently talking like a hammy actor in a melodrama. He is hot-tempered and seems to be always angling for a fight. He refuses to help Falstaff in his plot against the ladies of Windsor, and instead joins Nim in derailing the plan by telling Ford and Page about Falstaff&#8217;s designs on their wives. Discovering that Mistress Quickly makes a fair bit of money acting as an intermediary in love affairs, he sets his cap at her as a good way of getting the money Falstaff refuses to give him. He dresses up as Hobgoblin for the fairy scene for a chance to get some physical revenge on the knight.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nym</persname>
<persdescription>Nym is one of Falstaff&#8217;s followers, and is obsessed with humors. He refuses to help Falstaff with his plans of seduction, and to revenge himself on the fat knight&#8217;s insults convinces Pistol to join him and inform Ford and Page of Falstaff&#8217;s designs on their wives. He has a very one-track mind. He is a conman, who manages to trick Slender out of an expensive chain.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Robin</persname>
<persdescription>Robin is Falstaff&#8217;s page, but is not the most faithful of servants. Though he brings Falstaff&#8217;s love letters to Mistress Page and Mistress Ford, he is easily convinced by them to turn traitor and lead his master into their trap, despite the fat knight&#8217;s threat of dismissing him from service if he should mention Falstaff&#8217;s planned double-dealing with the ladies. Mistress Page&#8217;s bribing him with new clothes doubtless helps. He is ambitious to be grown, and knows how to flatter a lady.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Peter Simple</persname>
<persdescription>Peter Simple is Slender&#8217;s servant, an obsequious fellow much impressed by his social betters who must put up with a lot from his foolish master.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">John Rugby</persname>
<persdescription>John Rugby is Dr. Caius&#8217;s servant. He is deeply intimidated by his master.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mistress Alice Ford</persname>
<persdescription>Mistress Alice Ford is a middle-aged lady of Windsor, married to Master Frank Ford. She was quite impressed by Falstaff until he sends her a love letter, at which point she begins to scorn him, and even more so when she discovers that her best friend, Mistress Page, has received exactly the same letter. She is aware that her husband is wildly jealous, and terrified at what will happen if he should discover that Falstaff is wooing her. She agrees with Mistress Page&#8217;s suggestion to trick Falstaff, and sees how this may help her cure Ford&#8217;s jealousy. She sets herself up as the main bait to the fat knight, and acts her role very convincingly. Though her husband is quick to question her fidelity, he trusts her enough to leave her in charge of the family finances &#8212; the main source of Falstaff&#8217;s attraction to her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mistress Margaret Page</persname>
<persdescription>Mistress Margaret Page is a middle-aged lady of Windsor who is fond of her husband George, though she has rather different ideas about who should marry their daughter Anne. She is astounded and infuriated to suddenly be wooed by Falstaff, feelings that grow when she discovers that her friend Mistress Ford has received exactly the same love letter she has. She immediately thinks of causing him mischief, and also sees there an opportunity of helping Mistress Ford overcome her husband&#8217;s manic jealousy. An imaginative woman, she is well-respected by all; she is also concerned for her son William&#8217;s education. She is excellent at playing a role, but does not consider that she may have passed this talent on to her daughter, and is therefore taken by surprise when Anne manages to escape and marry the man she wishes rather than the upper-class French Doctor her mother prefers. Mistress Page is trusted and loved by her husband, and is in charge of the family finances &#8212; the main source of Falstaff&#8217;s attraction to her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mistress Anne Page</persname>
<persdescription>Anne Page is the daughter of Master George Page and Mistress Margaret. A lovely brown-haired girl of marriageable age, she is not enthusiastic about either of her parents&#8217; choices for her husband, though she hopes to get their approval for Master Fenton, whom she prefers. She is rather more intelligent than her suitor Slender, whom she has to put up with because of her father, and has no taste for the French Caius. In the end she is willing to deceive both her parents and the suitors in order to run off with Fenton.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mistress Quickly</persname>
<persdescription>Mistress Quickly is Dr. Caius&#8217;s housekeeper, a foolish woman with a poor command of language, mixing up her English words and unable to identify Latin as a foreign language as opposed to dirty English. As she knows Anne Page, she acts as a go-between for all of her suitors, encouraging all of them and taking credit for any success they have, as she herself has no particular opinion as to which one should gain Anne so long as she gets paid. Mistress Quickly is also used as a go-between by Mistress Page and Mistress Ford to Falstaff, something that makes Pistol realize that she has her value and is worth pursuing. Despite her problems with English, she is able to learn enough good language to play the Queen of the Fairies in the final prank on Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Abraham Slender</persname>
<persdescription>Master Abraham Slender is Justice Shallow&#8217;s nephew, a rich and foolish man who wishes to marry Anne Page. Far from being the brightest, he keeps a notebook with good lines to use on women, but forgets to bring it with him and is left dependent on his uncle&#8217;s promptings to try and woo Anne, with limited success. He relies on Shallow for almost everything, and it is his misfortune that his uncle is not much brighter than he is himself. He agrees with Page&#8217;s suggestion that he run off with Anne during the final prank on Falstaff, but never considers that she might trick him. Blond and tall, he has a weak face and a small beard, and struts when he walks.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The First Servant (John) works for the Fords, and removes the rather heavy laundry-basket containing Falstaff at his mistress&#8217; order and dumps its contents in the ditch. He is hopeful that this will not become a regular occurrence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Servant (Robert) works for the Fords, and removes the rather heavy laundry-basket containing Falstaff at his mistress&#8217; order and dumps its contents in the ditch. He is hopeful that this will not become a regular occurrence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Children of Windsor</persname>
<persdescription>Children of Windsor [mute roles] are Evans&#8217;s students, whom he trains to play fairies in the final prank on Falstaff.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Postmaster&#8217;s Boy</persname>
<persdescription>The Postmaster&#8217;s Boy [mute role] is one of Evans&#8217;s students, who plays a fairy in the final prank on Falstaff. He is always part of the plot to let Anne elope with Fenton. He dresses in white and learns the code words that Slender has arranged, and goes off with him. As he is masked, Slender does not discover his mistake until they are in church.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Boy</persname>
<persdescription>A Boy [mute role] is one of Evans&#8217;s students, who plays a fairy in the final prank on Falstaff. He is always part of the plot to let Anne elope with Fenton. Masked and dressed in green, he runs off with Dr. Caius, who does not discover that he is not Anne until after a marriage ceremony is performed.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>