<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Much Ado About Nothing">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="D. PEDRO.">Don Pedro</persname>
<persdescription>Don Pedro is the Prince of Aragon. He has just won a war against his illegitimate half-brother Don John. He reconciles himself to his brother, though he doesn&#8217;t speak to him much and may merely be keeping him close to keep an eye on him. Though a bachelor himself, he has a high enough regard for marriage to help Claudio in asking for Hero&#8217;s hand and to join in mocking Benedick for his insistence on never marrying. Willing and able to trade barbs with Beatrice at her own level, he soon decides she would be well-matched with Benedick, and entirely hatches the plot to bring them together. Despite all his reasons to distrust his half-brother, he believes Don John&#8217;s accusations readily enough to agree to spy on Hero&#8217;s window, and swears that if the allegations are true he will join Claudio in disgracing the lady in church to repair his own honor, which is tarnished by having arranged the match. His conviction of his rectitude after the scene in the church is such that he will not offer any hint of apology for his behavior to Leonato, and is able to quickly switch tacks and return to mocking Benedick. Though horrified when it turns out he has been gulled and willing to mourn Hero, he still refuses admit that there was anything wrong with his behavior per se, merely that he acted on faulty information.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="D. JOHN.">Don John</persname>
<persdescription>Don John is a bastard, in both the legal and ethical senses of the term. The essence of his character is that he is evil. Having recently rebelled against his half-brother Don Pedro and lost, he is forced to follow the winners to Leonato&#8217;s. He does not admit having been in any way wrong. His general disposition is melancholy, that is, depressed and depressing. He believes that the more depressed he appears, the happier his brother&#8217;s followers are. However, he fully intends to work any mischief he can, and as Claudio was one of the chief instruments of Don John&#8217;s defeat, the thought of ruining his life is particularly pleasing. While his first attempt to spark jealousy in Claudio is only momentarily successful, his follower Borachio&#8217;s plan works marvellously&#8213;so well that Don John pays him a thousand ducats in recompense. Having accomplished his desired evil ends&#8213;Hero dead, Claudio distraught, Don Pedro shamed, Leonato dishonored&#8213;Don John flees, but is caught. It seems that Benedick will arrange his punishment, a thought likely to strike fear in him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CLAUD.">Claudio</persname>
<persdescription>Claudio is a Count of Don Pedro&#8217;s suite, who has distinguished himself in the recent war. He is from Florence, though he has an emotional uncle living in Messina. Young, still beardless, and built enough like the Prince that the latter can pass for him, Claudio is, to put it charitably, not very bright, as well as easily deceived and quick to jealousy. He is also, judging by the verses he will read at Hero&#8217;s tomb, an absolutely dreadful poet. Still, he is quick enough of wit to join in with Don Pedro&#8217;s mockery of Benedick. He is the latter&#8217;s boon companion of the moment. He is insecure, willing to believe the least suggestion that he is bring betrayed and always overreacting to that belief, particularly when he chooses to publicly disgrace Hero in church when he believes her unfaithful, rather than simply calling the wedding off in the morning. He refuses to fight either of the two old brothers who challenge him, but must accept to match with Benedick. As soon as he hears that he was deceived, he swears that he is once again as in love with Hero as he was before, and accepts any penance Leonato wishes to place on him. Steadied to marry Leonato&#8217;s niece, no matter how ugly, he is shocked to discover that she is actually Hero, who isn&#8217;t dead after all and is for some reason still willing to marry him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BENE.">Benedick</persname>
<persdescription>Benedick is a gentleman of Padua serving in Don Pedro&#8217;s army. He wears a beard at the beginning of the play. According to Beatrice, he adopts a new best friend once a month, possibly out of a concern for money; his present one is Claudio. Benedick is best known for his apparent distaste for women, despite Beatrice&#8217;s status as his favorite verbal sparring partner, and his insistence that he will never marry. When Claudio falls in love with Hero, Benedick is disgusted that yet another bachelor is going to abandon that happy state. It is known that he and Beatrice share a history. He appears to have no taste for music that is not military. When he overhears the conversation designed to make him fall for Beatrice, he realizes that there is nothing he can actually hold against her, and determines to marry her, soon finding double meanings in her unfriendly words to him. He shaves his beard off and becomes melancholy, or at least affects to, as this is how lovers are prescribed to be. He chooses to remain with Beatrice and her family rather than leave after the fracas at the church, and is quick to suspect Don John&#8217;s hand in it. Tested between his love for Beatrice and for his friend, he chooses the former and agrees to fight Claudio to the death. He refuses to be drawn into battles of wit with either Claudio or the Prince, but regains enough of his sense of humor to flirt shamelessly with Margaret and extravagantly compliment her when asking for her help with Beatrice. Unlike Claudio, he realizes that he is a terrible poet, and gives up on attempts to write a sonnet. He does however discover that kissing Beatrice is one way to make her be quiet, come over to the side of dancing music, and begin to mock the Prince for being a bachelor. Upon Don John&#8217;s capture at the end of the play, he promises to think up a punishment for him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="LEON.">Leonato</persname>
<persdescription>Leonato, the governor of Messina, is an older man, with a white beard. He has a daughter, Hero, and is the guardian of an orphaned niece, Beatrice. He indulges the latter in her flights of wit, and appears to greatly enjoy them. A good subject, he is delighted but cautious at the thought of his daughter marrying the prince when his brother Antonio reports that Don Pedro may woo her. He is just as happy to marry her off to Claudio at the prince&#8217;s request, and joins in with Don Pedro&#8217;s plot to bring Beatrice and Benedick together. When his daughter is accused of being a harlot at her wedding, his instinct is to believe the charges because they were made by the prince. His rage at her is however transferred to Don Pedro and Claudio when he is convinced of Hero&#8217;s innocence. He does however attempt to calm down his brother when the latter lashes out at the two young men who will not fight with them because of their advanced age. When it is discovered that the accusation was merely a well-planned slander, he decides to let the original planned marriage go ahead, but to make Don Pedro and Claudio suffer a little first, speaking to them with no little sarcasm and imposing the penance of telling the world of Hero&#8217;s innocence. He is friendly if impatient with his social inferiors such as Dogberry, but this may only be because this long-winded fellow comes to speak to him on the morning of his daughter&#8217;s wedding.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANT.">Antonio</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio is Leonato&#8217;s brother. An old man, he has a tendency to wag his head in a characteristic way. He apparently has a son who provides for the music in Leonato&#8217;s house. When a servant tells him that Don Pedro intends to woo Hero, he rushes to tell his brother, who is slightly skeptical of the thought. After the disaster in the church, he begins by playing the level-headed part, attempting to calm Leonato down, but when they are confronted by the prince and Claudio, he is incapable of restraining himself and loses his temper, insulting both Claudio and Don Pedro so severely than Leonato must attempt to calm him down in return. He has a very traditional view of the family that does not seem quite sure of how to deal with Beatrice, rarely addressing her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BALTH.">Balthasar</persname>
<persdescription>Balthasar is an attendant of Don Pedro&#8217;s and a musician. A singer, he most likely plays the lute to accompany himself. He is self-deprecating about his talent, and Benedick agrees with that self-assessment. He also talks too much, and is a bad dancer&#8213;his lack of ability in that direction ruins his chances with Margaret.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CON.">Conrade</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH CON. AND BORA.">Both Conrade and Borachio</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Conrade is one of Don John&#8217;s followers. He attempts to cheer Don John up and to convince him that he should be, at the least, happy that Don Pedro has taken him back, and use that favor to pursue his own ends. Don John has little ear, for this, however, and Conrade soon appears to be left out of the plot that Don John and Borachio put together. He comes across Borachio the night before Hero&#8217;s wedding. The latter is completely drunk and tells the tale of the deception he has just practiced, which Conrade finds most entertaining. He is then arrested. Brought before the sexton, he denies being a villain, and tells Dogberry to his face that he is an ass, provoking a remarkable tirade from the constable. He is brought with Borachio before Don Pedro and the others, but says nothing. He is apparently a Capricorn&#8213;at least, his ruling star is Saturn&#8213;but Don John does not find him as depressed as he should be for that star sign.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BORA.">Borachio</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH CON. AND BORA.">Both Conrade and Borachio</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Borachio is one of Don John&#8217;s followers. His name tells us well enough that he is a drunkard. He also has, however, a crafty mind. He knows to bring any news that might serve as the basis for mischief to Don John. He is having a fling with Margaret, and has no qualms about using her as a prop in his plot for Don John without her knowledge. The fact that he is able to get as far as he does with the confirmed flirt Margaret suggests that he is a good dancer, as that appears to be a requirement for her favor. Unfortunately, Borachio does not know to hold his tongue when drunk, which leads to his and Conrad&#8217;s arrest and the discovery of the whole plot. The news of Hero&#8217;s death appears to bring out some remorse in him, and confesses in full to Don Pedro. He is also honest enough to spontaneously clear Margaret of all blame when it appears she&#8217;s about to be dragged into the mess.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FRIAR.">Friar Francis</persname>
<persdescription>Friar Francis is in the tradition of Romeo and Juliet&#8217;s Friar Laurence; both are long-winded, well-meaning, somewhat interfering gentlemen who think it is a fine idea to make people believe a young girl is dead. He is convinced of Hero&#8217;s innocence by her countenance at the wedding and shock at the accusations. He proposes that they should say that she died, thereby hopefully making Don Pedro and Claudio remorseful, rekindling Claudio&#8217;s love, and allowing for time to discover what&#8217;s actually going on. He is in charge of marrying everyone at the end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="HERO.">Hero</persname>
<persdescription>Hero is Leonato&#8217;s daughter. A sweet and obedient girl overshadowed by her cousin Beatrice, she almost never speaks in her elders&#8217; presence. On her own with Ursula, however, she is quite capable of speech, particularly when she knows that Beatrice is overhearing her, and that therefore the plot to make her cousin and Benedick fall in love is advancing apace. She takes her father&#8217;s instructions to receive a suit from the Prince well, and offers no objection when the suit is for Claudio instead; during her talk in the garden, she claims to be fully in love with Claudio. When he suddenly turns on her on their wedding day, accusing her of being a harlot, she is shocked to the core and can summon no defense against the unexpected and false charges leveled at her. The blow is such that she faints. Reviving, she is able to say only that she has no idea what evidence there is against her. She accepts to go into seclusion until things are worked out. When the mystery is unraveled, she accepts to marry Claudio all the same, though no explanation why is given. She is quickly able to tease Beatrice and reveal that she has written a sonnet admitting to loving Benedick, essentially the first and only spontaneous action we see from her. She is a short woman, and (if one can trust Benedick&#8217;s opinion) dark of skin.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="BEAT.">Beatrice</persname>
<persdescription>Beatrice is Leonato&#8217;s orphaned niece. She appears to be somewhat taller than Hero, as well as older. She has a ready with which she clearly enjoys displaying, and is much given to mockery. Her favorite target is Benedick, with whom she has something of a history, to the extent that she exercises her talent for mocking him on the poor unsuspecting messenger and takes the first opportunity to needle him once he arrives. She has no care for a husband, and therefore little patience with the suggestion that her ready tongue will prevent her from gaining one. She has little care for social convention, and is quite capable of trading witticisms with the Prince as an equal. She is shocked to hear herself described as prideful by Hero and Ursula. She is shocked and enraged at the accusations thrown at her cousin, putting her in a vulnerable enough state that she will cry, almost admit to loving Benedick, and asking him to kill Claudio for her. When Benedick publically asks her if she loves him following the reconciliation of Claudio and Hero, Beatrice quickly returns to her habit of replying with witticisms, though it is quickly proved that she has recently written a not-very-adequate sonnet confessing to her love. Benedick is finally able to stop her flow of words by kissing her, as they agree to marry, though they insist this is not out of love.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MARG.">Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Margaret is Hero&#8217;s waiting-gentlewoman. A fashion-obsessed flirt who requires good dancing abilities in her men, she is witty enough to hold her own against both Benedick and Beatrice in certain circumstances. She joins in the plot to convince Beatrice that Benedick is in love with her, playing the important role of convincing her to go eavesdrop on Hero and Ursula. She has a fling with Borachio, which is serious enough that he can convince her to engage in a little role-playing and pretend to be Hero one night. She is unaware of the repercussions of this game until after Borachio&#8217;s arrest, when she is questioned by Leonato. She is one of the veiled ladies who mystify Claudio at the end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="URS.">Ursula</persname>
<persdescription>Ursula is one of Hero&#8217;s waiting-gentlewomen. She recognizes the masked Antonio as they dance together at the ball and gleefully joins in the plot to make Beatrice and Benedick fall in love, praising Benedick extravagantly to Hero when she knows that Beatrice is eavesdropping.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DOG.">Dogberry</persname>
<persdescription>Dogberry is the constable of the Watch, whose job is to patrol the streets of Messina at night and keep order. Dogberry has very few doubts about himself. Some of these are not entirely warranted: he is a determined word-mangler, whose attempts to use learned words go continually awry, a fact of which he is blissfully unaware. Since none of his underlings understand either the words he is using or those he is attempting to, this goes unremarked upon by the lesser sort. He is also very conscious of his place, and continually interrupts his second-in-command Verges when the letter attempts to speak. His instructions to the Watch seem somewhat contradictory to the whole purpose of patrolling. His inability to get to the point holds some responsibility for the scene in the church. By his own report, he is an officer, owns his own house, is rich enough that he has suffered investment losses, owns two gowns (which might be considered the equivalent of owning two very good suits), and thinks himself a fine specimen of a man. He is also old enough to call upon his years as worthy of respect.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="VERG.">Verges</persname>
<persdescription>Verges is the Headborough, and Dogberry&#8217;s partner as commander of the Watch. He is an old man, and seems to be completely under Dogberry&#8217;s thumb. Despite this, he does his best to actually accomplish the duties of the Watch, which he appears to understand much better than does his superior. He appears to show no resentment of Dogberry&#8217;s continual interruptions, and it is possible that he is somewhat weak in the head. He is apparently shorter than Dogberry.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SEX.">Sexton</persname>
<persdescription>The Sexton is in charge of examining the men detained by the Watch, and it is his misfortune that the Watch should be commanded by Dogberry. The interrogation is soon taken over by Dogberry, but the Sexton is able to guide the matter in the correct direction. He has heard all the story of what happened in the church, as well as knowing of Don John&#8217;s flight, and is therefore convinced of the truth of the accusations. He resolves to let Leonato know of it at once.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="BOY.">Boy</persname>
<persdescription>A Boy attending on Benedick is none too bright. He fetches Benedick&#8217;s book at his request.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Messenger is sent by Don Pedro to announce his coming to Leonato. More than a mere letter-carrier, he knows enough to be able to fully answer all questions put to him, including the names of the best fighters and Benedick&#8217;s humor. He is not fully prepared for Beatrice&#8217;s wit or the tenor of her comments on Benedick. He comes to tell Leonato that they are ready for him at the church and later reports to Don Pedro that Don John has been caught.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. WATCH.">First Watchman</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. WATCH. AND 2. WATCH.">Both First and Second Watchmen</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Watchman suggests either Seacoal or Hugh Oatcake as leaders of the patrol, on the basis of their ability to read and write. He joins in the testimony to the Sexton.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. WATCH.">Second Watchman</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. WATCH. AND 2. WATCH.">Both First and Second Watchmen</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Watchman (George Seacoal) is a member of the Watch who is able to read and write, and is therefore put in charge of the nightly patrol. Along with the other members of the Watch, he asks and receives clarifications of their charge which allow him to decree that they should all sit in one spot by the church until two o&#8217;clock and then go home. Hearing Borachio&#8217;s tale, however, he leads the Watch to arrest them. He testifies on the matter to the Sexton.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="WATCH.">Watchmen</persname>
<persdescription>The Watchmen (one of whom is Hugh Oatcake) are part of the neighbourhood watch that Dogberry commands, charged with patrolling the streets of Messina at night. They are neither particlarly bright nor conscientious, but still arrest Conrade and Borachio and lead them to the Sexton.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="A LORD.">Lord</persname>
<persdescription>A Lord is among Claudio&#8217;s and Don Pedro&#8217;s suite when they visit Hero&#8217;s tomb. As he can confirm that they have reached the right place, he is likely a native of Messina, and plausibly not one of Don Pedro&#8217;s own followers. He might even be a follower of Leonato&#8217;s sent as witness that Don Pedro and Claudio have kept their word.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>