<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Othello">

<persona>
<persname short="">Duke of Venice</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Venice has more pressing concerns than the family problems of one old Senator, but he allows Brabantio to interrupt his council of war all the same. He is not taken in by the Turkish maneuvers that seem to threaten Rhodes rather than Cyprus. He is at first sympathetic to Brabantio&#8217;s plight, but when the Senator asks for the imprisonment of the very general the Duke needs to fend off the enemy, he becomes rather less adamant on that point. He attempts to reconcile Brabantio, Othello and Desdemona, but in the end tells them to take care of their own affairs.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Brabantio</persname>
<persdescription>Brabantio is an old man and a Senator of Venice. He is a genteel racist: he has been very friendly to Othello and often invited him to his house to honor him and for the sake of hearing the tales of his life, but when his daughter runs away with the Moor, however, he is appalled, and convinced that witchcraft is the only explanation. He sues to the Duke for justice, but when Desdemona admits that she was fully complicit in her escape from her father&#8217;s house, he admits his defeat and tries to change the subject back to political affairs. He does not disguise his mortification or sorrow, but gives his daughter to Othello all the same, though in terms that essentially disown her. He is incapable of resisting a parting shot at Othello warning him of her faithlessness. His sorrow over his daughter brings about an early death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Senator</persname>
<persdescription>First Senator is certain that the Turkish move towards Rhodes is nothing but a ruse, and convinces the rest of the war council so.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Senator</persname>
<persdescription>Second Senator is part of the war council of Venice, and concludes that despite the disparity in numbers in the information they are receiving, the general message is clear and all that they need be concerned about.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gratiano</persname>
<persdescription>Gratiano is Brabantio&#8217;s brother. He is one of the Venetians who arrive on Cyprus after Othello&#8217;s victory, in his case bringing the news of Brabantio&#8217;s death. Walking home with Lodovico he comes across the wounded Cassio and is convinced by Iago of Bianca&#8217;s likely guilt in the matter. He is shocked that Iago would raise a weapon against a woman. He appears quite taken aback at the strange world he seems to have come into, and soon the most he can do is wish torture on Iago. As the last remaining relative of Othello&#8217;s wife, he inherits all of the Moor&#8217;s wealth. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lodovico</persname>
<persdescription>Lodovico is a kinsman of Brabantio&#8217;s. He leads the Venetian party that comes to Cyprus after Othello&#8217;s victory to proclaim Cassio the new governor. He is shocked to find Othello publicly shaming his wife and worries about the general&#8217;s sanity. Walking home with Desdemona&#8217;s uncle Gratiano, he comes across the wounded Cassio. He takes command on arriving at Desdemona&#8217;s bedchamber, order Othello disarmed and leading the interrogations, the answers to which he will take to inform the Senate in Venice. He is an upright, honest gentleman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Othello</persname>
<persdescription>Othello is a Moor and a mercenary retained by the Venetian state. Widely travelled and experienced, he considers himself of no country until he binds himself to Desdemona. He spends nine months at peace in Venice, there being no war requiring him, during which time he is often invited to Brabantio&#8217;s, where he sings for his supper with the tale of his life and travelers&#8217; tales. These seduce Desdemona, Brabantio&#8217;s daughter, and he falls in love with her. They elope at a time when the rumors of new wars with the Turks make it likely that Othello&#8217;s services will soon be needed by Venice, and his commission to relieve Cyprus helps shield him from Brabantio&#8217;s wrath. Well into middle-age, he has a healthy self-regard, portraying himself as a man not ruled by passion. He sometimes seems incapable of speaking without using the grandiloquent language that characterizes him, and he possesses tremendous natural authority, enough that he can stop a fight with a single sentence. He is quick to discipline. He is, however, more vulnerable than he realizes: he is insecure over the age difference with his wife, as well as the fact of his race. His ancient (ensign) Iago&#8217;s suspicions about Cassio and Desdemona strike him close, especially coming from so trusted and honest a man. Desdemona&#8217;s importuning about Cassio only convinces him further of her guilt. Othello is a deeply trusting man, even to credulousness, and suspicions quickly convince him that he may be wrong to trust. Though not known for ever being angry, even in the middle of battle, his rage over possibly being betrayed is so strong that it renders him almost incoherent, sending him into a fit and persuading him to murder his wife. He insults and humiliates her publicly, even in front of her relatives, and goes so far as to strike her, either not knowing or not caring what harm he is doing to his image. That image is very important to him: even after killing his wife and discovering that he has been played like a fiddle and a fool by Iago, he insists on trying to define how he will be remembered before he commits suicide, though he betrays a certain lack of self-knowledge in his description of himself.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Cassio</persname>
<persdescription>Cassio is a young Florentine officer in Venice&#8217;s army. Academically trained, he has had little if any real wartime experience. A gallant, courteous gentleman, perhaps too gallant with the ladies at time, he has been friendly with Othello for some time, and acted as a go-between for him and Desdemona. Othello has chosen him to be his lieutenant. He is naive, incapable of holding his liquor, and has a hair-trigger temper when drunk. When sober, however, he is friendly with everyone, though he compares people to what he has known in Florence. He holds his reputation to be his highest worth, and is crestfallen when he loses it and his position over a foolish drunken quarrel whose start he cannot even remember. Convinced by Iago&#8217;s arguments, he takes his hopes of reinstatement to the lieutenancy to Desdemona. He has a long-standing agreement with Bianca, though he finds it impossible to take seriously her hopes of marrying him and rather neglects her. He uses her easily, though, asking her to copy the mysterious handkerchief he finds in his room. Once the wars are done, he is named Governor of Cyprus by the Venetian Senate. Returning home from Bianca&#8217;s one evening before taking up his new position, he is set upon by a Venetian he does not know, and badly wounded. He is horrified when, soon after, he discovers the suspicions Othello has had of him and the extent of Iago&#8217;s villainy. It is left to him to decide what punishments will be inflicted on the man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Iago</persname>
<persdescription>Iago is an ancient (ensign) serving Othello, a battle-hardened veteran of 28 whose bluff honesty leaves him trusted and even liked by all who meet him. He is obsessed with the grubbiness of sex, to which he reduces all love, and is haunted by the thought that his wife Emilia has betrayed him with his general, Othello. He hates the latter, who has chosen an academically-trained man to be his lieutenant instead of the battle-hardened Iago. He is a master manipulator, managing to play people like puppets with ease, using his blunt honesty to convince them of what he chooses. He is also a brilliant improviser, setting his plot against Othello without having thought it fully through but able to use every occasion and person he meets to further his purpose. He can change his manner instantly depending on what&#8217;s required, whether it&#8217;s spewing filth to rouse Brabantio, trading witticisms with Desdemona, openly confessing his dissimulations to his gull Roderigo, or tentatively suggesting to Othello that he look to his wife. He is a misogynist, an abusive husband, and a racist. He leads Roderigo on for the sake of getting the latter&#8217;s money, and manages to use him as an agent to cause the disruptions required for Iago&#8217;s plot. Though he originally plans to find a way to sleep with Desdemona to repay Othello for having (as he thinks) slept with Emilia, this idea soon graduates to the full plan of having the Moor murder his wife while Iago takes care of murdering Cassio. His improvisation only fails when he makes the fatal mistake of sending Emilia to tell Othello and Desdemona of the attack on Cassio, something he could hardly fail to do. He refuses to offer any explanation for his actions when he is found out and caught.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Roderigo</persname>
<persdescription>Roderigo is a young man of Venice desperately in love with Desdemona, who has been rejected both by her and her father. He is completely under Iago&#8217;s spell, who milks his wallet for all it&#8217;s worth in the promise of furthering his suit to the lady. At Iago&#8217;s urging he wakes Brabantio to announce Desdemona&#8217;s flight to him, travels to Cyprus disguised in the hopes of gaining her favor, and in the end is willing to murder Cassio in the thought that this will bring him closer to his goal. He is rather brainless, somewhat cowardly, and only dimly perceives to what an extent he is Iago&#8217;s puppet. Wounded during his attempt on Cassio&#8217;s life, he is murdered by Iago to stop his mouth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Montano</persname>
<persdescription>Montano is the Governor of Cyprus. He sends news to the Venetian Senate of the Turkish advance towards the island. Esteemed by the Duke, he is however not considered as great a soldier as Othello, whom they send to replace him for the crisis. As he has served under the Moor and regards him highly, Montano has no complaints as to this. An upright soldier, he is an honorable gentleman, and disturbed at Cassio&#8217;s drunkenness. When he is gravely wounded by the latter, he charges Iago on his worth as a soldier to speak the truth about what happened during the quarrel. He is recovered enough to be on guard the night of Desdemona&#8217;s murder, and is one of those who responds to Emilia&#8217;s calls for help. He disarms Othello before he can do himself any harm, and chases after Iago, successfully capturing him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Clown</persname>
<persdescription>A Clown is one of Othello and Desdemona&#8217;s servants. He is incapable of resisting an opportunity for wordplay.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Desdemona</persname>
<persdescription>Desdemona is the daughter of the Venetian Senator Brabantio. A beautiful, happy girl, she has rejected all Venetian suitors, but is conquered by Othello&#8217;s tales of his life, and absconds from her father&#8217;s her to elope with him. Brought before the Duke and the Senate, she has the courage to stand up to her father and announce her choice to cleave to the Moor. She refuses to return to her father&#8217;s house, and requests instead to be allowed to follow Othello to the wars, partly because they have not yet consummated their marriage. She has a good wit, and enjoys sparring with Iago, having apparently grown fond of her lady-in-waiting&#8217;s husband during their voyage to Cyprus. She is also good friends with Cassio, who was her go-between to Othello when they were wooing, and is therefore more than willing to press Othello to restore him to favor. A kind and caring person, she is immediately concerned when Othello seems not well. She is rather na&amp;iuml;ve, and is shocked to discover Othello to be jealous, something he has never shown any sign of being. She also does not seem to catch on to his clear hints that she should drop the matter of Cassio. She is convinced by his tale of the magic in her missing handkerchief, and terrified by it. She blames government matters for his changed manner, not knowing of anything she can possibly have done to cause it herself. Even when publicly humiliated, she does not lose her temper, merely stating her innocence. She is capable of standing up to Othello as well when her honor is in question, but she is in the main rather passive. She trusts Iago enough to ask him for advice. She seems to judge other women by her own standards, unable to imagine that they might act otherwise than she does herself. Though she begs for her life on her deathbed, she still refuses to admit to a false guilt. With her last breath, she attempts to exonerate her husband of her murder.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Emilia</persname>
<persdescription>Emilia is Iago&#8217;s wife. As Desdemona intends to follow Othello to the war, the latter requests that Emilia become his wife&#8217;s attendant. Worldly-wise and mistreated by her husband, who suspects her of infidelity and regularly humiliates her in public, she is not the happiest of women. Hopeful of her husband&#8217;s favor, she picks up Desdemona&#8217;s handkerchief when the latter lets it fall, and gives it to Iago, who has been pestering her to take it. She defends Desdemona&#8217;s honor to the hilt, even to Othello&#8217;s face, and is convinced that someone has been poisoning his mind. She speaks loudly and passionately, not using the most demure language when she is angry. She does not believe that men see women as genuine human beings, and blames husbands for most sins a woman commits, though she looks down on courtesans. When she finds Desdemona murdered by Othello, she refuses to hold her tongue, screaming for help. She is desperate for her husband to deny what Othello claims he has done, but when Iago does not, she refuses to obey him, and willingly risks death to speak the truth. She is murdered by her husband.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Bianca</persname>
<persdescription>Bianca is a courtesan in Cyprus. Though she makes her living by selling her body, she is madly in love with one of her clients, Cassio, and dotes on him to excess. She hopes that he will marry her, and does not seem to realize that he laughs at her. Even when he gives her a handkerchief that she is convinced he received from another woman, she begs him to come to dinner at her house. She is arrested on suspicion of being involved in the assault on him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman of Cyprus stands with Montano looking out at the storm-ridden sea in the hopes of making out what is happening with the Turkish and Venetian fleets, but can see nothing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sailor</persname>
<persdescription>A Sailor brings news to the Venetian war council that the Turkish fleet is heading to Rhodes rather than Cyprus. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>An Officer goes with Cassio to find Othello and bring him to the Duke. He informs Brabantio of this, as well as the fact that the Senator himself has been called for.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger brings news to the Venetian war council that two Turkish fleets have met near Rhodes and are now aiming for Cyprus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Herald</persname>
<persdescription>A Herald proclaims the general festivities on Cyprus for the victory over the Turks, with an added plea for extra merriment to celebrate Othello&#8217;s marriage.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger brings news to the Venetian war council that two Turkish fleets have met near Rhodes and are now aiming for Cyprus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Musician</persname>
<persdescription>The First Musician playing the pipes is quite willing to cease playing when paid to do so.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Gentleman of Cyprus brings Montano the news that the Turkish fleet is sunk by the storm and that Cyprus is therefore safe. Having this news from Cassio, he shares the latter&#8217;s worry at the fact that the storm parted Othello&#8217;s ship from the rest of the fleet.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman of Cyprus is reasonably certain that the Turkish fleet will be drowned by the storm. He recognizes Iago, and knows the forms of salutation between ships and fortress.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>