<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Pericles">

<persona>
<persname short="GOW.">Gower</persname>
<persdescription>Gower is the English poet John Gower, whose work Confessio Amantis provided part of the plot of the play. Speaking in an old verse-form that signifies authority, he guides the audience through the play, most likely reading at times from a book. He sums up matters that would take too much time to show and offers the morals that should be taken away.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT.">Antiochus</persname>
<persdescription>Antiochus is the King of Antioch. He is an evil man who sleeps with his daughter and wants to keep her all to himself. As such he devises a riddle that any man wishing to marry her must solve; when they do not, he gets to cut off their heads. He is one of the most powerful men of the region, but does not go to war when poisoning an enemy will serve just as well. His realization that Pericles has guessed his secret sets the prince off on his wanderings. He dies when he is hit with a bolt of lightning.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PER.">Pericles</persname>
<persdescription>Pericles is the Prince and King of Tyre. A passive man who mostly reacts to events rather than causing them, he leads a rather doom-laden life, each blow leading him a little lower until he sinks into catatonic depression. He can be subject to dark moods in which he is dangerous, and his councilors know it. He is a good fighter and a physically brave man, willing to risk death in the hopes of achieving the hand of Antiochus&#8217;s daughter, but when he solves the riddle and realizes that Antiochus is aware that he has, he flees. Conscious of the danger to his realm from Antiochus if he stays there, he takes to the seas to visit Tarsus, though in the long run this will endanger his throne. Though a decent, honest man, he does not appear to be the most communicative of monarchs, often forgetting to let his councilors know that he&#8217;s still alive when he&#8217;s travelling. Shipwrecked in Pentapolis, he hides his identity as King until Antiochus is dead. He is deeply in love with his wife Thaisa, and mourns her death deeply. Having almost lost his throne when spending too far away without giving news of himself after his first shipwreck, after the second he spends the next fourteen years in Tyre. He leaves his daughter Marina with some friends on the other side of the sea, swearing not to cut his hair until she is married. He is distraught at the news of her death, fourteen years later, at which point he is very hairy indeed. This final blow leaves him almost comatose with depression, unspeaking and unresponsive, until he is brought back to life by the singing and talk of a young lady who turns out to be his not-dead daughter. At this point he hears the music of the spheres, and Diana the goddess of chastity appears to him in a vision. Obedient to her, he recounts his story at her temple at Ephesus, where he is reunited with his also-living wife, at which stage it would seem that his troubles are at an end. Though he apostrophizes the heavens, he never blames them, only begging for mercy. The list of his misfortunes &#8212; in danger of assassination, shipwrecked, almost shipwrecked again, wife dead in childbirth, daughter dead &#8212; lead one to wonder what exactly he&#8217;s done to deserve them; the answer is nothing. He is a very average sort of monarch, something of an Everyman to whom bad things happen.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HEL.">Helicanus</persname>
<persdescription>Helicanus is a counselor of Pericles&#8217;s, one who refuses to flatter him even when he is in a dangerous mood. Pericles trusts him enough to reveal to him why he has fled Antioch. He advises Pericles to travel to evade Antiochus&#8217;s assassins, and is named governor of Tyre during its lord&#8217;s absence. He is a deeply loyal man, who is shocked when some lords suggest that he take the crown, though he agrees that the lack of news from Pericles is troubling, and that if too much time passes, for the good of the country he will take the throne. He is relieved when Pericles returns. When the latter learns of his daughter&#8217;s death and sinks into depression, Helicanus follows him on his ship, for three months unsuccessfully attempting to get a response out of him. He is known as a wise man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ESCA.">Escanes</persname>
<persdescription>Escanes is a lord of Tyre, whom Helicanus trusts a great deal. When both Pericles and Helicanus are absent from Tyre, he governs the state in their place.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIM.">Simonides</persname>
<persdescription>King Simonides of Pentapolis is a monarch with a taste for show and practical jokes. He is beloved by his subjects as well as by his daughter Thaisa. He organizes a huge tournament as a birthday present for her. He wishes to absolutely certain that Thaisa and Pericles are genuinely in love with each other before he allows them to wed, and so pretends to be a jealous father to test them. He is erudite, and a benevolent man, the antithesis of Antiochus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLE.">Cleon</persname>
<persdescription>Cleon is the Governor of Tarsus. A weak and passive man who tends to let things happen, and is under his wife Dionyza&#8217;s thumb. He accepts to look after Pericles&#8217;s daughter when the latter leaves Marina with him, but however horrified he is fourteen years later when Dionyza has the girl killed, he does nothing other than expostulate a little. When Marina turns out to be alive and it becomes known what has happened, his people rise against him and burn him alive with his wife in his palace.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LYS.">Lysimachus</persname>
<persdescription>Lysimachus is the Governor of Mytilene, and not unknown to the brothels, though he is cautious and insists that the prostitutes he takes are disease-free. He is kind to the women he pays for there, and affected enough to not want to admit to what the trade they ply is. Like all the other men exposed to Marina, he is quickly converted from his lecherous ways and is very generous to her for it. He is intrigued when a ship decked in mourning approached his port and goes out to meet it. His opinion of Marina is by this time high enough that he agrees she may be able to cure the catatonic Pericles. Apparently he never tells Pericles that he first met Marina in a brothel, as he is able to convince the Prince of Tyre to let him marry his daughter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CER.">Cerimon</persname>
<persdescription>Cerimon is a physician of Ephesus. He is a kind, generous, and charitable old man, known throughout the town for his goodness and his skill. He is an excellent doctor, with hundreds of cures to his credit. When Thaisa is brought to him, he quickly realizes that she is not dead, and is able to revive her. He has very few doubts about his own skill.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="THAL.">Thaliard</persname>
<persdescription>Thaliard is a lord of Antioch who is ordered by Antiochus to poison Pericles, on pain of his own execution. He follows Pericles to Tyre. He is not particularly pleased at his mission, and seems happy that Pericles has gone to sea and that he will therefore not be faced with the necessity of killing him immediately.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PHIL.">Philemon</persname>
<persdescription>Philemon is one of Cerimon&#8217;s servants. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LEON.">Leonine</persname>
<persdescription>Leonine is a servant of Dionyza&#8217;s. He is a loyal and obedient man, willing to kill Marina in spite of his own inclination when ordered to. He once parted two people fighting, and was hurt in the process. He is not however brave enough to face up to a brace of pirates. Before returning to claim that she is dead, he makes sure that the pirates do indeed carry her off rather than simply raping her and leaving her be.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MARSHAL.">Marshal</persname>
<persdescription>A Marshal is in charge of seating the various participants of the tournament at the feast based on their performances.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAND.">Pander</persname>
<persdescription>Pander is a pimp running a brothel in Mytilene. He sends Boult to buy new women at the market, as those he already has are all rotted with venereal diseases. He lets his wife the Bawd take care of the prostitutes, while he looks after the money. He is unsentimental and makes no pretences about his job. Purchasing Marina for the high price he can get for selling her virginity, he is soon driven to distraction by how she instead turns all of his best and richest clients into virtuous men.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BOULT.">Boult</persname>
<persdescription>Boult is the doorkeeper at the brothel, and the third-in-command. Among his tasks are procuring new women at the slave market and advertising the new arrivals, and one of the perks of the job is his right to have a free go at the ladies on occasion. He is very taken with Marina and receives permission to sleep with her once she has been deprived of her virginity by a paying client. As she begins to convert the clients from whoring, he becomes convinced that there&#8217;s nothing for it but for him to take that task upon himself. Possessing the Pander and Bawd&#8217;s confidence, he is nevertheless bribable, and on being paid by Marina is able to convince them to follow the girl&#8217;s plan to be hired out as a teacher and singer. A bit of a crawler, he begs clients for tips as they leave, and knows them all. He is a realistic man, considering that the low morality of his job is still better than being mutilated in a war.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAN.">Man</persname>
<persdescription>A Man [mute role] comes to Cerimon for help after the storm, and is given a prescription.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DAUGH.">Daughter of Antiochus</persname>
<persdescription>Antiochus&#8217;s daughter is a beautiful girl, who has an incestuous relationship with her father. Whether she enjoys it or not is unknown. She is killed by a bolt of lightning.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DION.">Dionyza</persname>
<persdescription>Dionyza is Cleon&#8217;s wife. Though she swears to Pericles to bring up Marina with as much care as her own daughter Philoten, she soon grows envious of Marina for being just a bit better at everything than Philoten. This envy grows until she decides to have Marina murdered. She is excellent at acting kind to the girl in the meantime, however. Brusque and unsentimental, she has her husband completely under her thumb, and considers him a weakling. When Marina turns out to be alive and it becomes known what has happened, his people rise against Cleon and herself and burn them alive in their palace.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="THAI.">Thaisa</persname>
<persdescription>Thaisa is Simonides&#8217;s daughter. A beautiful girl, she is courted by princes from all over the world, but falls completely in love with the seemingly humble knight Pericles, who wins her birthday tournament. Insisting to her father that she will marry no-one else, no matter the cost, she passes his testing of her with flying colors. Though educated enough to read, she shows no great signs of intelligence. Appearing to die in childbirth, she is thrown overboard, only to be revived by Cerimon when he finds her. She then decides become a nun, for some reason never trying to find out if her husband is still alive. She is overjoyed to find him still living fourteen years later, and to meet her daughter Marina. She has a beautiful voice, good posture, and straight eyebrows.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Marina</persname>
<persdescription>Marina is Pericles and Thaisa&#8217;s daughter, born at sea in the middle of a storm. With her father mourning the death of his wife, she is left with his friends Cleon and Dionyza, who promise to bring her up along with their daughter Philoten. Trained in all the maidenly arts, she is an excellent weaver, embroiderer, musician, singer, dancer, little realizing that her superiority to Philoten in these matters enrages Dinoyza. A very innocent fourteen-year-old, she mourns the death of her nurse Lychorida deeply, and is stunned to discover that Leonine has been ordered to murder her. Captured by pirates and sold to a brothel, her almost pathological chastity makes her less of a bargain that the owners expected. Simply by talking, she is able to convince all the clients who want to pay for her to stop whoring. By bribing Boult, she gets him both to not rape her and to propose to the Bawd and Pander that she be hired out as a teacher rather than as a whore. Her fame growing, she is called upon to attempt to reach the catatonic man on a newly-arrived ship, who turns out to be her father. She looks very much like her mother, as well as having her voice, eyes, and straight-backed posture. Beautiful, obedient, accomplished, and chaste, she is every father&#8217;s ideal daughter. She marries Lysimachus, who first met her in the brothel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LYC.">Lychorida</persname>
<persdescription>Lychorida is Thaisa&#8217;s old nurse, and appointed to take care of her child once it is born. In the middle of the storm she brings the newborn Marina to Pericles, announcing at the same time Thaisa&#8217;s death. Pericles leaves her with Marina at Tarsus. Greatly loved by her charge, she dies fourteen years later, and is given a great tomb by Cleon and Dionyza.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAWD.">Bawd</persname>
<persdescription>Bawd is the Pander&#8217;s wife. She is in charge of the occupants of the brothel and has no patience for virginal modesty. If one of the prostitutes has a child, she brings it up until it&#8217;s of an age to join the trade. She is impressed by Marina&#8217;s possibilities, though she thinks her an impossible goody-two-shoes. An excellent businesswoman, she has a good sense of marketing as well as connections, particularly her trading with the governor, Lysimachus. Marina&#8217;s converting the latter is the last straw for her, and she orders Boult to rape the girl and get things over with. She finally agrees to hire out Marina as a teacher and singer rather than as a prostitute, and that way finally begins to make some profit on her investment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. FISH.">First Fisherman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Fisherman is the master of the fishing crew. Though he drives his men hard and has a cynical view of how society works, he has a softer side that pities those caught on ships in storms. He is charitable towards the shipwrecked and is as generous as he can afford to be.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SAIL.">First Sailor</persname>
<persdescription>The First Sailor informs Pericles that Thaisa&#8217;s body must be thrown overboard, as it is ill-luck to have a corpse on board a ship, especially during a storm. He pays no attention when told he is merely superstitious.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. KNIGHT., ALL KNIGHTS.">First Knight</persname>
<persdescription>The First Knight is from Sparta, and comes to Pentapolis to woo Thaisa. He is a gallant man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. LORD. TYRE.">First Lord of Tyre</persname>
<persdescription>First Lord of Tyre is glad to see Pericles return from Antioch, or at least says that he is. He is envious of Escanes for having Helicanus&#8217;s ear, and leads the mutiny that tries to dethrone Pericles and have Helicanus take the crown. Convinced by Helicanes to wait for a year, he pledges to travel to try and find Pericles in the meantime and convince him that he had best retrn home. This mission is successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DIA.">Diana</persname>
<persdescription>Diana is the goddess of chastity. She appears to Pericles in a dream and commands him to publically tell his story at the altar of her temple in Ephesus (one of the Seven Wonders of the World). She does not tell him why, but his obedience restores his wife to him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT. MESS.">Antiochan Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Antiochan Messenger reports to Antiochus that Pericles has fled, leaving the king no choice but to send Thaliard after him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. LORD. TYRE.">Second Lord of Tyre</persname>
<persdescription>Second Lord of Tyre is glad to see Pericles return from Antioch, or at least says that he is. He is convinced later that Pericles is dead, and that therefore Helicanus should take the crown, as otherwise he fears for the stability of the state. He is convinced by Helicanus&#8217;s arguments to wait a year, and goes with the other Lords in their successful endeavor to find Pericles and warn him that he had best return home.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. FISH.">Second Fisherman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Fisherman (Pilch) has little regard for the shipwrecked, especially those who appear to have no useful skills in life. He does not think much of poor men&#8217;s chances in society, and though he offers to help Pericles look more respectable, he makes sure that Pericles will remember to reward them once he&#8217;s gained his fortune.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. FISH.">Third Fisherman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Fisherman (Patchbreech) has a small store of pity for the storm-wrecked, but he is more concerned with witty ranting about the rich, for whom he has a poor regard &#8212; particularly rich churchmen. He is a loyal subject to his king. He wears in old, often-repaired trousers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. LORD. PENT.">First Lord of Pentapolis</persname>
<persdescription>First Lord of Pentapolis announces to Simonides that the knights are ready for the tournament. He does not think much of Pericles, given his rusty armor. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. LORD. PENT.">Second Lord of Pentapolis</persname>
<persdescription>Second Lord of Pentapolis considers Pericles to be some sort of barbarian, given how he dresses for the tournament.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. LORD. PENT.">Third Lord of Pentapolis</persname>
<persdescription>Third Lord of Pentapolis thinks that Pericles may be a poseur who specifically let his armor grow rusty just to impress people.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. KNIGHT., ALL KNIGHTS.">Second Knight</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Knight is a prince of Macedon, who comes to Pentapolis to woo Thaisa. He is disappointed that he and his fellow knights are not allowed to speak with her once the tournament is over.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. KNIGHT., ALL KNIGHTS.">Third Knight</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Knight is from Antioch, and comes to Pentapolis more to win the tournament than in the hopes of winning Thaisa&#8217;s hand. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALL KNIGHTS.">Fourth Knight </persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Knight is Athenian, and comes to Pentapolis to woo Thaisa. He is complimentary of her good looks.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALL KNIGHTS.">Fifth Knight</persname>
<persdescription>The Fifth Knight is a Corinthian prince, proud of his trustworthiness.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FIVE PAGES">Five Pages</persname>
<persdescription>Five Pages [mute roles] bear the insignia of the five knights to Simonides and Thaisa for them to identify and interpret.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. LORD. TYRE.">Third Lord of Tyre</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Lord of Tyre [mute role] joins the other two in their conspiracy to have Pericles replaced by Helicanus, and follows them on their successful endeavor to find Pericles and warn him that he had best return home.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SAIL.">Second Sailor</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Sailor finds a large chest to use as a coffin for Thaisa&#8217;s body before throwing it overboard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT. EPH.">First Gentleman of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman of Ephesus was so terrified by the storm that he left his house out of fear it would collapse on him. He is surprised to see his neighbor Cerimon also up early, and is awed to see him revive an apparent corpse, swearing to tell everyone he knows of it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GENT. EPH.">Second Gentleman of Ephesus</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman of Ephesus was so terrified by the storm that he left his house out of fear it would collapse on him. He is very complimentary, to not say fawning, about his neighbor Cerimon, and tends to agree with everything he says. He is impressed by the doctor&#8217;s reviving of Thaisa.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EPH. SERV.">Ephesan Servant</persname>
<persdescription>An Ephesan Servant has come to Cerimon in hopes of help for his master, but learns that there is nothing to be done. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. PIRATE.">First Pirate</persname>
<persdescription>The First Pirate stops Leonine from killing Marina, and considers the man a villain for doing so. He guarantees Boult that she&#8217;s a virgin when selling her. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. PIRATE.">Second Pirate</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Pirate is delighted at having capture Marina, who he realizes will fetch an excellent price.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. PIRATE.">Third Pirate</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Pirate is intent that all the pirates should have their share of Marina&#8217;s price.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT. MYT.">First Gentleman of Mytilene</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman of Mytilene came to the brothel intent on purchasing Marina&#8217;s virginity, and is completely converted to virtue by her arguments.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GENT. MYT.">Second Gentleman of Mytilene</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman of Mytilene came to the brothel intent on purchasing Marina&#8217;s virginity, and is completely converted to virtue by her arguments, wanting nothing more now than to hear nuns singing holy hymns.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. TYR. MESS.">First Tyrian Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>First Tyrian Messenger [mute role] brings news to Pericles from Helicanus that Thaliard is after him. He is knighted by Pericles.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. TYR. MESS.">Second Tyrian Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Second Tyrian Messenger [mute role] brings Pericles the news that Antiochus and his daughter are dead, struck by lightning, and that it is therefore now safe for Pericles to return to Tyre, which would be a good idea given that the Tyrian lords are on the verge of giving the crown to Helicanus. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GENT. TYRE.">First Gentleman of Tyre</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman of Tyre accompanies Pericles on his ship, and is called up by Helicanus to make sure there is a decent welcoming party for Lysimachus when the latter comes on board.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TYR. SAIL.">Sailor of Tyre</persname>
<persdescription>Sailor of Tyre speaks with the Sailor of Mytilene who asks him where his ship is from, and informs Helicanus of Lysimachus&#8217;s arrival.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MYT. SAIL.">Sailor of Mytilene</persname>
<persdescription>Sailor of Mytilene [mute tole] brings Lysimachus to Pericles&#8217;s ship to find out whose it is. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VIRGINS">Virgins</persname>
<persdescription>Virgins [mute roles] are nuns of Diana attending on her altar with Thaisa.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LORD. TAR.">Lord of Tarsus</persname>
<persdescription>A Lord of Tarsus comes to tell Cleon of the approach of a friendly-seeming fleet. With all the other Tarsians, he swears to pray for Pericles when the latter announces that he has brought food to the city.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR. LADY.">Marina&#8217;s Lady</persname>
<persdescription>Marina&#8217;s Lady [mute role] accompanies her when she is teaching, and comes with her on board Pericles&#8217;s ship. She may sing the song with Marina.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. CER. SERV.">Cerimon's First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Cerimon&#8217;s First Servant knows his master will be interested when a large chest is tossed up on the shore after a storm, and brings it to him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CER. SERV.">Cerimon's Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Cerimon&#8217;s Second Servant [mute role] helps his fellow servant carry in the large chest they have found on the shore.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LORD. MYT.">Lord of Myteline</persname>
<persdescription>Lord of Myteline accompanies Lysimachus on his visit to Pericles&#8217;s ship, and is the first to think that Marina might succeed in curing him.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>
