<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Richard III">

<persona>
<persname short="K. EDW.">King Edward the Fourth</persname>
<persdescription>King Edward IV is the same as the King Edward of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>, who won his throne by battle. He is much older now, and very ill. He is incurably optimistic and hopes to be able to reconcile all of the warring factions of his court, but at the same time is suspicious and superstitious enough to imprison his brother Clarence on the word of the fortune-teller. (Considering how easily Clarence betrays people &#8212; see <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref> &#8212; this is not necessarily foolish on his part.) His marrying a penniless widow and raising her brothers and sons to the nobility incensed many of his followers (see Henry VI Part Three) and they have still not calmed down, despite the King&#8217;s best efforts. He still enjoys the company of women, and keeps a mistress fairly openly. Though he signs a death warrant for his brother, he rescinds the order; the shock of hearing that it has been carried out shocks him to his core and brings on his death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRINCE.">Edward, Prince of Wales</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Edward is King Edward&#8217;s eldest son and heir to his throne, the same as the baby of the final scene in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. He is a proud and intelligent child who intends to rule properly, and is suspicious of his uncle Richard. He loves his mother&#8217;s relatives and is quietly distraught at their execution. He gives every sign of growing into an excellent monarch, even intending to fight in France like another Henry V, but this is not to be. Disinherited and locked in the Tower by his uncle, he is smothered in his sleep along with his brother. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="YORK.">Richard, Duke of York</persname>
<persdescription>Duke of York (Richard) is King Edward&#8217;s second son. He is a cheeky young thing, bright beyond his years, given to eavesdropping and not shy with his opinions. He gets on reasonably well with his namesake uncle, but slanders him in his absence; he is the only person who dares to comment on Richard&#8217;s deformities in his presence. Even his mother and brother think he goes too far sometimes. He is scared of ghosts. Locked in the Tower by his uncle, along with his brother Edward, he is smothered in his sleep. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLAR.">George, Duke of Clarence</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST. OF C.">Ghost of Clarence</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>George, Duke of Clarence is the brother of King Edward and Richard of Gloucester, and the same as the Clarence of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. Not the most intelligent of the three brothers, he is easily led by the nose by Richard, whom he is convinced loves him dearly. Always an object of suspicion because of his betrayals during the civil wars (see <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>), he is sent to the Tower by Edward on the basis of a superstitious prophecy. The memory of his various treacheries gnaws at his conscience. Clarence is known to be a convincing speaker, and attempts to talk his way out of his assassination; always gullible, he dies refusing to believe that Richard is behind his death. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EDW.">Edward Plantagenet</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CHIL.">Children</persname>
	<persname short="GHOSTS. PRINC.">Ghosts of Princes</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Edward Plantagenet is the son of George Duke of Clarence, and is in his grandmother the Duchess of York&#8217;s keeping after Clarence&#8217;s arrest. Ferreting out the fact of his father&#8217;s death from his grandmother, he blames the King, as he trusts his uncle Richard&#8217;s slanders against Queen Elizabeth. He refuses to weep for the King&#8217;s death unless the Queen weeps for his father&#8217;s. Richard has him locked up to avoid more succession troubles as he takes the throne.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GLOU., K. RICH.">Richard, Duke of Gloucester</persname>
<persdescription>Richard Duke of Gloucester, later King Richard III, is rather a nasty piece of work. Duplicitous, ambitious, murderous, and quite jolly about all of these things, he has been planning to take the crown for some time now (see <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>). He possesses a very keen, very dark sense of humor, and revels in his own mischief. He thinks nothing of killing off brothers or other family members in order to obtain his goal, although it must be admitted that once he gets the throne he doesn&#8217;t really seem to know what to do next. Though crippled, with an essentially useless left arm, a limp and a hunchback, he is a brilliant soldier and very dangerous fighter, though his abilities on the battlefield are almost nothing next to what he can do with his mind alone. He is excellent at insinuating and sowing discord, and is a master at double entendres. The ultimate actor, he insists on his own honesty to anyone who will hear before dropping the mask and confiding to himself (or the audience) that he is not. Even those who know perfectly well what he is capable of remain convinced that he will never turn on them, because they know and are therefore accomplices, never realizing that Richard works only for one person, himself. Richard is and has always been loathed by his mother, who suffered during her pregnancy with him and considers him her greatest shame. He tests himself constantly, whether in aiming for the crown when he no longer has war to distract him, successfully wooing the widow of a man he killed over the coffin of her father-in-law, or organizing a coup that sheds almost no blood. He despises his brother Edward&#8217;s sensuality, as he himself takes little pleasure in anything but manipulating people and his own successful villainy. He is a great religious hypocrite, swearing mostly by Saint Paul and always clothing himself in meekness and piety. Richard has a talent for bringing out the worst in people and bending that worst to his own will without their realizing it. Though he prefers to work indirectly, he is not a coward, and refuses to flee from the battle of Bosworth, fighting at the most dangerous parts of the battle, seeking out Richmond. As self-aware as he is, he is deeply disturbed when on the eve of the battle of Bosworth he discovers he has a conscience; he is almost as unsettled by the fact that no-one will mourn for him when he dies as by the realization that he does actually love one being &#8212; himself.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RICHM.">Henry, Earl of Richmond</persname>
<persdescription>Henry, Earl of Richmond is the grown-up Richmond of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>, Lord Stanley&#8217;s stepson and the next heir in blood of the Lancastrian cause. He becomes the focal point of resistance to Richard, offering refuge to all those who flee England in fear as Richard&#8217;s regime takes over. A pious man, he rallies his troops in God&#8217;s name, offering himself as England&#8217;s salvation against tyranny and rekindling their anger by listing Richard&#8217;s wrongs. Pardoning all those who fought against him so long as they acknowledge his victory, he marries the daughter of King Edward and Queen Elizabeth as a way to join the two families of York and Lancaster in one and thus end the cause of the civil wars. It is possible that he has dressed several of his men as himself to keep himself safe in the battle of Bosworth. He kills Richard personally, and becomes King Henry VII.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CARD.">Cardinal Bourchier</persname>
<persdescription>Cardinal Bourchier, Archbishop of Canterbur, accompanies Prince Edward to London, and then goes to help convince Queen Elizabeth to let her son York leave sanctuary. He stands upon the privilege of the church, but is reasonably easy to convince otherwise.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ARCH.">Thomas Rotherham, Archbishop of York</persname>
<persdescription>Thomas Rotherham, Archbishop of York, is a friend of Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s. He is shocked at the news of the arrest of Rivers and Grey, and offers the Queen sanctuary.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ELY.">John Morton, Bishop of Ely</persname>
<persdescription>John Morton, Bishop of Ely, is a member of the regency council following King Edward&#8217;s death, who wishes the young Prince to be crowned as soon as possible. He owns a garden that produces superlative strawberries.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BUCK.">Duke of Buckingham</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF BUCK.">Ghost of Duke of Buckingham</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Duke of Buckingham is Richard&#8217;s closest ally as he maneuvers himself onto the throne. An enemy of the Queen&#8217;s family, he disregards Queen Margaret&#8217;s warnings about Richard; he believes himself to be much more in control of the situation than he actually is, not realizing that Richard allows him to see himself in the driver&#8217;s seat. A good actor, Buckingham is the major force in the coup that sets Richard on the throne, and the mastermind of the show that convinces the citizens that the Duke of Gloucester is reluctant to take the crown. He is cunning and cynical, but cannot go as far as Richard does; the thought of putting the Princes to death shocks him, which immediately loses him Richard&#8217;s favor. Realizing that he will never be safe and that the new King does not intend to share any form of power, he flees the court and soon raises a rebellion against the man he put on the throne. His army is scattered by a flood, and the invading Richmond does not trust him, leading to the failure of his rebellion and his own capture. He realizes as he is led to execution that he is paying exactly the penalty he begged for himself should he break his oath when he swore friendship with Queen Elizabeth. Buckingham is a proud, daring, and ambitious man who suffers from not realizing the extent of Richard&#8217;s malice and the fact that nobody can trust him. His ghost comes to haunt Richard the night before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NOR.">Duke of Norfolk</persname>
<persdescription>John, Duke of Norfolk, the same as the Norfolk of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>, is a loyal supporter of King Richard&#8217;s who commands one of the main battalions at Bosworth. He points out to Richard that there is no time for private executions at the start of a battle. He is later unable to come to Richard&#8217;s rescue, and is killed in the battle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SUR.">Earl of Surrey</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Surrey, son to Duke of Norfolk, is one of Richard&#8217;s supporters, who does not look very optimistic on the eve of the battle of Bosworth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RIV.">Earl Rivers</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF R.">Ghost of Earl Rivers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Earl Rivers (Anthony Woodvile) is Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s brother, the same as the Rivers of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. Ennobled following his sister&#8217;s marriage, he is one of the chief irritants to the old nobility at the court of England, who regard him as an upstart. Though he tries to keep in his place, he will defend his sisters against all comers, including Richard Duke of Gloucester, one of their chief enemies. He fought on the Yorkist side in the wars and was present at the killing of Queen Margaret&#8217;s son Edward. He dislikes Lord Hastings and was responsible for having him sent to the Tower. He attempts to comfort his sister after King Edward&#8217;s death, and questions why his nephew should only have a small escort to come to London, though he agrees with Buckingham&#8217;s explanation that a large escort might frighten the country. He is mistrusted by the common people as well as by the nobility, and no-one other than his sister weeps for him when he is taken and executed on Richard&#8217;s orders. He meets his death well, though remembering the curse Queen Margaret put on him for not saving her son at his murder. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOR.">Marquess of Dorset</persname>
<persdescription>Marquess of Dorset is Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s son by her previous marriage, ennobled after his mother&#8217;s marriage to King Edward. This leaves him a deep irritant to the traditional nobility, who regard him as an upstart, and to the populace, who resent his pride. He fought on the Yorkist side in the wars and was present at the killing of Queen Margaret&#8217;s son Edward. He attempts to comfort his mother after King Edward&#8217;s death. He flies England to join Richmond in France to avoid being arrested and executed like his brother and uncle after Richard takes power.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GREY.">Lord Grey</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF G.">Ghost of Lord Grey</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Lord Grey is Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s son by her previous marriage, ennobled after his mother&#8217;s marriage to King Edward. This leaves him a deep irritant to the traditional nobility, who regard him as an upstart, and to the populace, who resent his pride. He attempts to reassure his mother that they are secure despite the King&#8217;s illness. He is one of the lords who go to fetch Prince Edward after the King&#8217;s death, on which journey he is arrested on Richard&#8217;s orders and soon put to death. He dies well. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="OXF.">Earl of Oxford</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Oxford is one of Richmond&#8217;s supporters and military leaders, the same as the Oxford of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. He has been a Lancastrian supporter all his life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HAST.">Lord Hastings</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF H.">Ghost of Lord Hastings</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Lord William Hastings is the Lord Chamberlain, the same characters as the Hastings of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. He is not a friend of Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s family, particularly as her son has had him imprisoned. However, he is a loyal subject of King Edward&#8217;s and a strong supporter of legitimacy, preferring to see the rightful heir on the throne however young and even if it means bringing the Queen&#8217;s family to power. He is a faintly gullible sort, unable to understand why the Queen should take sanctuary after her husband dies, seeing as they have all sworn friendship at the late King&#8217;s request. He takes Mrs. Shore, King Edward&#8217;s mistress, for his own after Edward dies. Hastings has great hopes for power under Richard as Protector, seeing it as a chance to settle accounts with some old enemies, and never dreams that he might himself be at risk. He is an energetic man with a carefree manner about him, and is not a particularly deep thinker; he takes every man at face value and pays no attention to ill omens, which is unfortunate for him. His inability to see where things are headed costs him his head. His ghost comes to haunt Richard the night before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="STAN.">Lord Stanley</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Stanley, Earl of Derby is a close friend of Lord Hastings and Henry Earl of Richmond&#8217;s stepfather. He is no great fan of the Queen&#8217;s family, but he is a good and honest man so far as he can afford to be. The execution of Rivers, Grey and Vaughan disturb him, as he sees that no-one may now be safe, and a premonitory dream almost leads him to flee the country until Hastings refuses to follow him. He dares say nothing when Hastings is suddenly condemned to death. Though he appears to support Richard, he works against him as much as he can, helping Dorset to escape to France and acting as go-between for the marriage arrangement between Richmond and Princess Elizabeth. Despite his reputation for honesty he cannot entirely trick Richard, who takes his son George as a hostage when Richmond attacks. As he loves his son, Stanley waits until the last possible moment before betraying Richard. He takes it upon himself to crown Richmond as King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LOV.">Lord Lovel</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Lovel is one of Richard&#8217;s supporters. He takes Lord Hastings to his execution and delivers the head to Richard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAUG.">Sir Thomas Vaughan</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF V.">Ghost of Sir Thomas Vaughan</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Vaughan is a knight in the escort sent to fetch Prince Edward to England. He is arrested at the same time as Rivers and Grey, and is executed with them. His ghost returns to haunt Richard before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RAT.">Sir Richard Ratcliffe</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Richard Ratcliffe is one of Richard&#8217;s chief supporters, and his major executioner at the time of his coup. He takes care of the deaths of Rivers, Grey and Vaughan, as well of that of Lord Hastings. He is one of Richard&#8217;s close attendants on the eve of the battle of Bosworth. Ratcliffe is a very loyal man, staying faithful to Richard even when the latter mistreats him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CATE.">Sir William Catesby</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Catesby is one of Richard&#8217;s chief supporters and an important figure in his coup. He attempts to win Hastings over to Richard&#8217;s cause with a quite stunning lack of subtlety, and fails. He is one of the main actors in the scene that convinces the citizens that Richard is reluctant to take the throne. He later arranges for the marriage of Clarence&#8217;s daughter to a nobody and starts spreading the rumors that make the Lady Anne&#8217;s death less of a surprise. A close attendant on Richard, he follows him to the battle of Bosworth and attempts to help him to flee when it becomes clear that all is lost, only to see his offer refused. Catesby is a very loyal man, staying faithful to Richard even when the latter mistreats him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TYR.">Sir James Tyrrel</persname>
<persdescription>Sir James Tyrell is a poor and bitter knight who is willing to do anything to enrich himself and make himself more prominent. He is a crawler and a sycophant, but discovers that he has a conscience after killing the two Princes for Richard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BLUNT.">Sir James Blunt</persname>
<persdescription>Sir James Blunt is one of Richmond&#8217;s supporters, a captain in his army, and serves as his messenger to Stanley on the eve of the battle of Bosworth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HERB.">Sir Walter Herbert</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Walter Herbert is one of Richmond&#8217;s supporters, a well-known and respected soldier. He is convinced that Richard&#8217;s followers will all desert him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BRAK.">Sir Robert Brakenbury</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Robert Brakenbury is the Lieutenant of the Tower of London, a stubbornly loyal man who does his job to the letter no matter his own thoughts on the matter. He does not wish to get caught up in politics, rather only to obey whoever happens to be wearing the crown, which is where he recognizes his loyalties to lie. He washes his hands of all that does not concern him and prefers not to know what is going on even when it is obvious. He is killed at the battle of Bosworth, fighting for Richard.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BRAND.">Sir William Brandon</persname>
<persdescription>Sir William Brandon [mute role] is one of Richmond&#8217;s supporters, given the high (and dangerous) honor of carrying the Earl&#8217;s standard into the battle of Bosworth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHRIS.">Christopher Urswick</persname>
<persdescription>Christopher Urswick, a Priest is used as a messenger between Stanley and Richmond. He brings Stanley an update on Richmond&#8217;s forces.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HAST.">Hastings</persname>
<persdescription>Hastings, a Pursuivant is a herald who works for the College of Arms. He crosses paths with Hastings as the latter is about to leave to go to the council meeting, and is told of the coming execution of Rivers, Grey and Vaughan, and given a large sum of money to go spend in a pub. He is a deferential man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="Q. ELIZ.">Queen Elizabeth</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Elizabeth is the wife of King Edward, the Lady Gray of <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>. A penniless widow with children when she married the King, she is hated by most of the old nobility for her rise to power and the way her family has snuck its way into aristocratic ranks (see <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>). Despite her best efforts, she is unable to gain their friendship and is blamed for all of King Edward&#8217;s unpopular decisions, which leaves her terrified of what will happen to her and her family once the very ill King dies. She puts up with a great deal from her opponents, but even her patience has its limits and she sometimes snaps, especially at her brother-in-law Richard, the worst of her detractors and a man she rightly fears. The fact that he is to be Protector over her son until his majority shakes her, and she flies to sanctuary with her younger son York to attempt to avoid the calamities she foresees. This is unfortunately unsuccessful, as York is taken from her and she is separated from her children forever. Her brother Rivers is executed, along with her son by a previous marriage, Gray; she urges her last remaining son, Dorset, to flee. She promises to do anything to have her daughters spared by Richard, and is shocked and horrified when Richard proposes to marry her daughter Elizabeth. His persuasion appears to convince her to try to get her daughter&#8217;s agreement to the marriage, but she may simply be dissembling to give herself time to get away. Her daughter ends up marrying Richmond. Queen Elizabeth is rarely strong, and generally takes fate&#8217;s blows without trying to avoid them; her suffering is almost constant throughout the play, and she is haunted by Queen Margaret&#8217;s curse on her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="Q. MAR.">Queen Margaret</persname>
<persdescription>Queen Margaret is the widow of King Henry VI, the same character as the Queen Margaret of the <persnameref>Henry VI</persnameref> plays. Though exiled, she returns to England to witness the destruction of her enemies. Half-crazed by grief, she ritually curses all those who stood by as her son was murdered and did nothing as well as those who did the deed and those who profited. She refuses to acknowledge any of her own crimes (see the Henry VI plays) and concentrates instead on the people who hold the power she has lost. She ends up almost befriending Queen Elizabeth once the latter&#8217;s woes come to match her own. Her hatred seems to be all that keeps her alive. She is often more a chorus figure than an actual character.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DUCH.">Duchess of York</persname>
<persdescription>The Duchess of York is the mother of King Edward, Clarence and Richard, and the widow of the Duke of York of the three <persnameref>Henry VI </persnameref>plays. She is a tough, uncompromising woman whom grief has left bitter and who has no illusions about her third son, whom she openly detests and considers a shame to herself. She tries to protect her grandchildren from the realities of the world, but unsuccessfully; she is not overly kind to her daughter-in-law Queen Elizabeth, and forever reminds people of just how many family members she herself has lost. She is sick of seeing all her family fight for the crown and all the ills that desire causes. She ends up as a full opponent of her own son, openly challenging him for the murders he has done, which so discomfits him that he has drums drown her out. Her last words to him are a curse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANNE.">Lady Anne</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="GHOST OF LADY.">Ghost of Lady Anne</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Lady Anne is the daughter of the Earl of Warwick (see <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>) and the widow of Prince Edward of Lancaster, whom Richard helped kill. She is the only person to follow her father-in-law Henry VI&#8217;s coffin to burial and to mourn him. Suddenly courted by Richard at the height of her grief, she is taken off her guard but finds herself unable to resist his performance as a lover. Despite her quite genuine hatred, despair and mourning, and her insistence that she is making no promises, she ends up completely seduced by him. Though this ends up making her Queen, it does not bring her happiness, which she blames on her having cursed Richard&#8217;s future wife before taking on that role. Richard&#8217;s bad dreams keep her awake at night, and she does not sleep well. She is soon perfectly aware that Richard does not care for her, and grows certain that he will kill her. She grows ill and dies, very likely poisoned by him. Anne is a weak and passive woman, though she attempts to be a good aunt to the various children of her husband&#8217;s brothers. Her ghost comes to haunt Richard the night before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRESS.">Tressel</persname>
<persdescription>Tressel [mute role] is a gentleman who accompanies the Lady Anne as she takes the corpse of Henry VI to burial. He escorts her when she leaves to go to Crosby House at Richard&#8217;s request.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BERK.">Berkeley</persname>
<persdescription>Berkeley [mute role] is a gentleman who accompanies the Lady Anne as she takes the corpse of Henry VI to burial. He escorts her when she leaves to go to Crosby House at Richard&#8217;s request.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="KEEP.">Keeper in the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Keeper is George Duke of Clarence&#8217;s jailer, who converses pleasantly enough with his prisoner.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAY.">Lord Mayor of London</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Mayor of London is one of the chief officials of the country, whose recognition of Richard as King is key for his coup to succeed. He is sent for so that Buckingham and Richard can justify Hastings&#8217;s execution to him, which they easily do. He does not realize that he is being co-opted into becoming a part of Richard&#8217;s plot, but is slowly convinced to come with his aldermen and ask Richard to take the throne. Whether he does so out of genuine conviction, out of opportunism at seeing which way the wind is turning, or out of fear, is unknown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHER.">Sheriff of Wiltshire</persname>
<persdescription>The Sheriff of Wiltshire leads Buckingham to his execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PURS.">Pursuivant</persname>
<persdescription>Hastings, a Pursuivant is a herald who works for the College of Arms. He crosses paths with Hastings as the latter is about to leave to go to the council meeting, and is told of the coming execution of Rivers, Gray and Vaughan, and given a large sum of money to go spend in a pub. He is a deferential man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MARG.">Margaret Plantagenet</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="CHIL.">Children</persname>
	<persname short="GHOSTS. PRINC.">Ghosts of Princes</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Margaret Plantagenet, Countess of Salisbury, is the daughter of George Duke of Clarence, and is in her grandmother the Duchess of York&#8217;s keeping after Clarence&#8217;s arrest. She follows her brother Edward&#8217;s lead in things, swearing to pray against the King whom they blame for their father&#8217;s death, and refusing to weep for the King unless the Queen weep for their father. She loves her cousin Edward, who ought to become King, and goes with her aunt Anne to try and see him at the Tower. Richard puts her out of the way by marrying her off to someone of no consequence, to avoid more succession troubles as he takes the throne.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRIEST.">Sir John</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John, a Priest comes to speak to Lord Hastings the morning of the council meeting, but Lord Hastings puts him off till the next Sunday.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MUR.">First Murderer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.">Both First and Second Murderers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Murderer is a reasonably cautious man, requiring a warrant to get to Clarence and commending Brankenbury on the wisdom of informing the King that he has handed Clarence over. He is a resolute man who intends to stiffen his companion&#8217;s spine, and does not give in to the hints of conscience that occasionally attack him. He enjoys toying with his victim, answering all of his pleas with the plainspoken assertion that he is going to die, and giving reasons for it. He comes up with the odd idea of drowning Clarence in a cask of wine. He is scornful of his companion&#8217;s attack of remorse, but happy to pocket the entire fee on his own, and intelligent enough to know to get out of the country as soon as possible once the deed is done.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MUR.">Second Murderer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. 1. MUR. AND 2. MUR.">Both First and Second Murderers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Murderer is a blunt fellow who is less secure about his job than he would like. He is irritated about the fact that he has a conscience, but he has learned to control it, though it sometimes takes a while. The promise of gold always helps the process. Clarence speaking to him and his companion weakens his resolve, and he attempts to bolster himself by giving Clarence reasons why he deserves to die. Not wanting the man to die under an illusion, he lets him know that it is Richard who has sent them. He distracts Clarence in the oldest way to give the First Murderer a chance to stab him, but seeing Clarence dead truly bothers him and he runs off, refusing any part of the fee.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GENTLEMAN.">Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>A Gentleman is one of those carrying King Henry&#8217;s coffin.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. CIT.">First Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>The First Citizen is shaken by the King&#8217;s death, but is more optimistic than his fellows, trusting that the royal uncles on both sides of the family are wise men. He is either very trusting or putting a good face on his fears.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. CIT.">Second Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Citizen is deeply worried by what will come after the King&#8217;s death, though he holds out some hope that the council will govern well until Prince Edward comes of age.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. CIT.">Third Citizen</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Citizen is profoundly uneasy about what will happen after the King&#8217;s death. He realizes all too well that there are two factions in the regency council that hate each other, and is aware of how dangerous Richard of Gloucester is and how intractable are the Queen&#8217;s relatives. He believes in being ready for the worst, just in case.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS. QUEEN.">Messenger to the Queen</persname>
<persdescription>Messenger to the Queen brings the Queen the news that her son and brother have been arrested on Richard and Buckingham&#8217;s orders.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="STAN. MESS.">Stanley Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Stanley Messenger is sent to Lord Hastings with the tale of Lord Stanley&#8217;s premonitory dream, to beg Hastings to fly to the north with Stanley.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCRIV.">Scrivener</persname>
<persdescription>A Scrivener is a public scribe with particularly nice handwriting who has been hired by Catesby to write up the official explanation for Hastings&#8217;s execution so that it can be posted for all to see. He realizes quite well that the explanation is nonsense, but also that no-one is going to dare point out the fact, himself included.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALD.">Aldermen of London</persname>
<persdescription>Aldermen of London accompany the Lord Mayor to request that Richard take the crown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HALB.">Halberds</persname>
<persdescription>Halberds [mute roles] escort a variety of people to their deaths, as well as King Henry&#8217;s coffin to its grave.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TWO BISH.">Two Bishops</persname>
<persdescription>Two Bishops [mute roles] walk out on the walls of Baynard&#8217;s Castle with Richard to give the impression that he has been praying rather than plotting to take the throne.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAGE.">Page</persname>
<persdescription>A Page keeps tabs on people who might be useful to the King for him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger comes to inform Richard that rebellion has broken out in Devonshire.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger comes to inform Richard that rebellion has broken out in Kent.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger attempts to inform Richard that Buckingham&#8217;s army has been ruined by a flood, but is beaten by the ill-tempered King first.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="4. MESS.">Fourth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fourth Messenger comes to inform Richard that rebellion may have broken out in Yorkshire, but that Richmond refused to trust Buckingham&#8217;s men and has gone back to France.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="5. MESS.">Fifth Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Fifth Messenger is sent by Richard to order Stanley to bring his forces to the battle, and returns to inform the King that Stanley refuses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GHOST. OF HENRY.">Ghost of King Henry VI</persname>
<persdescription>The Ghost of King Henry VI comes to haunt Richard the night before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond. His reasons for disliking Richard can be found in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GHOST. OF ED.">Ghost of Prince Edward of Lancaster</persname>
<persdescription>The Ghost of Prince Edward of Lancaster comes to haunt Richard the night before the battle of Bosworth and to bless Richard&#8217;s opponent Richmond. His reasons for disliking Richard can be found in <persnameref>Henry VI, Part Three</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. LORD. RICH.">First Lord to Richmond</persname>
<persdescription>First Lord to Richmond comes with others of Richmond&#8217;s company to wake him up on the morning of the battle of Bosworth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. LORD. RICH.">Second Lord to Richmond</persname>
<persdescription>Second Lord to Richmond comes with others of Richmond&#8217;s company to wake him up on the morning of the battle of Bosworth, and wonders what sort of state he&#8217;s in.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>