<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Romeo &amp; Juliet">

<persona>
<persname short="">Chorus</persname>
<persdescription>Chorus introduces each of the first two acts, setting both the theme of the play and its style. Speaking in sonnet form, he accustoms the ear to listen for echoes of that style.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Prince Escalus</persname>
<persdescription>Prince Escalus of Verona has the misfortune of ruling over a state where two major families are locked in an unending war. The mere authority of his presence is no longer enough to make people pay attention to him: he must back it up with threats of torture and death. He does not even summon Capulet and Montague to appear together before him, but gives them separate appointments. When a further brawl not only kills one of the chief troublemakers but also the Prince&#8217;s own kinsman, Mercutio, he exiles the killer Romeo and attempts to bring peace by hitting the two families in their pocketbook. He soon loses another kinsman, County Paris, and concludes to his own guilt in the affair for not having been severe enough with the warring families. Despite the power of his speeches, his authority seems rather disregarded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Paris</persname>
<persdescription>County Paris is a nobleman of Verona, close kin to the Prince and to Mercutio. He is a suitor to the hand of Capulet&#8217;s daughter Juliet, and though he accepts that she is still young, he hopes to marry her soon all the same. He comes to visit Capulet after Tybalt&#8217;s death to see how his suit proceeds, and is soon scheduled to marry Juliet in three days. He rushes to ask Friar Laurence to officiate at the ceremony. Meeting Juliet on his way out, he is kind but possessive towards her. His wedding day is marred when the bride turns out to have died overnight. That night, he goes to pay homage at her grave, and spots Romeo breaking in. Supposing him trying to perpetrate some outrage on the dead bodies of Tybalt and Juliet, he steps forward to stop him, and is killed. Despite having kept himself aloof from the feud between the two families, he hence ends up one of its victims. He is a pleasant man of whom there seems to be no ill to tell.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Montague</persname>
<persdescription>Montague is the head of an old family of Verona. Caught up in his family&#8217;s old quarrel with the Capulets, he is willing to throw himself bodily into the fray despite his age. He is concerned about his son Romeo&#8217;s melancholy. When Romeo kills Tybalt, his father defends him to the Prince, arguing that Tybalt&#8217;s life was already forfeit and that Romeo hence committed no crime. By the end of the play he will lose both his son and his wife. He offers a gold statue of Juliet to Capulet as a sign of their new friendship at the end of the play, one-upping Capulet&#8217;s proffered handshake.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Capulet</persname>
<persdescription>Capulet is the head of an old family of Verona. He has only one child left, Juliet, and he does everything in his power to do his best for her and obtain an honorable and noble marriage for her. He wishes to wait until she is sixteen for her to be married, though, and insists that she too must consent to the match before it is made. He therefore requires his chosen wooer, Paris, to get to know her and hopefully have her come to like him. Capulet is both irascible and honorable: while he calls for his sword despite his wife&#8217;s mockery in the opening brawl and fully intends to fight in it himself, he also refuses to eject Romeo from his feast, given that the lad has a good reputation and is a guest &#8212; though he may mainly be afraid of the Prince&#8217;s reaction if a fight ensues. He feels his age, missing the days when he could be as wild as the young men in masks who come to his feast. He has little patience for his hot-tempered nephew-by-marriage Tybalt, and intends to have mastery over him. When the young man is killed, he is silent before the Prince, allowing his wife to plead for vengeance. He attempts to cheer things up by advancing Juliet&#8217;s marriage to Paris, and loses his temper completely when she demurs, threatening to disown her and coming close to beating her. When she relents, he becomes rather giddy, advancing the wedding to the next day and spending the whole night in making the preparations for the ceremony. Juliet&#8217;s death hits him hard; and when the whole story is revealed at the graveyard, he is remorseful and is the first to hold out his hand to Montague. When the latter one-ups his gesture by offering a rich golden statue of Juliet, he quickly matches the offer.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Old Capulet</persname>
<persdescription>Old Capulet, Capulet&#8217;s cousin, is an old man, possibly even his uncle. He sits with Capulet at the feast and gossips of old times and people they know.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Romeo</persname>
<persdescription>Romeo is the only son of the Montague family of Verona. He is well-versed in Petrarchan-style poetry, which forms the essence of his speaking style. He seems to take little part in the feud with the Capulets, being far too busy mooning over Rosaline. Even when he comes across evidence of yet another brawl, though he laments that it should have occurred, he quickly turns it into a commentary for his love for Rosaline. Said love is washed quite clean from his mind the moment he meets Juliet, Capulet&#8217;s daughter. Sneaking into her garden and speaking with her, he is forced by her common sense and the reality of her existence to cease using the fake, stylized language he used about the unobtainable Rosaline. Convinced by his confessor Friar Laurence that his marriage to Juliet may help to reconcile the two warring families, he refuses to respond to Tybalt&#8217;s taunts and challenges, leading his best friend Mercutio to consider him a coward. Attempting to stop the fight between Tybalt and Mercutio, he merely causes the latter&#8217;s death, which is enough to make his pacific disposition crack and for him to kill Tybalt in return. The fact of exile brings him to the brink of suicide at the thought of never seeing Juliet again, refusing to see all the ways in which he is lucky. Waiting for news in Mantua, he hears of Juliet&#8217;s death and rushes to her grave to kill himself to be with her. He is a good companion and gets along well with most people. He is especially close to Mercutio and to Friar Laurence, as well as to his cousin Benvolio. Even old Capulet, the head of his family enemies, admits him to be a virtuous young man. He is also highly emotional and given to acting on his impulses. He is in his mid-teens.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mercutio</persname>
<persdescription>Mercutio is a kinsman of the Prince&#8217;s, and a close friend of Romeo&#8217;s. He is extremely quick-witted, has a fantastical min, and is an excellent fencer who does not care for overly mathematical fencing. He has a taste for puncturing things that are taken too seriously, especially love, and is extremely good at this. He reduces love to mere lust, and dislikes that love makes a good ol&#8217; boy become a melancholic personage to whom nothing can be said. Invited to Capulet&#8217;s feast, he allows Romeo and Benvolio to crash the party with him. He is very good friends with Benvolio, though the latter&#8217;s attempts to keep him under control rarely succeed. Quite able to provoke a quarrel with Tybalt, he steps back to allow Romeo to have his duel, but is sickened when the latter refuses. Stepping in to fight instead, he is mortally wounded, but manages to curse the feud and all its participants before dying.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Benvolio</persname>
<persdescription>Benvolio is Montague&#8217;s nephew. By nature law-abiding and peaceful, he attempts to break up the opening quarrel only to end up embroiled in it. Fond of his cousin Romeo, he does not seem to take his melancholy overly seriously. He attempts to cure Romeo of his passion for Rosaline by suggesting that they crash the Capulet party that evening and look at all the various beauties of Verona. Neither Romeo&#8217;s love poetry nor Mercutio&#8217;s fantastical imaginings have much effect on him: he is more concerned about missing a meal. He is very much the straight man of their trio, attempting to calm both down, with occasional but rare success. He coaxes Romeo to flee after killing Tybalt, and does his best to excuse his cousin&#8217;s act to the Prince.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Tybalt</persname>
<persdescription>Tybalt is the nephew of Capulet&#8217;s wife, and that family&#8217;s chief troublemaker. An excellent fenceman, he seeks out opportunities to fight, any excuse being good. He is willing to start a fight at his uncle&#8217;s feast, being only restrained by the latter&#8217;s fury. Instead, he sends Romeo a formal challenge. He despises anyone who speaks of keeping the peace, and when Romeo simply states that he is not a villain, he does not take this for an answer. He does not much care for Mercutio, and is quite willing to fight with him when challenged. He kills Mercutio by stabbing him under Romeo&#8217;s arm, and having fled is foolish enough to return to the square, where he ends up in the fight with Romeo where he loses his life. Though we do not see this side of him, the Nurse considers him to be courteous and honest, and the best friend she had.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Petruchio</persname>
<persdescription>Petruchio is one of Tybalt&#8217;s friends. He is present at the Capulets&#8217; feast and accompanies Tybalt when the latter goes seeking Romeo the next day. He hurries Tybalt away after Mercutio&#8217;s death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Friar Lawrence</persname>
<persdescription>Friar Laurence is a Franciscan friar who is confessor to both Juliet and Romeo, and whom Paris immediately thinks of when he requires a priest for his wedding. A gardener with a vast knowledge of plants and their properties, Friar Laurence is something of a mentor to Romeo, often telling him off for the ridiculousness of his calf-love for Rosaline. The speed at which Romeo switches his affections from Rosaline to Juliet appalls him, but he chooses to assist the young man in the hopes of bringing an end to the war between Capulets and Montagues. He tries to snap Romeo out of his suicidal angst after being banished, and plans for him to stay in Mantua for a time before making all well. Paris and Capulet&#8217;s insistence on Juliet&#8217;s early marriage to the County throws a kink into his plans, and he is faced with another suicidal teenager. This time, the idea of suicide makes him think of counterfeit deaths, and he thinks up an elaborate plot to fake Juliet&#8217;s death and sneak her out of Verona. When his letters explaining this to Romeo do not make it to their intended recipient, he is not overly concerned, but hurries to Juliet&#8217;s grave to wake up her up. The closer he gets the more worried he gets, and when on meeting Balthasar he learns that Romeo has arrived at the grave he is taken with fear. He attempts to get Juliet to leave the tomb, but when she demurs he is too frightened of the approaching Watch to stay with her. Captured, he admits all the story to the Prince, taking full responsibility and offering his life to the Prince.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Friar John</persname>
<persdescription>Friar John is sent by Friar Laurence to Mantua, with letters informing Romeo that Juliet is not in fact dead. Unaware of the importance of the letter, he does not use extreme measures to pass it on when he is stopped from entering Mantua for fear of the plague.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Balthasar</persname>
<persdescription>Balthasar is Romeo&#8217;s manservant. He brings the rope ladder to the Nurse for her to leave in Juliet&#8217;s room. Hearing the news of Juliet&#8217;s death, he hurries to Mantua to inform his master of it. He accompanies Romeo to the Capulet tomb. When ordered to leave, however, he instead decides to hide nearby and watch what happens, being afraid of Romeo&#8217;s intent. When Friar Laurence arrives, he tells all he knows, but still does not dare to follow the friar into the tomb.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Abram</persname>
<persdescription>Abram is one of Montague&#8217;s servingmen. He and a companion are silently insulted by two of Capulet&#8217;s men in the public square, which he queries. He insists he has no intention of quarreling until such time as he refuses to admit that Capulet is a better man than Montague. This sets off the opening brawl.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sampson</persname>
<persdescription>Sampson is one of Capulet&#8217;s servants. He has a taste for bawdy puns and a great liking for women. He sets Gregory on to start a quarrel with the Montague servants, while making sure that they stay on the right side of the law by not being seen to start the brawl. He bites his thumb at the Montagues to put them in an impossible situation, and leads them to where they must draw and fight.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gregory</persname>
<persdescription>Gregory is one of Capulet&#8217;s servants. He has a tendency towards wordplay, and plays this well with Sampson. He helps the latter in starting a quarrel with the Montague servants while appearing to be the offended party. He is insistent that the quarrel between the masters must be shared by their servants. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Peter</persname>
<persdescription>Peter is a servingman of the Capulets&#8217; who accompanies the Nurse when she goes out of the house, partly as her protection and partly to carry her fan. At Juliet&#8217;s death, he begs the musicians to play some merry music for him, and taunts them when they refuse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Page to Paris</persname>
<persdescription>Paris&#8217;s Page accompanies his master to Juliet&#8217;s grave. Frightened of graveyards at night, he stays all the same, until he sees his master in a fight with some unknown man, and runs to fetch the Watch.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Apothecary</persname>
<persdescription>Apothecary is a poor, starving, skeletal man with massive eyebrows whose shop does little business. Despite the threat of death if he is caught having sold poison, he accepts to give Romeo a deadly dose in return for a great deal of money.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lady Montague</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Montague, tries to hold back her husband from doing any actual fighting, and is worried that her son Romeo might have joined in. She dies of grief when he is exiled. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lady Capulet</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Capulet is approximately 28, and makes mock of her aged husband&#8217;s pretensions to fighting. She is not entirely certain of how to broach the subject of marriage to her daughter, and is rather over-elaborate in her instructions of how to look at Paris during the night&#8217;s feast. She is Tybalt&#8217;s aunt, and much devoted to him; when the Prince merely exiles his killer Romeo, she plans to have him poisoned. She reveals this to Juliet while trying to comfort the girl in her distress over Tybalt&#8217;s death. When Juliet refuses to marry Paris, Lady Capulet thinks her husband&#8217;s anger is too great, but she still has no sympathy for her daughter. The discovery of the truth of her daughter&#8217;s death makes her suddenly feel old.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Juliet</persname>
<persdescription>Juliet is the only child of the Capulet family. A fortnight shy of fourteen, she is an obedient child, but reveals herself to be passionate and willing to betray all that she has been brought up to when she falls in love with Romeo. Though she can play Petrarchan word-games as well as Romeo, she has little patience for them once she has completely fallen for him. She is a practical girl, arranging for such things as meeting-times, secret messages, and marriage plans, things that Romeo simply doesn&#8217;t think of. She is also impatient (a quality her nurse plays on) and physical: her love for Romeo is not merely spiritual, and she impatiently looks forward to her wedding night. When only a few hours after her marriage she discovers that Romeo has killed her cousin Tybalt, she is at first torn, but quickly dismisses Tybalt from her thoughts to concentrate on Romeo&#8217;s banishment. He sneaks in for the night, and she does not want him to leave in the morning, but soon has to force him to go, at which time she is taken by a terrifying premonition of their deaths. Believing that her grief is over her cousin&#8217;s death, her parents attempt to mend it by bringing her wedding to County Paris forward. Standing up to them, Juliet finds herself cut off from her parents&#8217; love; her last comfort, the Nurse, betrays her by suggesting that she go ahead with marrying Paris. Ready to kill herself if all else fails, she accepts Friar Lawrence&#8217;s plan to fake her death, and takes his sleeping potion despite her fears. Waking to find Romeo dead beside her, she refuses to leave with the Friar, she stabs herself before anyone can reach her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nurse</persname>
<persdescription>Nurse is Juliet&#8217;s closest companion, the woman who in essence brought her up. Gossipy, chattering, teasing, and with a taste for bawdy stories, she greatly loves the Capulets, considering Tybalt to be her best friend. She acts as an intermediary between Juliet and Romeo despite her misgivings and her belief that County Paris is the better man, and sneaks in the rope ladder that allows Romeo to visit Juliet for their wedding night. She at times has scant regard for men in general compared to her deceased husband, and thinks that Romeo&#8217;s blubbering after killing Tybalt is unmanly and useless. She attempts at all times to protect her charge, standing up to Capulet when he threatens to disinherit Juliet, but also counseling the girl to marry County Paris after all when she sees no way for it to be avoided. Distraught at Juliet&#8217;s death, she tells the musicians to put away their instruments. Other than caring for Juliet, she works in the Capulet pantry. When going out, she has herself accompanied by Peter. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Citizens of Verona</persname>
<persdescription>Citizens of Verona are thoroughly fed up with both Capulets and Montagues, and come out armed with clubs to beat them all up in the hopes that they&#8217;ll stop fighting.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>Third Watchman arrives at the graveyard with the Chief Watchman. He is sent to search for anybody who may be around, and finds Friar Lawrence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>Second Watchman arrives at the graveyard with the First Watchman. He is sent to search for anybody who may be around, and finds Balthasar.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Watchman</persname>
<persdescription>First Watchman is brought by Paris&#8217;s Page to the Capulets&#8217; monument. Finding the various corpses, he sends for everybody involved, though unable to theorize what has occurred. He has Balthasar and Friar Lawrence held until the Prince can arrive.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Musician</persname>
<persdescription>Third Musician is a singer. He does not quite know how to react to Peter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Musician</persname>
<persdescription>Second Musician plays the rebec. He attempts to have Peter calm down and put his dagger away. Like the first musician, he will not play without pay. He convinces his fellow musicians to stick around to profit from the food.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Musician</persname>
<persdescription>First Musician is hired for Juliet&#8217;s wedding, and after her death refuses to play a merry song for Peter, particularly as he cannot pay. He most likely plays a lute, or other plucked-string instrument.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>Second Servingman (Clown) is unable to read, which does not prevent Capulet from sending him out to deliver the invitations to his feast. He asks the first learned person he meets for help, and thus informs Romeo and Benvolio of the feast and Rosaline&#8217;s presence at it. He helps with the table service at the feast. He is sent to hire cooks for Juliet&#8217;s wedding and is not afraid of joking with Capulet, who appreciates his wit.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>First Servingman is a superior servant in the Capulet household, with permission to address Lady Capulet directly. He orders others about as they serve the feast, and has a taste for marzipan.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Anthony</persname>
<persdescription>Anthony is a servant of Capulet&#8217;s, overworked the night of the feast. He is sent to invite the guests to Juliet&#8217;s wedding.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Potpan</persname>
<persdescription>Potpan is a servant of Capulet&#8217;s, overworked the night of Capulet&#8217;s feast.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>