<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Sir Thomas More">

<persona>
<persname short="SHREWSBURY.">Earl of Shrewsbury</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Shrewsbury is a member of the King&#8217;s Council who grows worried at the rising temper of Londoners against the foreigners. He insists on the seriousness of his fears when Surrey seems likely to dismiss them. He is given the charge of knighting More by the King, to whom he is close. He is an older man. He argues with Rochester and More in the hopes of changing their minds about signing the King&#8217;s articles, and is downcast when they will not.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SURREY.">Earl of Surrey</persname>
<persdescription>The Earl of Surrey is the youngest member of the King&#8217;s Council, and the first to think of More as a man who might be able to help quell the riot. He does not approve of the actions of the foreigners, and worries about the reactions they may provoke. He does not think much of the intelligence of the lower classes, and they in return do not much like him, and refuse to listen to him when he tries to speak to them. He is a very conservative man, shocked at the concept of rebellion and disobedience to the King, no matter whether it comes from a carpenter or the Lord High Chancellor. Nevertheless, he attempts to save Rochester&#8217;s life, even when the latter continues to refuse to sign the King&#8217;s articles, and wishes More would be less obstinate.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PALMER.">Sir Thomas Palmer</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas Palmer is a member of the King&#8217;s household. He is concerned about rising feelings against foreigners, and attempts on several occasions to bring the Frenchmen to heel, though to no avail. He raises forces to help the Mayor quell the riots. He later brings the council the articles that the King wishes them to sign. He has prior instructions of what to do with those who refuse to sign, particularly More, and he follows through with these instructions without a fault. He is a widower.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHOLMLEY.">Sir Roger Cholmley</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Roger Cholmley is a bold man, willing to tell his superiors to their faces that he believes they are at fault in not telling the King what is going on in the land, particularly in regard to the foreigners. He is among the noblemen leading the King&#8217;s forces to help the Mayor quell the riots.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MORE.">Sir Thomas More</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Thomas More is an honest, kind and witty man who rises from being a Sheriff of London to Lord High Chancellor (the highest post in the kingdom) before being sent to jail and executed for obeying his conscience rather than the King. A good talker, he is able to calm a riot by using logic and strong imagery on the rioters. He is a great friend of the poor, who adore him as the one man in government who has their interests at heart; people are shocked to discover that he does not take bribes. He is known throughout the world as a wise man, and the just-as-well-known Erasmus is delighted at the opportunity to meet him and talk with him. What is less known is that he is an inveterate practical joker who cannot resist an opportunity for a joke, or for that matter to show off &#8212; even taking a missing actor&#8217;s part in a play and improvising the role. To be fair, as a rule his jokes have a moral point to them. A good family man, he thinks that his wife talks too much, and excludes her by speaking Latin, which the rest of the family understands but she does not. He refuses to blindly sign something the King desires him to, insisting that he may consider the matter first; demoted from his post, and later jailed and condemned to death, he takes this all with great philosophy. He is capable of jesting even on the scaffold. He is an older man, and his beard is rather thin. He is beloved by everybody who knows him for his incomparable moral rectitude.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LORD MAYOR.">Lord Mayor</persname>
<persdescription>Lord Mayor is in theory the most powerful man in London. He takes his responsibilities seriously, including urging charity to help with the burial of condemned prisoners. He respects More highly and has the good sense to listen to him. The Lord Mayor is rather overwhelmed by the riot and unable to deal with it properly, not being as well-seen by the people as More is. He is deeply grateful to the man, and also deeply loyal to the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MUNDAY.">Sir John Munday</persname>
<persdescription>Sir John Munday tries to quell the rioting apprentices, but merely gets knocked about for his pains.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SURESBY.">Justice Suresby</persname>
<persdescription>Justice Suresby is a judge with some rather strong opinions. He is quite full of himself and convinced that he knows the causes of all the wrongdoing in the world. In particular, he thinks that if rich people did not carry money on them, they wouldn&#8217;t be robbed. He lacks the sense to be careful when talking with a pickpocket, and ends up the butt of Thomas More&#8217;s point-making practical joke.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RECORDER.">Recorder</persname>
<persdescription>The Recorder is the court clerk and stenographer, noting down verdicts for the record. He plays by the rule of offering money to help buy a funeral for a destitute person condemned to death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERG.">Sergeant at Arms</persname>
<persdescription>The Sergeant at Arms is sent to offer the mob the King&#8217;s mercy on condition they cease and desist immediately; unfortunately, he comments aloud on their simple-mindedness and merely enrages them further.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLERK.">Clerk of the Council</persname>
<persdescription>The Clerk of the Council attends the council meetings to take notes and provide for the Lords what they need as they deliberate.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ERASMUS.">Erasmus</persname>
<persdescription>Erasmus is one of the most learned men in Europe, and a very famous person indeed. A Dutchman, he is well-read and delighted to be able to finally meet Sir Thomas, whose books he admires, and with whom he looks forward to having wise conversations. He takes well to being made the butt of one of More&#8217;s practical jokes.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROCHESTER.">Bishop of Rochester</persname>
<persdescription>The Bishop of Rochester (Doctor Fisher) is a member of the King&#8217;s Council. On reading the articles the King wishes him to sign, he instantly refuses, as a matter of conscience. Unshakeable, he knows perfectly well that he will lose his head for this, but never wavers in his determination.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROPER.">Roper</persname>
<persdescription>Roper is Sir Thomas&#8217;s son-in-law. He is highly obedient to his father-in-law, and tries to shield his mother-in-law from worries. He worships Sir Thomas, trading Latin tags with him, agreeing with all that he says and always remembering not only More&#8217;s wisdom but the fact that he is known to be wise. He attempts to convince Sir Thomas to sign the King&#8217;s articles with the argument that being More, he could get away with it. More&#8217;s upcoming death brings him to tears.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROP. WIFE.">Roper&#8217;s Wife</persname>
<persdescription>Roper&#8217;s Wife is Sir Thomas&#8217;s daughter, who suffers from a terrible premonitory nightmare the night before More&#8217;s disgrace. She tries to shield her mother from worries she attempts to convince her father to submit to the King&#8217;s demands, being certain that More will then be restored to his place. She is not successful.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LINCOLN.">John Lincoln</persname>
<persdescription>John Lincoln is a hot-tempered Londoner growing more and more discontented with the abuses of the foreigners. A poor man, he is nevertheless an excellent orator and writer, and spearheads the complaints that result in the rioting. Though he begins reasonably, he quickly becomes a rabble-rousing leader using the most inane of arguments to whip up the xenophobia of his followers. He almost loses control of the mob, but with them he is calmed down by More&#8217;s arguments. A brave man, he accepts the verdict on him, and when he is hanged he jumps from the scaffold rather than having to be pushed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GEORGE.">George Betts</persname>
<persdescription>George Betts is the hot-tempered friend of John Lincoln who encourages him to beat up foreigners who are found acting badly in the streets. While Lincoln intends to proceed by open petitions to the Mayor against the foreigners, Betts encourages the idea of direct action, namely rioting on May Day. He proceeds from wanting to beat them to wanting to kill them. Calmed by More&#8217;s words, he is one of those condemned to death but reprieved by the King.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WILLIAMSON.">Williamson</persname>
<persdescription>Williamson is a London carpenter hard put upon by the foreigners&#8217; actions. Not only does Cavaler steal the pigeons he bought for dinner, but De Barde is intent on carrying off his wife Doll and having his way with her. For that matter, he was once sent to prison for disrespecting a Frenchman. He joins in with the rioting, though he is worried that he and the other leaders might be identified. He is less hot-tempered than his wife, whom he loves dearly and who clearly wears the pants in their relationship. She helps him to face up to his own execution bravely.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SHERWIN.">Sherwin</persname>
<persdescription>Sherwin is a Londoner growing impatient with the antics of the foreigners. He witnesses Caveler stealing the pigeons from Williamson. He is more cautious than some of his fellow rioters, worried that burning the foreigners&#8217; houses might set the whole city on fire.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BARDE.">Francis de Barde</persname>
<persdescription>Francis de Barde is a French immigrant who has the Ambassador&#8217;s ear. He is rude, brusque, full of himself, and has both an eye for the ladies and an inability to understand the word &#8216;No&#8217;. He is also fond of money.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAVELER.">Caveler</persname>
<persdescription>Caveler is a French immigrant who has the Ambassador&#8217;s ear. He is haughty and cares nothing for the local inhabitants. He also has a taste for fine food and no qualms about stealing the best quality of meat for an Englishman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LIFTER.">Lifter</persname>
<persdescription>Lifter is a pickpocket who has been caught and brought to trial. Very good at his job, and a fast talker, he is saved from the death penalty because Thomas More wants to use him in a practical joke to prove a point. By successfully picking the pocket of his judge, he frees himself.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SMART.">Smart</persname>
<persdescription>Smart [mute role] is a rich man who has had his purse, which contained a great deal of money, stolen from him by Lifter. He has him arrested and brought to trial.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HARRY.">Harry</persname>
<persdescription>Harry is an apprentice, a quarrelsome teenager who enjoys the opportunity of getting in a scrap and beating up schoolmasters and students. He is glad of the excuse to riot against the foreigners, and does not appreciate being called simple.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROBIN.">Robin</persname>
<persdescription>Robin is an apprentice, a quarrelsome teenager who likes his drink and the opportunity of getting in a scrap and beating up schoolmasters and students. He is glad of the excuse to riot against the foreigners, and does not appreciate being called simple.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="KIT.">Kit</persname>
<persdescription>Kit is an apprentice, a quarrelsome teenager who enjoys fighting with others, whether with a large stick or with swords. He is glad of the excuse to riot against the foreigners, and does not appreciate being called simple.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MORRIS.">Morris</persname>
<persdescription>Morris is the Lord of Winchester&#8217;s secretary, and Faulkner&#8217;s employer. He has been telling Faulkner to cut his hair for some time now, to no avail. He convinces him to do so to avoid jail, though when the young man begins moping he threatens to fire him and have nothing more to do with him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="FAULKNER.">Faulkner</persname>
<persdescription>Faulkner, servant to Morris, is a long-haired lout with little respect for high-placed members of society. He denies having anything to do with the brawl at which he was arrested and insists he will only be judged by More. He refuses to cut his hair, even under the threat of three years in jail, but after being in jail for a couple of hours changes his mind, though with deep regret. Cutting his hair leaves him rather emotional.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GOUGH.">Gough</persname>
<persdescription>Gough is More&#8217;s secretary, and is among the first to hear the news of his condemnation. He is sent by Lady More to tell the servants, as well as to inform them of the money that More has left to each of them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CATESBY.">Catesby</persname>
<persdescription>Catesby is More&#8217;s steward, and is among the first to hear the news of his condemnation. He is sent with Gough to inform the servants of this, and to give them the money that More has promised them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="RANDALL.">Randall</persname>
<persdescription>Randall is one of More&#8217;s servants, who bears a great resemblance to his master. He joins in More&#8217;s prank on Erasmus, dressing up as Sir Thomas and pretending to be him, shocking the visitor with his bizarre mannerisms and bad jokes. He is finally revealed by More after he makes a particularly derogatory joke about Holland to the Dutchman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOWNES.">Downes</persname>
<persdescription>Downes is a high-ranked officer who is sent along with Surrey and Shrewsbury to arrest More and take him to the Tower if he refuses to sign the King&#8217;s orders.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BUTLER.">Ned</persname>
<persdescription>Ned the Butler is in charge of the wine cellar at More&#8217;s house. He is very fond of his master, and regards him highly. He does not understand why More is likely to be condemned to death, not seeing any reason for him to be, though he admits that he does not understand high policy.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BREWER.">Robin</persname>
<persdescription>Robin the Brewer is in charge of making the ale for More&#8217;s household. He is downcast at More&#8217;s arrest, but keeps some hope that he may escape.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HORSEKEEPER.">Ralph</persname>
<persdescription>Ralph the Horsekeeper is in charge of More&#8217;s stables. He suspects that More is too good for this world and will be condemned to death.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PORTER.">Giles</persname>
<persdescription>Giles the Porter guards More&#8217;s door. Emotional and given to swearing, he admires More for his honesty and refusal to take bribes, even though it left him penniless.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LIEUTENANT.">Lieutenant of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Lieutenant of the Tower is in charge of all prisoners brought to the Tower. He is very affected by More&#8217;s presence, respecting him, his humility and his unflagging sense of humor. He is shocked to discover that More was not corrupt, and is therefore very poor. He is distraught when he has to hand More over to the executioner.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GENTLEMAN PORTER.">Gentleman Porter of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Gentleman Porter guards the gate of the Tower of London; as part of the perks of his job, he is allowed to take the prisoners&#8217; rich coats from them for his own use.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HANGMAN.">Hangman</persname>
<persdescription>The Hangman is appointed to chop off More&#8217;s head. As is customary when a low-born person is to execute a nobleman, he begs More&#8217;s forgiveness, and is given the condemned man&#8217;s money as part of his fee.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAN.">Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>The Servingman is sent by More to dismiss the actors when their services are no longer required. Bringing them ten angels (a substantial amount), he decides to keep two of them for himself. Unfortunately he is found out, and loses his job.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CROFTS.">Crofts</persname>
<persdescription>Crofts is a messenger from the King. He brings the King&#8217;s orders that the trial of the rioters be conducted quickly.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERVANT.">Servant to More</persname>
<persdescription>A Servant is one of More&#8217;s servants, and comes to tell him when people wish to speak to him, be they actors or peers of the realm. He looks after More at the Tower and takes his chamberpot to the doctor most days.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY.">Lady More</persname>
<persdescription>Lady More is Sir Thomas&#8217;s wife. Much less well educated than any other member of her family, she cannot speak Latin, leaving her husband able to shut her out from conversation when he thinks she is talking too much. She is either ignorant of theatre, or has no taste for it. She is kept in ignorance by her husband as well as by her children and son-in-law, and is aware of it. She does not take well to More&#8217;s loss of favor, especially the fact that she herself is no longer able to go to court. She is full of fear about More&#8217;s fate, particularly after suffering from a prophetic dream that greatly disturbs her. How much she actually loves her husband is unknown, but she does not want to see him end up on the scaffold.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DAUGHTER.">Daughter to More</persname>
<persdescription>Daughter to More is Sir Thomas&#8217;s second child. She is horrified at the idea of her father being executed and with her mother and sister unsuccessfully attempts to move him to change his mind.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LADY MAYORESS.">Lady Mayoress</persname>
<persdescription>Lady Mayoress is the Mayor&#8217;s wife. She is conscious that she is merely the wife of an elected official rather than of an actual knight, like Lady More, and is self-conscious and deferential when invited to the house of so grand a personage.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOLL.">Doll Williamson</persname>
<persdescription>Doll Williamson is a good-looking, high-tempered, not-at-all-shy London woman who does not take kindly to being manhandled by a Frenchman. She effortlessly dominates her husband and has little patience with the men&#8217;s timidity in fighting back against foreigners; in fact, she threatens to rouse up all the women of London against the foreigners if the men don&#8217;t take action. When the rioting begins, she dresses herself up in full armor and eggs the others on, mocking her husband for being a wimp. She loves him nonetheless, and wishes to be hanged before he is so that she will not have to see him die. She likes More because of his kindness, honesty, wisdom, and the fact that he gave her brother a job.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="POOR WOMAN.">A Poor Woman</persname>
<persdescription>A Poor Woman has been fighting a lawsuit in the court for two years now, and Thomas More is the one with all the evidence in hand to help her win her case. When he is arrested, she loses his help and has nothing left to do but plead to the king and hope.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="INCLINATION.">Player of Inclination the Vice</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. PLAYERS.">All Players</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Player of Inclination the Vice is one of the actors. He offers Sir Thomas a choice of plays to hear at his feast for the Lord Mayor and the Aldermen. He plays the blatantly evil roles in the actors&#8217; plays. He is one of the senior members of the group, and tries to explain to Sir Thomas just why the play might not be ready on time or go quite as planned. Deeply impressed by Sir Thomas&#8217;s abilities, he is good at math and logic. In costume he carries a bridle in his hand and has a dagger at his belt.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VANITY.">Player of Lady Vanity</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. PLAYERS.">All Players</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Player of Lady Vanity is the boy actor in the company of players, and as the only one is charged with playing every female role in their repertoire.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WIT.">Player of Wit</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. PLAYERS.">All Players</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Player of Wit is an actor who plays the leading role in <persnameref>The Marriage of Wit and Wisdom</persnameref>. He is too young to have the beard required by his part, but is sensible enough to know that it is risky to compare a highly-placed person to an actor. He also has the wit to subtly find out whether the actors are right in their suspicion that they&#8217;ve been cheated out of some of their money by the Servingman.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PLAYER.">Player of Prologue</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. PLAYERS.">All Players</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Player of Prologue is one of the actors who plays for More. He is deeply impressed by More&#8217;s generosity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUGGINS.">Luggins</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL. PLAYERS.">All Players</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Luggins is one of the actors, who is unable to enter on cue because he has had to run to fetch a false beard that the company forgot to bring with it. He returns in time to be rewarded. He is startled and impressed that a learned man, who dines with the highest people in the land, should treat actors kindly and respect them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. OFFICER.">First Officer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="OFFICERS.">Officers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Officer is sent to remind the citizens of London to be on guard at the time of the rioters&#8217; execution, to prevent further disturbances.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. OFFICER.">Second Officer</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="OFFICERS.">Officers</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Officer is escorting the rioters to their execution and goes ahead to warn the Sheriff that due to the large crowds they&#8217;ll be a bit late.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. WARDER.">First Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The First Warder helps guard the way as More is brought to jail. He is not entirely certain of how things are progressing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. WARDER.">Second Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Warder is a fan of More&#8217;s, but is also aware that he has lost all of his power. He is worried about the crowds along the way as More is brought to jail, and feels a great deal of compassion for the poor Woman who has lost her advocate with More&#8217;s arrest. He announces the arrival of the Sheriffs to the Lieutenant of the Tower the morning of More&#8217;s execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. WARDER.">Third Warder of the Tower</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Warder is concerned about the size of the crowds lining the way that More is brought to prison. He is the first to notice the poor Woman forcing her way through the masses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. SHERIFF.">First Sheriff</persname>
<persdescription>The First Sheriff is Thomas More&#8217;s fellow officer of the law. He is present at the Lifter&#8217;s trial. A gung-ho sort of fellow, he starts hanging the condemned rioters before their reprieve can arrive. Nevertheless, he is willing to do what he can to help their deaths be more pleasant. A good bureaucrat, he is worried about the effect any error of his might have on his city&#8217;s reputation. He also does not like long-haired louts such as Faulkner. He is part of More&#8217;s escort to the scaffold.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. SHERIFF.">Second Sheriff</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Sheriff is part of More&#8217;s escort to the scaffold, and wishes he did not have that duty, as he both likes and respects the condemned man. He has known More since the latter&#8217;s student days.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESSENGER.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger comes from London to the Council to warn them that the Mayor is trapped in his own house by the riots, which are threatening to spiral out of control.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger warns the Mayor that the rioters have broken into the prisons and let the convicts out.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. MESS.">Third Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Messenger comes from the City Council to tell the Sheriff to hang the condemned prisoners in various locations around the city, and to get on with it. He also announces the Lord Mayor&#8217;s visit to More.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLOWN.">Clown Betts</persname>
<persdescription>Clown Betts is George Betts&#8217;s rather wild brother, Ralph. Fired up by the rioting, he is in favor of as much chaos as can be created, and first suggests burning the foreigners&#8217; houses. He was also one of those who broke the prisons open and let the convicts out. He is a rather manic man, and even at his execution is capable of joking.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>