<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Taming of the Shrew">

<persona>
<persname short="">Lord</persname>
<persdescription>A Lord gone hunting has a strange sense of humor which leads him to decide to turn a drunken beggar he finds lying by the roadside into a lord for a night. Rather wealthy, he has a persuasive tongue, able to convince Sly that all the wealth he sees is his. The lord also has the presence of mind to have a page of his cross-dress to play Sly&#8217;s supposed wife and to consider the use of onions to provide tears. What amusement the lord derives from all this is not entirely certain, but he makes himself into Sly&#8217;s main servant to be sure that he is present and can keep the other members of his household from spoiling the jest. He enjoys theater and remembers some of the players who come to his house.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Christopher Sly</persname>
<persdescription>Christopher Sly is a drunken beggar and tinker who insists that his family is of honorable lineage. Collapsing in a drunken stupor outside a pub he has been ejected from, he awakens to find himself transformed into a lord and told that he has been madly supposing himself to be a beggar for the past fifteen years. He is lusty and wishes to go straight to bed with his newly-discovered wife, but is instead shown a play called <persnameREF>The Taming of the Shrew</NAMEREF>, though he has no great taste for drama. He is greatly in debt, and likes only the cheapest goods, even when turned into a lord. He has a shrewish wife of his own, but thinks having seen the play has taught him how to deal with her. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Hostess</persname>
<persdescription>A Hostess (possibly Marian Hacket of Wincot) has had quite enough of Christopher Sly&#8217;s drunkenness and pennilessness.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Page (Bartholomew)</persname>
<persdescription>Page (Bartholomew) is the Lord&#8217;s page, commanded by him to dress as a lady and pretend to be Christopher Sly&#8217;s wife. He is quick-witted enough to avoid being thrust into bed by Sly, which the latter hopes to do at the first opportunity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Player</persname>
<persdescription>First Player remembers the Lord from previous occasions, and promises that the players can keep their seriousness, no matter how oddly the lord hearing their play may act. He will play one of the roles in the main play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Huntsman</persname>
<persdescription>Second Huntsman checks to see whether Sly is alive, and recognizes that he is dead-drunk. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>First Servingman goes to check the source of the trumpeting outside and returns to report that a company of players has arrived to offer their services to the Lord. He willingly joins in the joke played on Sly, offering him fine drink, praising his hunting skills, and jumping in to report how distraught the lady of the house has been at Sly&#8217;s madness, of which he offers a nice description. He notices that Sly is bored by the play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Baptista</persname>
<persdescription>Baptista is a wealthy gentleman of Padua, the father of two daughters. Desperate to have the eldest, Katherina, a rebellious, ranting, sort, out of his house and out of his hair, he refuses to let the younger daughter, a beautiful, docile, and therefore desirable young thing, marry before her sister. He dotes on the younger girl, hiring teachers of every sort to improve her. He has strong doubts about Katherina&#8217;s marketability, and discourages suitors from attempting to woo her for their own sake, though he is willing to settle half of his wealth on her at his death. For Bianca, he searches for the richest suitor he can find. He is taken aback at Petruchio&#8217;s manner at his wedding and quick departure, but makes no great protest. Though he finally agrees to let Lucentio marry Bianca, he is appalled to discover that the Lucentio he made the bargain with is actually Lucentio&#8217;s servant, and the man he thought Lucentio&#8217;s father is actually a random pedant. He is so amazed at the change Petruchio has wrought in Katherina&#8217;s character that he adds an extra twenty thousand crowns to her dower.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Vincentio</persname>
<persdescription>Vincentio is Lucentio&#8217;s father, a respectable, well-respected, and very rich old man from Pisa. On his way to Padua to visit his son at the university and bring him little extra money, he meets a mad couple who insist that the sun is the moon and he is a beautiful young woman. They then tell him that his son has just become their brother-in-law. He is uncertain whether this is still a jest or not. Arriving in Padua, he finds that someone else is impersonating him and that his son&#8217;s servants refuse to acknowledge him; seeing Tranio is rich garments, he is first convinced that Lucentio is spending all his money and then that Tranio has murdered his son. About to be carted off to jail as a madman, he is saved when his son arrives and reveals all the deception. He promises to satisfy Baptista in the matter of his daughter&#8217;s secret marriage, but also to have vengeance on Tranio. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Lucentio</persname>
<persdescription>Lucentio is a young man of Pisa, son to Vincentio, comes to Padua to go to university. Rather than waste his time in class, however, he disguises himself as a poor schoolteacher to have a chance to woo Bianca, with whom he falls completely in love the moment he sees her on his arrival in town. He has himself introduced to Baptista&#8217;s household, under the name Cambio, by his rival for Bianca, Gremio, who has no inkling that the young man he has hired has any plans of his own. He begins to woo Bianca under the cover of her Latin lesson. He agrees with the plan to have a stranger play the part of his father to convince Baptista to let him marry Bianca while the two of them run off to church to have it done, though on seeing his father on the verge of being run off to jail as a madman he is instantly remorseful. He hosts the feast celebrating the various marriages at the end, and there bets on Bianca&#8217;s superior obedience to the other newly-wed women present, only to lose a hundred crowns on the matter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Petruchio</persname>
<persdescription>Petruchio is a gentleman from Verona, the son of a well-known father, who comes to Padua in search of a rich wife. A blunt fellow, he does not hide what he intends, and has no fears of what his wife may be like so long as she brings money with her. He accepts to present Hortensio in disguise as a music-teacher at Baptista&#8217;s so that he can woo Bianca while he himself goes after Katherina. This he does with rapid-fire wit, refusing to take &amp;quot;no&amp;quot; for an answer and verbally overbearing her. Intending to take her down a notch or two, he arrives late at their wedding, dressed like a madman, and then takes her away to his home without even attending the wedding feast. He applies to her the methods used to tame wild falcons, keeping her almost starved and without sleep, bellowing at her and all around her, not to mention taking away dresses and other attires he had promised her on specious excuses, swearing that all of his objections are for her own good and out of his care for her. He never hits her, though he does warn her that he will if she strikes him again after she deals him a blow. Given to dressing in everyday attire, he insists to his wife that inner virtue counts far more than gaudy clothes, and takes her to visit her father for her sister&#8217;s wedding without buying her new clothes. He soon has Katherina agreeing to anything he tells her to, lecturing other women on how to best obey their husbands, and kissing him in public.

 The further adventures of his married life are chronicled in John Fletcher&#8217;s <persnameREF>The Woman&#8217;s Prize</NAMEREF>, or the <persnameREF>Tamer Tamed</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gremio</persname>
<persdescription>Gremio is an old man in Padua, and extremely rich. He is a suitor to Bianca&#8217;s hand, and cannot stand her sister. He is convinced by his rival Hortensio that a husband must be found for Katherina so that they may continue their wooing of the younger daughter. Since Baptista is looking for teachers for Bianca, Gremio hires a young schoolmaster to help instruct her, on condition that he deliver her love-notes and plead his case, never dreaming that the young man is in disguise and intends to woo her for himself. As soon as Katherina is betrothed, Gremio brings the matter of Bianca back to attention, though his offer for her is out-bid by the fake Lucentio. He is vastly amused by Petruchio&#8217;s treatment of Katherina, and though he is out-foxed in the matter of marrying Bianca, and loses her, he takes it in good part. He slightly knows Vincentio, and keeps him from being hauled off to jail, though he is not so certain that he will swear to his identity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Hortensio</persname>
<persdescription>Hortensio is a young man of Padua, a suitor to Bianca&#8217;s hand. Despairing of ever even having a chance of wooing her, due to her father&#8217;s insistence that the elder sister marry first, he is delighted when his old friend Petruchio comes for a visit, looking for a wife. He takes pains to warn Petruchio of Katherina&#8217;s character, while also mentioning the wealth of her dowry. To gain access to the younger sister, he disguises herself as a music teacher called Licio with Petruchio&#8217;s help, but on his first lesson Katherina beats him up, breaking his lute over his head. He presents a wooing note to Bianca in code, which has little effect. He is entirely under her thumb, but also promises that should she genuinely be in love with someone else, he will let her go. Seeing her kissing a mere schoolmaster, he vows to give her up as being unworthy of him. After all, a kind widow has been wooing him of late, and he takes off to marry her instead, deciding that beauty is not the most important feature a woman can have. He visits Petruchio and helps him in his games against Katherina, though also advising her, and taking it all down in case he needs to use these methods on the widow. A wagering man, he is willing to bet on his new wife&#8217;s obedience against Katherina&#8217;s and Bianca&#8217;s, to his discomfit when he loses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Tranio</persname>
<persdescription>Tranio is Lucentio&#8217;s servant and very close friend. A long-tongued gabbler and consummate conman, he brings his master back down to earth in the matter of Bianca, forcing him to consider the practicalities of wooing her rather than merely adoring her, much as he encourages him to have fun as well as study while at university. He is quite willing to play the game of being Lucentio, which role he takes to with gusto. As Lucentio, he woos Bianca in full view of her other suitors, distracting them from noticing the schoolmaster who is doing the same. He is able to outbid Gremio in offering for Bianca, though he then realizes that he must find a fake father to sign off on the promises he has made. He tricks Hortensio into swearing never to woo Bianca again by doing so himself. He then convinces the pedant to play the part of his father by swearing that doing so will save his life. When the real Vincentio&#8217;s arrival threatens to derail everything, he brazens it out, pretending to find the old man mad and insisting that he has never known him. He runs off as quickly as possible when the real Lucentio arrives, and by that evening is back serving tables, though he is still able to jest on almost-equal terms with Petruchio.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Biondello</persname>
<persdescription>Biondello is one of Lucentio&#8217;s servants. He is shocked to see his master and Tranio exchange their clothing, but accepts to play along with their switch. He is fascinated by Petruchio&#8217;s wild attire and manner on his wedding day, and rushes to tell Baptista of it. Tranio sets him to find an old man who will do for playing the part of Lucentio&#8217;s father, and he finally spots the pedant. He reports to Lucentio when Baptista is out of the way, and tells him of the marriage arrangements made for Lucentio and Bianca at Saint Luke&#8217;s church. He is taken aback when he sees the real Vincentio at Baptista&#8217;s door, and decides to continue playing the trick until Lucentio and Bianca are safely married, denying that he has ever seen Vincentio before. This earns him a beating. He is present at the great feast that ends the play, and unsuccessfully sent to fetch Bianca and the widow to their husbands.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Grumio</persname>
<persdescription>Grumio is Petruchio&#8217;s servant. He loses few opportunities to exercise his wit, however risky this is in his master&#8217;s company, and joins with Petruchio in making his marriage a mockery, dressing himself up madly and being his only companion to the ceremony. He has a very bad trip back to Petruchio&#8217;s house with his newly-wed master and his bride, during which Katherina tries to save him from Petruchio&#8217;s beating him. He wholeheartedly helps his master in his schemes against Katherina, refusing her food and swearing that the tailor mistook his order for the gown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Curtis</persname>
<persdescription>Curtis is one of Petruchio&#8217;s servants, in charge of his house. He is a gossip eager for news.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Pedant</persname>
<persdescription>A Pedant is a schoolmaster from Mantua, on a trip to Rome and Tripoli. He meets a young man in Padua who warns him that there is war between Padua and Mantua, and convinces him to pretend to be Vincentio of Pisa, who happens to be the young man&#8217;s father, for his safety. In return, he accepts to broker a marriage between the young man and his beloved. When the real Vincentio comes knocking at the door, he sticks to his role, accusing the real one of trying to cozen people under his name.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Katherina</persname>
<persdescription>Katherina is a sharp-tongued lady of Padua, known throughout the town for her rants. The bane of her father&#8217;s life, she is keenly aware of being the less-favored daughter, and mistreats her younger sister, tying her up, beating her and interrogating her. Fiercely quick-witted, she meets her match in repartee in Petruchio, who comes to woo her and manages to sidestep and evade her best efforts at verbally besting him. Giving in to the idea of marrying him, she is distraught at the shame when he fails to show up for the wedding. When Petruchio insists that the two of them must leave for his home following the wedding without attending the feast, she attempts to soften him by entreating him, but this proves as fruitless as insisting that she will not go. When she falls off her horse into the mud on the way to her new house, she tries to stop Petruchio from beating his servant Grumio. Half-starved by her husband, she begs Grumio for food, but is denied. Denied new clothes on genuine excuses, she accepts to return to her father&#8217;s house in everyday clothes, and finally either beaten down or exasperated by Petruchio&#8217;s unreasonable demands, she accepts to consider the sun the moon and an old man a young woman. Conscious of her honor, she dislikes the idea of kissing in public, though Petruchio is able to convince her to do so. Called upon to explain how marriage ought to work, she has the opportunity to lecture her perfect sister Bianca on the wrongs of her disobedience.

 The further adventures of her marriage are chronicled in John Fletcher&#8217;s <persnameREF>The Woman&#8217;s Prize</NAMEREF>, or the <persnameREF>Tamer Tamed</NAMEREF>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Bianca</persname>
<persdescription>Bianca is Baptista&#8217;s younger daughter, a beautiful, docile, and obedient creature. Wooed by many, including rich old Gremio and Hortensio, she is not so obedient that she will not allow herself to be wooed behind her father&#8217;s back by a young man disguised as one of her teachers, not to mention run off and marry him in secret, and later refuse to be at his beck and call. She is mistreated by her sister, who ties her up and regularly beats her. She is her father&#8217;s great favorite, and plays the part well. With others she is quite willing to be peremptory and assert herself, decreeing that she will decide the order and length of her lessons for herself, and, once married, willing to tell her husband he is foolish to bet on her. Her headstrong sister then lectures the perfect girl about her disobedient ways.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Widow</persname>
<persdescription>A Widow, daughter to Baptista, has been wooing Hortensio for some time. She is kind rather than beautiful, though not so obedient as Hortensio might wish. She has a slightly sharp tongue, and is quite willing to trade barbs with Katherina.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Tailor</persname>
<persdescription>A Tailor insists to Petruchio that the gown he brings for Katherina is exactly as ordered, and perfectly in vogue. He is not aware that he is merely being used as a prop in Petruchio&#8217;s schemes against Katherina, though he is reassured by Hortensio that he will be paid, despite Petruchio&#8217;s swearing the opposite.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Haberdasher</persname>
<persdescription>A Haberdasher brings a cap ordered for Katherina for her and Petruchio&#8217;s inspection, but is quickly told that it will not do at all. He is not aware that he is merely being used as a prop in Petruchio&#8217;s schemes against Katherina.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Servingman willingly joins in the joke on Sly. He offers the supposed lord food, bewails the effect Sly&#8217;s madness has had on the servants, suggests a trip to his picture gallery, and is the first to mention that his madness has lasted fifteen years.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Player</persname>
<persdescription>Second Player asks the Lord to let the company stay a night at his house and hear a play. He will play one of the roles in the main play.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Huntsman</persname>
<persdescription>First Huntsman is in charge of the Lord&#8217;s dogs, and his opinions on their worth diverge from his master&#8217;s. He agrees that his master&#8217;s psychological experiment on Sly will work and promises to play along.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Servingman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Servingman willingly joins in the joke on Sly. He is in charge of the wardrobe, and bemoans the effect Sly&#8217;s supposed madness has had on his supposed wife. He recalls all the names that Sly has pronounced in his drunkenness and can repeat them as being non-existent persons.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Peter</persname>
<persdescription>Peter is a servant at Petruchio&#8217;s house, who serves at table.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nicholas</persname>
<persdescription>Nicholas is a servant at Petruchio&#8217;s house. He is delighted to see Grumio again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Joseph</persname>
<persdescription>Joseph is a servant at Petruchio&#8217;s house and he is delighted to see Grumio again. He helps serve at table, confirming the meat is mutton.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Philip</persname>
<persdescription>Philip is a servant at Petruchio&#8217;s house. He is delighted to see Grumio again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Nathaniel</persname>
<persdescription>Nathaniel is a servant at Petruchio&#8217;s house. He is delighted to see Grumio again.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Baptista&#8217;s Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>Baptista&#8217;s Messenger brings word to Bianca to stop studying and instead help decorate Katherina&#8217;s rooms in anticipation of the wedding.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger comes to announce to Sly that his company of players is coming to perform a play for him, at doctors&#8217; orders.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>