<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="The Tempest">

<persona>
<persname short="">Alonso</persname>
<persdescription>Alonso is the King of Naples. An enemy of Prospero&#8217;s, he accepted Antonio&#8217;s proposition to help the latter usurp Prospero&#8217;s throne in return for Antonio&#8217;s swearing Milan&#8217;s fealty to Naples. On his way back from the wedding of his daughter in Tunis, a storm casts him on a magic island, where he searches for his son Ferdinand, whom he barely dares hope may have survived the wreck. Ariel&#8217;s imprecations and condemnations at the vanishing feast wake remorse in him, and believing that Ferdinand has drowned, he runs off to do the same to himself. Trapped inside his mind, he wakens to find Prospero before him, and immediately returns the freedom of his Dukedom to him and begs for his pardon. He is reconciled with him, particularly when he discovers that his son is in fact alive, and he is more than happy to acquiesce to Ferdinand marrying Prospero&#8217;s daughter. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Sebastian</persname>
<persdescription>Sebastian is the brother of Alonso, the King of Naples. He helped Antonio usurp Prospero, and is now convinced by the latter to kill his own brother and thus become King, the rightful heirs being either drowned or in Tunis. Prevented by Ariel&#8217;s actions from murdering Alonso, he follows him in his search for the missing Ferdinand. He is arrogant and insulting to his lesser. Ariel&#8217;s imprecations leave him searching for someone to fight. He is frightened at the magician&#8217;s knowledge of his plot against his brother, but recovers enough to mock Stefano&#8217;s pretensions.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Prospero</persname>
<persdescription>Prospero is the deposed Duke of Milan. He was rather a failure as Duke, spending most of his time cooped up in his library and allowing his brother Antonio to surreptitiously take over the state before finally doing so by force. He is learned, and in continuous study: every day he spends three hours reading in his study. He is also versed in the magical arts, though most of his magic is in fact performed by Ariel, who is bound to him in service. Protective of his daughter, he does not tell her of their history, nor for that matter of the existence of other human beings, until the day she is to meet the various people responsible for their exile. He is capable of harsh threats to keep his servants in line, and scarcely utters a kind word to Caliban. He promises Ariel his freedom, though there is always another task to do first; the spirit will not in fact be free until all the persons on the island have safely reached home. He is concerned for the safety of the innocents on board the ship, and though he wishes revenge on the various people who betrayed him he comes to consider that the pains they have suffered on the island suffice as purgation, and that forgiveness is the better course. He is delighted when Ferdinand and Miranda fall for each other, though he sets himself up as a tyrannical father to test their love and is strongly in favor of pre-marital abstinence. Though he succeeds in his goal of recovering his Dukedom, it is at the price of having to abandon his magic when he leaves the island.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Antonio</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio is Prospero&#8217;s brother. He usurped the throne of Milan from his brother with Alonso&#8217;s help, willingly abandoning the sovereignty of the Dukedom to Naples. He shows no appreciation for the island, and finds Gonzalo overly talkative and silly. He has no qualms about loudly mocking him. He suggests to Alonso&#8217;s brother Sebastian that the latter usurp the throne of Naples, and offers to perform the murder himself. Lacking chances to do the deed, he follows the King. Ariel&#8217;s imprecations leave him searching for someone to fight. He is arrogant, cynical, and a through-and-through villain, not willing to pray for salvation when the ship is sinking and blaming the wreck on the mariners. Faced by Prospero, who begrudgingly forgives him while taking back his Dukedom, he says nothing. He is still able to mock Caliban, however.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Ferdinand</persname>
<persdescription>Ferdinand is Alonso&#8217;s son. Cast up on his own on the island after the wreck, he is convinced that his father has drowned, not least by Ariel&#8217;s songs. He comes across Miranda and falls head over heels in love with her at first sight. He accepts his enforced servitude to Prospero for her sake, and his willingness gains him her hand. He is a fine specimen of a human being, plays chess, and assures Prospero that he doesn&#8217;t approve of pre-marital sex.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Gonzalo</persname>
<persdescription>Gonzalo is an old man, an honest counselor of Alonso&#8217;s. Charged with putting Prospero out to sea in a sinking ship, he took pity on the usurped Duke and gave him food, drink, books and all the necessities of life to take with him. A Panglossian optimist, he dreams of utopias and sees the best in everything, though he has no taste for the hard-swearing Boatswain. He recognizes that Alonso is suffering from guilt over Prospero when the latter becomes desperate after the vanishing feast. He is given to moralizing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Adrian</persname>
<persdescription>Adrian is a lord in Alonso&#8217;s suite. He appreciates the climate of the island where they have landed, and questions Gonzalo&#8217;s scholarship. He does not hear Ariel&#8217;s condemnations at the vanishing feast, and follows the King in fear for what he may do.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Francisco</persname>
<persdescription>Francisco is a lord in Alonso&#8217;s suite. He attempts to comfort the King with the hope that Ferdinand may be alive, but is unsuccessful. He is intrigued by the vanishing of the spirits at the feast.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Caliban</persname>
<persdescription>Caliban is the savage son of the witch Sycorax, and was born on the island. When Prospero arrives on the island, he shows him all its secrets that he knows, and in return is educated by Miranda and her father. He attempts to rape the girl, however, and is thereafter enslaved. He is not a happy slave. Prospero keeps him obedient by sending his spirits to torment him with pinching and bruising, though he cannot lock up Caliban&#8217;s tongue. He is more than willing to worship any person who brings him a hope of freedom, particularly if they give him alcohol, and so he falls in with Stefano and Trinculo, not realizing the extent of their foolishness. His thoughts towards Prospero are brutishly violent, but he is not immune to aesthetics, and enjoys the musics that can be heard throughout the island. When sobered up, he becomes aware of the madness of his revolt. Though distinctly human in form, he is considered deformed by many, and often called a monster; there is also something fishy about him, possibly his odor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Trinculo</persname>
<persdescription>Trinculo is Alonso&#8217;s jester. He is a coward and is delighted to have Caliban subservient to him. He has a taste for finery as well as for liquor, and plans to help Stefano become king of the island.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Stephano</persname>
<persdescription>Stephano is Alonso&#8217;s butler. He has something of a taste for liquor, and is well-served when he is cast up on the shore with a butt of wine that he held onto to avoid drowning. Finding Trinculo with Caliban, he swiftly gets the latter drunk and makes him swear obedience to him. He quickly becomes lord-like, threatening Trinculo with violence. He listens to Caliban and decides to kill Prospero so as to become king of the island and marry Miranda. He is quickly distracted from this plot by some shiny new clothes, then tormented by invisible spirits, before discovering that his master is still alive and that he is in serious trouble.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Master of a Ship</persname>
<persdescription>The Master of a Ship captains a ship bearing the King of Naples and his closest advisers home from a wedding in Tunis. He charges the Boatswain to keep the mariners at their task in the storm.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Boatswain</persname>
<persdescription>Boatswain is in charge of running the ship in the storm. He has no time for time-wasters and does not bother to shackle his tongue when talking to landlubbers coming on deck and getting in the way. After the ship splits, he spends some time with the crew under hatches, hearing dreadful noises, before waking up and discovering that their ship isn&#8217;t wrecked after all.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mariners</persname>
<persdescription>Mariners try to keep the ship afloat during the storm, but soon realize that all is lost and that their only hope is in prayer. They spend some time under strange hatches, haunted by odd sounds, but then awake to discover that their ship has not been wrecked after all.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Miranda</persname>
<persdescription>Miranda is Prospero&#8217;s daughter. Though she has some vague memories of her time at court when she was a toddler, in the main she has no recollection of a life other than being isolated on an island with no company but her father and Caliban. She is by nature kind, taking pity on the unknown travelers on the ship she sees sinking in the storm. She helped to educate Caliban and took pity on him until he attempted to rape her, since when she has preferred to have no contact with him. She falls completely in love with the first young man she sees, and is shocked when her father is unkind to him. She claims to have never seen him act that way before, despite having witnessed how Prospero acts to Caliban. She tries to ease Ferdinand&#8217;s burdens as much as she can. Among her accomplishments is chess playing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Ariel</persname>
<persdescription>Ariel is an airy spirit bound in service to Prospero and impatient for his release. He was confined to a tree by the witch Sycorax for refusing to serve her, and only freed when Prospero arrived on the island. The memory of this imprisonment and the threat of being so confined again is enough to keep him from complaining overmuch at Prospero&#8217;s demands. A shape-shifter, he is the main source of Prospero&#8217;s magic, using his own powers to accomplish Prospero&#8217;s wishes. He stage-manages the opening storm and by various means leads the various castaways to their respective punishments and purgations while making sure that they neither die nor commit any truly serious crimes. He is an accomplished singer, backed by a chorus of the lesser spirits that he commands, and portrays Ceres in the masque. He also plays the tabor and pipe. He is mischievous, but not completely insensible: he recognizes human emotions and what causes them even though he cannot feel them himself. He is set free once he has safely sent the ship back to Naples.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Iris</persname>
<persdescription>Iris is one of Prospero&#8217;s spirits, representing the goddess of the rainbow in the masque. She acts as the mistress of ceremonies for the performance, invoking Ceres and calling forth the nymphs and reapers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Ceres</persname>
<persdescription>Ceres is one of Prospero&#8217;s spirits (likely Ariel) representing the goddess of the harvest in the masque. She joins Juno to bless Ferdinand and Miranda&#8217;s union.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Juno</persname>
<persdescription>Juno is one of Prospero&#8217;s spirits, representing the Queen of Heaven and goddess of marriage in the masque. She joins with Ceres to bless Ferdinand and Miranda&#8217;s union.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>