<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Timon of Athens">
<persona>
<name short="ALCIB.">Alcibiades</name>
<description>Alcibiades is a young Athenian captain, a great soldier who has won many victories for Athens. He best loves war, but he is a true friend of Timon&#8217;s and a generous man. He attempts to save the life of one of his soldiers who in a temper killed another man, but is unsuccessful before the Senate of old, unyielding men. He is angered that they will not take his past services into account when he pleads with them, and rashly suggests that they are growing forgetful, leaving him exiled. He then rejoins his army, intent on conquering Athens in revenge. He is extremely proud and looks down on the senators as a pack of usurers. Horrified at how hard Timon has fallen, he attempts to help him, but is rebuffed. He uses Timon&#8217;s name as an excuse in his propaganda, and hopes to bring him onto his side just as the senators hope to, but his messenger arrives too late. He is threatening enough that the senators crumble and simply hand Athens over to him without fighting, and then magnanimous, as they were not. Alcibiades has a very simple view of the world, and within that view is an upright and decent man, is somewhat reckless.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="APEM.">Apemantus</name>
<description>Apemantus is a professional cynic, a snarling, nasty man who insults everybody he meets without appearing to derive any pleasure from doing so. He sees through flattery and refuses gifts from Timon, eating only poorly at his table. Though he pretends to like nobody, Apemantus strives to make Timon realize just how foolishly he is acting, but does not give his advice in the most diplomatic manner. When Timon loses all his wealth and becomes a misanthrope in the forest, it becomes evident that Apemantus is something of a poseur, who does not appreciate the fact that someone is stealing his role. Even though he claims to love no-one but himself, Apemantus still tries to feed Timon in the forest, only to be rejected by a man who now hates humanity even more than he does himself. The discovery that it is possible to be even nastier than he is enrages Apemantus, who tells everybody that Timon has found some gold so that he will be beset by visitors.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="CAPH.">Caphis</name>
<description>Caphis is the servant of a Senator who also dabbles in usury and has lent Timon a great deal of money. He is sent to obtain repayment, but is put off for an entire month by Flavius, until Caphis finally presents his bill to Timon directly, in the public street. He does not much like the task of asking a man for money, but holds his ground and refuses to be delayed any further.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="CUP.">Cupid</name>
<description>Cupid is one of the Ladies who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast, and explains the idea to Timon.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. BAN., ALL BAN.">First Bandit</name>
<description>The First Bandit does not see why a ruined man should be left any money at all, but insists he is not a thief. He realizes that Timon&#8217;s advice to continue stealing is not given out of kindness, but thinks that there&#8217;s no point in giving up robbery while there&#8217;s a war on.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. LADY. MASK., ALL LADY. MASK.">First Lady Amazon Masker</name>
<description>First Lady Amazon Masker is one of the Ladies who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast, and disclaims his praise.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. LORD., BOTH 1. LORD. AND 2. LORD., ALL LORDS.">First Lord</name>
<description>The First Lord is an Athenian gentleman, one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who thinks nothing of simply walking off the street to eat at Timon&#8217;s table and receiving rich gifts from him with no more repayment than flattery. He refuses to help Timon out in his need, claiming to have no money on hand at the time, and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. A fatuous, greedy, and rather silly fellow, he fails to see the problem in refusing to help Timon while still wearing a jewel the latter gave him in his cap when visiting him.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. SEN.">First Senator</name>
<description>The First Senator is an old man, one of the members of government who refuses to help Timon when he is in need.  He also offers windy reasons for applying laws strictly without mitigation, without considering greater concerns. His ill-considered exiling of Alcibiades puts all of Athens in danger. Due to this he is forced to plead with Timon for help against Alcibiades when the panic-struck Athenians want Timon as a dictator to save them from the rebels. He is unsuccessful. In the end he surrenders to Alcibiades to save the city.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. STRAN.">First Stranger</name>
<description>The First Stranger has his ear to the ground and knows what is happening to Timon&#8217;s fortunes before some of Timon&#8217;s supposed friends do. He is shocked that Lucius refuses to help the other man, and swears that had he been as well used by Timon as Lucius had, he would have helped. </description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="FLAM., THREE SERVANTS.">Flaminius</name>
<description>Flaminius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, sent to request fifty talents from Lucullus when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. An honest man, he refuses to be bribed, and is horrified at Lucullus&#8217;s refusal to help Timon. He tries to keep Timon away from direct contact with his creditors&#8217; servants, but is unsuccessful. He brings Lucullus&#8217;s invitation to a hunting party to Timon, along with some hunting greyhounds.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="FLAV.">Flavius</name>
<description>Flavius is Timon&#8217;s Steward, and the head of his household, and the man best aware of just how much his master spends. The state of Timon&#8217;s accounts brings him to despair, as does his inability to get Timon to understand that he is essentially bankrupt and that giving costly presents to anyone who shows up for dinner is not really an option. Timon&#8217;s last barrier against his creditors, he is forever putting off the debt collectors while he tries to find the money to pay them back and get it through Timon&#8217;s thick skull that he is in serious financial trouble. He even goes so far as to ask the Senate for help in Timon&#8217;s name without being asked to; due to their refusal, he is skeptical of Timon&#8217;s belief that his friends will help him. Flavius dearly loves his master and is deeply loyal to him. When the money finally runs entirely out and Timon leaves Athens, Flavius gives what he has to his fellow servants and goes off to find his vanished master. This ends up making his fortune, but does not make him happy. Easily moved to tears, Flavius admires goodness and is rather depressed by how little there is of it in the world. He leads the Senators to Timon&#8217;s cave for the sake of Athens, but has no great hope of their success.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="FOOL.">Fool</name>
<description>A Fool speaks truth in riddles, and has a good mocking tongue. He is not afraid of criticizing his mistress behind her back. Though he insults people, he appears downright kind when he is in Apemantus&#8217;s company.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="4. LORD., ALL LORDS.">Fourth Lord</name>
<description>The Fourth Lord is one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who refuses to help him out when he is in need and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is completely oblivious to the fact that Timon has some reason to be ticked off at his so-called friends.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="4. SEN.">Fourth Senator</name>
<description>The Fourth Senator is terrified of the arrival of Alcibiades&#8217;s army.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="HOR.">Hortensius</name>
<description>Hortensius is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to recover a debt. He does not like his task, given that he is fully aware that Timon has given his master gifts worth far more than the borrowed sum. He attempts to do the job all the same, but soon realizes that the odds of getting any money back are rather low, and that Timon is no longer entirely sane.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="ISID. SERV.">Isidore&#8217;s Servant</name>
<description>Isidore&#8217;s Servant is the servant of a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money. He is sent to recover the sum from Timon, but is unable to get past Flavius, who puts him off time and again. </description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="JEW.">Jeweller</name>
<description>A Jeweller [possibly named Titus] is a flattering man who brings Timon a jewel, knowing that the latter will buy it no matter the cost.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="ALL LADY. MASK.">Lady Amazon Maskers</name>
<description>Lady Amazon Maskers [mute roles] are a group of women who come to present a masque of the five senses at Timon&#8217;s feast.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="LUCIL.">Lucilius</name>
<description>Lucilius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, a younger man who has served his master well for some years now. One of his tasks is serving at table. He is in love with the Old Athenian&#8217;s daughter, and visits her at night. His fortune is made when Timon finds out that the Old Athenian disapproves of the match because of Lucilius&#8217;s poverty; Timon proceeds to enrich him. He is suitably grateful.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="LUC.">Lucius</name>
<description>Lucius is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering friends who is only generous to rich people. Quite shamelessly hypocritical, he refuses to help Timon in his need by pretending not to have enough money on him, even though he has just accuses everybody else who refused to help false friends. He then has the audacity to send his servant to ask for repayment of an earlier loan.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="LUC. SERV.">Lucius&#8217;s Servant</name>
<description>Lucius&#8217;s Servant is sent by his master to recover some money from Timon, and is well aware that the man is essentially bankrupt. He finds his task, and that of the various other servants on similar errands, rather unethical, as Timon has spent more on the various creditors than he has borrowed from them. Nevertheless, he does his best to get the money back.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="LUCUL.">Lucullus</name>
<description>Lucullus is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering and not particularly generous friends, though he does send him some hunting hounds when he invites Timon to hunt with him. He is a sleazy flatterer who attempts to get out of helping Timon by bribing Flaminius to say he didn&#8217;t see him. He lets himself off the hook by claiming to have warned Timon to be a bit more careful with his money.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="LUCUL. SERV.">Lucullus&#8217;s Servant</name>
<description>Lucullus&#8217;s Servant is trusted by his master, but not so much that Lucullus will attempt to offer a bribe in his presence.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="MER.">Merchant</name>
<description>A Merchant is a flattering man who attends Timon&#8217;s feast and is well aware of what Apemantus is like.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="MESS.">Messenger</name>
<description>A Messenger informs the Senate of just how bad the situation with Alcibiades&#8217;s approaching army is, and also informs them that Alcibiades too is seeking Timon&#8217;s support.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="MESS. VENT.">Messenger from Ventidius</name>
<description>A Messenger from Ventidius comes to beg Timon to pay off the debt when Ventidius is arrested for non-repayment of five talents, a huge sum.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="OLD ATH.">Old Athenian</name>
<description>An Old Athenian is a rich, upright, honorable and crusty old man with a healthy respect for his own position in life. Insistent that his only daughter shall marry a rich man to match his own position, he loves her enough to swear to disown her if she marries Lucilius, a mere servant. He is however perfectly happy to accept the young man as his son-in-law once Timon enriches him.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="PAIN.">Painter</name>
<description>A Painter is a starving artist in need of patronage who, along with his fellow crawler the Poet, hopes to get money off Timon by flattering him. He cannot decide whether to be self-deprecating about his art or not, and is rather affected about his calling. He is also quite open about the financial realities of life and the need to sell oneself &#8212; at least to other artists. The moment he hears that the ruined Timon has found gold, he runs to try his old tricks and get some money off of him, hypocritically swearing that he has come to visit simply out of friendship &#8212; with unexpected results, though he does get some gold out of it.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="PHI.">Philotus</name>
<description>Philotus is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to recover the debt, though he has little hope of doing so.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="PHRY., BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.">Phrynia</name>
<description>Phrynia is one of Alcibiades&#8217;s mistresses, accompanying him and his army as he marches on Athens. Timon accuses her of being a prostitute riddled with venereal disease, and she insults him back, but is willing to listen to his cursing so long as he gives her gold.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="POET.">Poet</name>
<description>A Poet is a verse-maker who lives by acquiring the support (and therefore money) of rich men whom he praises in his poems. Somewhat wiser to the ways of the world than his companion crawler the Painter, he attempts to warn Timon of the possibility that his luck might not hold and that his so-call friends are not true ones. Affected and afflicted by false modesty, he pretends not to work at his poetry and that what he produces is merely trifles, though he clearly hopes they will be taken otherwise. The moment he hears that the ruined Timon has found gold, he runs to try his old tricks and get some money off of him, hypocritically swearing that he has come to visit simply out of friendship &#8212; with unexpected results, though he does get some gold out of it.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="2. BAN., ALL BAN., ALL OTHER BAN.">Second Bandit</name>
<description>The Second Bandit has heard that Timon has some treasure on him and brings his fellows to find him, but insists that he is not a thief. Timon&#8217;s advice to continue thieving is so nasty that he decides to turn honest.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="2. LORD., BOTH 1. LORD. AND 2. LORD., ALL LORDS.">Second Lord</name>
<description>The Second Lord is an Athenian gentleman, one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who thinks nothing of simply walking off the street to eat at Timon&#8217;s table and receiving rich gifts from him with no more repayment than flattery. He refuses to help Timon out in his need, claiming to have no money on hand at the time, and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is fatuous and greedy, though unlike some of the other lords, he does show some (extremely faint) concern for Timon&#8217;s mental state. He is also aware that Timon&#8217;s fortune will not last, and that therefore one had best make the best use of it while one can.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="2. SEN.">Second Senator</name>
<description>The Second Senator is an old man, one of the members of government who refuses to help Timon when he is in need, and refuses to pay any attention to Alcibiades&#8217;s pleas for one of his men&#8217;s life. As a result, he is forced to plead with Timon for help against Alcibiades when the panic-struck Athenians want Timon as a dictator to save them from the rebels. He is unsuccessful. In the end he surrenders to Alcibiades to save the city.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="2. STRAN.">Second Stranger</name>
<description>The Second Stranger (Hostilius) is shocked that Lucullus has refused to help Timon out, and gossips to Lucius about it. He takes Lucius&#8217;s measure when the latter also refuses to help.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="SEM.">Sempronius</name>
<description>Sempronius is a lord of Athens, one of Timon&#8217;s flattering friends, and a very proud man who considers himself insulted to be asked for help after others instead of first. Or, at least, that&#8217;s his excuse for not helping Timon in his need.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="SER., THREE SERVANTS.">Servilius</name>
<description>Servilius is one of Timon&#8217;s servants, sent to request fifty talents from Lucius when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. He appears to accept Lucius&#8217;s word that he doesn&#8217;t have enough money on him to help out. He announces to Timon that Lucius has sent him some horses and he also announces the arrival of some Senators at Timon&#8217;s feast.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="SOLD.">Soldier</name>
<description>A Soldier is sent by Alcibiades to find Timon and ask for his support in his attack on Athens, but only finds Timon&#8217;s grave. He is illiterate, but knows the value of words, and brings a cast of the inscription on the tomb to his general.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="3. BAN., ALL BAN., ALL OTHER BAN.">Third Bandit</name>
<description>The Third Bandit has seen Timon before; like his fellows, he insists that he is not a thief. Timon&#8217;s advice to continue stealing is so nasty it almost convinces him to give up his job as a robber.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="3. LORD., ALL LORDS.">Third Lord</name>
<description>The Third Lord is one of Timon&#8217;s innumerable bootlickers, who refuses to help him out when he is in need and is shocked at Timon&#8217;s reaction. He is aware that Timon&#8217;s fortunes cannot last and that therefore one had best make use of it while one can. A gossip, he is less concerned about Timon&#8217;s mental state than about the state of his own hat.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="3. SEN.">Third Senator</name>
<description>The Third Senator practices usury on the side, and is deeply concerned about how much money Timon spends. Realizing that Timon&#8217;s endless parties can only result in his bankruptcy, he decides to call in his debts while Timon may still have some money left to pay them back, setting off the collapse of Timon&#8217;s credit. He is shocked at Alcibiades&#8217;s suggestion that he and the other old senators are growing forgetful. He is terrified of the arrival of the exile&#8217;s army.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="3. STRAN.">Third Stranger</name>
<description>The Third Stranger is appalled at Lucius&#8217;s refusal to help Timon.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="TIMAN., BOTH PHRY. AND TIMAN.">Timandra</name>
<description>Timandra is one of Alcibiades&#8217;s mistresses, accompanying him and his army as he marches on Athens. She has heard of Timon, who accuses her of being riddled with venereal disease. Though insulted by him, she is willing to listen to his cursing so long as he gives her gold.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="TIM.">Timon of Athens</name>
<description>Timon of Athens is a rich man of Athens with absolutely no sense of scale, either in prosperity or in misery. He believes that one can buy friendship, and showers rich gifts on anybody who attends his feasts &#8212; and anybody can simply walk in off the street to join them. His chief fault is his generosity and his belief in the goodness of man; he refuses to look at his accounts because he trusts that his steward, Flavius, is honest. He refuses to see debts to him repaid, and is convinced that anyone he has been kind to will naturally return the favor. An open and honest man, he has no understanding of hypocrisy and therefore no defense against flattery, which he takes at face value because he himself means everything he says. The discovery that he has managed to spend his entire fortune startles him, but it is not until nobody will help that he becomes disturbed. Harassed by creditors, he gives way to anger soon becoming as extravagant in his hatred for those who have disappointed him as he was in his gifts to them. He thereafter refuses to see any good in humanity and spends most of his time cursing it. He goes to live in a cave, and when he accidentally digs up a hidden pile of gold, he gives it to soldiers planning to sack Athens, to prostitutes and thieves, enjoining them to continue in their acts and grow worse at them until the entire world is destroyed. Finally dying, and as happy to do so as he is capable of being happy, he writes his own epitaph, a final insult to the whole of humanity &#8212; a curious conflation of the two parts of his personality, both requesting anonymity and making sure passers-by know his name.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="TIM. PAGE.">Timon&#8217;s Page</name>
<description>Timon&#8217;s Page is sent to bring two letters, one to Timon and one to Alcibiades. As he cannot read, he mixes the two up and is forced to ask Apemantus for help. He stands up reasonably well to the cynic&#8217;s insults.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="TIM. SERV.,THREE SERVANTS.">Timon&#8217;s Servant</name>
<description>Timon&#8217;s Servant is sent to request fifty talents of Sempronius when Timon&#8217;s debts catch up with him. He is appalled when Sempronius refuses to help his master.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="TIT.">Titus</name>
<description>Titus is the servant of one of Timon&#8217;s creditors, sent to ask for repayment on that debt. He is rather skeptical about the whole process, being quite aware that Timon has spent more on the various creditors than they have lent to him, and does not mind pointing this out. Nevertheless, he does his best to do his job.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="1. VAR. SERV.">Varro&#8217;s First Servant </name>
<description>Varro&#8217;s First Servant works for a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money (3,000 crowns), who is sent to recover a sum that&#8217;s been due for six weeks. He makes a weak attempt to match wits with the Fool, and knows quite well what is likely to happen if Apemantus starts to speak. Sent back with a second servant when he fails to get the money back, he is aware of the unfairness of what is happening to Timon. He is not overly fond of his master.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="2. VAR. SERV.">Varro&#8217;s Second Servant</name>
<description>Varro&#8217;s Second Servant works for a usurer to whom Timon owes a great deal of money (3,000 crowns), and is sent along with Varro&#8217;s First Servant to recover the sum when the latter is unsuccessful in getting the money back on his own. He is not particularly sympathetic to the out-of-work Flavius.</description>
</persona>

<persona>
<name short="VEN.">Ventidius</name>
<description>Ventidius is a friend of Timon&#8217;s who tends to live beyond his means, to the extent that he ends up in prison for debt. Luckily for him, Timon is foolishly generous and immediately pays the debt. Inheriting his father&#8217;s wealth, he does offer to repay this one debt, but may not be particularly surprised when Timon refuses to take them. Growing less foolish with his money after he is rich, he declines to help Timon in his need.</description>
</persona>

</personae>