<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Titus Andronicus">

<persona>
<persname short="SAT.">Saturninus</persname>
<persdescription>Saturninus is the elder son of the deceased Emperor of Rome and a candidate for his throne, who appeals to the old aristocracy as being the elder son. A young man, he proves to be untrustworthy, ungrateful, quarrelsome, lascivious and tyrannical. He disregards the old traditions of Rome, attempting to marry his brother&#8217;s betrothed, and shows no gratitude to Titus, to whom he owes the crown, even marrying the chief prisoner he brings home from his wars against the Goths. Saturninus is completely under Tamora&#8217;s spell, allowing the older woman to lead him by the nose and propose policy without the Emperor realizing that she is cheating on him. Not at all popular with the common people, Saturninus is afraid of them, and fears also losing his throne. He is more weak than evil, unwilling to see past the immediate appearance of things and taking the easiest course out. He is truly horrified at the murder of his brother Bassianus, even though he did not like said brother, and likewise at the guilt of his stepsons Demetrius and Chiron in Lavinia&#8217;s rape and Titus&#8217;s killing of the latter. He is not the happiest of men.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAS.">Bassianus</persname>
<persdescription>Bassianus is the younger son of the deceased Emperor of Rome, and a candidate for his throne, who appeals to the common people as being a better man than his brother Saturninus. Despite this vaunted ethical superiority, he is quite willing to offer a bribe to Titus when the old man becomes the one to choose who shall be Emperor. This does him no good. He accepts Titus&#8217;s decision, but cannot stomach it when Saturninus attempts to steal his fianc&amp;eacute;e Lavinia, and runs off with her. He is a good-natured and honorable man who pleads for Titus even though the old man does not want his help. He also despises both Tamora and Aaron, which unfortunately leads to his being murdered and tossed into a pit. He is a passionate man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TIT.">Titus Andronicus</persname>
<persdescription>Titus Andronicus is an old man, the head of the powerful Andronicus family, and a lifelong soldier. Deeply conservative, he is rigid, uncompromising, unsentimental, proud, religious, concerned for his family honor and possessed of a truly military respect for doing things the right way. Offered the possibility of becoming Emperor, he rejects it, refuses Bassianus&#8217;s offer of a bribe, and gives in to his knee-jerk reaction of making the elder son of the dead Emperor the new monarch, despite Saturninus&#8217;s evident unworthiness. One of the great soldiers of the age, Titus had 25 sons, 21 of whom are dead in the wars, and one daughter, Lavinia. His stiff-necked refusal to show mercy to Tamora and her sons dooms almost his entire family, while his trust in serving the Emperor no matter what leaves him vulnerable when Saturninus rejects him. A ruthless man, Titus kills his own son Mutius when he gets in his way and attempts to reject his entire family when they disapprove of his actions, including at first refusing to let them bury Mutius honorably. As the events of the play progress and prove that Titus&#8217;s well-ordered world does not work the way it should, the old man&#8217;s grasp on reality begins to waver. Just how far he progresses on the road to madness is a matter of opinion &#8212; though he shoots arrows with messages to the gods, he also recognizes Tamora in her disguise as Revenge. Not a man to do things by halves, he plots an extreme revenge on the Queen of Goths for what she does to him. Though he can never quite be accused of self-pity &#8212; he has reasons enough to grumble &#8212; he does spend rather a lot of time complaining. He loves his grandson Young Lucius a great deal.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MARC.">Marcus Andronicus</persname>
<persdescription>Marcus Andronicus is a Tribune of the People, Publius&#8217;s father, and Titus&#8217;s younger brother, the political face of the powerful Andronicus family. He announces and approves the nomination of his brother as Emperor, but accepts it when Titus chooses not to take the opportunity. He is appalled at Titus&#8217;s killing of Mutius and his refusal to let him be honorably buried. He attempts to make Titus somewhat more flexible, though he is not overly successful at this. He loves his niece Lavinia and is horrified when he finds her mutilated; as further blows fall on the family, he is brought to the edge of despair. He recovers somewhat, and is able to work out a way to communicate with Lavinia. He is probably the most intelligent of the Andronici, though this does not do him much good. He does what he can to control Titus when the latter essentially loses his mind, but does not in any way contradict him. He arranges for the meeting at Titus&#8217;s house and plays the honest broker at the feast. How much he knows of Titus&#8217;s plans for this meal is unknown, as he misses the murder of Chiron and Demetrius. Still, after everyone is dead, Marcus is finally able to get a family member named Emperor of Rome.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUC.">Lucius</persname>
<persdescription>Lucius is the eldest of Titus&#8217;s living sons, a strong soldier and a popular man. As uncompromising as his father, Lucius insists on sacrificing a Goth prisoner for his brothers&#8217; funeral. He refuses to accept that his sister Lavinia be taken from her fianc&amp;eacute; Bassianus and given to the new Emperor, Saturninus, instead. Hot-headed and quick to act on what he perceives is right, he attempts to save his two brothers Quintus and Marius from execution, leading to his banishment. He is a widower with a son of his own, Young Lucius. He is able to convince the Goths to accept him and leader despite being the son of their greatest enemy and to follow him in a war against their former Queen, Tamora. Named Emperor by the people after the final slaughter, he proves not to be a forgiving man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="QUIN.">Quintus</persname>
<persdescription>Quintus is Titus&#8217;s fifth son, a soldier who follows his elder brother Lucius&#8217;s lead. He joins with the others in keeping Lavinia from being given to Saturninus and in insisting that Mutius receive proper burial. The sight of his brother Martius being afraid chills him. Framed for Bassianus&#8217;s murder, he is executed on the Emperor&#8217;s orders.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MART.">Martius</persname>
<persdescription>Martius is one of Titus&#8217;s sons, a soldier who follows his elder brother Lucius&#8217;s lead. He joins with the others in keeping Lavinia from being given to Saturninus and in insisting that Mutius receive proper burial. Falling into the pit containing Bassianus&#8217;s body, he is terrified by the discovery. Framed for the murder, he is executed on the Emperor&#8217;s orders.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MUT.">Mutius</persname>
<persdescription>Mutius is one of Titus&#8217;s sons, a soldier who follows his elder brother Lucius&#8217;s lead. He joins with the others in keeping Lavinia from being given to Saturninus, acting as guard against any followers, with the result that he is killed by his father.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="Y. LUC.">Young Lucius</persname>
<persdescription>Young Lucius is Titus&#8217;s grandson, the son of Lucius. He does not think that his grandfather&#8217;s lamenting is doing anyone much good. He is somewhat terrified of his mutilated aunt Lavinia, whom he loves but fears has gone mad. Still a schoolboy, he is attentive to good storytelling and myths, which both Titus and Lavinia told him in better days, for which he loved them. He has his father&#8217;s hot temper and is quite ready to kill others, were it not that he is physically weak. He cannot quite dissemble his hatred of Chiron, Demetrius and Aaron, but manages to deceive them all the same. He is a good archer. He is heart-broken by Titus&#8217;s death, though he does end up as potential heir to the throne of Rome.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AEMIL.">Aemilius</persname>
<persdescription>Aemilius is a noble Roman used as go-between for the Goths and Romans. He brings the news of Lucius&#8217;s generalship of the Goths and their coming attack to Saturninus, and arranges the meeting between Goth leaders and the Emperor at Titus&#8217;s house. After the slaughter is over, he nominates Lucius as the new Emperor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PUB.">Publius</persname>
<persdescription>Publius is Marcus&#8217;s son. He helps his father keep an eye on his uncle Titus when the latter essentially loses his mind. He helps to capture Chiron and Demetrius and prepare them for their slaughter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SEMP.">Sempronius</persname>
<persdescription>Sempronius [mute role] is Titus&#8217;s kinsman, and joins him in his mad archery contest.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAI.">Caius</persname>
<persdescription>Caius [mute role] is Titus&#8217;s kinsman. He joins him in his mad archery contest, and helps to capture Chiron and Demetrius and prepare them for their slaughter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAL.">Valentine</persname>
<persdescription>Valentine [mute role] is Titus&#8217;s kinsman, and helps to capture Chiron and Demetrius and prepare them for their slaughter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALAR.">Alarbus</persname>
<persdescription>Alarbus [mute role] is Tamora&#8217;s eldest son, and as such is marked for sacrifice at the funeral of Titus&#8217;s sons. Despite his mother&#8217;s pleas, he is hacked into pieces and his entrails burnt.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DEM.">Demetrius</persname>
<persdescription>Demetrius is Tamora&#8217;s second son, and rather a lout. Though he voices righteous anger at the sacrificing of his elder brother Alarbus, that is the last time he appears serious. He is a quarrelsome, lascivious, and violent boy, with very low opinions on women &#8212; though he does love his mother. He is willing to share with his younger brother Chiron, though he thinks himself better due to be the elder. Together they are led by their mother&#8217;s lover Aaron. Demetrius does not approve of that relationship when he learns of it. He is not very bright, and does not realize that Titus might be dangerous, no more than he realizes just how far Aaron is willing to go in villainy. He believes that having his mother as wife of the Emperor gives him leave to do whatsoever he pleases. Acting on this belief ends up getting him baked into a pie.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CHI.">Chiron</persname>
<persdescription>Chiron is Tamora&#8217;s youngest son, and rather a lout. He does not appreciate his elder brother&#8217;s insistence that being older should have precedence. He is violent and lascivious, and somewhat more imaginative than his brother, coming up with the idea of raping Lavinia on top of her husband&#8217;s dead body. Still, he is not very bright, following Aaron&#8217;s suggestions and being unable to conceive that Titus might be dangerous. He is horrified to discover that Aaron has been having an affair with Tamora. He believes that having his mother as wife of the Emperor gives him leave to do whatsoever he pleases. Acting on this belief ends up getting him baked into a pie.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AAR.">Aaron</persname>
<persdescription>Aaron the Moor is a black man captured by Titus among the Goths, and Tamora&#8217;s lover. He is not a very nice man, as he not only enjoys doing evil but also likes to lead others into doing so as well. He encourages Chiron and Demetrius to rape Lavinia rather than attempt to seduce her, and plots the death of Bassianus before framing two of Titus&#8217;s sons for it. If that were not enough, he convinces Titus to chop off his own hand, as far as one can tell simply for his own amusement. He never shows any sign of genuinely caring for another human being until he is suddenly presented with his baby son by Tamora, and decides not to kill it. Running away to save the baby, he is captured by the Goths and finds himself in Lucius&#8217;s power. He proceeds to brag about how evil he is. Whether he tells the truth or is merely bragging is unknown. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MESS.">Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>A Messenger brings Titus the heads of his sons, along with his chopped-off hand. He feels a bit bad about this.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRIB.">Tribune</persname>
<persdescription>A Tribune speaks for his fellow lawmakers, and confirms that they will name Emperor whomsoever Titus chooses.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CLO.">Clown</persname>
<persdescription>A Clown is a not-very-bright Roman sent as a messenger by Titus to Saturninus, who hangs him. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TAM.">Tamora</persname>
<persdescription>Tamora is the Queen of the Goths, and the mother of Alarbus, Demetrius and Chiron. Captured in battle along with her sons by Titus, she pleads for the life of her eldest but is rejected, and vows revenge on Titus. An attractive older woman, she attracts the attention of the new and young Emperor of Rome, Saturninus, who marries her. Intelligent, deceitful and dangerous, she is able to lead Saturninus by the nose. He never questions the closeness of her relationship with Aaron the Moor. A vicious woman, she chooses to take her revenge slowly, using her lover Aaron and her sons to break Titus&#8217;s heart and mind, as she sets them to murder, rape, mutilate and frame those he loves best. Her conduct is so appalling that even the Goths are willing to make war on her. She falls pregnant by Aaron and orders him to kill the baby when it turns out to be black. She finally overreaches by thinking that Titus is madder than he is, leading to her sons&#8217; capture and killing. Her reaction to discovering that she is eating her sons&#8217; bodies in a pie is not recorded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAV.">Lavinia</persname>
<persdescription>Lavinia is Titus&#8217;s only daughter, a beautiful and chaste young woman who is every conservative father&#8217;s ideal, obedient, quiet, patient, loving, and never a bother to anyone. Extremely passive, she takes few initiatives. Bassianus&#8217;s fianc&amp;eacute;e, she says nothing when Titus accepts to give her to Saturninus instead, nor when her brothers carry her off to protect her from this fate. Still, she is capable of sauciness, mocking Tamora when coming across her and Aaron together in the woods. She is quickly reduced to silence again, however, when she is raped on top of her husband&#8217;s dead body, then to prevent her from identifying her violators has her tongue pulled out and her hands cut off. She is a kind and literate woman, fond of her nephew Young Lucius, and manages to use books to explain to her family what has happened to her. She is quite willing to join in Titus&#8217;s revenge on her ravishers, holding the basin to collect their blood when Titus kills them. Her reaction to Titus&#8217;s decision to kill her for her and his honor is not recorded.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NUR.">Nurse</persname>
<persdescription>A Nurse brings Aaron&#8217;s black bastard baby to him so that he can fulfill Tamora&#8217;s orders to kill it. Doing this ends up getting her killed instead. She is distressed by the whole affair, a racist, and doesn&#8217;t consider that Aaron could possibly be dangerous.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SENATORS">Senators</persname>
<persdescription>Senators [mute roles] refuse to listen to Titus&#8217;s pleading as they lead his sons to execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRIBUNES.">Tribunes</persname>
<persdescription>Tribunes follow their leader Marcus in most things, though they refuse to listen to his brother Titus&#8217;s pleading as they lead his sons to execution. They accept Titus&#8217;s choice of Saturninus as Emperor, and later Aemilius&#8217;s nomination of Lucius as his replacement.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BL. CHILD.">A Black Child</persname>
<persdescription>A Black Child is the bastard baby of Aaron and Tamora. His existence risks Tamora&#8217;s life, so she orders Aaron to kill him. As Aaron kind of likes him, his life is spared, but he is later captured by the Andronici. What occurs to this baby is a mystery.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUDGES">Judges</persname>
<persdescription>Judges [mute roles] refuse to listen to Titus&#8217;s pleading as they lead his sons to execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. GOTH.">First Goth</persname>
<persdescription>The First Goth is a leader in the Goth army. Convinced of the justice of Lucius&#8217;s cause, he brings his army along to help his former enemy have revenge. He is shocked at Aaron&#8217;s glee in evil.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. GOTH.">Second Goth</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Goth is a soldier in the Goth army who captures Aaron and brings him and his baby to Lucius.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. GOTH.">Third Goth</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Goth introduces Aemilius to Lucius&#8217;s presence.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ROM. CAP.">Roman Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Roman Captain announces Titus&#8217;s return to Rome.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>