<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Troilus &amp; Cressida">

<persona>
<persname short="PRI.">Priam, King of Troy</persname>
<persdescription>Priam is the King of Troy and the father of fifty sons, among whom are Hector, Troilus, Paris, Deiphobus, and Helenus, and many daughters including Cassandra. He also has a bastard son, Margarelon. He is an old man stuck in an apparently endless war who does not rule by decree but by consensus with his royal council, which includes his sons. He is not altogether pleasant with Paris, who is the cause of it all.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HECT.">Hector</persname>
<persdescription>Hector is Priam&#8217;s son, the brother of Troilus, Paris, Deiphobus and Helenus, and the pride and joy of Troy. Easily the best of the Trojan fighters, he is also fair, chivalrous and merciful, more likely to let a defeated foe go than to kill him, particularly if the opponent is weak. His expectation that the Greeks will act in a similar way leaves him defenseless against Achilles&#8217;s brutality. Hector is horrified when, in a bloodthirsty rage, his youngest brother Troilus castigates him for this charity. Caught up in societal expectations despite his misgivings, Hector can see how ludicrous a war that could be ended by handing Helen back is, but cannot bring himself to take this way out as it would be dishonorable. Known for his gallantry, it is unusual for him to lose his temper, and he is sensible enough to pay some small attention to his sister Cassandra&#8217;s prophecies; though he ends up disregarding them, he is one of the few to do so, and she loves him for it. Nevertheless, he is dismissive of feminine fears and irritated when his wife Andromache tries to keep him from going to war simply because she&#8217;s had a bad dream. Hector refuses to be impressed by Achilles, whose pretensions irritate him; foolishly he allows Achilles to go rather than killing him when they first fight, never thinking that the Greek would use his soldiers to slaughter an unarmed man. He is one of the few decent men in either Troy or Greece, though conscious enough of his honor and the possibility of gain to kill a Greek for the sake of his armor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRO.">Troilus</persname>
<persdescription>Troilus is the youngest of Priam&#8217;s fifty sons, the brother of Hector, Paris, Diphobus, Helenus and Cassandra. He is a hotheaded young man, quick to make up his opinions and sticking to them in despite of all argument. He considers himself to be desperately in love with Cressida, and engages her uncle and guardian Pandarus&#8217;s help in gaining her favors. His protestations of eternal love and devotion ring a bit hollow considering that when he discovers that his lady love is to be handed over to the Greeks, he never protests the decision, merely mopes about it. An idealist, he rejects common-sense arguments about returning Helen to the Greeks in favor of defending honor. Incapable of hiding his feelings, he is recognized as being no hypocrite as well as being more dangerous than Hector because he is less subject to chivalry on the battlefield. He turns into a bloodthirsty Trojan equivalent of Achilles when Cressida betrays him, giving up honor for the hardheaded view that the point of war is to slaughter as many of the enemy as possible. Troilus is extremely dismissive of his sister Cassandra, who he considers mad and of no consequence, and is unable to conceive of working outside societal rules, never even considering that Cressida might not go to the Greeks. He offers her no comfort when she receives the order to leave and never contests it. Not having helped her, he then clumsily questions her faithfulness, but gives her little reason to remain faithful to him once she leaves Troy. He is aghast at her giving in to Diomedes when he spies on the two of them with Ulysses, and grows to a murderous rage. Troilus ends the play casting Pandarus aside and swearing to take revenge on Achilles for his treatment of Hector.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAR.">Paris</persname>
<persdescription>Paris is one of Priam&#8217;s sons, the brother of Hector, Troilus, Deiphobus and Helenus, and the main reason there&#8217;s a war on, as he abducted Helen from her husband Menelaus several years ago. A bit of a wimp, he never acknowledges his responsibility for the war, nor even considers the possibility of giving Helen up. His compassion for Troilus when the latter has to give up Cressida therefore rings rather hollow. He is effeminate and entirely under Helen&#8217;s thumb, refusing to go to battle when she would rather he didn&#8217;t and spending a great deal of time lolling around with her. He is not particularly intelligent, and is foolish enough to set himself up for insults by asking Diomedes&#8217;s opinion on the whole Helen mess. Many Trojans are not especially fond of him, as much for causing the war as for his lack of doing his full part in it, and they tend not to take him very seriously.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DEI.">Deiphobus</persname>
<persdescription>Deiphobus is one of Priam&#8217;s sons, and therefore the brother of Hector, Troilus, Paris and Helenus. He is one of the Trojan warriors who fetch Cressida to hand over to the Greeks.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HEL.">Helenus</persname>
<persdescription>Helenus is a priest and one of Priam&#8217;s sons, and therefore the brother of Hector, Troilus, Paris and Deiphobus. He is not the most renowned fighter, but will take part in battles nevertheless. Clearly an older brother, he points out that Troilus&#8217;s arguments for keeping Helen in Troy don&#8217;t actually stand up.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MAR.">Margarelon</persname>
<persdescription>Margarelon is Priam&#8217;s bastard son, who attempts to have a fight with Thersites. He does not approve of cowardice.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AENE.">Aeneas</persname>
<persdescription>Aeneas is one of the Trojan commanders. A friendly man, he goes ahead to warn Troilus that Cressida is to be given to the Greeks, though he displays little sympathy for the lad and none whatsoever for Cressida. He acts as a herald between Hector and the Greeks. He is quite friendly with the enemy when they are not trying to kill one another. He is captured by Ajax in the last battle, but escapes. He will go on to be one of the few to escape Troy, and will later found Rome (see Virgil&#8217;s <persnameref>Aeneid</persnameref> for details).</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAL.">Calchas</persname>
<persdescription>Calchas is Cressida&#8217;s father, a Trojan priest who has gone over to the Greeks, not that they treat him very well for it. He requests that the Greeks exchange the captured Antenor for Cressida, though he subsequently offers little evidence of actually caring for her; rather, he appears to find her useful as a consort for Diomedes, as that keeps him in the Greeks&#8217; good graces.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAN.">Pandarus</persname>
<persdescription>Pandarus is a Trojan lord, Cressida&#8217;s uncle and guardian. He is an unashamed giggling gossip and a filthy-minded voyeur who delights in arranging love affairs and mocking the participants. Accepting to help Troilus gain Cressida&#8217;s favor, he praises the young man to the skies to her and ends up pushing them into bed together. Infinitely loquacious, he jokes about everything, taking any given opportunity to make naughty comments. He has little patience with oaths of love, much preferring that lovers should get to the physical side of things quickly, if only so he can comment on the fact. When Cressida is ordered to be handed over to the Greeks, he can think of nothing better to do than wail a great deal. Cressida&#8217;s unfaithfulness costs him Troilus&#8217;s friendship. Old and sick, Pandarus suffers from a cough and more than likely one or several venereal diseases that he ends up hoping the audience will catch.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AGAM.">Agamemnon</persname>
<persdescription>Agamemnon is the leader of the Greek army and Menelaus&#8217;s brother. He is rather full of himself and easily mocked by Patroclus. He insists on the nobility of the Greeks&#8217; cause and on the virtues of enduring hardship, but despite his high-sounding orations he is a determinedly ordinary man who uses the services of prostitutes. He shows no sign of particular intelligence, but has the sense to follow Ulysses&#8217;s advice. Agamemnon makes certain to be as chivalrous as he can and to treat his enemies well when they are not fighting.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MEN.">Menelaus</persname>
<persdescription>Menelaus is Agamemnon&#8217;s brother, the King of Sparta, Helen&#8217;s husband, and the most mocked man in the entire play. Having allowed his wife to be stolen away from him by Paris &#8212; the cause of the whole war &#8212; he is relentlessly ridiculed by everyone who meets him as a cuckold. Even Cressida manages to humiliate him as soon as she arrives at the Greek camp. He does not appreciate this fact, and prefers not to discuss his wife. He is a strong fighter who relentlessly follows Paris on the battlefield, but never quite manages to wound him seriously.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NEST.">Nestor</persname>
<persdescription>Nestor is an old Greek lord, an ancient part of history, white-bearded, decrepit, senile, long-winded and by his own admission useless in a fight due to his age. He is highly respected more for his age and what he has done than for anything he is capable of at present. Extremely tedious, never actually adding anything to the conversation but taking forever to not do so, he has a cough and trembles a lot when putting on his armor. He is lead by the nose by Ulysses in the latter&#8217;s plot to convince Agamemnon not to send Achilles as the Greek challenger to Hector. Nestor admires the Trojan hero greatly.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ULYSS.">Ulysses</persname>
<persdescription>Ulysses is one of the Greek leaders, a wily and sneaky man who easily manipulates those around him. He is the cleverest of the Greeks, and hence the most dangerous. He prefers thinking and tactics to blunt force, which makes some other fighters look down on him. Excellent at gathering information and therefore aware of almost everything that&#8217;s going on, he knows exactly what strings to play to make others come around to his point of view, whether in discussing Achilles&#8217;s and Patroclus&#8217;s mockery of the Greek leadership or praising Nestor&#8217;s wisdom. He comes up with the plot to goad Achilles into returning to the fighting and carries it out, directing the others in their parts. He neither likes nor trusts women, and immediately takes Cressida for no more than a whore. Never one to miss a chance to find out more, he agrees to help Troilus find Cressida in the Greek camp, where his opinion of her is not improved. With Diomedes, Ulysses was one of the Greeks who went to Troy to require Helen&#8217;s return and was refused, leading to the war. He will later come up with the idea of the Trojan Horse and bring the war to an end.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ACHIL.">Achilles</persname>
<persdescription>Achilles is one of the Greek generals, the leader of the Myrmidons. He is brutal, arrogant, scornful, and perfectly aware that he is the best of the Greek fighters and hence indispensable to their cause. Not the best of team players, he is quite willing to take himself and his men out of the fight whenever he feels like it and simply not fight, refusing to give a reason. He is extremely, some would say excessively, fond of his companion Patroclus, who amuses Achilles to no end with his mocking imitations of the other Greek leaders. Achilles is however easily manipulated by Ulysses&#8217;s plot to bring him back to the fight, as he cannot bear not being considered the strongest of the Greeks. Achilles has no time for chivalry, neither during a truce nor in battle, and has his soldiers slaughter Hector even though the Trojan is defenseless, very possibly not even bother to deal a blow himself. Though Achilles is wooing the Trojan princess Polyxena, he is much more attached to Patroclus, whose death in battle sends Achilles wild and finally brings him back to the fight. His rage is so great that he desecrates Hector&#8217;s body in the most insulting way, dragging it across the field behind his horse. Achilles is not a pleasant man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AJAX.">Ajax</persname>
<persdescription>Ajax is a large, brawny, well-muscled, and exceptionally stupid Greek leader. Full of self-regard while pleading that he is in fact modest, he is insanely easy to flatter and just as easy to make a fool of. He is far too slow-witted to take on Thersites in a battle of wits, though he occasionally tries. The ultimate brainless jock, he ends up winning only by threatening to beat Thersites up. Buttered up by the other leaders, he accepts Hector&#8217;s challenge to single combat, never dreaming that he is chosen only to irritate Achilles. Though Ajax looks down on Achilles, he is also envious of his reputation and imitates him often, as much in pride as in taking to his tent. Like Achilles, he is enraged at the death of a friend in the final battle, and searches out Troilus for revenge, but ends up fighting Diomedes instead in a quarrel over who has the better right to fight the young Trojan. Ajax is best summed up as being rather dense, but he is a good enough fighter to match Hector and to capture Aeneas in battle, at least for a moment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DIO.">Diomedes</persname>
<persdescription>Diomedes is a Greek leader with few illusions about how the world works. Absolutely without any form of idealism, he thinks that Helen has cost far too much blood on both sides and that she cannot be considered worth it. Though he takes some care to seduce Cressida, this is simply because it is the best way to get her into bed other than raping her. He has no respect for Paris, Troilus or Menelaus, and has no qualms about expressing his lack of regard for them, or his extremely poor opinion of Helen. He is a dangerous fighter, and not a particularly nice man. He forces Cressida to give him Troilus&#8217;s love-token of a sleeve and wears it in his helmet during the battle as a dare to Cressida&#8217;s former lover.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PATR.">Patroclus</persname>
<persdescription>Patroclus is Achilles&#8217;s companion, a young man who is excellent at doing mocking impersonations of the Greek leaders. He serves as Achilles&#8217;s doorkeeper along with being his inseparable friend. He is not the most warlike of men, and worries that Achilles may have decided to pull out of the war for his sake. There are indeed many rumors going about exactly what Patroclus&#8217;s relationship with Achilles is. He also has an odd relationship with Thersites, who risks replacing him as Achilles&#8217;s chief source of amusement. He is not the brightest of fellows. His death in battle will provoke Achilles into returning to the fight and to his greatest barbarities.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="THER.">Thersites</persname>
<persdescription>Thersites is a foul-mouthed Greek servant, first to Ajax and then to Achilles, and the most determinedly unpleasant person in all of Shakespeare. He is constitutionally incapable of saying a nice thing. Essentially a licensed fool, he casts a jaundiced eye on everything that passes by and offers venomous commentary thereon. Sarcastic, snide and sneering, Thersites is an abashed coward who punctures every high-sounding ideal he comes across and unanswerably reduces the war to an absurdity over a domestic dispute. He has no regard for anybody, Greek or Trojan, with the possible exception of himself. His mean-spiritedness encompasses the whole world, though he has a particular affection for savaging men&#8217;s obsession with sex, a subject on which Thersites is, unsurprisingly, cynical. He considers women to be whores as a matter of course.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HELEN.">Helen</persname>
<persdescription>Helen is Menelaus&#8217;s abducted wife, who quite happily ran away with Paris and has since become known to history (somewhat inaccurately) as Helen of Troy. She is the most beautiful woman in history, and she knows it. She leads Paris by the nose, even keeping him home from battle when she pleases. Flirtatious and pleasure-loving, she is considered to be no more than a whore by the vast majority of people.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="AND.">Andromache</persname>
<persdescription>Andromache is Hector&#8217;s wife, and loves him dearly. She is terrified at the idea of his death and tries to persuade him not to take the field after she suffers from premonitory bad dreams. She is very obedient to her husband.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CAS.">Cassandra</persname>
<persdescription>Cassandra is a prophetess, one of Priam&#8217;s daughters and the sister of Hector, Paris, Troilus, Deiphobus and Helenus. For refusing Apollo, she was cursed by him to always prophesize correctly but never be believed. She is generally considered to be mad, particularly by her brother Troilus. She is desperately fond of her brother Hector, who though he never follows her advice at least listens and considers it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CRES.">Cressida</persname>
<persdescription>Cressida is a young lady of Troy, under her uncle Pandarus&#8217;s guardianship since her father Calchas defected to the Greeks. Quick-witted, she is able to trade barbs with Pandarus on his own level, but her sauciness may be a defense mechanism. Life with Pandarus clearly consists mostly of mockery, and she is weary of this. Though attracted to Troilus, she holds off on giving in to him to make sure that he means it, until she is essentially handed over to him by her uncle. Given to the Greeks the next morning, she refuses to go, but with Troilus not even considering the possibility she has little option but to agree. Along with this lack of help, Troilus&#8217;s clumsy questioning of her faithfulness and presumption that she will be quick to betray him leave her with little reason to stick by him once she is handed over. Surrounded by a pack of sex-hungry Greeks who insist on all kissing her, she uses her only weapon, her attractiveness, to gain some measure of ascendance on them, though with the result that she is immediately considered no better than a whore. Her father apparently presumes that she will take up with some Greek or other, and she sees little other option. She feels bad about betraying Troilus, but is in an impossible situation, and in the end allows Diomedes to take Troilus&#8217;s love-token from her. Cressida knows how to play men, and enjoys putting them down, but whether she is a natural flirt or merely puts the disposition on is uncertain. She is also often defensive. Cressida is fully aware that in this very masculine world her sexuality is her only advantage and power, and acts on the fact.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PROLOGUE">Prologue</persname>
<persdescription>The Prologue comes out to give a bit of background on the Trojan War and inform the audience that the action of the play starts several years after the beginning of that war. He sets the tone both with his heightened language and by being dressed in armor.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TRO. BOY.">Troilus&#8217;s Boy</persname>
<persdescription>Troilus&#8217;s Boy fetches Pandarus for his master, and keeps a lookout for him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAR. SERV.">Paris&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Paris&#8217;s Servant is a saucy, quick-witted fellow who twits those who ask questions that can lead to wordplay.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GREEK TRUM.">Greek Trumpeter</persname>
<persdescription>A Greek Trumpeter [mute role] is not particularly well-treated, but does get paid. He sounds Ajax&#8217;s challenge to Hector.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ALEX.">Alexander</persname>
<persdescription>Alexander is Cressida&#8217;s manservant. He keeps up with the latest news to pass it on to his mistress.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT.">Antenor</persname>
<persdescription>Antenor [mute role] is a Trojan commander captured by the Greeks, for whom the Trojans will exchange almost any requested hostage &#8212; in this case, Cressida. He is known for his good judgment.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TROJ. TRUM.">Trojan Trumpeter</persname>
<persdescription>A Trojan Trumpeter [mute role] accompanies Aeneas to the Greek camp to deliver Hector&#8217;s challenge.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DIO. SERV.">Diomedes&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Diomedes&#8217;s Servant is sent by his master to bring Cressida Troilus&#8217;s captured horse.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GREEK. KNI.">Greek Knight</persname>
<persdescription>A Greek Knight [mute role] in armor wears extremely costly armor that makes him a prime target on the battlefield and attracts Hector&#8217;s attention.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MYR.">Myrmidon</persname>
<persdescription>A Myrmidon hears the Trojans&#8217; trumpets sounding the retreat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MYRMIDONS.">Myrmidons</persname>
<persdescription>Mymidons are Achilles&#8217;s followers, the descendants of a people that used to be ants until the gods transformed them. They obey Achilles implicitly, no matter how dishonorable the order, and kill the unarmed Hector. They proclaim the news of Hector&#8217;s death, claiming that Achilles did the killing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MUSIC.">Musicians</persname>
<persdescription>Musicians [mute roles] attend on Paris and Helen, serenading them at their command. Essentially, they are a walking stereo system.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TROJ. SOLD.">Trojan Soldiers</persname>
<persdescription>Trojan Soldiers [mute roles] return to town after the fighting, following the noble fighters. They are not seen to be worthy of commentary, unlike the named warriors.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>