<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Twelfth Night">

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="DUKE.">Orsino</persname>
<persdescription>Orsino, the Duke and Count of Illyria, is a young man deeply and fashionably in love with Olivia. Her rejection of him leaves him in a deep and just as fashionable melancholy. Rather than press his suit in person, he sends messengers to Olivia, and it is in fact quite possible that he has never actually met her, merely seen her at a distance. Now that he is in love, he no longer hunts, but he has a deep love of music that he frequently indulges in. He has a great affection for his newly-acquired page, Cesario, and gives him sage advice about love and women. He also uses Cesario as a messenger to Olivia. He was not always so weary, and has fought in sea-battles, including one against Antonio. Discovering that Cesario is loved by Olivia, he swears to drag them apart. Discovering that they are married, he turns his rage against Cesario in person. Discovering that Cesario is in fact a woman, who loves him dearly and is not married to Olivia, he decides to marry her instead.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SEB.">Sebastian</persname>
<persdescription>Sebastian is Viola&#8217;s twin brother. After the shipwreck, he was rescued by Antonio, and spent three months in his company. Deciding that he cannot continue moping over his sister&#8217;s death, he sets forth for Orsino&#8217;s court, but on arriving in Illyria he discovers that Antonio has followed him. He proceeds to have a very confusing day, where his enjoyment of the usual touristy activities of sightseeing are continually interrupted by a series of mad people who claim to know him, including a pair of insulting ones with whom he almost ends up in a fight. His bafflement and belief that all Illyrians are insane do not stop him from following the beautiful woman who breaks up the fight, however. He is not entirely unconvinced that he&#8217;s dreaming, but can find no good reason not to follow this woman and the priest she drags in, and so goes along with her plans of secret marriage. Meeting his two opponents again, he shows them no mercy, breaks their heads, and rushes to apologize to his wife&#8213;only to discover that his sister is alive and that Olivia originally fell in love with her, not him. he confusion is quickly cleared up, and all is well. Sebastian seems an uncomplicated fellow, as quick to anger as to calming down, loyal and generally well-disposed.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="ANT.">Antonio</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio is a sea captain. Though considered a pirate by Illyrians, he considers himself an honorable opponent. Though due to his history of capturing Illyrians ships, he is not very welcome in Orsino&#8217;s lands, he knows which is the best inn in town. He is deeply infatuated with Sebastian, whom he saved from drowning, to the extent of following him to Illyria despite the personal danger to him. He is shocked and wounded when Sebastian (as he thinks) later refuses to acknowledge knowing him, let alone having borrowed his purse. When the real Sebastian rushed up to embrace him and return his money, he is deeply confused, and incapable of telling the difference between the twins. What happens to Antonio, who discovers that Sebastian has been married since they last saw each other that afternoon, is uncertain. Generally he joins in with the reveling, if in a bit of a lonely way; but it is not impossible that everyone forgets about him and that he&#8217;s executed after all.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CAP.">Sea Captain</persname>
<persdescription>A Sea Captain was the captain of the ship that Viola and Sebastian were traveling on. He saw Sebastian tie himself to a mast, and so offers Viola some hope that he may still be alive. He tells Viola of Illyria, Orsino and his love for Olivia. He accepts to help Viola disguise herself as a man and to present her to the Duke, and keeps her women&#8217;s clothes in his custody. He is later arrested at Malvolio&#8217;s suit, but Olivia promises that he will be freed and able to tell his part in the story.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="VAL.">Valentine</persname>
<persdescription>Valentine is one of Orsino&#8217;s attendants. He was sent to Olivia as a messenger of love, but was not allowed to speak to her. He brings back the news that she has pledged to mourn a full seven years for her brother. He also advises Cesario (Viola) that he (she) is in a good position, and that Orsino&#8217;s favors are not inconstant.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CUR.">Curio</persname>
<persdescription>Curio is one of Orsino&#8217;s attendants. He seeks to distract Orsino by taking him to hunt, but Orsino refuses. He knows Feste, and is sent to find him so that he can sing a song Orsino particularly desires to hear.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SIR TO.">Sir Toby Belch</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Toby Belch is Olivia&#8217;s uncle and something of a minor-league Falstaff. A penniless drunkard who sets stock by his nobility of birth, with a taste for pickled herrings that likely leave him flatulent, he makes himself quite at home at his niece&#8217;s. He has the full confidence of Sir Andrew, whom he considers a fool, and can play him like a charm. This allows him easy access to Sir Andrew&#8217;s money. He has managed to convince Sir Andrew that he has a chance at Olivia&#8217;s hand. Though most of what Sir Toby does appears to be purely for his own entertainment, he is quite capable of moments of genuine nastiness, reminding Malvolio of the difference in their social class, tying the steward up and having him locked in a dark room, putting Sir Andrew in situations that could lead to his serious injury or death, and in the end telling Sir Andrew to his face what he is. Sir Toby is quick to pull his sword, though we have no evidence as to whether he has any prowess with it. Taken with Maria&#8217;s wit and prank-planning ability, he marries her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SIR AND.">Sir Andrew Aguecheek</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Andrew Aguecheek is an unfortunate fellow. He is tall and very thin, with pale hair that lies flat and lanky, though he may occasionally attempt to curl it. He is quarrelsome and a coward, a drunk, and very stupid. He is also very rich, though he does not realize that this is why Sir Toby appears to like him. He throws away his money almost without realizing it, and according to Sir Toby can play music and speak three or four languages, though this rumor is quickly put to rest. (He can speak a few words of French, though.) He himself admits that he has spent most of his time fencing, dancing, and bear-baiting. Toby has brought him to Olivia&#8217;s with the promise of helping him marry her. In verbal games, he is completely outclassed by Sir Toby, not least because he does not understand half the words Toby uses. Featherbrained, his mind flits from subject to subject, and Sir Toby plays him easily. He enjoys a good song. In the past, he was once adored by someone. His mention of this may be a moment of realization, or a boast. The latter interpretation sits well with his general childishness, such as his swearing to sue Sebastian for hitting him, even if he did start it himself. We do not know his reaction when Sir Toby finally tells him to his face exactly what he is.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="MAL.">Malvolio</persname>
<persdescription>Malvolio, whose name might be translated as &#8216;ill-will,&#8217; is Olivia&#8217;s steward. Something of a puritan, he abhors disorder and drunkenness, along with bear-baiting and for that matter laughter: he does not smile. He is disgusted that Olivia takes pleasure in the jokes of a professional jester. He also has a more than healthy self-regard; in fact, he is appallingly full of himself. His social aspirations are also somewhat unbounded: he dreams of acceding to the nobility, for which he believes himself well-suited. His fantasies about marrying Olivia are almost entirely non-erotic, focusing rather on the power, wealth and respectability he would thus gain. When Sir Toby pulls rank on him in the middle of the night, reminding him that he is nothing but a steward, his immediate reaction is to pull rank on Maria, who is even lower in the social hierarchy. He is therefore well-primed to interpret the letter in the garden the way he does, especially as it urges him to act towards others in the way that is his natural bent. Locked away in a dark room and left with no option but to beg the fool he has earlier humiliated for help, he is still unable to do so in a truly humble manner, and on discovering that he has been completely fooled, his only reaction is a promise of revenge.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="FAB.">Fabian</persname>
<persdescription>Fabian is a member of Olivia&#8217;s household who has lost that lady&#8217;s favor due to Malvolio&#8217;s telling her about a bear-baiting Fabian was involved with. For revenge, he joins in the plot to make a fool of the steward. He also helps Sir Toby keep control of Sir Andrew. Apparently a natural prankster, he helps to set up the duel between Andrew and Cesario, building up the latter&#8217;s fear of Sir Andrew. Feste does not appear to consider him trustworthy, refusing to let him see the letter Malvolio sends to Olivia from his prison. Having later read the letter aloud to Olivia and all the others, Fabian quickly confesses the whole plot, in the hope that with everyone being so happy and about to be married, they won&#8217;t be too hard on the plotters, and take it all as a good joke.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="CLO.">Feste</persname>
<persdescription>Feste was Olivia&#8217;s father&#8217;s jester, and is now hers, though it appears that he wanders around a bit. An excellent singer, he also plays the pipe and tabor. He is not especially tall, nor especially thin. An expert in wordplay, he attempts to bring Olivia out of her melancholy and mourning, though this brings him Malvolio&#8217;s scorn. His wordplay is also useful in convincing people to give him money. Though he joins in the plot against Malvolio, it is clear that his first loyalty is to Olivia: he runs to find her when Sir Toby and Sir Andrew set upon Cesario, and refuses to let Fabian read the letter the steward sends Olivia from his prison, apparently thinking the prank has gone long enough. When Malvolio is freed, however, Feste does make certain to remind him of the scorn he has poured on his underlings. He appears to be the only member of Olivia&#8217;s household who thinks she should be cheered up. As he was her father&#8217;s jester, it is likely that he has known her all her life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="OLI.">Olivia</persname>
<persdescription>Olivia is an orphaned, gray-eyed countess who has sworn to remain in mourning for seven years after the recent death of her brother. Though aware of all his qualities, she cannot fall in love with Orsino, despite his pestering her with love letters. She is fond of Feste, relies on Malvolio, and has her patience strained by her uncle Toby. She is nevertheless caring and patient, as demonstrated in her treatment of Malvolio when he appears to lose his mind. She has few illusions about the world, being as well-aware of Malvolio&#8217;s defects as of her uncle&#8217;s drunkenness as of her own mind. She is ready to fall topsy-turvy in love with Cesario, however, bowled over by his wit and willingness to toss away the script. Despite his rejection of her, she begs him to return, hoping to bring him to love her by degrees &#8212; not entirely unlike Orsino. She is quite capable of losing her temper, especially when her uncle is on the verge of fighting with Cesario. She is similarly impulsive enough that when Cesario suddenly starts treating her well, she rushes to find a priest who will marry them in secret. She is therefore deeply hurt when he later denies this and runs away after Orsino, swearing he loves the Duke more than he does her. This confusion is cleared up when it is discovered that the Cesario Olivia fell for is in fact a woman by the name of Viola, while the one who was taken with her and married her is Viola&#8217;s twin brother Sebastian. She is somewhat shocked at this, but accepts that Viola, who will now be marrying Orsino, will be her sister.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="VIO.">Viola</persname>
<persdescription>Viola is a lady of Messaline. When dressed as a man she is identical to her twin brother Sebastian. Shipwrecked on the coast of Illyria, convinced that her brother is drowned, she disguises herself as a man for her own safety, and seeks refuge at Orsino&#8217;s court, where she quickly becomes his favorite page under the name of Cesario. Sent to woo Olivia, she so impresses that lady, partly by her willingness to throw her script away, that Olivia falls in love with her, which is unfortunate seeing as she&#8217;s a woman and happens to be in love with Orsino. She defends her gender&#8217;s ability to love to Orsino, can be readily terrified at being forced to fight, and is quick-witted enough to realise that her brother may still be alive when Antonio recognises her. Despite this, she is confused enough when accused of having married Olivia that she does not consider that Sebastian may be an answer to the enigma. When her brother, Sebastian, arrives on the scene and all is unravelled, she admits to her gender and accepts Orsino&#8217;s proposal of marriage.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="female">
<persname short="MAR.">Maria</persname>
<persdescription>Maria is Olivia&#8217;s waiting-gentlewoman. Though she begins by attempting to keep Sir Toby under control, she quickly becomes one of his cronies and the brains behind the plot against Malvolio. Her motives may be mercenary: by the end of the play she will have married Sir Toby, thus escaping becoming a member of the gentry. This is a particularly neat revenge on Malvolio, who pulls rank on her: she achieves exactly what he cannot and becomes his social superior. Whether this is social climber or genuine affection is unknown. Close to her mistress, she is able to imitate her handwriting well enough to deceive the steward, though not Olivia herself. She is clearly a persuasive lady, able to convince Feste to join in on the joke and able to mislead Olivia into believing Malvolio mad.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="SERV.">Olivia&#8217;s Servant</persname>
<persdescription>Olivia&#8217;s Servant is not part of the cabal of upper servants who mock Malvolio. He simply does his job, unaffected by the madness that seems to have taken over the house.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="PRIEST.">Priest</persname>
<persdescription>The Priest is fetched by Olivia to marry her to her young man in secret. Apparently he does not ask for the groom&#8217;s name during the ceremony, as Olivia is still unaware two hours later that he&#8217;s called Sebastian Called forth as a witness, he testifies that he has married Olivia to the young man standing by Orsino&#8217;s side.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="1. OFF.">First Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The First Officer recognizes Antonio from the sea-fight, and arrests him. He has no interest in Antonio&#8217;s quarrel with Viola.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona gender="male">
<persname short="2. OFF.">Second Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Officer does not actually know Antonio, but arrests him. He has no interest in Antonio&#8217;s quarrel.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>