<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Two Noble Kinsmen">

<persona>
<persname short="THE.">Theseus, Duke of Athens</persname>
<persdescription>Theseus is the Duke of Athens, a mighty warrior who has recently conquered the Amazons and is supposed to be marrying their Queen, Hippolyta. Interrupted on the way to the ceremony, he takes a great deal of convincing before he agrees to put his marriage off and go fight Creon instead. He believes that reason should rule over passion, and therefore in the end does as he is asked. Impressed by Palamon and Arcite&#8217;s valor in the war, he brings them back as prisoners and has them cured of their wounds. He shares a deep friendship with Pirithous, who is able to convince him to let Arcite go. He enjoys having entertainments presented to him by his subjects, and rewards them well. He has a hot temper at times, and is a bit inflexible about changing his mind after he swears something when he is in a rage. Hippolyta and Emilia are able to soften him, though, as he is in love with his wife and fond of his sister-in-law. He is however quick to arrange for the latter to marry a former prisoner of his, and takes little notice of her apparent uncertainty in the matter. He is a pious man. He is the same as the Theseus of <persnameref>A Midsummer Night&#8217;s Dream</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PIR.">Pirithous</persname>
<persdescription>Pirithous is Theseus&#8217;s dearest friend, and has a great deal of influence on him. When Theseus decides to make war on Creon before marrying, Pirithous is charged with keeping the festivities going all the same before joining the Duke at the war. He is very fond of Emilia. His influence with Theseus is enough to get the latter to agree to release Arcite from prison. He is greatly impressed by strong, noble-looking men. He rushes to stop Palamon&#8217;s execution after he witnesses Arcite&#8217;s fatal accident.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAL.">Palamon</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ARC. AND PAL.">Both Arcite and Palamon</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Palamon is a nephew of the tyrant Creon of Thebes. He neither likes nor approves of his uncle, and would leave his court and fight against him, were it not dishonorable. He is deeply attached to his cousin Arcite, his war-mate and best friend, and quite self-congratulatory about what good friends they are. The two are almost indistinguishable, both being just as self-involved, and both falling powerfully in love with Emilia merely at the sight of her. Palamon is gloomier than his cousin, and has more of a temper. He sings to himself when alone in prison, and is very kind to his Jailer&#8217;s Daughter, who tends to him &#8212; even kissing her once. When she offers to free him, he is concerned for her and her father, and does not respond to her declaration of love. He is appreciative of Arcite&#8217;s caring for him in the woods, but still only wishes to recover his strength so as to be able to fight his cousin. He chooses to pray to Venus, the goddess of Love, before his battle with Arcite, and though he loses the fight in the end he gains the lady. He is generous, and twice offers the Jailer money for his daughter&#8217;s dowry, as thanks for her freeing him; he also obtains from Theseus that neither Jailer nor Daughter be held to blame for his escape. He is quite cheerful about having his head chopped off after he loses the battle to Arcite. He insists throughout that he has first rights to Emilia, as he saw her a few seconds before Arcite did.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ARC.">Arcite</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH. ARC. AND PAL.">Both Arcite and Palamon</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Arcite is a nephew of the tyrant Creon of Thebes. He neither likes nor approves of his uncle, and would leave his court and fight against him, were it not dishonorable. He has a pretty face and black hair, and has had a number of casual flings in his time. He is deeply attached to his cousin Palamon, his war-mate and best friend, and quite self-congratulatory about what good friends they are. The two are almost indistinguishable, both being just as self-involved, and both falling powerfully in love with Emilia merely at the sight of her. Freed thanks to Pirithous&#8217;s pleading, but banished from Athens, he disguises himself to compete in the wrestling and racing organized for Emilia&#8217;s birthday, where he wins all the competitions. Becoming a servant to Emilia, he pities Palamon. He is slightly more affected and more cheery than his cousin, as well as more cautious. Despite the deadly rivalry between them, he files through Palamon&#8217;s chains and feeds him so that he will be in good shape to fight each other. He chooses to pray to Mars, the god of War, before his battle with Palamon, and wins the fight. However, he is thrown by his horse, and as he dies admits that since Palamon saw Emilia a few seconds before he did himself, his cousin&#8217;s claim is the more valid one.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAL.">Valerius</persname>
<persdescription>Valerius is a noble Theban who comes to bring Palamon and Arcite to Creon when the latter learns of Theseus&#8217;s attack. He warns the cousins to take their time, in the hopes that Creon will calm down before they arrive.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HER.">Herald</persname>
<persdescription>A Herald is doing his job wandering the field of battle once it is over to identify the dead when he finds the gravely-wounded Arcite and Palamon there. He informs Theseus of their identity.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JAIL.">Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>A Jailer (also called Keeper) is in charge of Theseus&#8217;s prison for high-ranking captives. This job has the potential for high income, as prisoners will pay their jailers for amenities, but unfortunately Theseus doesn&#8217;t send that many noble people to prison. At present the jail only contains Palamon and Arcite, and the Jailer is rather concerned with marrying off his daughter. Though courteous to his prisoners, he is quick to put them in chains if he&#8217;s worried about them. He is also terrified of blame when Palamon escapes. Not the most observant of men, he fails to realize at first that his daughter has lost her mind. He disapproves of premarital sex and though he accepts the Doctor&#8217;s cure, he is appalled at how far the Doctor is willing to let the Wooer go in his impersonation of Palamon. However, having to appear at the battle between Palamon and Arcite and their followers, he misses the Wooer and his daughter arranging to go to bed together. He brings Palamon and his followers to the block.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WOOER.">Wooer to the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter</persname>
<persdescription>The Wooer is in love with the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter, and hopes to marry her. He is a little dim, and perhaps a little shy as well. He is not an imaginative man, and is worried that his inability to sing will make his impersonation of Palamon fail. He trusts the Doctor, however, especially when the latter convinces him that he should sleep with the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter if she seems to be in the mood for it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DOCT.">Doctor</persname>
<persdescription>A Doctor is consulted by the Jailer and his friends in the hopes of curing the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter&#8217;s madness. He finds it a most interesting case. Though not entirely certain that he can cure her, he decides that the world should join her in her madness to try and bring her out of it. He is much more concerned for his own success than for the believability of the Wooer&#8217;s impersonation of Palamon or for the Jailer&#8217;s concern for morality, and doesn&#8217;t much believe in 18-year-old girls&#8217; chastity anyway. He considers fathers who think their grown daughters are perfectly chaste to be fools.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HIP.">Hippolyta</persname>
<persdescription>Hippolyta is the Queen of the Amazons, now marrying Theseus. She is a strong, athletic woman, an excellent fighter and huntress. She is moved enough by the pleas of the three Queens to kneel to Theseus to beg him to put off their wedding and fight Creon first. She is not emotional and does not cry, and is certain that Theseus loves her best in the world. She notices a man&#8217;s muscles more than his face. She begs for Theseus&#8217;s reprieve on Palamon and Arcite. She is very fond of her sister Emilia. She is the same as the Hippolyta of <persnameref>A Midsummer Night&#8217;s Dream</persnameref>.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EMIL.">Emilia</persname>
<persdescription>Emilia is Hippolyta&#8217;s sister. Like her an Amazon, she has fought in battles with her sister. She is a kind and pitying woman. Still mourning the death of her childhood friend Flavina, she is convinced that she will never share a love as intense or as close as she had with the deceased girl. She enjoys gardens, though she is not fully acquainted with the names of all the flowers. She likes her brother-in-law Theseus, who organizes races and wrestling for her birthday. Emilia remains completely unaware that she has become the love-object of the two warring cousins Palamon and Arcite until she comes across them fighting each other to the death over her. She is appalled by this, and hopes to have them banished so that she will not have to deal with them again. She refuses to choose one over the other, both because she cannot see either as better than the other and because she does not wish to condemn one of them to death. She finds both as worthy as the other and does not know which one&#8217;s victory to hope for in the battle over her; she is also horrified that three other men will die simply because of her existence and beauty, and refuses to actually attend the fight. There is no sign that she actually loves either of them, and she has little reaction to the sudden change in husband at the end, though she pledges to keep the day of Arcite&#8217;s death as a memorial day to him for the rest of her life.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="DAUGH.">Jailer&#8217;s Daughter</persname>
<persdescription>The Jailer&#8217;s Daughter is 18, immature, romantic, and more than ready to lose her virginity. She takes care of the imprisoned Arcite and Palamon, bringing them their food and keeping the cell fresh, and falls completely in love with Palamon. She is aware that he is unlikely to marry her, given the differences in their social rank, but she nevertheless hopes to at least become his mistress. Her passion is so great that she risks her father&#8217;s life by freeing Palamon and leading him to the woods. She is worried then when he does not kiss her after she admits her love, and, lost in the woods, cold, hungry, unable to find him again, her wits become addled and she slowly loses her mind. She becomes very child-like, while at the same time harping on her physical desire for Palamon. She joins in with the morris dancers and then goes on her way. She picks flowers by a river, and when she sees the Wooer she was meant to marry, she jumps into the water and would drown if he did not jump in after and save her. She is calmed down when the Wooer pretends to be Palamon at the Doctor&#8217;s suggestion, and soon agrees to marry him. Whether she ever realizes that the man she takes to bed with her is not the one she is in love with is unknown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="WOMAN.">Waiting-Woman to Emilia</persname>
<persdescription>A Waiting Woman attends on Emilia. She is a good seamstress and not shy about her skill. She also knows her flowers, and can reproduce them in her handiwork. She enjoys a mild dirty joke on occasion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BOY">Boy</persname>
<persdescription>A Boy leads the wedding procession, singing an epithalamium while strewing flowers.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BAVIAN.">Bavian</persname>
<persdescription>Bavian is one of the morris dancers, disguised as a creature with a long tail and a long tool. His role in the dance is to act very lewdly, to the extent that Gerrold feels it necessary to warn him not to overdo it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="GENT.">Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>A Gentleman of Athens comes to tell Emilia that Arcite and Palamon have arrived for their duel.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SCHOOL.">Gerrold</persname>
<persdescription>Gerrold is a schoolmaster, who organizes the morris dance to entertain Theseus. He is pompous, convinced of his superiority, given to Latin quotes, and somewhat over-the-top in the writing of his speech to the Duke. A true man of the theatre, he is horrified to find a cast member missing, and when the Jailer&#8217;s mad Daughter wanders in, he quickly drafts her into his cast instead of helping her. He is wooing the tanner&#8217;s daughter.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HYM.">Hymen</persname>
<persdescription>Hymen is the god of marriage, and leads Theseus and Hippolyta&#8217;s wedding procession.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRO.">Prologue</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="EPI.">Epilogue</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>Prologue/Epilogue comes forward on behalf of the acting company to talk to the audience at the beginning and end of the play. In colloquial language and a few dirty jokes, he begs the audience to like the play, if only out of fear of making Chaucer (who wrote the original story the play is based on) roll over in his grave. He is uncertain at the end whether the company has succeeded in pleasing the audience, but reminds them that it&#8217;s only a story, after all, and was only made to entertain.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. QUEEN.">First Queen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL QUEENS.">All Queens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Queen is the widow of King Capaneus, who died fighting Creon of Thebes. She leads the trio of pleading Queens and tells their tale to Theseus. She has met him before, but has aged greatly since then. She is worried that Theseus may delay, and urges him on with every argument she can muster. Her only aim is to have Creon beaten and humbled, and to be able to bury her husband&#8217;s body. She is dressed in black, with a stained veil and an impressive crown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. QUEEN.">Second Queen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL QUEENS.">All Queens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Queen is the widow of a king who died fighting Creon of Thebes. With the two other queens she comes to plead to Theseus that he make war on Creon so that they may recover their dead husbands&#8217; bodies and bury them. She pleads in the name of motherhood to the soon-to-be-married Hippolyta, whose personal power and history she admires. She is dressed in black, with a stained veil and an impressive crown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. QUEEN.">Third Queen</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL QUEENS.">All Queens</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Queen is the widow of a king who died fighting Creon of Thebes. With the two other queens she comes to plead to Theseus that he make war on Creon so that they may recover their dead husbands&#8217; bodies and bury them. She pleads to the unmarried Emilia, in the name of maidenhood, to help them convince Theseus. She is dressed in black, with a stained veil and an impressive crown.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. COUN.">First Country Folk</persname>
<persdescription>First Country Folk is one of the morris dancers, who seeks to reassure Gerrold that they will not fail him. He participates in the dance even though it will anger his wife. He is enraged at Cicely&#8217;s absence, but quickly perceives the advantage of having a madwoman stumble on them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. COUN.">Second Country Folk</persname>
<persdescription>Second Country Folk is one of the morris dancers, who has an eye for the ladies. He is slightly concerned over whether Gerrold will actually come join them. He is either a glove-maker or wooing Cicely, of whom he has a low opinion. He dislikes broken promises, especially when they risk a run at fortune, and has a bit of a temper when it comes to unknown people who may join in the wrestling.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. COUN.">Third Country Folk</persname>
<persdescription>Third Country Folk is one of the morris dancers, who convinces the others of the need for rehearsal. He makes sure that the musicians are in their proper places, and is quick to see the advantage of a madwoman joining them in their dance to replace the missing Cicely.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="4. COUN.">Fourth Country Folk</persname>
<persdescription>Fourth Country Folk is one of the morris dancers. He is unconcerned at the idea that taking a day off might be problematic for their work, and is enraged at Cicely&#8217;s truancy and swears to get back at her the next time he sees her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. FRIEND.">Jailer&#8217;s First Friend</persname>
<persdescription>Jailer&#8217;s First Friend witnessed Theseus finding Palamon, and comes to tell the Jailer of it. He is disturbed by the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter&#8217;s madness, and pities her for it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. FRIEND.">Jailer&#8217;s Second Friend</persname>
<persdescription>Jailer&#8217;s Second Friend hears Palamon clear the Jailer of any responsibility in his escape, and also how Palamon obtained a pardon for the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter along with her father. He comes to tell the Jailer of this, along with how Palamon has given the Daughter a large sum of money as dowry. He is disturbed by the Jailer&#8217;s Daughter&#8217;s madness, and pities her for it.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="BROTH.">Jailer&#8217;s Brother</persname>
<persdescription>The Jailer&#8217;s Brother sees his niece running madly towards the city and stops her. He manages to lead her back to her father by agreeing with everything she says. He disagrees with his brother&#8217;s defeatism in thinking her incurable.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. MESS.">First Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The First Messenger comes from Arcite, Palamon, and their followers to let Theseus know they have arrived. He is highly impressed by the two cousins&#8217; companions. He later rushes to stop Palamon&#8217;s execution.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. MESS.">Second Messenger</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Messenger rushes in to tell the Jailer that he is late for the battle between Palamon and Arcite.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SERV.">Servant</persname>
<persdescription>A Servant attends Emilia as she sits out the tournament between Palamon and Arcite, and from time to time reports to her how the fight is going.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. KNIGHT.">First Knight</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. KNIGHT. AND 2. KNIGHT.">Both First and Second Knights</persname>
	<persname short="ALL KNIGHTS.">All Knights</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Knight Attending Palamon has a reddish face, with thick, blonde, curly hair. He is 25 years old, unbearded, and very strong. He is not at all downcast at losing the fight and having to have his head chopped off, since his honor is unmarred. He is a generous man, and is armed with a golden-handled axe.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. KNIGHT.">Second Knight</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="BOTH 1. KNIGHT. AND 2. KNIGHT.">Both First and Second Knights</persname>
	<persname short="ALL KNIGHTS.">All Knights</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Knight Attending Palamon is a small man with well-muscled arms. He has white hair and a round, freckled face, grey eyes, and a winning smile. He is 36 years old, and wears oak leaves in his hair, along with his lady&#8217;s favor. He is armed with a silver mace. He recommends perfect patience and calm to his companions as they wait to have their heads chopped off. When he hears of the girl who freed Palamon from jail, he double-checks that she is virtuous before joining in with giving up his money to her.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. KNIGHT.">Third Knight</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL KNIGHTS.">All Knights</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Knight attending Palamon seems quite unfazed at having lost the battle and having to have his head chopped off, and merely wants to know who will go first.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="TABORER.">Timothy the Taborer</persname>
<persdescription>Timothy the Taborer plays the tabor in the morris dancer, giving the beat.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ART.">Artesius</persname>
<persdescription>Artesius [mute role] is an Athenian soldier, particularly good at getting the enemy to come to where Theseus wants them to be. Theseus sends him to muster the army before they attack Creon.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="NELL.">Nell</persname>
<persdescription>Nell is a freckled country wench and one of the morris dancers. She does not think that she and her fellow wenches need Gerrold&#8217;s instructions.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>