<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="Two Gentlemen of Verona">

<persona>
<persname short="DUKE.">Duke of Milan</persname>
<persdescription>The Duke of Milan intends to marry his daughter, Silvia, to Sir Thurio; he himself is planning to woo a lady, though it has been a long time and he does not quite remember how to go about it. He is tricky and hot-tempered, and exiles Valentine for having the audacity to try to run off with Silvia. He then requests that Proteus go slander Valentine so that Silvia won&#8217;t mind marrying Thurio so much. He is apparently not much of a fighter, as running after his escaped daughter and Sir Eglamour he is captured by a band of outlaws. Freed by Valentine, he decides that the young man&#8217;s not so bad after all.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="VAL.">Valentine</persname>
<persdescription>Valentine is a young gentleman of Verona. He thinks that men in love are foolish until he himself falls head-over-heels for the Duke of Milan&#8217;s daughter, Silvia. Not the brightest, at least when it comes to women, he needs to have his servant Speed interpret Silvia&#8217;s actions to understand that she loves him back. He is delighted when his dear friend Proteus joins him at court, and immediately asks him for help in abducting Silvia. Asked by the Duke how best to woo a lady, he is too dense to realize that he is being led into a trap, and tells the Duke exactly what he has been planning with the Duke&#8217;s daughter. He is of noble aspect, which helps convince a band of outlaws to make him their leader, which he accepts to do; as he is honorable, however, he insists that they not attack women or the poor. While they agree, he has a hard time keeping them in line over the next few days. Walking through the forest, he sees his dear love Silvia about to be raped by his friend Proteus, and intervenes. Discovering that his friend betrayed him, he insults him, until Proteus apologizes, at which point Valentine is perfectly happy again and donates the love of his life to his childhood friend.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PRO.">Proteus</persname>
<persdescription>Proteus is a young gentleman of Verona whose emotions are extremely changeable and lacks self-control. Utterly in love with Julia, he forgets her immediately and becomes even more utterly in love with Silvia the moment he arrives in Milan and sees her. The fact that this is trampling on his best friend Valentine&#8217;s territory causes him only a little angst. Ruled by his passion, he betrays his best friend, lies to the Duke, pretends to be working on Thurio&#8217;s behalf, swears that Julia is dead, and perseveres in wooing Silvia even when she makes it clear that she is disgusted by his actions. He does not recognize Julia when she is disguised as a boy, and employs her to get the painting Silvia has promised him. Following Silvia to the forest when she runs away, he is so overcome by his desire for her that he attempts to rape her, only being stopped by Valentine&#8217;s arrival and intervention. He is overcome with remorse, though has no objection when Valentine offers to let him have Silvia anyway. Discovering that the boy Sebastian is actually Julia, he immediately falls for her again, quite forgetting Silvia.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="ANT.">Antonio</persname>
<persdescription>Antonio is Proteus&#8217;s father. He is discontented at how his son is mooning around rather than doing anything to improve his state in the world, and at Panthino&#8217;s suggestion decides to send the boy to court to make him become a man instead of wasting his time.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="THU.">Thurio</persname>
<persdescription>Thurio is a foolish gentleman at the court of Milan, and a suitor to Silvia&#8217;s hand. A dark-faced fellow, he has the Duke&#8217;s approval to marry Silvia. As Silvia despises him, he is forced to ask Proteus for help in wooing her. He does not actually think much of Silvia, following her to the forest more out of anger at Sir Eglamour for helping her than for her own sake. Threatened by the outlaw Valentine, he quickly disclaims any interest in the lady.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="EGL.">Eglamour</persname>
<persdescription>Sir Eglamour is a knight at the Duke&#8217;s court, who was deeply in love with a lady, who died. To mourn her, he swore to never love again, and to remain chaste the rest of his life. He is touched by Silvia&#8217;s plight and agrees to escort her when she runs away to try and find Valentine. He is not, however, as brave a knight as he seems, and runs away when they are attacked by outlaws, leaving Silvia to them.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="HOST.">Host</persname>
<persdescription>The Host runs an inn where Proteus and Julia each stay while they are in Milan. A bit of a gossip, he often chats with Lance and knows of Proteus&#8217;s passion for Silvia. He enjoys music.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SPEED.">Speed</persname>
<persdescription>Speed is Valentine&#8217;s servant. He is given to endless wordplay, and is rarely quiet. Proteus hires him to bring Julia a letter. He does not abstain from mocking his master or moralizing at him, or pointing out some hard truths on occasion. He appears to be somewhat brighter than his master. He enjoys Launce&#8217;s company, though the latter manages to get him in trouble on occasion.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LAUNCE.">Launce</persname>
<persdescription>Launce is Proteus&#8217;s servant. Not the brightest, he occasionally mixes up his big words. He is crestfallen at having to leave his family to follow Proteus to Milan. He is devoted to his dog Crab, even taking the blame for every one of the many, many things the dog does wrong. He enjoys gossip, ale, and bad puns. He realizes that his master is acting wrongly, but does nothing about it. He falls in love with a milkmaid with a bad reputation, but who is rich. When Proteus sends him to offer Silvia a small lapdog, he manages to have it stolen, and offers her Crab instead. This does have the effect Proteus hoped for.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="PAN.">Panthino</persname>
<persdescription>Panthino is Antonio&#8217;s servant. At the request of his master&#8217;s brother, he suggests to Antonio that he force his son to leave home and make something of himself in the world.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="JUL.">Julia</persname>
<persdescription>Julia is a young lady of Verona beloved by Proteus. Though at first unimpressed by him, she soon falls completely in love with him, and is distraught when he is sent to Milan. A fairly spunky lady, she dresses up as a boy to safely journey to Milan to see him, only to discover on arrival that he has forgotten her and is paying court to the Duke&#8217;s daughter. To be able to be near him she offers herself to Proteus as a servant, and he sends her to bring Silvia a letter and the ring that she herself had given him at their parting. She finds Silvia very kind, and therefore cannot hate her. She does nothing to try to stop Proteus from raping Silvia, but faints when Valentine offers his love to Proteus. Revealing her identity, she regains Proteus&#8217;s love. Auburn-haired and grey-eyed, the journey to Milan gives her a tan.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="SIL.">Silvia</persname>
<persdescription>Silvia is the blonde-haired, grey-eyed daughter of the Duke of Milan. She plays the game of courtly love well, calling all her wooers &#8216;Servant&#8217; and trying to subtly reveal to Valentine that she loves him back by having him write a love-letter for her, and then giving it to him. She has enough spirit to plan to run away with Valentine, and is greatly downcast when he is found out and exiled. Beset by Sir Thurio, whom her father wishes her to marry, and by Proteus, whom she despises for his treachery, she has the courage to plan to run away to find Valentine with the help of Sir Eglamour. Despite her hatred of Proteus, she is noble enough to allow him to have a painting of her. She greatly pities Proteus&#8217;s first love Julia. Captured in the forest by outlaws, she has the misfortune of being rescued by Proteus, who attempts to rape her. When Valentine intervenes, and then quickly pardons his friend and offers him Silvia, she speaks not a word.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="LUC.">Lucetta</persname>
<persdescription>Lucetta is Julia&#8217;s waiting-woman. Strong-spirited, she does not take well to being badly-treated by her mistress. She does not have much faith in men&#8217;s fidelity. Somewhat perturbed by the strength of Julia&#8217;s passion, she nevertheless helps her mistress dress as a boy so that she may go seek out Proteus.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="MUSIC.">Musicians</persname>
<persdescription>Musicians are hired by Thurio to serenade Silvia at night.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="1. OUT.">First Outlaw</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL OUTLAWS">All Outlaws</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The First Outlaw is quite blunt about being the enemy of those whose path crosses his band&#8217;s, and considers the stabbing to death of men and the stealing away of women to be no more than petty crimes. He is a banished gentleman of Milan.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="2. OUT.">Second Outlaw</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL OUTLAWS">All Outlaws</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Second Outlaw is all for killing travellers. He is interested to know that Valentine speaks several languages, and offers to make him the outlaws&#8217; leader. He is one of those who capture the Duke and Thurio. He is an exiled gentleman from Mantua, where he killed a man.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="3. OUT.">Third Outlaw</persname>
<persaliases>
	<persname short="ALL OUTLAWS">All Outlaws</persname>
</persaliases>
<persdescription>The Third Outlaw is greatly impressed by Valentine, and thinks him just the sort of man the outlaws need as a leader. He is from Verona, from whence he was banished for trying to run off with a lady. He is one of those who capture the Duke and Thurio.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="CRAB">Crab</persname>
<persdescription>Crab is a moderately-sized dog. Launce&#8217;s pet, he is very badly-behaved.</persdescription>
</persona>

</personae>