<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../plays.xsl"?>

<personae playtitle="The Winter&#8217;s Tale">

<persona>
<persname short="">Leontes, King of Sicilia</persname>
<persdescription>Leontes is the King of Sicily. We do not know what he is like in ordinary times, for he is struck by an almost insane fit of jealousy soon after the play begins. One thing we do know is that he wooed Hermione for a full three months before convincing her to marry him. His fit grows worse as time goes on, from the suspicion that Hermione is cheating on him with his childhood friend Polixenes to a conviction that he is right. He finds tiny clues that he invests with the force of truth, to the extent that he commands Camillo to murder Polixenes. When Camillo instead tells Polixenes and flees with him, Leontes is convinced that this is even more evidence against Hermione. He rages at his most faithful lords for pleading on Hermione&#8217;s behalf, his words and accusations growing wilder at each step, accusing them of being traitors, threatening to have Paulina burnt for advocating for Hermione, and sending Antigonus to abandon the new-born child in the wilderness on peril of his life. He swears that he will treat the Queen fairly, holding an open trial and sending to Apollo&#8217;s oracle at Delphi for divine sanction. He has the Queen thrust into prison and has her brought to trial before she is fully recovered from giving birth. He has announcements proclaiming her guilt posted throughout his kingdom before the trial begins, and institutes himself both prosecutor and judge in her case, telling her to expect nothing less than death as a sentence. When the oracle is read out and proves to be in Hermione&#8217;s favor, Leontes&#8217;s madness hits its highest point as he blasphemes the gods, denying the oracle&#8217;s truth. Immediately, he receives news of his son&#8217;s death, and suddenly sees himself clearly. He swears to make up for what he has done, only to be told that Hermione has died. His sense of guilt is such that he begs Paulina to berate him more, and swears to let the world know of his fault and to visit Hermione&#8217;s tomb once a day for the rest of his life. For sixteen years he remains sunk in this depression, doing endless penance, to the extent that his lords beg him to forgive himself, and to marry again. Leontes keeps Paulina by him to keep him from forgetting what he has done, and swears not to marry again without her consent. He is somewhat revived when Florizel arrives, to the extent that he casts an appraising look at Perdita, but Paulina nixes that tendency in the bud. This is just as well, since it soon turns out that the girl is his daughter. On viewing the statue of Hermione, he is so struck by its verisimilitude that he wishes to spend twenty years looking at it, and to kiss it. He absolves Paulina of any charge of witchcraft if she will make the statue move, as promised. He is almost speechless when Hermione returns to life. Still, he is observant enough to have noted that Camillo is in love with Paulina, and he gives them to each other in marriage.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mamillius</persname>
<persdescription>Mamillius is Leontes&#8217;s and Hermione&#8217;s son. He is a prince, beloved by all Sicilians, all of whom are waiting to see him grown. He has something of a combative nature, being willing to fight (something to be hoped for in princes). Physically he resembles Leontes to a great degree. He has grown to the age where he does not wish to be treated as a baby, though as he is apparently still unbreeched and under the care of the women of the household, he is likely under seven years old. He is a tale-teller with a particularly talent for horror stories. Torn from his mother&#8217;s arms just as he is beginning one of these tales at her request, he falls ill, and after some weeks dies, just as his father blasphemes Apollo&#8217;s oracle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Camillo</persname>
<persdescription>Camillo is a highly honorable, honest, and loyal Sicilian lord, though he is not above a little trickery in a good cause. He attempts to convince Leontes that his suspicions are unfounded, but in the end agrees to murder Polixenes on the condition that Leontes take Hermione back. He finds it impossible to become a murderer, however, and instead reveals all to Polixenes and flees with him. He becomes the Bohemian king&#8217;s closest confidant. Once he finds out what Leontes&#8217;s jealousy led to, he continually attempts to effect a reconciliation between the two kings, partly because he is homesick. Polixenes rejects all such advances. He is friendly with Florizel, who regards him highly for his integrity. In the prince&#8217;s love for the shepherdess Camillo sees an opportunity to reconcile the king with Leontes, as well as with his son in the long term. Despite his length of service with Polixenes, his higher loyalty is always to Leontes. On his return, Leontes marries him to Paulina, having noted that Camillo is in love with the lady. Whether this is a long-standing devotion dating from the days of her marriage to Antigonus or a new development on Camillo&#8217;s return to Sicily is uncertain.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Antigonus</persname>
<persdescription>Antigonus is a lord at Leontes&#8217;s court. He is married to Paulina, and has three daughters. A grey-bearded old man, he is willing to stake almost all he has on Hermione&#8217;s innocence, believing that the king must have been convinced by some Iago-like figure of her disloyalty. He is also afraid of the ridicule Leontes&#8217;s madness will bring on the court. He attempts to rule his wife, but she is too forceful a personality, leading him to be considered henpecked. He stands up to Leontes, but obeys him when his allegiance is called on, and also when having sworn to obey before hearing the command he receives the order to abandon Hermione&#8217;s baby in deserted place. He receives a visitation from Hermione&#8217;s ghost, who tells him what to do with the child. Though he dislikes the oath, unlike Camillo he does not break it, though he does what he can for the baby before being eaten by a bear. While in the process of having his shoulder chewed on, he is still able to cry out his name and rank to a passerby.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Cleomines</persname>
<persdescription>Cleomines is one of the Sicilian lords sent to Delphi to ask Apollo&#8217;s oracle for a verdict on Hermione&#8217;s case. He is awed by the experience. He does not like the public shaming the Queen is enduring. Over the course of 16 years he is convinced that Leontes has done more than enough to atone for his wrongs, and does not approve of Paulina&#8217;s constant needling of the King, nor of her presumption in having Leontes swear not to marry but by her consent. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Dion</persname>
<persdescription>Dion is one of the Sicilian lords sent to Delphi to ask Apollo&#8217;s oracle for a verdict on Hermione&#8217;s case. He is greatly impressed by the visual aspect of the oracle&#8217;s temple. He hopes for Hermione&#8217;s innocence to be confirmed. Sixteen years on, he hopes for Leontes to remarry, if only for the sake of begetting an heir. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Polixenes, King of Bohemia</persname>
<persdescription>Polixenes is the King of Bohemia. He is a close childhood friend of Leontes&#8217;s, and is willing to abandon his kingdom for nine months to visit the latter. He is convinced to remain longer by Hermione, with whom he gets on well. He realizes that all is not well from Leontes&#8217;s actions before Camillo reveals that he is to be poisoned. Sixteen years do nothing to blunt the effect this revelation has. He has no interest in a reconciliation with Leontes, nor in letting Camillo return to Sicily. He is a concerned father who worries about his son becoming attached to a shepherdess. He strongly approves of cross-breeding noble plants with vile ones, but does not carry the logic of his argument over to his bloodline. He appears unaware of this contradiction. Though he recognizes Perdita&#8217;s natural nobility, the thought of Florizel marrying her enrages him, revealing a temper we did not know he had. When he discovers that Florizel has fled with the girl, he chases after him instead of merely disinheriting him as threatened. Seeing Leontes again in the context of the discovery of Perdita&#8217;s identity is enough for him to be reconciled. He also ennobles the girl&#8217;s adoptive family, whom he called traitors when she was not of noble birth.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Florizel</persname>
<persdescription>Florizel is Polixenes&#8217;s son. He is deeply in love with Perdita, whom he visits disguised as a countryman; to all but her he goes by the name of Doricles. He does not share her fears about the difference in their ranks, believing that all will turn out well. He is ready to become betrothed to her, but obstinately refuses the arguments that he should let his father know. After Polixenes threatens to disown him if he ever visits Perdita again, he stays constant to her, and resolves to wander the world with her rather than live without. He respects Camillo and is willing to take his advice to disguise himself and fly to Sicily. He is prepared to lie to Leontes, swearing that he comes by his father&#8217;s command and that Perdita is a Libyan princess. Found out, he still begs Leontes to intervene with Polixenes, and it luckily turns out that Perdita is Leontes&#8217;s daughter, and all therefore turns out well. Physically, he resembles his father to a strong degree.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Archidamus</persname>
<persdescription>Archidamus is a Bohemian lord, part of Polixenes&#8217;s suite when the latter visits Sicily. He is impressed by Sicilian hospitality and by Mamillius, and insists to Camillo that Bohemia will be unable to match the magnificence of Sicily when Leontes pays them a return visit.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Old Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>The Old Shepherd is a Bohemian. At the age of 67, searching for sheep, he comes across the baby Perdita and adopts her. Thanks the gold that was left with her, he becomes the richest man of his district. He has a crusty old man&#8217;s opinion of teenage boys. Likewise, he chides the 16 year-old Perdita for not being as good a Queen of the Feast as his late wife was. He is hospitable, readily welcoming strangers to his house as a way to make new friends. He approves of Doricles as a husband for his daughter, and tells all and sundry that he&#8217;ll get a remarkable dowry for her; indeed, he promises him as much as Doricles himself will bring to the wedding. He is floored by the revelation that Doricles is in fact Prince Florizel; his reaction is such that it worries Camillo that he may die. In terror that he will be hanged, he resolves to tell the Polixenes how he found Perdita, and present all the evidence that she is not, in fact, his daughter. Accepting Autolycus&#8217;s offer of mediating, he finds himself shipped to Sicily, where he is confronted by Polixenes. He attempts to tell the King what he knows, though the latter refuses to hear and threatens him with a variety of methods of execution. Upon Leontes&#8217;s arrival, he is finally able to tell his story, and the kings are so overjoyed that Polixenes ennobles him.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Clown</persname>
<persdescription>The Clown is the Old Shepherd&#8217;s son. He is, to put it charitably, not the brightest of fellows, but he is good-natured. Out with his father to search for missing sheep, he witnesses a ship sinking in the storm, and a gentleman being eaten by a bear who calls to him for help. He does not do so, but does bury what&#8217;s left of him. 16 years on, sent by his adopted sister to do the shopping for the sheep-shearing feast, he charitably helps a man who&#8217;s been beaten by a ruffian, not realizing that his pocket is being picked. He has a taste for music, and is being wooed by both Dorcas and Mopsa &#8212; or perhaps he is wooing them. He convinces his father to tell the King that Perdita is not actually a member of their family by blood. He is certain that Autolycus is a gentleman, and is terrified of the punishments the rogue claims are being prepared for them. He takes well to being made a gentleman, and attempts to convince Autolycus to go honest.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Autolycus</persname>
<persdescription>Autolycus is a short rogue, formerly one of Florizel&#8217;s servants. A consummate conman and pickpocket, he sings a great deal, both for his own pleasure and as part of his cons. He is well-known for going to all merry gatherings and having his way with people&#8217;s purses. He was whipped from Florizel&#8217;s servants, consorts with brothel-owners, worked as a bailiff, married a tinker&#8217;s wife, attempted a variety of jobs, and settled on being a trickster. He arrives at the sheep-shearing as a pedlar, selling ballads and knick-knacks, and takes the opportunity to note who has money and where the keep it; and having sold his stock, he then takes their remaining money. He can counterfeit having been beaten at a moment&#8217;s notice as well as play the gentleman. By chance he is around in time to exchange his clothes with Florizel before the latter&#8217;s flight, and overhears enough of the plot to know what&#8217;s going on. He also overhears the Old Shepherd and the Clown debating, and offers to be their advocate to the King in return for gold. He brings them aboard Florizel&#8217;s ship, and it is therefore thanks to him that the mystery of Perdita&#8217;s identity is revealed. He is not overly pleased at this, as it&#8217;s a good thing rather than a roguish trick. Extremely quick-witted and able to turn any situation to his advantage, he is a coward, and trembles at the very thought of being caught and hanged.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mariner</persname>
<persdescription>A Mariner is captain of the ship that bears Antigonus and the baby to the shores of Bohemia. He knows the land to be dangerous. He drowns with his ship at about the same time that Antigonus becomes a snack.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Jailer</persname>
<persdescription>A Jailer appears sympathetic to Paulina, but follows his orders to the letter. He is afraid of punishment for letting the baby leave the jail, but is willing to be convinced by Paulina&#8217;s arguments.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Hermione</persname>
<persdescription>Hermione is Leontes&#8217;s wife, and the daughter of the Emperor of Russia. Very much aware of her dignity, she has a son, Mamillius, and is nine months&#8217; pregnant at the start of the play. She is persuasive, able to convince Polixenes to remain an extra week, and easy to enter in conversation with. Though exhausted at times by her son&#8217;s energy, she enjoys having him tell her stories. When she is suddenly attacked by an irrational Leontes accusing her of adultery, she had first believes this to be a misunderstanding, but on realizing that he is in earnest she submits to his will, though refusing to speak any word that might suggest her guilt. She gives birth to a daughter in prison and is willing to trust Paulina with her, but this is the last time she sees the child. She is not fully recovered from childbirth when she is brought to court to answer the charges against her. Her pride is evident as she lists all the wrongs done to her and states that she is fighting for her honor, not her life. When the news of her son&#8217;s death arrives, she is however overcome.  Whether she dies at this point is a matter of opinion. She is seems so and is accepted as such, and what seems to be her ghost appears to Antigonus to tell him what to do with her child, but 16 years later appears as a statue which is revived. Either she was dead, and her statue brought to life; or she hid away for sixteen years, posed as a statue to hear Leontes&#8217;s remorse, and then decided to return to life. Each production must make up its own mind, though the evidence tends to point towards the latter interpretation. It should be noted is that though she takes Leontes&#8217;s hand in this scene, she does not speak to him, only to her daughter. However, she also will not look at Polixenes until Leontes bids her to.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Perdita</persname>
<persdescription>Perdita is Hermione&#8217;s and Leontes&#8217;s daughter, though she is unaware of this. At the age of sixteen, she is named as queen of a sheep-shearing feast, and takes it well in hand, though her &#8216;father&#8217; accuses her of not being as good at it as his late wife was. She is in love with Florizel, Polixenes&#8217;s son, and he with her. She is aware of the difference in their ranks, and frightened of it. She is not shy, however, and willing enough to discuss the ethics of cross-breeding flowers with strangers. When Polixenes reveals himself and insults her as an enchantress and lower-class, she holds her tongue even though she is tempted to tell him that they live in the same world.  Like her mother, she mixes spirit and demureness, is consciously submissive rather than naturally so, and is intelligent. She can be convinced to pretend to be a Libyan princess when she and Florizel flee to Sicily. This is when Perdita discovers that her father is not her father, but that she is a foundling; that she is in fact Leontes&#8217;s daughter; and that he had her abandoned in a desert place when she was a day old. Her reaction to this latter fact is not recorded. Perdita&#8217;s natural, inherited nobility shines through even when she is believed to be a mere shepherdess. She does not approve of bad language, is a good dancer, resembles her mother and is found beautiful by all men who see her. Paulina thinks her far less beautiful than Hermione, however. Whether this is true or merely another reprimand to Leontes is in the eye of the beholder. She is subject to seasickness.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Paulina</persname>
<persdescription>Paulina is Antigonus&#8217;s wife. She is an authoritative, upstanding, courageous and highly moral woman willing to risk her life for what she believes is right. She is willing to defy convention when need be, and rejects the idea that her husband can command her in an unethical manner. Unlike all the men at Leontes&#8217;s court, she does not beg in Hermione&#8217;s favor, but challenges the king to his face, forcing her way into his presence with his newborn child. Rather than swear on her life that the Queen is good, Paulina simply states that Hermione is, dares Leontes to have her burnt, and calls him a tyrant. After Hermione&#8217;s death, Leontes keeps her by his side as a constant reminder of what he has done; she keeps him from forgetting, as well as from marrying again. She insists on Hermione&#8217;s superiority to any woman mentioned, and rebukes Leontes for taking an appreciative look at Perdita. She orchestrates Hermione&#8217;s resurrection; and either has miraculous powers, or has been keeping Hermione hidden for sixteen years in a small house she owns that she visits two or three times a day. Whichever is the case, she considers her life&#8217;s work to be done thereafter, but Leontes grants her a new lease on life by convincing her to marry Camillo.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Emilia</persname>
<persdescription>Emilia is one of Hermione&#8217;s ladies, allowed to attend on the Queen as she gives birth. She convinces Hermione to trust Paulina&#8217;s plan to show the baby to Leontes.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Mopsa</persname>
<persdescription>Mopsa is a shepherdess being wooed by the Clown, who has promised her some trinkets if she would come to the feast with him. She is fond of ballads, particularly merry ones, and enjoys singing. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Dorcas</persname>
<persdescription>Dorcas is a shepherdess, who claims that the Clown has promised more to her than to Mopsa. She loves a good ballad and enjoys singing.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Time, as Chorus</persname>
<persdescription>Time, the Chorus serves as a bridge for the sixteen years that pass between Acts One and Four. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Lady</persname>
<persdescription>The First Lady is one of Hermione&#8217;s suite, and enjoys teasing Mamillius, though he claims she treats him too much like a baby. She predicts that he&#8217;ll seek out their companies once his sibling is born and everyone&#8217;s attention is gone. (She may be Emilia.)</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Officer</persname>
<persdescription>The Officer is the highest official in Hermione&#8217;s trial other than the King, charged with reading the indictment and administering oaths, as well as reading the oracle.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Lord</persname>
<persdescription>The First Lord at Leontes&#8217;s court witnessed Polixenes&#8217;s flight with Camillo. He joins with Antigonus in pleading for the Queen, pledging on his life that she is faithful. He leads the court in kneeling to Leontes to convince him to stop his madness, but berates Paulina for speaking too harshly to a king. He meets Polixenes when the latter arrives in Bohemia, and is sent with a message to Leontes demanding that the latter arrest Florizel and Perdita.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Servant of the Old Shepherd</persname>
<persdescription>The Servant of the Old Shepherd is very enthusiastic about all comers to the feast, be they peddlers or dancers. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Lady</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Lady is one of Hermione&#8217;s suite. Mamillius prefers her to the First. Her hair is darker than the First Lady&#8217;s. (She too may be Emilia.)</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The First Gentleman was present at the opening of the fardel that was found with Perdita, but was sent away before he could witness the whole scene of reconciliation. He is hoping to find out more as he chats with Autolycus. On hearing more, he agrees that they should all go see Hermione&#8217;s statue.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Gentleman (Ruggiero) hears that the oracle has been fulfilled, but wants confirmation of the tale. He has at times noticed Paulina&#8217;s visits to a small house nearby, and suggests that they all go along to see Hermione&#8217;s statue.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Gentleman</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Gentleman is Paulina&#8217;s steward, and as such was present during the whole reconciliation scene between the kings, when Perdita&#8217;s identity is discovered. He was very moved by the scene, and remembers some very specific details.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">First Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The First Servant is charged with reporting on Mamillius&#8217;s condition when the boy falls ill, and announces the child&#8217;s death. He also announces Florizel and Perdita&#8217;s arrival. He is awed by the latter&#8217;s appearance.</persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Second Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The Second Servant is among those who try to restrain Paulina from bursting in on the King. </persdescription>
</persona>

<persona>
<persname short="">Third Servant</persname>
<persdescription>The Third Servant announces Cleomenes and Dion&#8217;s return.</persdescription>
</persona>
</personae>